<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="eac.css"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
    <control>
        <recordId>GB-237-eac-p3950</recordId>
        <maintenanceStatus>new</maintenanceStatus>
        <publicationStatus>inProcess</publicationStatus>
        <maintenanceAgency>
            <agencyCode>GB-237</agencyCode>
            <agencyName>Special Collections, Edinburgh University Library</agencyName>
        </maintenanceAgency>
        <languageDeclaration>
            <language languageCode="eng">English</language>
            <script scriptCode="Latn" xml:lang="Gla">Gaelic</script>
        </languageDeclaration>
        <conventionDeclaration>
            <abbreviation>ISAAR(CPF)</abbreviation>
            <citation xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:type="simple">
                <span localType="bibTitle">International Standard Archival Authority Record For
                    Corporate Bodies, Persons and Families</span>
            </citation>
        </conventionDeclaration>
        <maintenanceHistory>
            <maintenanceEvent>
                <eventType>created</eventType>
                <eventDateTime standardDateTime="2010-03-16">11 May 2010</eventDateTime>
                <agentType>human</agentType>
                <agent>Scott Broderick</agent>
                <eventDescription>draft completed</eventDescription>
            </maintenanceEvent>
            <maintenanceEvent>
                <eventType>revised</eventType>
                <eventDateTime standardDateTime="2010-07-27">27 July 2010</eventDateTime>
                <agentType>human</agentType>
                <agent>Scott Broderick</agent>
                <eventDescription>draft completed</eventDescription>
            </maintenanceEvent>
            <maintenanceEvent>
                <eventType>revised</eventType>
                <eventDateTime>16 January 2013</eventDateTime>
                <agentType>human</agentType>
                <agent>Guinevere Barlow</agent>
            </maintenanceEvent>
        </maintenanceHistory>
        <sources>
            <source xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:type="simple">
                <sourceEntry>1841 census for Appin</sourceEntry>
                <descriptiveNote>
                    <p><span localType="ead-unitid">Census 1841 525/00 007/00 001</span>
                        <span localType="ead-repository">General Register Office for
                        Scotland</span></p>
                </descriptiveNote>
            </source>
            <source xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:type="simple">
                <sourceEntry>1851 census for Appin</sourceEntry>
                <descriptiveNote>
                    <p><span localType="ead-unitid">Census 1851 525/00 010/00 002</span>
                        <span localType="ead-repository">General Register Office for
                        Scotland</span></p>
                </descriptiveNote>
            </source>
            <source xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:type="simple">
                <sourceEntry>1861 census for Appin</sourceEntry>
                <descriptiveNote>
                    <p><span localType="ead-unitid">Census 1861 525/02 001/02 015</span>
                        <span localType="ead-repository">General Register Office for
                        Scotland</span></p>
                </descriptiveNote>
            </source>
            <source xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:type="simple">
                <sourceEntry>1871 census for Appin</sourceEntry>
                <descriptiveNote>
                    <p><span localType="ead-unitid">Census 1871 525/02 001/02 011</span>
                        <span localType="ead-repository">General Register Office for
                        Scotland</span></p>
                </descriptiveNote>
            </source>
            <source xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:type="simple">
                <sourceEntry>1881 census for Appin</sourceEntry>
                <descriptiveNote>
                    <p><span localType="ead-unitid">Census 1881 525/02 001/02 009</span>
                        <span localType="ead-repository">General Register Office for
                        Scotland</span></p>
                </descriptiveNote>
            </source>
            <source>
                <sourceEntry>Marriage certificate</sourceEntry>
                <descriptiveNote>
                    <p><span localType="ead-unitid">Marriage 1823 525/0020 0218</span>
                        <span localType="ead-repository" xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            >General Register Office for Scotland</span></p>
                </descriptiveNote>
            </source>
            <source>
                <sourceEntry>Death certificate</sourceEntry>
                <descriptiveNote>
                    <p><span localType="ead-unitid">Death 1886 525/02 0008</span>
                        <span localType="ead-repository" xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                            >General Register Office for Scotland</span></p>
                </descriptiveNote>
            </source>
            <source>
                <sourceEntry>Field notebook of Alexander Carmichael</sourceEntry>
                <descriptiveNote>
                    <p><span localType="ead-unitid">GB 237 Coll-97/CW120</span><span
                            localType="ead-repository">Edinburgh University Library</span></p>
                </descriptiveNote>
            </source>
        </sources>
    </control>
    <cpfDescription>
        <identity>
            <entityId>GB-237-EAC-p3950</entityId>
            <entityType>person</entityType>
            <nameEntry>
                <part localType="family">MacColl</part>
                <part localType="given">Donald</part>
            </nameEntry>
            <descriptiveNote>
                <p>[Domhnall a' Bhrocair; Am Brocair]; foxhunter, Mill of Fasnacloich, Glencreran,
                    Appin</p>
            </descriptiveNote>
        </identity>
        <description>
            <existDates>
                <dateRange>
                    <fromDate standardDate="1793" notAfter="1798" notBefore="1788">c1793</fromDate>
                    <toDate standardDate="1886-06-09">9 June 1886</toDate>
                </dateRange>
            </existDates>
            <biogHist>
                <p>Donald MacColl, foxhunter, was born in Glen Creran, Appin, the illegitimate son
                    of Rachel Cameron and, reputedly, John MacColl, shepherd. This John was the son
                    of Duncan MacColl, Dunnchadh Dhomhnaill mac Iain Duibh, who had fought at
                    Culloden under James Stewart of Fasnacloich. An enemy bullet went through his
                    thigh, while another carried off his scabbard from the hilt; he narrowly escaped
                    with his life.</p>
                <p>Donald MacColl married Anne or Agnes Rankin (c. 1796–1880) from Corrychurrachan
                    in the Parish of Kilmallie, daughter of Donald Rankin, crofter, and Mary
                    MacColl, on 29 June 1823. He told Carmichael that there were nine children from
                    the marriage: seven daughters, three of whom had died in Glasgow, and two sons,
                    one of whom ‘took early to sea &amp; is now on grund a chuain’, the other a
                    ‘shep[herd] in Mull (An t Saobhai[dh])’ [CW120/68]. Census accounts, however,
                    suggest only four girls and two boys; MacColl may possibly have been referring
                    to the number of children brought up in his household, including granddaughters.
                    In 1841 the family were living in Salachail towards the head of Glen Creran, but
                    by 1851 they had moved down to Fasnacloich, where the couple were to stay until
                    their deaths. By 1871 Donald had retired, while in the 1881 census he is
                    recorded as ‘Pauper, was a Foxhunter’, living with his 48-year old daughter Mary
                    and her daughter Mary Stevenson, aged 11.</p>
                <p>A celebrated local character and one of the best sources for the oral tradition
                    of his native district of Appin, ‘Am Brocair’ was interviewed by Alexander
                    Carmichael during at least three long recording sessions in the autumn of 1883,
                    on 29 August and the 27–28 September. Although it is not at all clear where
                    these interviews begin and end, the lack of other names suggests that, with the
                    exception of a single Fenian lay, all Appin tradition written into the first
                    half of the notebook CW120 was taken down from Donald MacColl himself.</p>
                <p>Even in Carmichael’s rushed notes, translated as they were jotted down, MacColl’s
                    force of character comes through clearly: he had no hesitation in informing his
                    interviewer that he knew he ‘was [from the] north from my Gaelic!’ [CW120/65]
                    The repetition of certain rhymes, mainly connected with the local saint Curalan
                    or Cyril, may be evidence of the ‘Senile Decay’ given as the cause of MacColl’s
                    death some three years later, but is more likely to be due to Carmichael
                    attempting to elicit further details of a subject which had obviously awakened
                    his curiosity: maybe the saint would make a good subject for a newspaper column.
                    The first interview between them appears to have ended with a walk up to the
                    site of Cladh Churalain, the graveyard of St Cyril, on the slopes of Beinn
                    Churalain, from where MacColl showed Carmichael landmarks in Benderloch opposite
                    [CW120/97].</p>
                <p>Donald MacColl had retired from his trade when Carmichael met him, and was full
                    of anecdotes and experiences from a lifetime spent hunting foxes with his
                    ‘doggies’: 53 years altogether, on average killing fifty of his quarry yearly,
                    making a grand total of over 2,500 animals over his entire career [CW120/63].
                    ‘He had innumerable interesting and instructive stories about foxes and other
                    wild animals, among which he had lived most of his long life of nearly one
                    hundred years’ [Carmina Gadelica vol. ii, 381n.5]. Like many of his kind, he was
                    fascinated by the shrewd and devious ways of foxes: for example, if the female
                    is killed, the male takes on responsibility for their cubs: ‘There is no other
                    fear tai[ghe] in Britain better’ [CW120/69]. ‘Many a time the foxes took a turn
                    out of me. But many a time I took a turn out of them in return’ [CW120/69].</p>
                <p>MacColl gave Carmichael some variant details about the history of his own
                    kindred, supposedly derived from a bastard son of ‘Moraire Donullach’ who fled
                    Skye for the Island of Coll after having committed a murder [CW120/70]. As a
                    reward for hospitality shown to the Duke of Argyll, the MacColl dùthchas of
                    Glasdrum in Glen Creran had been given to them as gràinnseach or a granary along
                    with Corrabheinn for mutton. The feu duty for the farm was paid to the Stewarts
                    of Appin, with the còir or charter being ‘car[ried] on per[son] or kept in [a]
                    cos dar[aich] [oak hollow] or under a stone. The MacColls [were] strong[er] than
                    the S[t]ew[art]s of Ap[pin]’ [CW120/164]. Other subjects touched upon included
                    the sixteenth-century hero Domhnall nan Òrd of Invernahyle, the quarrels between
                    the Stewarts of Appin and the Campbells, the Forty-Five, the clearances, the
                    last of the Stewarts of Appin, local wedding and funeral customs, and buried
                    treasures in the neighbourhood.</p>
                <p>The subject which clearly appealed to Carmichael the most, however, was material
                    concerning the local saint Curulan or Cyril: MacColl retailed for him various
                    legends of his life, together with details of his church, graveyard, and healing
                    well. Most intriguing of all is a series of references to ‘naoimh deilbh’ or
                    images of Curulan and his fellow saint Moluag, once kept in the church but burnt
                    by three ‘scamps’, apparently in the late eighteenth century [CW120/75]. These
                    scamps were in fact the sons of local gentry, and their actions are probably to
                    be ascribed to adolescent yahooism rather than reformation iconoclasm. All three
                    were said to have suffered agonising deaths as a result [CW120/83, CW120/88,
                    CW120/122].</p>
                <p>Donald MacColl told Carmichael that he had seen Sir Walter Scott (1771–1832)
                    several times when the novelist was visiting Fasnacloich [CW120/63, CW120/67,
                    CW120/86, CW120/153]. He had met and spoken to Donnchadh Bàn nan Òran, Duncan
                    Bàn Macintyre (1724–1812), in Glasdrum while the poet was travelling around the
                    Highlands with his wife Mary Macintyre (c1750–1824), better known as Màiri Bhàn
                    Òg, collecting subscriptions for the third edition of his songs, published in
                    1804 [CW120/176].</p>
                <p>Although MacColl told Carmichael he had ‘no oran luai[dh] no oran bhuana’
                    [CW120/172], he did sing him at least one song, a version of Hi hiù ro bhò chan
                    eil mi slàn, an air better known today in the Canadian Maritimes
                    [CW120/168].</p>
                <p>Carmichael may have visited Donald MacColl on another occasion, as is suggested
                    by an anecdote ascribed to him in <span localType="mods-titleinfo">Carmina
                        Gadelica</span>, but not found in the field notebooks, concerning a
                    discovery earlier in the century of ‘masses of wheatears’, apparently
                    hibernating under a bank [CG ii, 251; also 345]. On the other hand, the
                    ascription of a Sian Sionnaich or Charm against Foxes to Donald MacColl in <span
                        localType="mods-titleinfo">Carmina</span> [CG ii, 128–9] appears to have
                    been done as a gesture of piety towards the foxhunter’s memory. The practical
                    MacColl would have little use for Carmichael’s rather elaborately pious
                    incantation, which seems to have been derived in reality from an Òr an
                    t-Sionnaich given him by Mary Stewart or Màiri Bhreac, an old dairymaid in
                    Malacleit, North Uist, on 19 March 1877 [CW108/4]. </p>
                <p>Donald was a widower at the time of his death in 1886 and the cause was recorded
                    as senile decay, and his daughter Mary MacColl signed the certificate.</p>
                <chronList>
                    <chronItem>
                        <date standardDate="1793" notAfter="1798" notBefore="1788">c1793</date>
                        <placeEntry>Glencrerran, Appin</placeEntry>
                        <event>birth</event>
                    </chronItem>
                    <chronItem>
                        <date standardDate="1883-06-29">29 June 1823</date>
                        <event>marriage</event>
                    </chronItem>
                    <chronItem>
                        <date standardDate="1883-08-29">29 August 1883</date>
                        <placeEntry>Glen Creran, Appin</placeEntry>
                        <event>visited by Alexander Carmichael</event>
                    </chronItem>
                    <chronItem>
                        <date standardDate="1883-09-27">27 September 1883</date>
                        <placeEntry>Glen Creran, Appin</placeEntry>
                        <event>visited by Alexander Carmichael</event>
                    </chronItem>
                    <chronItem>
                        <date standardDate="1883-09-28">28 September 1883</date>
                        <placeEntry>Glen Creran, Appin</placeEntry>
                        <event>visited by Alexander Carmichael</event>
                    </chronItem>
                    <chronItem>
                        <date standardDate="1886-06-09">9 June 1886</date>
                        <placeEntry>Glen Creran, Appin</placeEntry>
                        <event>death</event>
                    </chronItem>
                </chronList>
            </biogHist>
        </description>
    </cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>
