<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE isaarcpf SYSTEM "isaar.dtd">
<isaarcpf> 
  <aarheader audience="internal" langencoding="ISO 639"
	aarstatus="edited-full-draft"> 
	 <aarid source="GB-0237" type="FPI"></aarid> 
	 <aarid source="GB-0237" type="FPI"> "-//Edinburgh University Library
		Special Collections Division :: Archival Authority Records//DOCUMENT
		GB-0237-NAHSTE-P1090 20020423 //EN" </aarid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P1090</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>Archimedes, of Syracuse</subtitle> 
		  <author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Olivier Usher, Edinburgh
			 University Library Special Collections Division, 23 April 2002</author> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt> 
		  <publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
			 Division</publisher> 
		  <address> 
			 <addressline>The University of Edinburgh</addressline> 
			 <addressline>George Square</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Edinburgh EH8 9LJ</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Scotland</addressline> 
			 <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> 
		  </address> 
		  <date type="single" normal="20020423">23 April 2002</date> 
		</publicationstmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>XML generated using the ISAAR(CPF) DTD and XMetal template
		  prepared, as part of the NAHSTE project, in collaboration with the GASHE
		  project, by Sarah Higgins, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division, 2001, with assistance from Pete Johnston, Lesley Richmond and Moira
		  Rankin, Glasgow University Archive Services. </creation> 
		<langusage> 
		  <language>EN</language> 
		</langusage> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item>No revisions to date </item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </aarheader> 
  <frontmatter> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P1090</titleproper> 
		<subtitle>Archimedes, of Syracuse</subtitle> 
		<author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Olivier Usher, Edinburgh
		  University Library Special Collections Division, 23 April 2002</author> 
		<publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division</publisher> 
		<date type="single" normal="20020423">23 April 2002</date> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 
  <aar id="GB-0237-NAHSTE-P1090"> 
	 <authcontrolarea> 
		<head>AUTHORITY CONTROL AREA</head> 
		<unitid label="Identity Code" encodinganalog="isaar11" type="NAHSTE"
		 repositorycode="0237">GB 0237 NAHSTE P1090</unitid> 
		<authentry encodinganalog="isaar13" label="Authority Entry"
		 authfilenumber="GB 0237 NAHSTE P1090"
		 normal="Archimedes of Syracuse">Archimedes, of Syracuse</authentry> 
	 </authcontrolarea> 
	 <infoarea encodinganalog="isaar2"> 
		<head>INFORMATION AREA</head> 
		<occsphere encodinganalog="isaar226"> 
		  <head>Occupation, Sphere of Activity</head> 
		  <p>Archimedes of Syracuse (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="-292/-217">c287-212 BC</date>) was a mathematician and inventor. His
			 father was Pheidias, an astronomer, of which we know nothing. While he is
			 famous now, as he was then, largely because of his inventions, it is reported
			 that he despised invention as being less "pure" than geometry, and he never
			 wrote about his creations. Little is known about his life, though he is
			 described by some as having been a relative - by others as a close friend - of
			 Hiero (or Hieron) II, King of Syracuse, who employed him as a tutor to his son.
			 He almost certainly spent a part of his life studying in Alexandria - where he
			 is thought to have played an important role in the development of Euclidian
			 mathematics. It is probably here that he met Conon of Samos, who he remained in
			 correspondence with as a personal as well as professional friend.</p> 
		  <p>Among the inventions he is credited with is the Screw of Archimedes,
			 an early type of pump he is thought to have created when in Alexandria, which
			 is still used in traditional agriculture in some areas of the world. He is also
			 - almost certainly apocryphally - said to have installed an arrangement of
			 mirrors on the city defences of Syracuse which set fire to attacking Roman
			 ships. He is believed to have invented the compound pulley as a way of
			 demonstrating the possibility of moving very large masses - he bragged that,
			 moved to a position outside the Earth, he could move the entire planet without
			 difficulty. More famously (though also less probably), he is said to have
			 thought of a way of proving King Hiero II had been cheated when supplied with a
			 new crown, by comparing the mass and volume of a block of pure gold of equal
			 mass with the crown. By showing the crown had a larger volume than the equally
			 massive block of gold, so the story goes, he proved that a metal with a lower
			 density had been added to the gold. While the story is improbable, it may
			 relate to one of his real achievements, the elucidation of Archimedes' Law,
			 which explains the change in weight due to buoyancy experienced by objects
			 submerged in water.</p> 
		  <p>He wrote a number of books, ten of which have survived largely
			 intact. These deal mostly with geometrical problems - particularly centres of
			 gravity of solids, studies of spheres and conical sections, spirals and other
			 mathematical matters. Among his propositions, particularly interestingly, are
			 an approximation of 'pi' - which he reached after circumscribing and inscribing
			 a circle with two 96-sided polygons, an explanation of the law of levers, a
			 foundation for theoretical mechanics, a means of accurately approximating
			 square roots of large numbers, a precursor to Newton and Leibniz's calculus and
			 a proposed system of numbering for large figures which went high enough -
			 8x10^16 in modern notation - to count to a higher number than the number of
			 grains of sand that would fill the universe - or so Archimedes believed.</p> 
		  <p>Archimedes' work the <bibref><title>Sandreckoner</title></bibref>,
			 in which he introduces his number system, is of historical interest, because it
			 contains an early reference to Aristarchus' heliocentric system and uses
			 results of Phidias (his father) and Eudoxus to determine the size of the
			 universe. It is dedicated to Gelo (Gelon), King Hiero's son. In his book, the
			 <bibref><title>Method</title></bibref>, Archimedes explains his scientific
			 methods to the reader, and is a unique document, detailing how one of the
			 greatest minds of the classical world worked. In <bibref><title>On the Sphere
			 and the Cylinder</title></bibref>, which he considered to be his most important
			 work, Archimedes proves that a sphere's surface area is two thirds that of the
			 circumscribing cylinder (including bases) and a sphere's volume is two thirds
			 that of a circumscribing cylinder.</p> 
		</occsphere> 
		<relships encodinganalog="isaar228"> 
		  <head>Relationships</head> 
		  <p>Archimedes was the son of astronomer Pheidias. He had a close
			 relationship with astronomer and mathematician Conon of Samos.</p> 
		</relships> 
		<otherinfo encodinganalog="isaar229"> 
		  <head>Other Significant Information</head> 
		  <p>Notable publications:</p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>On Plane Equilibria or Centres of Gravity of
			 Planes</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>On the Sphere and the Cylinder</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>On Spirals</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>On Floating Bodies</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>The Sandreckoner</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>Method</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>On Conoids and Spheroids</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>A Collection of Lemmas</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>The Quadrature of Parabola</title></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>The Measurement of the Circle</title></bibref></p> 
		</otherinfo> 
		<honqual encodinganalog="nahste2210"> 
		  <head>Honours, Qualifications and Appointments</head> 
		  <p>None known</p> 
		</honqual> 
	 </infoarea> 
	 <notearea encodinganalog="ISAAR3"> 
		<archnote encodinganalog="isaar31"> 
		  <head>Notes</head> 
		  <p>List of sources for the biographical information:</p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica vol II</title>, ( 
			 <imprint><geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="530"
			 normal="London (England)">London (England)</geogname>, 
			 <publisher>William Benton</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1976"
			 certainty="certain">1976</date>)</imprint></bibref> </p> 
		  <p> <bibref>
			 <persname source="ncarules" normal="Gillispie, Charles C"
			 role="editor">Gillispie, Charles C</persname>, <title
			 render="italic">Dictionary of scientific biography, vol II</title>, (<imprint>
			 <geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="483"
			 normal="New York (N.Y.), United States">New York </geogname>, 
			 <publisher>Scribner's</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1970"
			  certainty="certain">1970</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><corpname source="ncarules"
			 normal="University of St Andrews" role="author">University of St
			 Andrews</corpname>, <title>Archimedes of Syracuse</title>, (<extref
			 href="http://www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk/~history/Mathematicians/Archimedes.html">http://www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk/~history/Mathematicians/Archimedes.html</extref>,
			 <imprint><publisher>University of St Andrews</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="199901">January
				1999</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</archnote> 
		<rules encodinganalog="isaar32"> 
		  <head>Rules or Conventions</head> 
		  <p>Authority record created according to the <bibref>
			 <corpname normal="National Council on Archives">National Council on
			 Archives</corpname> <title>Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and
			 Corporate Names (NCA Rules)</title> <imprint> 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1997">1997</date></imprint></bibref>
			 and <bibref> <corpname normal="International Council on Archives">International
			 Council on Archives: Ad Hoc Committee on Descriptive Standards</corpname>
			 <title>International Standard Archival Authority Record for Corporate Bodies,
			 Persons and Families (ISAAR)CPF</title> <imprint> 
			 <date type="publication"
			  normal="1995">1995</date></imprint></bibref></p> 
		</rules> 
		<creationdate encodinganalog="isaar33"> 
		  <p>Personal name authority record compiled for the NAHSTE project by
			 <persname role="archivist" normal="Usher, Olivier">Olivier Usher</persname>,
			 Edinburgh University Library Special Collections Division, 
			 <date type="single" normal="20020423">23 April
				2002</date></p></creationdate> 
	 </notearea> 
  </aar>
</isaarcpf>
