<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE isaarcpf SYSTEM "file:///C|/Program%20Files/SoftQuad/XMetaL%202/Rules/isaar.dtd">
<isaarcpf> 
  <aarheader audience="internal" langencoding="ISO 639"
	aarstatus="edited-full-draft"> 
	 <aarid source="GB-0237" type="FPI"> "-//Edinburgh University Library
		Special Collections Division :: Archival Authority Records//DOCUMENT
		GB-0237-NAHSTE-P1351 20020211//EN" </aarid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P1351</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>Koller | Pio C | 1904-1979 | Hungarian geneticist</subtitle> 
		  <author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Margaret Stewart, Edinburgh
			 University Library Special Collections Division, 24 June 2002</author> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt> 
		  <publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
			 Division</publisher> 
		  <address> 
			 <addressline>The University of Edinburgh</addressline> 
			 <addressline>George Square</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Edinburgh EH8 9LJ</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Scotland</addressline> 
			 <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> 
		  </address> 
		  <date type="single" normal="20020624">24 June 2002</date> 
		</publicationstmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>XML generated using the ISAAR(CPF) DTD and XMetal template
		  prepared, as part of the NAHSTE project, in collaboration with the GASHE
		  project, by Sarah Higgins, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division, 2001, with assistance from Pete Johnston, Lesley Richmond and Moira
		  Rankin, Glasgow University Archive Services. </creation> 
		<langusage> 
		  <language>EN</language> 
		</langusage> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item>No revisions to date</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </aarheader> 
  <frontmatter> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P1351</titleproper> 
		<subtitle>Koller | Pio C | 1904-1979 | Hungarian geneticist</subtitle> 
		<author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Margaret Stewart, Edinburgh
		  University Library Special Collections Division, 24 June 2002</author> 
		<publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division</publisher> 
		<date type="single" normal="20020624">24 June 2002</date> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 
  <aar id="GB-0237-NAHSTE-P1351"> 
	 <authcontrolarea> 
		<head>AUTHORITY CONTROL AREA</head> 
		<unitid label="Identity Code" encodinganalog="isaar11" type="NAHSTE"
		 repositorycode="0237">GB 0237 NAHSTE P1351</unitid> 
		<authentry encodinganalog="isaar13" label="Authority Entry"
		 authfilenumber="GB 0237 NAHSTE P1351" normal="Koller, Pio C">Koller | Pio C |
		  1904-1979 | Hungarian geneticist</authentry> 
	 </authcontrolarea> 
	 <infoarea encodinganalog="isaar2"> 
		<head>INFORMATION AREA</head> 
		<occsphere encodinganalog="isaar226"> 
		  <head>Occupation, Sphere of Activity</head> 
		  <p>Pius Charles Koller, who was one of the founders of cytogentics, was
			 born in Budapest where he first studied at the university for the priesthood
			 and took his doctoral degree in science in 
			 <date normal="1926" type="single">1926</date>. He then went to
			 Cambridge to work with Professor Reginald Crundall Punnett 
			 <date normal="1875/1967" type="life-span">1875-1967</date> at the
			 Institute of Genetics. There he met the American geneticist, Landsfield and
			 collaborated with him on studies of Drosophila. At Cambridge he researched the
			 chemistry of genetics with Professor Szent-György (<date normal="1893/1986"
			 type="life-span">1893-1986</date>), and later he also worked with Conrad Hal
			 Waddington (<date normal="1905/1975" type="life-span">1905-1975</date>).</p> 
		  <p>He first came to Edinburgh in 
			 <date normal="1929" type="single">1929</date> when Professor Francis
			 Crew (<date normal="1886/1973" type="life-span">1886-1973</date>), Buchanan
			 Professor of Animal Genetics invited Professor Landsfield to Edinburgh, and he
			 brought Pio Koller with him. At the invitation of Crew, and with an extension
			 of his Hungarian study grant Koller, who had been taught the technique of
			 genetical study on Drosophila by Landsfield, was able to remain at the
			 Institute of Animal Breeding at Edinburgh for a few months. Koller obtained his
			 Ph.D at Cambridge before returning to genetical work in Hungary. He came back
			 to Edinburgh in 
			 <date normal="1932" type="single">1932</date> by which time he had
			 learnt from Cyril Dean Darlington (<date normal="1903/1981"
			 type="life-span">1903-1981</date>), who was working on chromosomes at the John
			 Innes Institute, the cytological technique - the beginnings of the new field of
			 cytogenetics. Koller pursued the interpretation of the relationship between the
			 behaviour of the chromosome and the behaviour of the genetic material in rats,
			 mice and duck hybrids. His work focused on the little studied field of the
			 crossing of parental chromosomes to offspring, on how variation results from
			 chromosome behaviour, and the transferral of genes from the y to the x
			 chromosomes thus separating the sex-linked genes. This work took him into
			 animal breeding and the physiology of poultry and other birds. It was an
			 exciting period in the development of genetics at the Institute and Pio later
			 described Edinburgh as the centre for genetics in UK and Europe at this time.
			 </p> 
		  <p>During World War II Koller was unable to remain in Hungary and he
			 along with other young scientists who were refugees of the European
			 totalitarian regimes were encouraged by Crew to come to Edinburgh. In addition
			 to obtaining research grants for them that enabled their pioneering work to
			 continue, Crew also purchased a hostel in Newington for them all to live in.
			 Koller remained in Edinburgh throughout the war except for one year in 
			 <date normal="1936" type="single">1936</date> when he was a
			 Rockefeller Fellow, but he returned from California early to assist Crew with
			 the international Genetics Congress of 
			 <date normal="1939" type="single">1939</date>. In 
			 <date normal="1944" type="single">1944</date> Koller moved to London
			 as Research Cytologist at the Royal Cancer Hospital, and from 
			 <date normal="1946" type="single">1946</date> he was at the Chester
			 Beatty Research Institute in London. He had come to cancer work from the
			 experiments that he, Charlotte Auerbach (<date normal="1899/1994"
			 type="life-span">1899-1994</date>), Muller and others had carried out in
			 Edinburgh. As part of the war effort they were charged with discovering the
			 effects of mustard gas attacks and Koller noticed that the pathological effect
			 of the gas was, as in radiation sickness, on the cell's nucleus. He hoped that
			 mustard gas might be used to treat cancer cells in the same way that radiation
			 did. This work and the studies he carried out on radiation induced sterility
			 and the inheritance of damaged genetic material by the offspring of people
			 contaminated by radiation were his most important achievements. Koller was
			 Professor of Cytogenetics at the Institute of Cancer Research after he left
			 Edinburgh in 
			 <date normal="1944" type="single">1944</date> until his retirement in
			 
			 <date normal="1969" type="single">1969</date>.</p> 
		</occsphere> 
		<relships encodinganalog="isaar228"> 
		  <head>Relationships</head> 
		  <p> In addition to those colleagues mentioned above, Pio Koller also
			 collaborated with J.N. Pickard (<date normal="1928" type="single">1928</date>)
			 on rabbits, with Miller on sheep, with Bertold Wiesner on pregnancy testing,
			 with Guido Pontecorvo and with Alan Greenwood who succeeded Francis Crew as
			 Director of the Institute of Animal Breeding at the University of Edinburgh.
			 Koller also worked with Holding in London, and number of younger geneticists in
			 Stockholm, including Thelma Townsen and William Briden.</p> 
		</relships> 
		<otherinfo encodinganalog="isaar229"> 
		  <head>Other Significant Information</head> 
		  <p>Notable publications: Koller published numerous research papers in
			 the Journal of Genetics and the British Journal of Cancer.</p> 
		</otherinfo> 
		<honqual encodinganalog="nahste2210"> 
		  <head>Honours, Qualifications and Appointments</head> 
		  <p><date normal="1933" type="single">1933</date>: Awarded D.Sc,
			 University of Edinburgh</p> 
		  <p><date normal="1936/1937" type="appointmentdate">1936-1937</date>:
			 Appointed Rockefeller Fellow, Pasadena, California</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1970">1970</date>: Visiting Professor,
			 Harvard Medical School</p> 
		</honqual> 
	 </infoarea> 
	 <notearea encodinganalog="ISAAR3"> 
		<archnote encodinganalog="isaar31"> 
		  <head>Notes</head> 
		  <p>List of sources for the biographical information:</p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>University of Edinburgh Journal, 'Obituary', vol.
			 29</title>, ( <imprint><geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="517"
			 normal="Edinburgh">Edinburgh</geogname>, 
			 <publisher>University of Edinburgh</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication"
			 normal="1980">1980</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>Who's Who 1978</title>, ( <imprint><geogname
			 source="lcsh" authfilenumber="499" normal="Great Britain">Great
			 Britain</geogname>, 
			 <publisher>A and C Black Ltd</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication"
			  normal="1978">1978</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</archnote> 
		<rules encodinganalog="isaar32"> 
		  <head>Rules or Conventions</head> 
		  <p>Authority record created according to the<bibref><corpname
			 normal="National Council on Archives">National Council on
			 Archives</corpname><title>Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and
			 Corporate Names (NCA Rules)</title><imprint> 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1997">1997</date></imprint></bibref>
			 and <bibref><corpname normal="International Council on Archives">International
			 Council on Archives: Ad Hoc Committee on Descriptive
			 Standards</corpname><title>International Standard Archival Authority Record for
			 Corporate Bodies, Persona and Families (ISAAR)CPF</title><imprint> 
			 <date type="publication"
			  normal="1995">1995</date></imprint></bibref></p> 
		</rules> 
		<creationdate encodinganalog="isaar33"> 
		  <p>Personal name authority record compiled for the NAHSTE project by
			 <persname role="researcher" normal="Stewart, Margaret">Margaret
			 Stewart</persname>, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections Division, 
			 <date type="single" normal="20020624">24 June
				2002</date></p></creationdate> 
	 </notearea> 
  </aar>
</isaarcpf>
