<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE isaarcpf SYSTEM "isaar.dtd">
<isaarcpf> 
  <aarheader audience="internal" langencoding="ISO 639"
	aarstatus="edited-full-draft"> 
	 <aarid source="GB-0237" type="FPI"> "-//Edinburgh University Library
		Special Collections Division :: Archival Authority Records//DOCUMENT
		GB-0237-NAHSTE-P0389 20020404 //EN" </aarid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P0389</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>Lister | Sir | Joseph | 1827-1912 | baronet | professor of
			 surgery, University of Glasgow</subtitle> 
		  <author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Olivier Usher, Edinburgh
			 University Library Special Collections Division, 04 April 2002</author> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt> 
		  <publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
			 Division</publisher> 
		  <address> 
			 <addressline>The University of Edinburgh</addressline> 
			 <addressline>George Square</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Edinburgh EH8 9LJ</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Scotland</addressline> 
			 <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> 
		  </address> 
		  <date type="single" normal="20020404">04 April 2002</date> 
		</publicationstmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>XML generated using the ISAAR(CPF) DTD and XMetal template
		  prepared, as part of the NAHSTE project, in collaboration with the GASHE
		  project, by Sarah Higgins, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division, 2001, with assistance from Pete Johnston, Lesley Richmond and Moira
		  Rankin, Glasgow University Archive Services. </creation> 
		<langusage> 
		  <language>EN</language> 
		</langusage> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item>No revisions to date </item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </aarheader> 
  <frontmatter> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P0389</titleproper> 
		<subtitle>Lister | Sir | Joseph | 1827-1912 | baronet | professor of
		  surgery, University of Glasgow</subtitle> 
		<author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Olivier Usher , Edinburgh
		  University Library Special Collections Division, 04 April 2002</author> 
		<publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division</publisher> 
		<date type="single" normal="20020404">04 April 2002</date> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 
  <aar id="GB-0237-NAHSTE-P0389"> 
	 <authcontrolarea> 
		<head>AUTHORITY CONTROL AREA</head> 
		<unitid label="Identity Code" encodinganalog="isaar11" type="NAHSTE"
		 repositorycode="0237">GB 0237 NAHSTE P0389</unitid> 
		<authentry encodinganalog="isaar13" label="Authority Entry"
		 authfilenumber="GB 0237 NAHSTE P0389" normal="Lister, Sir, Joseph">Lister | Sir
		  | Joseph | 1827-1912 | baronet | professor of surgery, University of
		  Glasgow</authentry> 
	 </authcontrolarea> 
	 <infoarea encodinganalog="isaar2"> 
		<head>INFORMATION AREA</head> 
		<occsphere encodinganalog="isaar226"> 
		  <head>Occupation, Sphere of Activity</head> 
		  <p>Joseph Lister (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1827/1912">1827-1912</date>) is one of the most important names in the
			 history of surgery. The inventor of antiseptic surgery, Lister was born in 
			 <date type="single" normal="1827">1827</date> into a Quaker family,
			 the son of Joseph Jackson Lister, fellow of the Royal Society and inventor of
			 the achromatic lens for microscopes. Because of his non-conformist religious
			 beliefs, Lister was excluded from Oxford and Cambridge universities as well as
			 King's College, London, so he studied medicine at University College. Here, he
			 was influenced by opthalamist Wharton Jones and physiologist William
			 Sharpley.</p> 
		  <p>In 
			 <date type="single" normal="1853">1853</date>, Lister moved to
			 Edinburgh, and in 
			 <date type="chairdate" normal="1860">1860</date>, he took the chair
			 of clinical surgery at the University of Glasgow. It was here - and at the
			 attached Royal Infirmary - that he became deeply involved with antiseptics. His
			 work brought him into regular contact with the atrocious conditions at the
			 Infirmary, where amputations had no more than a 60% survival rate, and
			 operations to the abdomen and cranium were not even attempted because of the
			 enormous risk of infection. Lister experimented with his new techniques on
			 compound fracture victims, because their high mortality rates, and their
			 frequency in an industrial city such as Glasgow made them ideal for repeated
			 experimentation. His work continued when he obtained chairs in the University
			 of Edinburgh in 
			 <date type="chairdate" normal="1869">1869</date> and University of
			 London in 
			 <date type="chairdate" normal="1877">1877</date>.</p> 
		  <p>Influenced by the theories of Pasteur, who had demolished the
			 accepted belief that infection was due either to oxidation of the wound or
			 'spontaneous generation' of pathogens, Lister began to experiment with chemical
			 methods of preventing the infection of wounds by airborne bacilli. His early
			 experiments involved the coating of wounds with a potent dose of carbolic acid
			 (phenol, a coal tar derivate), which formed an antiseptic crust of coagulated
			 blood on the wound. His earliest attempts at this procedure were unsuccessful,
			 but he soon began to have remarkable improvements in success rates. His method
			 was also applied to tuberculosis of the wrist joint, with a similar degree of
			 success (it saved a number of lives, and also a number of hands from
			 amputation). The drawback of the carbolic acid treatment, however, was the
			 toxicity of the acid. He was aware that the damage caused by the acid treatment
			 could also damage the body's repair mechanisms.</p> 
		  <p>This led to the development of a number of antiseptic wound
			 dressings designed to provide a disinfectant barrier between the wound and the
			 surrounding air, while reducing to a minimum the carbolic acid entering the
			 damaged tissue. This led to a dressing made of shellac (plaster) mixed with 25%
			 carbolic acid, spread on calico and coated with gutta-percha dissolved in
			 benzene. Thus, the carbolic acid prevented bacteria from entering the dressing
			 and the gutta-percha prevented the carbolic acid from entering the wound. He
			 also introduced the sterilisation of surgical instruments with heat and
			 carbolic acid and the frequent cleaning of the surgeon's hands during an
			 operation with a mild antiseptic solution. This avoided the caustic
			 disinfectant from having to enter the wound while ensuring a germ-free
			 environment. A carbolic acid spray (to disinfect the atmosphere of the
			 operating theatre) was tried but eventually abandoned because the spray's very
			 marginal benefits did not justify its dangerous side effects (carbolic acid
			 inhalation). Cleanliness was a far better disinfectant for operating rooms.</p>
		  
		  <p>Lister's other innovations were improved ligatures (which, because
			 of disinfection, could be fully embedded in the wound, without worry about
			 infection, and therefore did not need to hang out of the wound as it healed)
			 and the introduction into Britain of drainage tubes - which he used in an
			 operation on Queen Victoria in his role as Surgeon in Ordinary to the
			 monarch.</p> 
		  <p>Despite the widespread academic hostility to and scepticism about
			 his innovations (especially on his return to London), Lister served as
			 president of the Royal Society (<date type="appointmentspan"
			 normal="1895/1900">1895-1900</date>) and the British Association for the
			 Advancement of Science (<date type="appointmentdate"
			 normal="1896">1896</date>), as well as being a founding member of the British
			 Institute of Preventative Medicine - which now bears his name. On his death,
			 there was considerable support for a burial in Westminster Abbey, but he had
			 insisted on being buried with his wife.</p> 
		</occsphere> 
		<relships encodinganalog="isaar228"> 
		  <head>Relationships</head> 
		  <p>Joseph Lister was the son of Joseph Jackson Lister, a Fellow of the
			 Royal Society and inventor of the achromatic doublet lens.</p> 
		</relships> 
		<otherinfo encodinganalog="isaar229"> 
		  <head>Other Significant Information</head> 
		  <p>Notable publications:</p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>The Collected Papers of Joseph, Baron Lister</title>,
			 <imprint> (<date type="publication"
			 normal="1909">1909</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</otherinfo> 
		<honqual encodinganalog="nahste2210"> 
		  <head>Honours, Qualifications and Appointments</head> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1852">1852</date>: Awarded Batchelor of
			 Medicine (MB), University of London</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1852">1852</date>: Awarded Fellowship of
			 the Royal College of Surgeons (FRCS)</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1860">1860</date>: Elected
			 Fellow of the Royal Society</p> 
		  <p><date type="chairspan" normal="1860/1869">1860-1869</date>:
			 Appointed Professor of Surgery, University of Glasgow</p> 
		  <p><date type="chairspan" normal="1869/1877">1869-1877</date>:
			 Appointed Chair of Clinical Surgery, University of Edinburgh</p> 
		  <p><date type="chairspan" normal="1877/1892">1877-1892</date>:
			 Appointed Chair of Clinical Surgery, King's College, London</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1878">1878</date>: Appointed
			 Surgeon in Ordinary to Queen Victoria</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1881">1880</date>: Awarded Honorary
			 Doctorate, University of Cambridge</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1880">1880</date>: Awarded Honorary
			 Doctorate, University of Oxford</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1881">1881</date>: Awarded Boudet
			 Prize</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1883">1883</date>: Awarded Baronetcy of
			 Lyme Regis</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1885">1885</date>: Awarded Prussian
			 Honour "pour le m&#x00C3;&#x00A9;rite"</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1893">1893</date>: Elected
			 Foreign Secretary, Royal Society</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentspan" normal="1894/1900">1894-1900</date>:
			 Elected President of the Royal Society</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1896">1896</date>: President,
			 British Association for the Advancement of Science</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1902">1902</date>: Awarded Order of
			 Merit</p> 
		</honqual> 
	 </infoarea> 
	 <notearea encodinganalog="ISAAR3"> 
		<archnote encodinganalog="isaar31"> 
		  <head>Notes</head> 
		  <p>List of sources for the biographical information:</p> 
		  <p><bibref>
			 <persname source="ncarules" normal="Gillispie, Charles C"
			  role="editor">Gillispie, Charles C</persname>, <title
			 render="italic">Dictionary of Scientific Biography, vol VIII</title>, ( 
			 <imprint>
			 <geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="483"
			  normal="New York (N.Y.), United States">New York </geogname>, 
			 <publisher>Scribner's</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1973"
			 certainty="certain">1973</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title render="italic">Concise Dictionary of National
			 Biography, vol II, 1901-1970</title>, (<imprint>
			 <geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="532" normal="Oxford (England)">Oxford
			 </geogname>, 
			 <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1982"
			 certainty="certain">1982</date>)</imprint></bibref> </p> 
		  <p><bibref><title render="italic">Encyclopaedia Britannica, vol
			 14</title>, (<imprint>
			 <geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="502"
			 normal="Chicago (Illinois), United States">Chicago</geogname>, 
			 <publisher>William Benton</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1964"
			 certainty="certain">1964</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</archnote> 
		<rules encodinganalog="isaar32"> 
		  <head>Rules or Conventions</head> 
		  <p>Authority record created according to the <bibref>
			 <corpname normal="National Council on Archives">National Council on
			 Archives</corpname> <title>Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and
			 Corporate Names (NCA Rules)</title> <imprint> 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1997">1997</date></imprint></bibref>
			 and <bibref> <corpname normal="International Council on Archives">International
			 Council on Archives: Ad Hoc Committee on Descriptive Standards</corpname>
			 <title>International Standard Archival Authority Record for Corporate Bodies,
			 Persons and Families (ISAAR)CPF</title> <imprint> 
			 <date type="publication"
			 normal="1995">1995</date></imprint></bibref></p> 
		</rules> 
		<creationdate encodinganalog="isaar33"> 
		  <p>Personal name authority record compiled for the NAHSTE project by
			 <persname role="archivist" normal="Usher, Olivier">Usher, Olivier</persname>,
			 Edinburgh University Library Special Collections Division, 
			 <date type="single" normal="20020404">04 April
				2002</date></p></creationdate> 
	 </notearea> 
  </aar>
</isaarcpf>
