<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE isaarcpf SYSTEM "file:///C|/Program%20Files/SoftQuad/XMetaL%202/Rules/isaar.dtd">
<isaarcpf> 
  <aarheader audience="internal" langencoding="ISO 639" aarstatus="draft"> 
	 <aarid source="GB-0237" type="FPI"> "-//Edinburgh University Library
		Special Collections Division :: Archival Authority Records//DOCUMENT
		GB-0237-Baillie-P2488 20020904//EN" </aarid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>GB 0237 Baillie P2488</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>Hetherington | Sir | Hector James Wright | 1888-1965 | social
			 philosopher</subtitle> 
		  <author>Originally compiled for the GASHE project by John O&apos;Brien,
			 Glasgow University Archive Services, 04 September 2002. Amended for the Baillie
			 Project by Grant Buttars, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
			 Division, 03 June 2003</author> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt> 
		  <publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
			 Division</publisher> 
		  <address> 
			 <addressline>The University of Edinburgh</addressline> 
			 <addressline>George Square</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Edinburgh EH8 9LJ</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Scotland</addressline> 
			 <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> 
		  </address> 
		  <date type="single" normal="20030603">03 June 2003</date> 
		</publicationstmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>XML generated using the ISAAR(CPF) DTD and XMetal template
		  prepared, as part of the NAHSTE project, in collaboration with the GASHE
		  project, by Sarah Higgins, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division, 2001, with assistance from Pete Johnston, Lesley Richmond and Moira
		  Rankin, Glasgow University Archive Services. </creation> 
		<langusage> 
		  <language>ENG</language> 
		</langusage> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item>No revisions to date </item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </aarheader> 
  <frontmatter> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<titleproper>GB 0237 Baillie P2488</titleproper> 
		<subtitle>Hetherington | Sir | Hector James Wright | 1888-1965 | social
		  philosopher</subtitle> 
		<author>Originally compiled for the GASHE project by John O&apos;Brien,
		  Glasgow University Archive Services, 04 September 2002.Amended for the Baillie
		  Project by Grant Buttars, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division, 03 June 2003</author> 
		<publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division</publisher> 
		<date type="single" normal="20030603">03 June 2003</date> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 
  <aar id="GB-0237-Baillie-P2488"> 
	 <authcontrolarea> 
		<head>AUTHORITY CONTROL AREA</head> 
		<unitid label="Identity Code" encodinganalog="isaar11" type="Baillie"
		 repositorycode="0237" countrycode="GB">GB 0237 Baillie P2488</unitid> 
		<authentry encodinganalog="isaar13" label="Authority Entry"
		 authfilenumber="GB 0237 Baillie P2488"
		 normal="Hetherington, Sir Hector James Wright">Hetherington | Sir | Hector
		  James Wright | 1888-1965 | social philosopher</authentry> 
	 </authcontrolarea> 
	 <infoarea encodinganalog="isaar2"> 
		<head>INFORMATION AREA</head> 
		<occsphere encodinganalog="isaar226"> 
		  <head>Occupation, Sphere of Activity</head> 
		  <p>Sir Hector James Wright Hetherington (1888-1965) was born July 1888,
			 in Cowdenbeath, Scotland. He grew up in Tillicoultry, and was educated at
			 Dollar Academy, before entering Glasgow University in 1905. He studied
			 classics, philosophy, and later economics, graduating M.A. with honours in
			 1907. He had intended to become a minister of the United Free Church, but was
			 persuaded by Sir Henry Jones, Professor of moral philosophy, to become his
			 assistant.</p> 
		  <p>In 1914, he left Glasgow to take up the post of Lecturer in
			 philosophy, at Sheffield University. He only stayed in Sheffield a year, before
			 accepting the Chair of philosophy at Cardiff. In 1920, he was appointed
			 Principal of the Royal Albert Memorial College, Exeter. Under
			 Hetherington&apos;s guidance, the College was reconstituted as the University
			 College of the South West of England, and put on the grant list of the
			 University Grants Committee. This set the College on the path to full status as
			 the University of Exeter in 1955. He also oversaw an improvement in the
			 College&apos;s financial position, and an expansion of the College campus.
			 There was a similar expansion in teaching facilities, with a new department in
			 Adult Education, and investment in the Law department.</p> 
		  <p>In 1924, Hetherington accepted the post of Professor of moral
			 philosophy at Glasgow University. However his stay at Glasgow was short, and in
			 1927, he moved to Liverpool to become Vice-Chancellor of the University. During
			 his nine years at Liverpool University, his main concern was the extension of
			 the Library and the Students Union. Financial problems meant that other
			 expansion projects had to be put on hold. The Union extension was completed in
			 1935. Hetherington did not see the Library extension completed but his fund
			 raising was vital to the project, and he received the gift of £100,000 for the
			 extension, the largest donation that the University had received. Hetherington
			 also saw the School of Architecture rehoused, and the planning for a new
			 gymnasium and Organic Chemistry Laboratory was started. He also steered the
			 University into calmer financial waters with a significant reduction of the
			 University&apos;s capital debt.</p> 
		  <p>In 1936, Hetherington was appointed Principal of Glasgow University,
			 a post he would hold for the rest of his career. The University had suffered a
			 period of contraction and financial stagnation during the depression years, and
			 the new Principal would have to deal with the needs and difficulties brought
			 about by the Second World War. Nevertheless, Hetherington tackled the need for
			 new buildings with typical energy, and aided by a building grant from the
			 University Grants Committee, saw the completion of the Student&apos;s Reading
			 Room. This was just the beginning, and over the course of his term of office,
			 Glasgow saw an impressive program of expansion. This included a new Engineering
			 building, buildings for Surgery and for Virology, a building for Modern
			 Languages, the Stevenson building, a Veterinary Hospital, extensions to the
			 Anatomy and Zoology departments, and reconstruction of parts of the main
			 building to give better accommodation to the departments of Mathematics,
			 Political Economy, and Geography, as well as to the University offices. Plans
			 were also drawn up for two Halls of Residence, a Refectory, a Mathematics
			 building, a new Queen Margaret Union, the Adam Smith building, a Genetics
			 building, and a new Library.</p> 
		  <p>Hetherington also introduced improvements to the teaching facilities
			 of the University with many new Chairs, new departments of non-professorial
			 standing, and additional teaching staff in all departments. He brought in a new
			 policy for hiring staff, to ensure the best people were found, and encouraged
			 the setting up of training schemes to address the problem of a lack of highly
			 trained technical staff in scientific departments.</p> 
		  <p>Hetherington encouraged the students to play a full part in
			 University life, regularly visiting the Freshers camp, the OTC, and the Halls
			 of Residence, and supporting the work of the Graduates Association in linking
			 graduates clubs throughout the world. He also oversaw the University&apos;s
			 fifth centenary celebrations. He was a member of various committees, and was
			 Chairman of the Committee of Principals and Vice-Chancellors, of the Colonial
			 University Grants Committee, and of the Commission on the Royal University of
			 Malta.</p> 
		  <p>He retired in 1961, and died suddenly in London, 15 January
			 1965.</p> 
		</occsphere> 
		<relships encodinganalog="isaar228"> 
		  <head>Relationships</head> 
		  <p>None</p> 
		</relships> 
		<otherinfo encodinganalog="isaar229"> 
		  <head>Other Significant Information</head> 
		  <p>None</p> 
		</otherinfo> 
		<honqual encodinganalog="nahste2210"> 
		  <head>Honours, Qualifications and Appointments</head> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1907" type="single">1907</date>: M.A. University of
			 Glasgow</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1915/1920" type="inclusive">1915-1920</date>: Professor
			 of philosophy, Cardiff University</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1920/1924" type="inclusive">1920-1924</date>:
			 Principal, Royal Albert Memorial College, Exeter</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1924/1927" type="inclusive">1924-1927</date>: Professor
			 of moral philosophy, University of Glasgow</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1927" type="single">1927</date>: LL.D.</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1927/1936" type="inclusive">1927-1936</date>:
			 Vice-Chancellor, Liverpool University</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1936" type="single">1936</date>: Knighthood</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1936/1961" type="inclusive">1936-1961</date>:
			 Principal, University of Glasgow</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1948" type="single">1948</date>: K.B.E.</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1961" type="single">1961</date>: Freedom of the city of
			 Glasgow</p> 
		  <p> 
			 <date normal="1962" type="single">1962</date>: G.B.E.</p> 
		</honqual> 
	 </infoarea> 
	 <notearea encodinganalog="ISAAR3"> 
		<archnote encodinganalog="isaar31"> 
		  <head>Notes</head> 
		  <p>List of sources for the biographical information:</p> 
		  <p> <bibref>
			 <persname source="ncarules" normal="Hutcheson, Robert T"
			  role="author">Hutcheson, Robert T.</persname>, <title>Hector Hetherington
			 1888-1965, The College Courant, Vol.18, No.34</title><imprint> Glasgow, 
			 <publisher>University of Glasgow</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1965"
			  certainty="certain">1965</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</archnote> 
		<rules encodinganalog="isaar32"> 
		  <head>Rules or Conventions</head> 
		  <p>Authority record created according to the <bibref>
			 <corpname normal="National Council on Archives">National Council on
			 Archives</corpname><title>Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and
			 Corporate Names (NCA Rules)</title><imprint> 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1997">1997</date></imprint></bibref>
			 and <bibref> <corpname normal="International Council on Archives">International
			 Council on Archives: Ad Hoc Committee on Descriptive
			 Standards</corpname><title>International Standard Archival Authority Record for
			 Corporate Bodies, Persons and Families (ISAAR)CPF</title><imprint> 
			 <date type="publication"
			  normal="1995">1995</date></imprint></bibref></p> 
		</rules> 
		<creationdate encodinganalog="isaar33"> 
		  <p>Personal name authority record compiled for the GASHE project by
			 <persname role="archivist" normal="O&apos;Brien, John">John
			 O&apos;Brien</persname>, Glasgow University Archive Services, 
			 <date type="single" normal="20020904">04 September 2002</date></p> 
		  <p>Original GASHE ID: P0009</p></creationdate> 
	 </notearea> 
  </aar>
</isaarcpf>
