<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE isaarcpf SYSTEM "isaar.dtd">
<isaarcpf> 
  <aarheader audience="internal" langencoding="ISO 639"
	aarstatus="edited-full-draft"> 
	 <aarid source="GB-0335" type="FPI"> "-//Edinburgh University Library
		Special Collections Division :: Archival Authority Records//DOCUMENT
		GB-0237-NAHSTE-P0263 20020308 //EN" </aarid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P0263</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>Gregory | James | 1638-1675 | professor of mathematics, St
			 Andrews and Edinburgh</subtitle> 
		  <author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Duncan Fisher, Edinburgh
			 University Library Special Collections Division, 8 March 2002</author> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt> 
		  <publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
			 Division</publisher> 
		  <address> 
			 <addressline>The University of Edinburgh</addressline> 
			 <addressline>George Square</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Edinburgh EH8 9LJ</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Scotland</addressline> 
			 <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> 
		  </address> 
		  <date type="single" normal="20020308">8 March 2002</date> 
		</publicationstmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>XML generated using the ISAAR(CPF) DTD and XMetal template
		  prepared, as part of the NAHSTE project, in collaboration with the GASHE
		  project, by Sarah Higgins, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division, 2001, with assistance from Pete Johnston, Lesley Richmond and Moira
		  Rankin, Glasgow University Archive Services. </creation> 
		<langusage> 
		  <language>EN</language> 
		</langusage> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item>No revisions to date</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </aarheader> 
  <frontmatter> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P0263</titleproper> 
		<subtitle>Gregory | James | 1638-1675 | professor of mathematics, St
		  Andrews and Edinburgh</subtitle> 
		<author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Duncan Fisher,</author> 
		<publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division</publisher> 
		<date type="single" normal="20020308">8 March 2002</date> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 
  <aar id="GB-0237-NAHSTE-P0263"> 
	 <authcontrolarea> 
		<head>AUTHORITY CONTROL AREA</head> 
		<unitid label="Identity Code" encodinganalog="isaar11" type="NAHSTE"
		 repositorycode="0237">GB 0237 NAHSTE P0263</unitid> 
		<authentry encodinganalog="isaar13" label="Authority Entry"
		 authfilenumber="GB 0237 NAHSTE P0263" normal="Gregory, James">Gregory | James |
		  1638-1675 | professor of mathematics, St Andrews and Edinburgh</authentry> 
	 </authcontrolarea> 
	 <infoarea encodinganalog="isaar2"> 
		<head>INFORMATION AREA</head> 
		<occsphere encodinganalog="isaar226"> 
		  <head>Occupation, Sphere of Activity</head> 
		  <p>James Gregorie (he favoured this Scottish spelling over 'Gregory')
			 was born in Drumoak, near Aberdeen, Scotland, in 
			 <date type="birth" normal="163811">November 1638</date>. His father
			 having died young, he was sent by his older brother to Aberdeen to attend
			 grammar school and then Marischal College. Their mother had taught her sons to
			 love geometry, and everyone hoped that James in particular would developed his
			 clear talent in mathematics, and also his growing interests in optics and
			 astronomy. </p> 
		  <p>The young graduate established a grown-up reputation in London in 
			 <date type="single" normal="1663">1663</date>, with a digest of what
			 he had learned thus far, the Optica Promota. It was unremarkable except for
			 some very original thoughts on a compact reflecting telescope. Suddenly he had
			 admirers in the scientific establishment. They included John Collins,
			 accountant and science gossip, Robert Hooke, the Oxford physicist who
			 eventually built the telescope, and Sir Robert Moray, Scots polymath and
			 founding member of the Royal Society, who introduced him to as many influential
			 men as he could. The telescope design also attracted the attention of a young
			 man in Cambridge, one Isaac Newton, who was at work on a similar project of his
			 own; Gregorie carried on much friendly correspondence with him later. </p> 
		  <p>He bolstered his reputation in<date type="single"
			 normal="1664">1664</date> by moving to Padua for a few years, for study under
			 Stefano degli Angeli, pupil of Evangelista Torricelli (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1608/1647">1608-1647</date>). There he brought out two works of
			 proto-calculus, the Vera circuli et hyperbolae quadratura and the Geometriae
			 pars universalis. These, breathlessly reviewed by Collins, secured his
			 admission to the Royal Society upon his return. He updated his colleagues, who
			 were eager to hear, on continental science, and he entered the professional
			 lists on his own, with an Exercitationes geometricae. These were meant as a
			 sortie against Christian Huygens and Nicholas Mercator. </p> 
		  <p>By 
			 <date type="appointmentdate" normal="1669">1669</date> his prestige
			 was great enough that Sir Robert could help find him a job. He arranged an
			 appointment to the new chair of mathematics at St Andrews. Gregorie went,
			 married a local widow, and settled into teaching basic maths and science. He
			 found the post disappointingly provincial. Through Collins he kept
			 corresponding with the scientific establishment, which continued to hold him in
			 high esteem. Even Huygens, he learned, his erstwhile enemy, tried for a while
			 to persuade Louis XIV to invite him to Paris on a stipend from the
			 Acad&#x00C3;&#x00A9;mie des Sciences. </p> 
		  <p>Indeed St Andrews was comparitively inward-looking. Not only could
			 Gregorie not evangelize for higher mathematics, he was hindered in his plans
			 for a formal astronomy programme, complete with an observatory. He had been
			 known to go door-to-door to raise funds for this. However, in 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1672">1672</date>, in exchange for
			 contributing a little essay to a colleague's scurrilous book against a Glasgow
			 rival, (the <bibref><title>Great and New Art of Weighing
			 Vanity</title></bibref>), he was given the University's commission to proceed
			 at last. Its grateful author, regent William Sanders, wrested it from a stoutly
			 resistant faculty. Gregorie left for London in raptures in 
			 <date type="single" normal="1673">1673</date>, meaning to caucus with
			 astronomer John Flamsteed, to buy equipment, and to meet Newton if he could.
			 </p> 
		  <p>He had the misfortune to return to St Andrews after a student
			 uprising. Young scholars had rebelled, sure enough, over the issue of
			 antiquated curriculum. Regents resentful of Gregorie's established modishness
			 now withheld his servants and salary, and debarred professional visits from
			 colleagues. Gregorie was compelled by 
			 <date type="appointmentdate" normal="1674">1674</date> to accept a
			 new professorship of mathematics at Edinburgh. There, at last, he had money and
			 encouragement, and he was not denied contact with colleagues. Sadly, he was
			 felled by a stroke in October of the very next year, at the age of 37, and was
			 dead a few days later. It was fitting at least that he was stricken before a
			 telescope, showing the moons of Jupiter to enthusiastic students. </p> 
		  <p>Denied by geography much knowledge of the parallel mathematical work
			 in Britain and abroad, James Gregorie nevertheless discovered for himself the
			 general interpolation and biomial theorems, derived a number of trigonometric
			 series, notably for the natural and logarithmic tangent and secant, and found a
			 series solution to a problem posed by Kepler, employing 20 years before Newton
			 a Taylor development of a function in terms of its nth order derivatives. In
			 applied science, in dynamics in particular, he bridged Galieleo's Discorsi and
			 Newton's Principia, proposing solutions to dozens of astronomical problems,
			 ranging from planetary ellipses to designing the 'catadioptric' telescope of
			 mirrors and lenses. Much of the correspondence from his short career is lost to
			 us, and he was reluctant to publish. But all evidence suggests that James
			 Gregorie was a weightier figure than tradition has allowed. Newton, in
			 particular, almost certainly owes him more than anyone has yet recognized. </p>
		  
		</occsphere> 
		<relships encodinganalog="isaar228"> 
		  <head>Relationships</head> 
		  <p>John Collins (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1625/1683">1625-1683</date>), maths teacher, book seller, and
			 accountant, collected and disseminated scientific news zealously, a friendly
			 register of all the latest developments. He was famously encouraging of young
			 mathematicians like Gregorie. Christian (or Christiaan) Huygens (<date
			 type="life-span" normal="1629/1695">1629-1695</date>), the formidable Fleming,
			 was famous by James Gregorie's scientific coming-of-age for his work in the
			 early calculus, statics, and practical astronomy, and above all, for inventing
			 the pendulum clock. Sir Robert Moray, or Murray, or Murrey (<date
			 type="life-span" normal="1603/1678" certainty="uncertain">c1608-1673</date>),
			 was a professional diplomat, friendly with Richelieu, Mazarin, and Charles II.
			 His avocational interest in chemistry made him a formidable lobbyist for
			 scientific enterprises like the Royal Society. Gregorie probably never met Sir
			 Isaac Newton (<date type="life-span" normal="1642/1727">1642-1727</date>) in
			 person. Stefano degli Angeli (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1623/1697">1623-1697</date>) was a Bologna-trained statics expert. He
			 was also a priest, in which capacity he remained even while occupying the chair
			 in mathematics in Padua. Nicholas Mercator (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1615/1692" certainty="uncertain">c1620-1687</date>), was England's
			 German-born expert on logarithms, and the designer of the fountains at
			 Versailles. John Flamsteed (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1646/1719">1646-1719</date>), not appointed astronomer royal until 
			 <date type="appointmentdate" normal="1675">1675</date>, was still
			 teaching himself the art, enrolled as a non-resident student in Cambridge. When
			 James Gregorie went to see him, Sir Jonas Moore, Master of the Royal Ordnance,
			 was about to propose that Flamsteed be installed in an observatory at Chelsea
			 College. Nephew David Gregory (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1659/1708">1659-1708</date>), who favoured this English spelling of the
			 family name, sat eventually in the maths chair at Edinburgh and then the
			 Savilian chair of astronomy in Oxford, but was still a student in Marischal
			 College when his Uncle James died. </p> 
		</relships> 
		<otherinfo encodinganalog="isaar229"> 
		  <head>Other Significant Information</head> 
		  <p>Notable publications: </p> 
		  <p><bibref><title> Optica Promota, Seu Abdita Radiorum Reflexorum &amp;
			 Refractorum Mysteria, Geometrica Enucleata; cui Subnectitur Appendix,
			 Subtilissimorum Astronomiae Problemata in Resolutionem Exhibens</title>, ( 
			 <imprint>London,<date type="publication" normal="1663"
			 certainty="certain">1663</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title> Vera Circuli et Hyperbolae Quadratura, in Propria
			 Sua Proportionis Specie, Inventa &amp; Demonstrata</title>, ( 
			 <imprint>Padua,<date type="publication" normal="1667"
			 certainty="certain">1667</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title> Geometriae pars Universalis, Inserviens Quantitatum
			 Curvarum Transmutatationi &amp; Mensurae</title>, ( <imprint>Padua,<date
			 type="publication" normal="1668"
			 certainty="certain">1668</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>Exercitationes Geometricae</title>, ( 
			 <imprint>London,<date type="publication" normal="1668"
			 certainty="certain">1668</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</otherinfo> 
		<honqual encodinganalog="nahste2210"> 
		  <head>Honours, Qualifications and Appointments</head> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1668">1668</date>: Elected
			 member, the Royal Society of London</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1669">1669</date>: Appointed
			 Professor of Mathematics, University of St Andrews</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1674">1674</date>: Appointed
			 Professor of Mathematics, University of Edinburgh </p> 
		</honqual> 
	 </infoarea> 
	 <notearea encodinganalog="ISAAR3"> 
		<archnote encodinganalog="isaar31"> 
		  <head>Notes</head> 
		  <p>List of sources for the biographical information:</p> 
		  <p><bibref><persname source="ncarules" normal="Gillespie, CC "
			 role="editor">Gillespie, CC, ed</persname>, <title>Dictionary of Scientific
			 Biography</title>, (<imprint><geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="530"
			 normal="New York">New York</geogname>, 
			 <publisher>Scribner's</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1970/1990"
			  certainty="certain">1970-1990</date>)</imprint>, s.v. "Gregory, James" by
			 <persname normal="Whiteside, DT" role="author">DT Whiteside</persname></bibref>
			 </p> 
		  <p><bibref><persname source="ncarules"
			 normal="Turnbull, Herbert Westren" role="author">Turnbull, Herbert
			 Westren</persname>, <title>James Gregory. Tercentenary Memorial Volume</title>,
			 (<imprint>London, for the Royal Society of Edinburgh 
			 <publisher>G Bell &amp; Sons Ltd</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1939"
			  certainty="certain">1939</date>)</imprint></bibref> </p> 
		</archnote> 
		<rules encodinganalog="isaar32"> 
		  <head>Rules or Conventions</head> 
		  <p>Authority record created according to the <bibref>
			 <corpname normal="National Council on Archives">National Council on
			 Archives</corpname> <title>Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and
			 Corporate Names (NCA Rules)</title> <imprint> 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1997">1997</date></imprint></bibref>
			 and <bibref> <corpname normal="International Council on Archives">International
			 Council on Archives: Ad Hoc Committee on Descriptive Standards</corpname>
			 <title>International Standard Archival Authority Record for Corporate Bodies,
			 Persons and Families (ISAAR)CPF</title> <imprint> 
			 <date type="publication"
			  normal="1995">1995</date></imprint></bibref></p> 
		</rules> 
		<creationdate encodinganalog="isaar33"> 
		  <p>Personal name authority record compiled for the NAHSTE project by
			 <persname normal="Fisher, Duncan" role="researcher">Duncan Fisher</persname>,
			 Edinburgh University Library Special Collections Division, 
			 <date type="single" normal="20020308">08 March
				2002</date></p></creationdate> 
	 </notearea> 
  </aar>
</isaarcpf>
