<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE isaarcpf SYSTEM "isaar.dtd">
<isaarcpf> 
  <aarheader audience="internal" langencoding="ISO 639"
	aarstatus="edited-full-draft"> 
	 <aarid source="GB-0237" type="FPI"> "-//Edinburgh University Library
		Special Collections Division :: Archival Authority Records//DOCUMENT
		GB-0237-NAHSTE-P0305 20020530 //EN" </aarid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P0305</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>Huxley | Thomas Henry | 1825-1895 | man of science</subtitle>
		  
		  <author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Olivier Usher , Edinburgh
			 University Library Special Collections Division, 30 May 2002</author> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt> 
		  <publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
			 Division</publisher> 
		  <address> 
			 <addressline>The University of Edinburgh</addressline> 
			 <addressline>George Square</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Edinburgh EH8 9LJ</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Scotland</addressline> 
			 <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> 
		  </address> 
		  <date type="single" normal="20020530">30 May 2002</date> 
		</publicationstmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>XML generated using the ISAAR(CPF) DTD and XMetal template
		  prepared, as part of the NAHSTE project, in collaboration with the GASHE
		  project, by Sarah Higgins, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division, 2001, with assistance from Pete Johnston, Lesley Richmond and Moira
		  Rankin, Glasgow University Archive Services. </creation> 
		<langusage> 
		  <language>EN</language> 
		</langusage> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item>No revisions to date </item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </aarheader> 
  <frontmatter> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<titleproper>GB 0237 NAHSTE P0305</titleproper> 
		<subtitle>Huxley | Thomas Henry | 1825-1895 | man of science</subtitle> 
		<author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Olivier Usher, Edinburgh
		  University Library Special Collections Division, 30 May 2002</author> 
		<publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division</publisher> 
		<date type="single" normal="20020530">30 May 2002</date> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 
  <aar id="GB-0237-NAHSTE-P0305"> 
	 <authcontrolarea> 
		<head>AUTHORITY CONTROL AREA</head> 
		<unitid label="Identity Code" encodinganalog="isaar11" type="NAHSTE"
		 repositorycode="0237">GB 0237 NAHSTE P0305</unitid> 
		<authentry encodinganalog="isaar13" label="Authority Entry"
		 authfilenumber="GB 0237 NAHSTE P0305" normal="Huxley, Thomas Henry">Huxley |
		  Thomas Henry | 1825-1895 | man of science</authentry> 
	 </authcontrolarea> 
	 <infoarea encodinganalog="isaar2"> 
		<head>INFORMATION AREA</head> 
		<occsphere encodinganalog="isaar226"> 
		  <head>Occupation, Sphere of Activity</head> 
		  <p>Thomas Henry Huxley (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1825/1895">1825-1895</date>), popularly known as 'Darwin's Bulldog'
			 because of his defence of the theories of Charles Darwin (<date
			 type="life-span" normal="1809/1882">1809-1882</date>), was a much more complex
			 person than this simplistic image of an unquestioning defender of Darwinism
			 would suggest. Though his father was a school mathematics teacher and assistant
			 headmaster, Huxley had little formal schooling (by some accounts, no more than
			 two years in all), and he was largely self-taught. His talent for drawing,
			 which was useful to him in later life when describing the animals he
			 investigated, was already clear when he was a child. He had initially hoped to
			 study mechanical engineering, but was pressured by his family into studying
			 medicine. Aged 14, Huxley attended a post-mortem, and seems to have caught a
			 disease or poisoning (the nature of which is not known precisely) that affected
			 his health for the rest of his life, requiring occasional recuperative trips to
			 the countryside.</p> 
		  <p>Huxley studied medecine at Charing Cross hospital, and graduated
			 with an MB from the recently founded University of London in 
			 <date type="single" normal="1845">1845</date>. Soon after, he joined
			 the Royal Navy, and was attached, first to HMS Victory (Nelson's ship) when he
			 worked at Haslar hospital, then to HMS Rattlesnake. It was on this ship that he
			 took part - officially as ship's surgeon - in the expedition of 
			 <date type="inclusive" normal="1846/1850">1846-1850</date> to Torres
			 Straights, near Australia. During this trip, with little equipment, Huxley
			 studied the marine life of the region. One of his papers, on the subject of the
			 organisms he had observed, was published in the Royal Society's
			 <bibref><title>Philosophical Transactions</title></bibref> while he was still
			 in Australia, and, shortly after his return to Britain, the work he had carried
			 out gained him election to the Royal Society. He took leave from the Navy to
			 carry out scientific work, but he entered into argument with the navy over
			 payment for his scientific work, and eventually left the forces, causing him
			 financial trouble that was resolved when he was recruited by the Royal School
			 of Mines (a precursor of modern-day Imperial College) as a lecturer in Natural
			 History.</p> 
		  <p>Huxley's scientific work can be defined as following three fairly
			 distinct periods (though there is, of course some overlap). The first, carried
			 out when he was studying, was in the field of human anatomy. During this
			 period, he discovered a previously unknown layer in the root of hair, which is
			 now know as Huxley's layer. The second period of work coincided largely with
			 the expedition and its aftermath. The subject of study here was microscopic
			 marine life. He reclassified hydroid polyps and medusae as belonging to one
			 group, hydrozoa. The connection he made was based on their dual membrane
			 structure, a feature he compared to the serous and mucous structures of embryos
			 of higher animals. The animals he categorised thus form the core of the group
			 now known as coelenterata. Later, he investigated the embryology of
			 vertebrates, saying that investigating adult forms of animals is not sufficient
			 to conclusively prove that two species are similar. Huxley insisted that it was
			 necessary to examine the entire development of the animals from conception to
			 make a proper judgement.</p> 
		  <p>The third period of Huxley's scientific career is that which earned
			 him his canine sobriquet which was related to Darwin's ground-breaking
			 <bibref><title>Origin of Species</title></bibref>. Darwin and Huxley were good
			 friends, and before the book's publication in 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1849">1859</date>, Darwin sent
			 Huxley the proof of his book, expecting considerable criticism. Unexpectedly,
			 Huxley praised the book enthusiastically and, presciently, warned Darwin of the
			 coming wrath of the creationists. Huxley was, however, not completely
			 unthinking in his praise, in 
			 <date type="single" normal="1862">1862</date>, in his address to the
			 Geological Society, he announced that he saw natural selection as a hypothesis,
			 as there was not yet any evidence of specialisation of animals through the
			 eras, which the theory of natural selection predicted. This was in line with
			 his agnosticism, a word he coined (though he did not mean it in today's
			 strictly religious sense of the word, rather he took it to mean scepticism of
			 that which cannot be proved, allied with acceptance of what can be
			 scientifically proven). After the <bibref><title>Origin of
			 Species</title></bibref> publication, the controversy Huxley had predicted
			 materialised, and he took a large part in it, publishing justifications of the
			 theory. He also, notoriously, engaged in a feud against naturalist Richard Owen
			 (<date type="life-span" normal="1804/1892">1804-1892</date>) and his acolyte,
			 Samuel Wilberforce (<date type="life-span"
			 normal="1805/1873">1805-1873</date>), Bishop of Oxford, at the 
			 <date type="single" normal="1860">1860</date> meeting of the British
			 Association for the Advancement of Science, which he comprehensively won, by
			 pointing out the Bishop's scientific blunders and attacking their attempt to
			 pervert science.</p> 
		  <p>Owen's contestation of Darwin was not in fact over the entire
			 contents of Darwin's book, but over the idea (only hinted at in the
			 <bibref><title>Origin of Species</title></bibref>) that man was descended from
			 apes. Owen argued, with some evidence from studies of primates' and humans'
			 brains, that the differences between humans and apes are greater than the
			 difference between apes and the lower primates. He was effectively arguing that
			 men were not descended from apes. Through experiments, Huxley eventually proved
			 that Owen was mistaken, and that there was overwhelming evidence to suggest
			 humans were in the same zoological group as apes and other primates. By 
			 <date type="single" normal="1870">1870</date>, Huxley was fully
			 convinced by the theory of evolution, and retracted his statement of eight
			 years earlier to the Geological Society. Palaeontological evidence of the
			 specialisation of horses' feet had been found in the change in the structure of
			 their feet from toes to hooves. </p> 
		  <p>Huxley also carried out some palaeontological work himself,
			 primarily on the devonian fish Agassiz had investigated, correcting some of his
			 work. This fell into the Darwinist period of his life.</p> 
		  <p>Huxley took an active interest in education, being an influential
			 member of the School Board of London, in which he argued the case for liberal
			 education. Interestingly, despite his scepticism of religion, he supported
			 teaching of the Bible in schools, though as a moral work, piece of good
			 literature and moral basis of British society, rather than as instruction in
			 religion. He also frequently delivered lectures to working mens' classes. He
			 firmly believed that even complex ideas could be communicated to the vast
			 majority of the population if explained properly. Some of his best lectures are
			 said to have been for these groups.</p> 
		  <p>He had much faith in science and scientists, and once said, that
			 "The man of science is the sworn interpreter of nature in the highest court of
			 reason". This trust of what could be scientifically proved formed the basis of
			 agnosticism (in his sense of the word) as much as the scepticism for all that
			 could not be proved to his satisfaction.</p> 
		</occsphere> 
		<relships encodinganalog="isaar228"> 
		  <head>Relationships</head> 
		  <p>Thomas Henry Huxley was a personal friend and professional defender
			 of Charles Darwin and had a close associate of Sir Joseph Dalton Hooker. His
			 son, Leonard Huxley, was a biographer and grandchildren Aldous Huxley, Julian
			 Huxley and Andrew Fielding Huxley all gained fame. Aldous Huxley was the author
			 of many books, including science-fiction novel <bibref><title>Brave New
			 World</title></bibref>, Julian Huxley was a biologist and philosopher, and
			 secretary-general of UNESCO and Andrew Fielding Huxley was a physiologist</p> 
		</relships> 
		<otherinfo encodinganalog="isaar229"> 
		  <head>Other Significant Information</head> 
		  <p>Notable publications:</p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>Zoological Evidences as to Man's Place in
			 Nature</title>, (<imprint><date type="publication" normal="1863"
			 certainty="certain">1863</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>On the Causes of Phenomena of Organic Nature</title>,
			 (<imprint><date type="publication" normal="1863"
			 certainty="certain">1863</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>Elementary Lessons in Physiology</title>, ( 
			 <imprint><date type="publication" normal="1866"
			 certainty="certain">1866</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>Manual of the Comparative Anatomy of Vertebrated
			 Animals</title>, (<imprint><date type="publication" normal="1871"
			 certainty="certain">1871</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>Elementary Biology</title>, (<imprint><date
			 type="publication" normal="1875"
			 certainty="certain">1875</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</otherinfo> 
		<honqual encodinganalog="nahste2210"> 
		  <head>Honours, Qualifications and Appointments</head> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1845">1845</date>: Awarded Batchelor of
			 Medicine (MB) degree, University of London</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1851">1851</date>: Elected Fellow of the
			 Royal Society</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1854">1854</date>: Appointed
			 Lecturer in Natural History, Government School of Mines</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1855">1855</date>: Appointed
			 Naturalist to the Geological Society</p> 
		  <p><date type="chairspan" normal="1863/1869">1863-1869</date>:
			 Appointed Hunterian Professor at the Royal College of Surgeons</p> 
		  <p><date type="chairspan" normal="1855/1858">1855-1858</date>:
			 Appointed Fullerian Professor at the Royal Institution</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentspan" normal="1870/1872">1870-1872</date>:
			 Appointed Member of the School Board of London</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentspan" normal="1883/1885">1883-1885</date>:
			 Elected President of the Royal Society</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1892">1892</date>: Appointed
			 Privy Councillor</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentspan" normal="1869/1870">1869-1870</date>:
			 Elected President of the Geological Society</p> 
		</honqual> 
	 </infoarea> 
	 <notearea encodinganalog="ISAAR3"> 
		<archnote encodinganalog="isaar31"> 
		  <head>Notes</head> 
		  <p>List of sources for the biographical information:</p> 
		  <p><bibref> <title>Concise Dictionary of National Biography</title>, ( 
			 <imprint><geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="532"
			 normal="London (England)">London (England)</geogname>, 
			 <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1992"
			  certainty="certain">1992</date>)</imprint></bibref> </p> 
		  <p> <bibref><title render="italic">Encyclopaedia Britannica, vol
			 11</title>, (<imprint>
			 <geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="502"
			  normal="Chicago (Illinois), United States">Chicago</geogname>, 
			 <publisher>William Benton</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1964"
			  certainty="certain">1964</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><persname source="ncarules" normal="Gillispie, CC"
			 role="author">Gillispie, CC</persname>, <title>Dictionary of Scientific
			 Biography, vol IV</title>, (<imprint><geogname source="lcsh"
			 authfilenumber="483" normal="New York (New York, United States)">New York (New
			 York, United States)</geogname>, 
			 <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1972"
			 certainty="certain">1972</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</archnote> 
		<rules encodinganalog="isaar32"> 
		  <head>Rules or Conventions</head> 
		  <p>Authority record created according to the<bibref><corpname
			 normal="National Council on Archives">National Council on
			 Archives</corpname><title>Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and
			 Corporate Names (NCA Rules)</title><imprint> 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1997">1997</date></imprint></bibref>
			 and <bibref><corpname normal="International Council on Archives">International
			 Council on Archives: Ad Hoc Committee on Descriptive
			 Standards</corpname><title>International Standard Archival Authority Record for
			 Corporate Bodies, Persona and Families (ISAAR)CPF</title><imprint> 
			 <date type="publication"
			 normal="1995">1995</date></imprint></bibref></p> 
		</rules> 
		<creationdate encodinganalog="isaar33"> 
		  <p>Personal name authority record compiled for the NAHSTE project by
			 <persname role="archivist" normal="Usher, Olivier">Olivier Usher</persname>,
			 Edinburgh University Library Special Collections Division, 
			 <date type="single" normal="20020530">30 May
				2002</date></p></creationdate> 
	 </notearea> 
  </aar>
</isaarcpf>
