<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE isaarcpf SYSTEM "isaar.dtd">
<isaarcpf> 
  <aarheader audience="internal" langencoding="ISO 639"
	aarstatus="edited-full-draft"> 
	 <aarid source="GB-0237" type="FPI"> "-//Edinburgh University Library
		Special Collections Division :: Archival Authority Records//DOCUMENT
		GB-0237-NAHSTE-P1869 20020508 //EN" </aarid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper> GB 0237 NAHSTE P1869</titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>Russell | Sir | Frederick Stratten | 1897-1984 | marine
			 biologist</subtitle> 
		  <author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Margaret Stewart, Edinburgh
			 University Library Special Collections Division, 08 May 2002</author> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt> 
		  <publisher>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
			 Division</publisher> 
		  <address> 
			 <addressline>The University of Edinburgh</addressline> 
			 <addressline>George Square</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Edinburgh EH8 9LJ</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Scotland</addressline> 
			 <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> 
		  </address> 
		  <date type="single" normal="20020508">08 May 2002</date> 
		</publicationstmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>XML generated using the ISAAR(CPF) DTD and XMetal template
		  prepared, as part of the NAHSTE project, in collaboration with the GASHE
		  project, by Sarah Higgins, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections
		  Division, 2001, with assistance from Pete Johnston, Lesley Richmond and Moira
		  Rankin, Glasgow University Archive Services. </creation> 
		<langusage> 
		  <language>EN</language> 
		</langusage> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item>No revisions to date</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </aarheader> 
  <frontmatter> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<titleproper> GB 0237 NAHSTE P1869</titleproper> 
		<subtitle>Russell | Sir | Frederick Stratten | 1897-1984 | marine
		  biologist</subtitle> 
		<author>Compiled for the NAHSTE project by Margaret Stewart, Edinburgh
		  University Library Special Collections Division, 08 May 2002</author> 
		<publisher>Edinburgh University Special Collections Division</publisher> 
		<date type="single" normal="20020508">08 May 2002</date> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 
  <aar id="GB-0237-NAHSTE-P1869"> 
	 <authcontrolarea> 
		<head>AUTHORITY CONTROL AREA</head> 
		<unitid label="Identity Code" encodinganalog="isaar11" type="NAHSTE"
		 repositorycode="0237"> GB 0237 NAHSTE P0336</unitid> 
		<authentry encodinganalog="isaar13" label="Authority Entry"
		 authfilenumber="GB 0237 NAHSTE P1869"
		 normal="Russell, Sir, Frederick Stratten">Russell | Sir | Frederick Stratten |
		  1897-1984 | marine biologist</authentry> 
	 </authcontrolarea> 
	 <infoarea encodinganalog="isaar2"> 
		<head>INFORMATION AREA</head> 
		<occsphere encodinganalog="isaar226"> 
		  <head>Occupation, Sphere of Activity</head> 
		  <p>Frederick Stratten Russell pioneered the measurements of fish stocks
			 that made possible the control of over-fishing by quotas. His earliest
			 experiences were of the sea - boats, fossils-hunting, fishing and the local
			 fisheries of Cornwall were the scenes of his childhood, and the sea lochs of
			 the north west coast of Scotland where he was the first to notice the decline
			 in fish numbers. Russell's schoolteacher father taught him Latin, Greek and
			 watercolour painting - skills of value to him in his later scientific work.</p>
		  
		  <p> During World War I he was an aerial observer and the photographs he
			 took whilst suspended beneath the fuselage of the aircraft at a height of
			 18-20,000 feet are amongst the more famous of the 1st World War. He was
			 decorated for gallantry and skill, and he described his wartime experiences as
			 enjoyable, exciting and a time of great camaraderie.</p> 
		  <p>At Cambridge after the war he developed an interest in marine
			 biology, and worked in Egypt for two years, before returning to the Marine
			 Biological Association Laboratory at Plymouth in 1924. During World War II
			 Russell joined RAF intelligence where his work was 'unfailingly skilful and
			 imaginative' in constructing evidence of enemy bombing strategy. Despite many
			 offers of academic jobs, Russell preferred after the War to stay at the
			 Plymouth Laboratory. His benevolent and astute care initiated a 'golden age'
			 for the Laboratory as a multidisciplinary international centre of excellence
			 where oceanographers and marine biologists worked with chemists and plant and
			 animal physiologists. Increased funding allowed the installation of seawater
			 tanks, an expanded library and well-equipped vessels. Russell's technical
			 knowledge of seafaring, commercial fishery, photography and minesweeping as
			 well as statistics and his experimental skills enabled him to investigate the
			 complex interplay of temperature, depth, light, sea currents, diurnal
			 variation, life and breeding cycles and the distribution of plankton. His
			 studies enabled him to draw up a plankton map of the UK waters - an invaluable
			 tool in fishing policy. Russell's other field of research was the life cycle
			 and taxonomy of medusae (jellyfish).</p> 
		</occsphere> 
		<relships encodinganalog="isaar228"> 
		  <head>Relationships</head> 
		  <p>As a student Russell was influenced by the Norwegian oceanographer,
			 Johan Hjort who gave him his first appointment in Egypt. His old teacher and
			 Director of the Laboratory, Dr. E.J. Allen, initiated his career at the
			 Plymouth Laboratory. Russell collaborated with Maurice Yonge, on the
			 publication of the first successful popular description of marine biology
			 (1928), and in the same year they joined the Great Barrier Reef Expedition.
			 Russell had many other collaborators after the War: W.R.G. Atkins, H.W. Harvey,
			 Marie Lebour and L.H.N. Cooper. He encouraged much important research at
			 Plymouth, e.g., O.E. Lowenstein's work in experimental zoology, and A.L.
			 Hodgkin and A.F. Huxley's neurophysiology work received the Nobel Prize. His
			 wife, Gweneth died in 1978. His only child, William was born in 1938.</p> 
		</relships> 
		<otherinfo encodinganalog="isaar229"> 
		  <head>Other Significant Information</head> 
		  <p>Notable publications: </p> 
		  <p>159 publications largely in journals. His monographs are:</p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>The seas: an introduction to the study of life in the
			 sea</title>, (<imprint><date type="publication" normal="1928"
			 certainty="certain">1928</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>The Medusae of the British Isles, vol. 1</title>, ( 
			 <imprint><date type="publication" normal="1953"
			 certainty="certain">1953</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>The Medusae of the British Isles, vol. 2</title>, ( 
			 <imprint><date type="publication" normal="1970"
			 certainty="certain">1970</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p><bibref><title>The eggs and planktonic stages of British marine
			 fishes</title>, (<imprint><date type="publication" normal="1976"
			 certainty="certain">1976</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</otherinfo> 
		<honqual encodinganalog="nahste2210"> 
		  <head>Honours, Qualifications and Appointments</head> 
		  <p>Appointed chairman of several government councils, and honorary
			 member of several learned societies and institutions. He was also awarded four
			 honorary degrees.</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentspan" normal="1928/1929">1928-1929</date>:
			 Appointed member, Great Barrier Reef Expedition</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentdate" normal="1938">1938</date>: Elected
			 Fellow of Royal Society</p> 
		  <p><date type="appointmentspan" normal="1945/1965">1945-1965</date>:
			 Appointed Director, Plymouth Laboratory, Marine Biological Association</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1955">1955</date>: Awarded CBE</p> 
		  <p><date type="single" normal="1965">1965</date>: Awarded
			 Knighthood</p> 
		</honqual> 
	 </infoarea> 
	 <notearea encodinganalog="ISAAR3"> 
		<archnote encodinganalog="isaar31"> 
		  <head>Notes</head> 
		  <p>List of sources for the biographical information:</p> 
		  <p><bibref>
			 <persname source="ncarules" normal="Denton, EJ " role="editor">Denton,
			 EJ</persname>, <title render="italic">Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the
			 Royal Society, vol. 32 pp 461-493</title>, (<imprint>
			 <geogname source="lcsh" authfilenumber="530"
			 normal="London (England)">London</geogname> 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1986"
			 certainty="certain">1986</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		  <p> <bibref><title render="italic">Cartage</title>, (
			 <extref href="http://www.cartage.org.lb/">http://www.cartage.org.lb/</extref> 
			 <imprint>, 
			 <date type="publication" normal="2002"
			 certainty="certain">2002</date>)</imprint></bibref></p> 
		</archnote> 
		<rules encodinganalog="isaar32"> 
		  <head>Rules or Conventions</head> 
		  <p>Authority record created according to the <bibref>
			 <corpname normal="National Council on Archives">National Council on
			 Archives</corpname> <title>Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and
			 Corporate Names (NCA Rules)</title> <imprint> 
			 <date type="publication" normal="1997">1997</date></imprint></bibref>
			 and <bibref> <corpname normal="International Council on Archives">International
			 Council on Archives: Ad Hoc Committee on Descriptive Standards</corpname>
			 <title>International Standard Archival Authority Record for Corporate Bodies,
			 Persons and Families (ISAAR)CPF</title> <imprint> 
			 <date type="publication"
			 normal="1995">1995</date></imprint></bibref></p> 
		</rules> 
		<creationdate encodinganalog="isaar33"> 
		  <p>Personal name authority record compiled for the NAHSTE project by
			 <persname role="researcher" normal="Stewart, Margaret">Margaret
			 Stewart</persname>, Edinburgh University Library Special Collections Division, 
			 <date type="single" normal="20020508">08 May
				2002</date></p></creationdate> 
	 </notearea> 
  </aar>
</isaarcpf>
