<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-363" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-363</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of James Hogg, the Ettrick Shepherd (1770-1835)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Apr 08 10:52:25 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-363</unitid> <physloc>Dc.4.101-103 Hogg</physloc><unittitle>Papers of James Hogg, the Ettrick Shepherd (1770-1835)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 letters manuscript, 2 poems manuscript. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>James Hogg was born in Ettrick, in the Scottish Borders, probably in November 1770. In his youth he was a shepherd at Willanslee and at Douglas Burn on the Yarrow, but he had aspirations of becoming a farmer. His earliest writing includes <title>Donald McDonald</title> (1800) and <title>Scottish pastorals</title> (1801). His first real earnings from his literary work and from a treatise on diseases in sheep were lost in a failed attempt to become a farmer in Dumfriesshire. In 1810 therefore, Hogg headed for Edinburgh. By 1815 he had established himself as a literary man, and he was granted the farm of Altrive by the Duke of Buccleuch which became his home. Hogg's ballads and tales include <title>The mountain bard</title> (1807), <title>The shepherd's calendar</title> (1829), <title>The brownies of Bodsbeck</title> (1818), and <title>Winter evening tales</title> (1820). Other work includes <title>The spy</title> (1810-1811), <title>The poetic mirror</title> (1816,) <title>The surpassing adventures of Allan Gordon</title> or <title>The three perils of man</title> (1822), <title>Tales of the wars of Montrose</title> or <title>The three perils of woman</title> (1823), and his famed <title>The private memoirs and confessions of a justified sinner</title> (1824). Hogg's work had been promoted by Sir Walter Scott (1771-1832) whom he first met in 1802, and he was also appreciated by Lord Byron (1788-1824). On his death on 21 November 1835, James Hogg - the Ettrick Shepherd - was a nationally recognised poet and song-writer.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The Hogg material is composed of: a poem in 8 stanzas, 1831; a letter to Messrs. Oliver and Boyd about <title>The mountain bard</title>, 1820; a letter to 'My dear Blakie' with the poem <title>When the kye come hame</title>, 1824; letter to Sir John Hay, 1833; and, letter to Mr. Boyde. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Letter to Oliver and Boyd, acquired September 1973, Accession no. E73.35. Letter to Boyde, acquired 1973, Accession no. E74.5.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). <title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins Publishers, 1994. (2) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). <title>The dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 9. Harris-Hovenden. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show various references to Hogg related material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): poem and letter, 1819 and 1821, at La.II.216; letter to W. Laidlaw, 1801, at La.III.584/13; mention in a letter of H. Boyd to A. Davenport, 1813, at La.II.646/53/2; mention in a letter from John Aitken to David Laing, 1819, La.IV.17; mention in a letter of George Chalmers to David Laing, 1819, La.IV.6/Chalmers/35; and, a copy of <title>Mountain bard</title>, 1873, La.IV.17. There is also a letter from the younger James Hogg, 1861, at La.II.646/122. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters (24) to Oliver and Boyd, 1818-1834, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Dep 312 NRA 10785 Oliver &amp; Boyd, and letters to Blackwoods, MSS of poems, 1811-1835, Ref. MSS 4001-4854 passim, and correspondence and papers, 1800-1833, see Catalogue of MSS vols 1-2, and miscellaneous poems and letters, Ref. MSS 9634, 10279, 20440, and correspondence, papers, poems, engraved portrait and material for a biography, 1814-1946, Ref. MSS 9610-9977, 10256-10999 Passim; correspondence and papers, Private, Ref. NRA(S)0112 1141 NRA 10167 Hog; letters from, Hornel Library, Ref. NRA(S)0118 NRA 10173 Hornel Library; correspondence and papers, Yale University Libraries, Beinecke Library; notebook and letters, London University Library, Ref. SL V 14 SL V 15; letters (9) to George Thomson, 1815-1823, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add.MSS.35264-35265.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish literature</emph> <emph altrender="z">19th century</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hogg</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1770-1835</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Poet</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
