<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-619" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-619</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Richard Baxter (b. 1925)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Dec 11 17:18:55 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-619</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 35</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Richard Baxter (b. 1925)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1895-1993">1895-1993</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box</extent> </physdesc> <origination>Baxter, Richard Fraser </origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Richard Fraser Baxter, Church of Scotland missionary in Malawi, was born in Glasgow on 25 February 1925. He was educated at Glasgow High School then, from 1943, at Glasgow University and Trinity College from where he graduated M.A. (1946) and B.D. (1951). Between 1944 and 1946 he served with the Royal Marines and from 1950 to 1951 he was an assistant minister at St Enoch's-Hogganfield, Glasgow. After completing his course at Trinity, Baxter worked as Scottish Secretary of the Student Christian Movement in Schools until 1954 when he was ordained. In the same year Baxter and his new wife Julie Renate (Ray, born 1927) left for Malawi (Nyasaland) where they worked as missionaries with the Church of Scotland until 1969. They were first based in Zomba where Baxter was district missionary and responsible for the mission schools. His educational work continued when he moved to Blantyre in 1958 to be Education Secretary of Blantyre Synod. After a period of leave the Baxters were stationed, from 1960, at Mulanje and Richard Baxter spent the next four years travelling between villages visiting congregations, schools and churches and training elders. In 1964 he was appointed minister of St Michael's and All Angels Church, Blantyre then a year later became the first Warden of the United (Anglican / Presbyterian) Lay Training Centre at Chilema. The Baxters left Malawi in 1969 and Richard Baxter took a post as Warden of Scottish Churches House, Dunblane which he held until 1974. From 1975 to 1982 he was minister at Kirkmahoe, Dumfries then between 1983 and 1995 acted as assistant minister at churches in Edinburgh with a spell in 1990 as interim Director of the Church of Scotland Centre, Tiberias, Israel. Baxter retired from active work in 1995 having served on a number of Church of Scotland committees. A keen singer and artist his interest in African music continued and a number of his illustrations and cartoons have appeared in publications. He was awarded an OBE in 1964.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of: annual reports written by Baxter (1956-1958); circular letters sent by the Baxters to friends and supporters (1955-1969); notebooks and diary entries written by Baxter describing his visits to congregations and village churches around Mulanje (1961-1962); general correspondence including a copy of a letter written by John Moir (1895, 1955-1960s); material relating to the United Church Lay Training Centre in Chilema (1965-1968); papers, articles and reports on Malawi and mission work including papers from a 1993 conference on the Malawi crisis of 1964 (1960-1993); and photographs of Malawi and church and mission work (1950s-1960s).</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>The material is arranged as described above.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>The collection was presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World by Richard Baxter in 2001.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>None expected.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself and information supplied by Richard Baxter.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The archives of the foreign missions of the Church of Scotland are held by the National Library of Scotland. Edinburgh University Special Collections has some collections relating to the early years of the Malawi missions. The Centre also holds the papers of Tom Colvin, Church of Scotland missionary in Malawi.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Baxter</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Richard</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1925</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
