<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-816" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-816</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Robert Shand Turner M.D. (1845-1931)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Jun 8 09:12:04 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-816</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1873; Dc.4.101-103 Turner</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Robert Shand Turner M.D. (1845-1931)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1870-1931">1870-1931</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box, 1 separate letter. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Turner, Robert Shand</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Robert Shand Turner was born in 1845. He received his preliminary education in Keith, Banffshire, and then studied at Aberdeen University graduating in 1864. He completed his medical training in Edinburgh. He took over his father's practice in Keith in the 1870s. The medical practice was disposed of in 1921, and then he went to live in Edinburgh. Dr. Robert Shand Turner died in 1931. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of several pamphlets that belonged to Dr. R. S. Turner, including a report on cholera in Penang, 1901, and manuscript lectures entitled <title>The germ theory</title>, <title>On diphtheria</title>, and <title>Illustrations of the power of the mind over the body</title>. There is also a reprint of <title>Sanitary conditions of our villages and rural districts</title>, a reprint from the <title>Banffshire journal</title> 1875. There is also a communication on transient albuminuria suggested by a memorandum of professor Sir Thomas Richard Fraser, Edinburgh University, 1888 watermark, at Dc.4.101-103 Turner.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Pamphlets and lectures, received from Dr. A. F. Turner, Dumfries, April 1971, Accession no. E71.10. Letter on transient albuminuria, received from Dr. A. F. Turner, Accession no. E67.22.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Medicine</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Turner</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert Shand</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1845-1931</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Doctor</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
