<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-435" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-435</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Material relating to Professor James Miller (1812-1864)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Sep 5 12:22:13 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-435 </unitid> <physloc>Dc.2.86; Dc.4.98/6, no.3; Dc.7.108; Gen. 1875, nos.86-87; Phot.Ill.157/18 </physloc><unittitle>Material relating to Professor James Miller (1812-1864)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1848-1859">1848-1859</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 notebook, 3 letters, 1 typescript document of circa 27,600 words</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>James Miller was born in Essie, Angus, on 2 April 1812. He was taught at home and then he studied at St. Andrews University. His education continued in Dundee before he embarked on a course as a medical student in Edinburgh. In 1832 he became licensed by the Royal College of Surgeons, Edinburgh, and in 1832 he became a Fellow of the College for which his thesis was entitled <title>Probationary essay on the dressing of wounds</title> (1840). For a few years he was an assistant to a surgeon in the city before his appointment as Professor of Surgery at Edinburgh University in 1842, succeeding Sir Charles Bell (1774-1842). In 1848 Miller was Surgeon-in-Ordinary - in Scotland - to Queen Victoria and Prince Albert. He also practised as a Physician. Another of his works was entitled <title>A system of surgery</title> (1864). Professor James Miller died on 17 June 1864. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material consists of: letters, 1856 and 1863; and, testimonial in favour of G. H. Pringle, 1852; notes of lectures on surgery by Professor Miller, 1858-1859. There is also material on surgical experience of chloroform, 1848. There is a portrait.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>Note that when this record was created any associated photographic/illustrative was unseen.</p> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.13. Masquerier-Myles. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters (275) from Robert Liston, 1834-1845, Wellcome Library for the History and Understanding of Medicine, see Accessions to repositories 1987.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgeons</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgery</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Miller</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1812-1864</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Surgeon</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
