<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll57" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-57</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Notebooks and Papers of Professor Robert Flint, Professor of Divinity at Edinburgh University, 1876-1903 </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-57</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 631-689; MSS FLI 1-5 </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Notebooks and Papers of Professor Robert Flint, Professor of Divinity at Edinburgh University, 1876-1903 </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1843-1924">1843-1924 </unitdate> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>58 notebooks and volumes, and 5 boxes (1 m). </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>Robert Flint was born on 14 March 1838 at Greenburn, Sibbaldie, Dumfriesshire. He was educated at Evan Water and Moffat Schools in the area, and then at the University of Glasgow. He became licensed to preach in 1858 and held successive charges at the East Church of Aberdeen, 1859-62, and at Kilconquhar, 1862-64. In 1864 he was appointed to the Chair of Moral Philosophy and Political Economy in the University of St. Andrews, a post he held till his transference to the Professorship of Divinity in the University of Edinburgh in 1876. In 1895 he declined the Moderatorship of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland. The Professor resigned his Chair at the University in 1903. His scholarly reputation had already been established when he came to Edinburgh. His books and pamphlets exercised a world-wide influence. They included <title>The philosophy of history in France and Germany </title> (1874), <title>Theism </title> (1876), <title>Anti-theistic theories </title> (1879), <title>Socialism </title> (1894), <title>Hindu pantheism </title> (1897), and <title>Agnosticism </title> (1903). He received honorary degrees from the Universities of Aberdeen, Edinburgh and Glasgow, and from Princeton and Yale. Professor Flint died in Edinburgh on 25 November 1910 and was buried at Liberton in the city. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The part of the collection contained within Gen. 631-689 includes notes of lectures 1843-51; notes for Flint's own lectures; notes on various subjects and from various works; handwritten text; and, essays. There are boxes of essays, lectures, sermons, admonitions, speeches, letters, accounts, publishing correspondence, photographs, and, newspaper cuttings. There are also papers connected with Edinburgh University courses, student names and essay marks, and galley proofs of <title>The life of Professor Flint </title> by William Paterson Paterson. In MSS FLI 1-5 there are theological lectures on exercise books, and miscellaneous lectures and sermons. </p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details (Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, Main Library, George Square, Edinburgh EH8 9LJ for Gen. 631-689; New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU for MSS FLI 1-5) </p> </accessrestrict> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Flint</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1838-1910</emph> </persname> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Natural theology</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Agnosticism</emph> </subject> <subject source="aacr2" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Theism</emph> </subject> <subject source="aacr2" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Socialism</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H57; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows at various shelfmarks references to Flint's lectures on Divinity taken down by another, and letters of and to Flint. </p> </relatedmaterial> </archdesc>
</ead>
