<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-167" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-167</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of the Campbell family of Barcaldine</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Dec 03 12:13:14 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-167</unitid> <physloc>Dk.8.3</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Campbell family of Barcaldine</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1789-1843">1789-1843</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>circa 52 letters. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Patrick Campbell, born in 1592, and known as Para dubh beag, was the first of the Campbells of Barcaldine. He was the son of Sir Duncan Campbell, 1st Baronet of Glenorchy. Along with his brother James, Patrick was legitimated under the great seal of Scotland, 27 December 1614. From his father he also obtained Innerzeldies and other lands in Perthshire.</p> <p>Barcaldine is in Ardchattan, Argyllshire. Barcaldine Castle on the Barcaldine estate - as distinct from Barcaldine House - was originally built by a 15th century Sir Duncan Campbell but also constructed by Sir Duncan Campbell of Glenorchy in 1609. It fell into disrepair in the 18th century and was restored in 1896.</p> <p>Sir Duncan Campbell, 1st Baronet of Barcaldine and Glenure, was born on 3 July 1786. Campbell was a captain with the 3rd Guards and (according to <title>Burke's peerage</title>) 'served at Copenhagen, in the Walcheron Expedition, and in the Peninsula'. He was a magistrate and deputy lieutenant for the county of Argyll. He married Elizabeth Dreghorn in 22 February 1815. Sir Duncan Campbell died on 2 April 1842.</p> <p>Sir Alexander Campbell, 2nd Baronet, was born on 15 June 1819. He married Harriette August Royer on 20 August 1855. Sir Alexander Campbell died on 11 December 1880. He was succeeded by his son, Sir Duncan Alexander Dundas Campbell, 3rd Baronet (1856-1926).</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers in the collection consist of correspondence over the period 1789-1843 including that between Lady E. Campbell, Sir Duncan Campbell, and Sir Alexander Campbell, and Lady M. L. Baillie, Elizabeth C. Brown, Mrs. M. R. Dennistoun, and Mrs. J. H. Dundas.</p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Groome, Francis H. <title>Ordnance gazetteer of Scotland: a survey of Scottish topography, statistical, biographical, and historical</title>. p.128. Edinburgh: Thomas C. Jack, 1882. (2) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). <title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. p.64. London: Harper Collins, 1994. (3) Burke, Sir Bernard. and Burke, Ashworth (eds.). <title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage, the privy council, and knightage</title>. pp.454-456. London: Burke's Peerage Ltd., 1929.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Campbell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Duncan</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1786-1842</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet of Barcaldine and Glenure</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Campbell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander </emph> <emph altrender="dates">1819-1880</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">2nd Baronet</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
