<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-527" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-527</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Correspondence of Robert Walker M.D. (1718-1791)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Mar 17 12:22:55 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-527</unitid> <physloc>Dc.6.121; MS 3109</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence of Robert Walker M.D. (1718-1791)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1724-1766">1724-1766</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box file, 1 box with volume</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Walker, Robert</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Robert Walker was born in 1718. He was apprenticed to Joseph Gibson, surgeon and pharmacist (chir. apoth) in 1734. He entered the Incorporation of Surgeons, Edinburgh, in 1747, and was President of the body in 1754. He was awarded the degree of M.D. from Edinburgh University in 1787 and he is described as a Virginian. His thesis <title>De cynanche maligna</title> was dedicated to Robert Walker and John Banister of Virginia, to William Shippen M.D. of Pennsylvania, and to Richard Walker his brother. Earlier in life too, he had entered the Royal Navy. Walker published <title>An inquiry into the smallpox</title> in 1790. He was married to Charlotte Jardin (1733-1819). Robert Walker died in 1791.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of a volume of correspondence, 1758 to 1766, and a volume 1724 to 1758.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained within the Library's finding aids.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgeons</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Walker</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1718-1791</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Surgeon</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
