<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-98" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-98</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Collection of Professor Donald Mackinnon (1839-1914) </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-98</unitid> <physloc>Mackinnon Coll. </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Collection of Professor Donald Mackinnon (1839-1914) </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1401-1899">15th century-19th century </unitdate> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>38 boxes, 2 large bundles, 610 volumes, 19 notebooks, 6 small miscellaneous volumes (18 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>Donald Mackinnon was born in Kilchattan on Colonsay, in the Hebrides, on 18 April 1839. He was educated locally and then later, from the age of eighteen, at the Church of Scotland Training College, Edinburgh, which was a popular route to studying at Edinburgh University. Between 1860 and 1863 he was engaged as a school-teacher in Lochinver, Sutherlandshire, where he made a close study of the dialects and literature of the North Highlands. Mackinnon studied at Edinburgh University where he obtained the degree of M.A. in 1870. Earlier, in 1869, he had become Clerk to the Church of Scotland's Educational Scheme, and in 1872 he was Clerk to the Endowed Schools and Hospitals Commission. After the passing of the Education Act, and on the formation of the School Board of Edinburgh, Mackinnon was appointed as its first Clerk and Treasurer. This was a difficult time to hold such a position because Scottish Education was in the transition stage from control by the Churches to control by elected bodies. In 1882, he became the first Professor of Celtic at Edinburgh University, and he held the chair until 1914. His experience and acquaintance with the North Highlands served him in his capacity as member of the Crofters Royal Commission chaired by Lord Napier in 1883. Mackinnon's contribution to the Commission's Report was impressive enough to speed up subsequent legislation for the improvement of conditions for Scotland's crofters. Among his publications were the <title>Reading book for the use of students of the Gaelic class at Edinburgh University </title> (1889), and <title>On the dialects of Scottish Gaelic </title>. Professor Donald Mackinnon died in Balnahard on Colonsay on 25 December 1914. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The collection of Professor Donald Mackinnon includes a 15th century manuscript on medieval physiography; a 16th century summary or abstract of the <title>Treatise of Maighstir Ricairdi </title> compiled from Hippocrates and others; and, tales and verse written in the 18th century. There are bundles of papers of different sizes with unrelated contents, notebooks containing lecture notes on Gaelic grammar and Gaelic literature, notebooks containing transcripts of Gaelic poetry, Gaelic versions of classical epics, notes on the history of Scotland, newspaper cuttings, draft copies of work, and books and papers. A large part of the collection is in the form of printed volumes, annuals, journals, and pamphlets. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.5./marc 541"> <p>The papers of Professor Donald Mackinnon were presented to by Miss K. Mackinnon in 1948. Some of the collection was presented to the Library in 1924 by Dr. Roger MacNeill, Medical Officer for Health for Argyll. </p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details </p> </accessrestrict> <odd encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.1"> <note encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.6.1./marc 500"> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>The Gambolier </title>, 25 November 1914, pp.64-66 (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University). </p> </note> </odd> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Mackinnon</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Donald</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1839-1914</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Napier</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Francis</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Baron Napier and Ettrick</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1819-1898</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> <controlaccess> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Crofters</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Gaelic language</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Gaelic literature</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H28; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows, at various shelfmarks, references to letters of, and letters to, Professor Mackinnon. </p> </relatedmaterial> </archdesc>
</ead>
