<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-428" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-428</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Correspondence relating to Sir Herbert Eustace Maxwell (1845-1937)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Aug 28 16:27:10 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-428</unitid> <physloc>Dc.3.99/15, ff.5-6; Gen. 1733/118</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence relating to Sir Herbert Eustace Maxwell (1845-1937)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1916-1934">1916-1934</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 letters. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Herbert Eustace Maxwell was born in Edinburgh on 8 January 1845. He was educated at Eton and he studied at Christ Church, Oxford. A country gentleman and writer, Maxwell succeeded his father becoming 7th Baronet of Monreith in 1877. He was the Conservative MP for Wigtownshire, 1880-1906, and was Lord-Lieutenant of Wigtownshire, 1903-1935. Maxwell was Rhind Lecturer in Archaeology at Edinburgh University in 1893 and 1911, and a Lecturer in Scottish History at Glasgow University in 1910. In 1899 he represented the UK at the Congress on the Prevention of Tubercolosis in Berlin. His publications include <title>Studies in the topography of Galloway</title> (1887), <title>Scottish land names</title> (1894), <title>Bruce and the struggle for Scottish independence</title> (1897), <title>Memories of the months</title> (1897), <title>Life of the Duke of Wellington</title> (1899), <title>The Creevey papers</title> (1903), <title>The making of Scotland</title> (1911), and <title>Edinburgh: an historical study</title> (1916). Sir Herbert Eustace Maxwell died on 30 October 1937.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The small collection consists of a letter to A. O. Curle and a letter to D. R. Cousin.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Letter to Cousin found in book, acquired January 1987, Accession no. E87.2.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise dictionary</title>. Part 2. 1901-1970. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1982. (2) <title>Who was who 1929-1940</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1941.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Maxwell related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter to Sir C. J. Pearson, 1891, at Gen. 756, no. 178; and, letter to Sir A. Geikie, 1915, at Gen. 525. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence and papers, 1863-1937, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Accs 7043, 7111, 8816 NRA 29224 Maxwell, and correspondence with Blackwoods, 1881-1900, Ref. MSS 4424-4723 passim; letters to Lady Londonderry, 1924-1937, Public Record Office of Northern Ireland, Ref. D3099/3/19 NRA 19803 Stewart; correspondence, 1929-1937, Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, Library and Archives, NRA 25004 Royal Botanic Garden.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Maxwell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Herbert Eustace</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1845-1937</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Politician and Writer</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
