<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-744" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-744</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Records of the Leighton Club </titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 9 09:11:23 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-744</unitid> <physloc>MSS LEI</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Leighton Club </unittitle> <unitdate normal="1941-1976">1941-1976</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box containing envelopes and folders of material, 6 volumes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Leighton Club</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The Leighton Club in Edinburgh was constituted in 1942. The Leighton referred to in the name of the Club is the scholar and Archbishop Robert Leighton (1611-1684) of Glasgow, who had studied at Edinburgh University and at Douai. Leighton had also been Minister of Newbattle, Midlothian. In 1956 the Leighton Club went through a merger with the Christian Unity Association. It disbanded in 1976. Glasgow's Leighton Club closed in 1965.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The records are composed of: 6 volumes of minutes, being minutes of the meetings held between December 1941 and May 1976; syllabuses, 1948-1974; bank and accounts books, 1953-1976; correspondence and receipts on closure, 1975-1976; Secretary's notebook, 1970-1975; typescript copies of the Club constitution; copies of printed Office of the Club; material on merging with Christian Unity Association; statement on closure of the Glasgow Leighton Club, 1965; and, papers, 1944-1968, entitled <title>Leighton's challenge to schism in Scotland</title> by Cecil Thornton, <title>Confirmation: a review of the Anglican discussion</title> by D. S. Bailey, <title>The Anglican concept of authority</title> by Glen Cavalifro, and <title>Do we still want unity?</title> by Frederick Levison and Fergus Harris.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Minutes of meetings deposited in New College Library after the Club's disbandment in 1976.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The administrative history was compiled using material contained within the collection and the local lists, and in (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia. (eds.). <title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins Publishers, 1994.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Leighton Club</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">New College (Edinburgh, Scotland)</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
