<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-411" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-411</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Sir Donald Francis Tovey (1875-1940)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Jul 17 15:05:22 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-411</unitid> <physloc>E2001.37; Gen. 715/4, no. 38; Gen. 1971/5; Gen. 1732 Tovey </physloc><unittitle>Papers of Sir Donald Francis Tovey (1875-1940)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1887-1945">1887-1945</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>55 boxes, circa 100 files, assorted albums, pictures, recordings, and small library of books (22 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Donald Francis Tovey was born at Eton on 17 July 1875. His father was an Assistant Master at Eton College. He was educated privately by the music and general teacher Miss Sophie Weisse (1851-1945) and later on studied under Sir Walter Parratt (1841-1924) and Sir C. H. Parry (1848-1918). Tovey then won a music scholarship to Balliol College, Oxford, graduating with a BA, Classical honours, in 1898. As a pianist, a series of chamber music concerts followed in London, Berlin and Vienna where he played with Halle, Joachim, Hausmann, Casals, and other artists. He also composed. In 1914 he was appointed to the Reid Chair of Music at Edinburgh University in succession to Professor Niecks (1845-1924). As Professor he broadened the music curriculum by instituting classes in musical interpretation, orchestration, history and analysis, thorough-bass, score reading, and advanced counter-point and composition. Tovey also established and conducted the Reid Orchestra and organised an annual series of concerts. His musical compositions were in many forms including chamber music, symphony, grand opera and concerto, and probably the most famous was his opera <title>The bride of Dionysus</title> produced in Edinburgh in 1929. His literary publications include the six volumes of <title>Essays in musical analysis</title> (1935-1939), and <title>A musician talks</title> (1941). Tovey was knighted in 1935. Sir Donald Francis Tovey died on 10 July 1940.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers include a wide range of material ranging from notes and drafts of lectures to accounts and administrative material, drafts of broadcasts to photographs and diaries, and cuttings and reviews. There is also correspondence between Tovey and Weisse, Tovey and Joachim, and Tovey and Speyer. There are also other miscellaneous papers and material.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>The Tovey Collection was transferred from the Reid Music Library in 2001, Accession no. E2001.37. </p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Rice, D. Talbot (comp.). <title>The university portraits</title>. pp.206-208. Edinburgh: The University Press, 1957. (2) <title>Who was who 1929-1940</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1941. (3) <title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise dictionary</title>. Part 2. 1901-1970. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1982.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: some MS scores, at Indiana University, Lilly Library, NRA 16244 Busch; and, letters to Sir Granville Bantock, Worcestershire Record Office, County Hall Branch, Ref. Continuation page 1 NRA 10623 Bantock</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Musicians</emph> </subject> <persname source="othersource"> <emph altrender="surname">Tovey</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Donald Francis</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1875-1940</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight, Musician</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> <!-- sub fonds level descriptions in dsc tag --> <dsc type="analyticover"> <c01 otherlevel="subfonds" level="otherlevel"> <did> <unitid>GB 0237 E2001.37</unitid> <unittitle>Tovey. The Tovey Collection</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1801-1999">19th century - 20th century</unitdate> <physdesc> <extent>42 boxes, circa 100 files, assorted albums, pictures, recordings, and small library of books (1.5 linear metres)</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <scopecontent> <p>The main bulk of the collection contains: Tovey's notes and drafts for radio broadcasts; Tovey's notes and drafts for written works; typescripts of lectures given by Tovey including those on Beethoven delivered in 1922, and typescripts of entries in the <title>Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>; music manuscripts and sketches; Tovey's memoirs and recollections, and Dr. Mary Grierson's notes and biography; material accumulating from uncompleted major projects including notes and drafts relating to the Firth manuscript; material relating to the Reid Orchestra including accounts and administrative items; material on <title>The bride of Dionysus</title>; a small library of written works, a number of which are duplicates; examination papers; posters advertising concerts; concert programmes; press cuttings and reviews; tributes; sketches and photographs; sound recordings; diaries; and, miscellaneous material and letters.</p> </scopecontent> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Grierson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Mary</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Firth</emph> <emph altrender="forename">George</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </c01> <c01 otherlevel="subfonds" level="otherlevel"> <did> <unitid>GB 0237 E2001.37</unitid> <unittitle>Tovey. The Tovey Correspondence</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1887-1945">1887-1945</unitdate> <physdesc> <extent>13 boxes (1.2 linear metres)</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <scopecontent> <p>The boxes of correspondence contain: letters from Tovey to Miss Sophie Weisse, Dr. Joseph Joachim, Mr. Edward Speyer, and other miscellaneous correspondents; and, letters to Tovey from Weisse, Pablo Casals, and Speyer.</p> </scopecontent> <otherfindaid> <p>Handlist with the title <title>The Tovey letters. The collection in the University Music Library as at 1st October, 1968</title> compiled by Dr. George Firth and completed 10/11/69</p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Weisse</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Sophie</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1851-1945</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Music teacher</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Joachim</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Joseph</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1831-1907</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Violinist</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Speyer</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Edward</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d 1934</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Musician</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Casals</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Pablo</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1876-1973</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Violin-cellist, Composer, Conductor</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </c01> <c01 otherlevel="subfonds" level="otherlevel"> <did> <unitid>GB 0237 Gen. 715/4, no. 38; Gen. 1971/5; Gen. 1732 Tovey</unitid> <unittitle>Tovey. Miscellaneous</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1918-1938">1918-1938</unitdate> <physdesc> <extent>16 letters, 1 note</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <scopecontent> <p>Miscellaneous papers include those to Professor C. G. Barkla and Principal Sir Alfred Ewing between 1918- and 1938; a letter concerning Madame Haas and J. Joachim; and, a note on the Niecks Memorial Prize in Music, 1927. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Letters to Barkla, purchased Sotheby, November 1976, Accession no. E76.50. Undated letter purchased November 1977, Accession no.E77.3. Note on Niecks Prize transferred from Reid Music Library, 1963, Accession no. E63.41</p> </acqinfo> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes also show a reference to a certificate in favour of a Miss Wylie, 1925, at Da.3.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Barkla</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Charles Glover</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1877-1944</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physicist</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Ewing</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James Alfred</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1855-1935</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight, Engineer, Principal of Edinburgh University</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </c01> </dsc> </archdesc>
</ead>
