<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-235" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-235</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Dr. Arthur Logan Turner (1865-1939)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri May 04 15:41:05 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-235</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 528-530; Dk.1.43</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Dr. Arthur Logan Turner (1865-1939)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 boxes, 1 file. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Arthur Logan Turner was born in Edinburgh on 6 May 1865, and was the son of Sir William Turner (1832-1916), Professor of Anatomy and Principal of Edinburgh University. Turner was educated at Fettes College in the city and then studied at Edinburgh University where he was awarded the degrees of Bachelor of Medicine and Master in Surgery in 1889. He became a Fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh in 1891 and was awarded the degree of Doctor of Medicine in 1894. His fields of interest were Octology, Laryngology, and Rhinology, and in particular the anatomy of the sinuses. In 1903, Turner became an Assistant Surgeon at the Ear and Throat Department at the Royal Infirmary in Edinburgh. In 1906, he was a Surgeon, and then in 1921, a Surgeon-Consultant. In 1924, he became Consultant Surgeon at the Royal Infirmary and at Deaconess Hospital in Edinburgh. He was also a Lecturer in Diseases of the Larynx, Ear and Nose at Edinburgh University from 1906 to 1924. During the First World War, and until 1919, Turner was a captain in the Royal Army Medical Corps (Territorial Forces). His publications included <title>The accessory sinuses of the nose: their surgical anatomy and the diagnosis and treatment of their inflammatory affections</title> (1901), <title>Sir William Turner: a chapter in medical history</title> (1919), <title>History of the University of Edinburgh, 1883-1933 (1933)</title>, and <title>Story of a great hospital: the Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh, 1729-1929</title> (1937). He collaborated in <title>Intracranial pyogenic diseases: a pathological and clinical study of the pathways of infection from the face, the nasal and paranasal air-cavities</title> (1931). He also edited <title>Diseases of the nose, throat, and ear: for practitioners and students</title> (1924), and <title>Joseph, Baron Lister: Centenary volume, 1827-1927</title> for the Lister centenary committee of the British Medical Association (1927). Turner left his mark on the administrative affairs not only of the Royal Infirmary, but also on the affairs of the Royal Hospital for Sick Children and the then Astley Ainslie Institution in Edinburgh. He was President of the Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh, 1925-1927 and became an honorary Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians in 1927. He was also Vice-President of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, 1930 to 1933. Dr. Arthur Logan Turner died on 6 June 1939. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>At Dk.1.43 is an album containing letters, programmes, admission cards, photographs and other matter relating to the 350th anniversary of the foundation of Edinburgh University, 1933. Also reviews of Turner's books <title>History of the University of Edinburgh 1883-1933</title> and <title>The story of a great hospital</title> with 39 letters of appreciation of the latter dated 1937-1938. At Gen. 528-530 are typescript and manuscript notes and extracts (circa 1937-1938) for a work on the history of the Scottish universities to the early 18th century, with particular reference to the influence of the Netherlands. The notes relate to: the medieval Scottish universities founded, 1410-1494; the Scottish universities in the post-reformation period, 1560-1600; the political and religious background in17th century England, Scotland, and Netherlands. There are also notes on: the literary background in Scotland; the Netherlands; Anglo-Dutch relations; and, medieval Scotland. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Presented by Miss. A. Turner, 1940.</p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1929-1940. A companion to Who's who ...</title>. Vol.3. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1941. (2) <title>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Edinburgh</title>. Vol.59. 1938-1939. p.282-283. Edinburgh: Neill and Co., 1940. (3) <title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol.10. 1939-1940. p.127-129. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Arthur Logan Turner material (check the Indexes for more details): a brief historical sketch of the Lister Memorial Scheme at Gen. 784/9/21; letters at Dc.4.102; and, a letter at Dk.7.36. </p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Turner</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Arthur Logan</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1865-1939</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Surgeon</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Aberdeen University</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Glasgow University</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">St Andrews University</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Netherlands</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
