<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-632" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-632</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of Professor John Caird (1820-1898)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Apr 15 11:42:02 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-632</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1429/10/11; Gen. 1730 Caird; Gen. 1981/53</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Professor John Caird (1820-1898)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>5 letters</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Caird, John</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>John Caird was born in Greenock on 15 December 1820. He was the brother of the philosopher Edward Caird (1835-1908). He was educated in Greenock and in his father's engineering office before studying at Glasgow University from which he graduated in 1845. He then prepared himself for the Church and was appointed to the Parish of Newton-on-Ayr . In 1847 he was Minister at Lady Yester's, Edinburgh, and then from 1849 at Errol, Perthshire, where he stayed until 1857 when he was appointed to Park Church, Glasgow. In 1857 too, Caird preached before Queen Victoria at Balmoral. In 1860 he was given the honorary degree of D.D. by Glasgow University, and in 1862 he was appointed Professor of Divinity at Glasgow University. On the completion of the new buildings on Gilmore Hill, he revived the university chapel. Caird was appointed Principal of Glasgow University in 1873. He received the honorary degree of LL.D. from Edinburgh University in 1884. His publications include the sermon given at Balmoral entitled <title>Religion in common life</title> and <title>Introduction to the philosophy of religion</title> (1880). Professor John Caird died in the home of his brother at Greenock on 30 July 1898.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The correspondence is composed of: letters, one of which is to Archdeacon Farrar, August 1897; letter to Mr. Bell who is presiding at a lecture; and undated letter about Herbert Spencer.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Farrar and other letters, acquired January 1970, Accession no. E70.2. Spencer letter, purchased 1974, Accession no. E74.25</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.22. Supplement. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show reference to Caird related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter to Sir W. Muir about the Gifford Lectures, April 1890, at Dk.2.14, p.12. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: 1855-97: correspondence with Blackwoods, 1855-1897, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 4111-4714 passim; and, letters to Gilbert Murray, 1888-1897, Oxford University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western Manuscripts, Ref. MSS Gilbert Murray NRA 16865 Murray.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Caird</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1820-1898</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Principal of Glasgow University</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Glasgow University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
