<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-877" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-877</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of Francis (1765-1842), 14th Lord Gray of Kinfauns</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Oct 28 10:01:06 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-877</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1981/131; Gen. 2040/80</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Francis (1765-1842), 14th Lord Gray of Kinfauns</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1815-1830">1815-1830</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Gray, Francis</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Francis Gray was born on 1 September 1765. He was the fourth son of John (1716-1782), 11th Lord Gray, and Margaret Blair, heiress of Kinfauns, Perthshire. His brothers Charles (1752-1786) and William John (d. 1807) were the 12th Lord Gray and 13th Lord Gray, but both died unmarried. Francis Gray married Mary Anne, daughter of Colonel James Johnston, in February 1794. He succeeded to the title in 1807 on the death of his brother. Francis, 14th Lord Gray, died on 20 August 1842. He was succeeded by his son John (1798-1867), 15th Lord Gray.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: letter from Lord Gray to John Miller about the Bill for improving the navigation of the River Tay, 1830; and, letter from Gray in Edinburgh, 1815, offering to assist Miss Webster with financial support of her claim upon an unspecified property, provided Mr. Boyd can give assurance of the validity of the claim.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Among miscellaneous letters of Scottish interest, purchased, December 1976, E. Hall, Accession no. E76.53</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Burke, Sir Bernard. and Burke Ashworth P. <title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage, the Privy Council, and knightage</title>. 87th edition. London: Burke's Peerage Ltd., 1929</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show various references to Gray related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter of Gray to Professor R. Jameson, 1815, at Gen. 129; letter to Professor R. Jameson saying he is sorry Jameson cannot come over on a mineralogical visit and thanking him for <title>Mineralogy of the British Isles</title>, 1816, at Gen. 1999/1/69; and, poem <title>Let princes boast their wide domains</title>, printed at Kinfauns Castle, 1831, at SRC.1.9 (formerly Df.3.59).</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gray</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Francis</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1765-1842</emph> <emph altrender="title">14th Lord Gray</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
