<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-513" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-513</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Records of the West Africa Committee</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Feb 20 12:03:36 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-513</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 836</physloc><unittitle>Records of the West Africa Committee</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1962-1965">1962-1965</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The membership of the West Africa Committee numbered around 140, many of the individuals representing or having commercial interests in West Africa. Members included those firms with interests as diverse as: cement production, banking, footwear, oil, rubber, shipping, chemicals, pharmaceuticals, brewing, and foodstuffs. The Committee issued confidential reports on the state of affairs in various West African countries, including Nigeria and Ghana. There appeared to be a West African Trade Section too, and there were Council and Executive Committee meetings of the West Africa Committee. In 1963, these were held in Paris. London was the usual venue for meetings however. The West Africa Committee published an annual report. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The records are composed of: agenda, minutes and reports of quarterly London meetings, and special monthly reports on Ghana and Nigeria, 1962-1965. There is one report on Sierra Leone, April 1965.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Records acquired March 1966, Accession no. E66.17.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>The Index notes that the material is private and confidential.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the material in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">West Africa Committee</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Ghana</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nigeria</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Sierra Leone</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
