<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-602" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-602</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of E. M. T. Epelle (d. 1973)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 3 11:20:46 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-602</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 22</physloc><unittitle>Papers of E. M. T. Epelle (d. 1973)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1965-1973">1965-1973</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 boxes</extent> </physdesc> <origination>Epelle, E. M. T. </origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>E. M. T. Epelle was a research assistant in the Department of Religion, University of Nigeria, Nsukka. He was involved in a project, initiated by Professor Andrew Walls and partially funded by the Theological Education Fund, to document church histories in Eastern Nigeria. His aim was to collect church histories and, where possible, acquire historical materials for all denominations in each district. The author of <title>Writing a Local Church History</title> (University of Nigeria, 1965), Epelle visited each area, gathered together church leaders and workers, and lectured them on the methods of writing the history of their church. He encouraged the formation of local History Committees who were charged with the responsibility of writing the histories which were then checked by Epelle. The final versions were deposited in the University and a copy was usually sent to Professor Andrew Walls at Aberdeen University. At the same time Epelle attempted to document African traditional religions by meeting with tribes and leaders in each area. The material that Epelle collected between 1965 and 1967, including early church records, was lost during the civil war but some of the copies in Aberdeen survived. Epelle resumed his gathering of information as soon as he could and also frequently lectured on church history and traditional religions. He continued his research until his sudden death on 10 May 1973. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of: correspondence (with Andrew Walls), papers and reports relating to Epelle's research (1966-1973); church histories (written by church history committees or Epelle) of Anglican churches in the Niger Delta Diocese (1966), unorthodox and Seventh Day Adventist churches in Aba and Opobo (1966, 1971), Methodist churches in Ikot Ekpene (1971), and Qua Iboe churches in East Central and South East states (1972); and some completed questionnaires on African tribal and traditional religions (1972).</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>Most of the material that was sent to Aberdeen by Epelle was in labelled files and the same arrangement has been kept. Some papers were loose and not identified, these have been added to the correct files where possible. </p> </arrangement> <custodhist> <p>See biographical history.</p> </custodhist> <acqinfo> <p>The material was sent to Aberdeen by Epelle then moved to Edinburgh University with the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>None expected.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>Professor Andrew Walls worked in Nigeria and various collections in the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World archives and library are a result of his interest in and knowledge of missionary and church workers in the area. Epelle's <title>Writing a Local Church History</title> (University of Nigeria, 1965) is in Edinburgh University Central Library.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Church history</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Epelle</emph> <emph altrender="forename">E M T</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nigeria</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
