<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-651" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-651</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of Col. Sir Henry Montague Hozier (1838-1907)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu May 1 10:48:06 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-651</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1981/156-158</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Col. Sir Henry Montague Hozier (1838-1907)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 letters.</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Hozier, Henry Montague</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Henry Montague Hozier was born in 1838. He was educated at Rugby and at Edinburgh Academy, and then at the Royal Military Academy, Woolwich. He became a Lieutenant in the Royal Artillery, and Lieutenant in the 2nd Life Guards. Hozier was Assistant Military Secretary to Lord Napier of Magdala in the Abyssinian Expedition and he served with the Royal Artillery Expedition to Beijing (Peking). In 1866 he was with the German army and was Assistant Military Attache in the war of 1870-1871. He received the Iron Cross from the German Emperor for his service in the 1870-1871 war. He was awarded the C.B. in 1897 and was created K.C.B. in 1903. His publications include <title>Seven weeks' war</title>, and the <title>History of British expedition to Abyssinia</title>. Hozier had married Henrietta Blanche Ogilvy, daughter of David Ogilvy, 7th Earl of Airlie on 28 September 1873. In September 1908, their second daughter Clementine Hozier married Sir Winston Leonard Spencer-Churchill, later the Prime Minister. Sir Henry Montague Hozier died on 28 February 1907.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The undated letters are about his publications, and one of the letters is incomplete.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who ... 1896-1916</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1920.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show another reference to Hozier related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter of Hozier, H. to James MacVeigh, 5 April 1897, at Gen.748&#x002A;</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hozier</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Henry Montague</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1838-1907</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Colonel, Author, Secretary of Lloyd's</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
