<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-620" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-620</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Latin Link</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown and edited by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 10 12:15:59 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-620</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 51</physloc><unittitle>Latin Link</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1896-1991">1896-1991 </unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>circa 120 boxes of minutes, correspondence, printed materials, personnel records, slides, films, photographs</extent> <physfacet>The slides can be viewed without special equipment but a projector is needed to view them at full size. A tape player is needed to listen to the audio cassettes. The films need a projector.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Andes Evangelical Mission; Evangelical Union of South America; Help from Brazil; Latin Link; South American Evangelical Mission</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> <language langcode="spa">Spanish or Castilian, </language> <language langcode="por">Portuguese, </language> and <language langcode="que">Quechua.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The Evangelical Union of South America (EUSA) was formed in 1911 by Regions Beyond Missionary Union (RBMU; founded 1894) and the South American Evangelical Mission (SAEM; founded 1895) in response to the Edinburgh 1910 World Missionary Conference (RBMU passing responsibility for its South American work over to EUSA, and continuing its own work elsewhere). EUSA worked in Argentina and Peru. Two years later EUSA was joined by the Help for Brazil Mission (founded 1892). In 1932 the Peru Inland Mission (PIM) was formed; this became part of RBMU in 1948. The Andes Evangelical Mission (AEM; originally known as the Bolivian Indian Mission) was founded in 1907 by New Zealander George Allan in Bolivia to minister to the Quechua Indians. In 1982 AEM UK united with EUSA. EUSA worked in Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil and Peru. On the 5th of June 1990 EUSA united with the Peru section of Regions Beyond Missionary Union to form Latin Link. The work done by these missions included church planting, medical and educational work, and Bible and Christian literature distribution. All of the missions that formed Latin Link were interdenominational.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of material (mainly from 1914 onwards) relating to the mission in general and to the work in Peru, Argentina, Brazil and Bolivia. It includes: 1. Minutes and reports produced in the mission offices in London and in the fields from 1914 onwards. 2. Correspondence with missionaries in the field, with regional and national councils, with other missions operating in the same areas, and with other evangelical agencies. 3. Publications and printed material including issues of the mission's journal <title>South America</title> (later <title>South America Now</title>), newsletters produced by missionaries in the field, and leaflets and pamphlets produced for publicity or information. 4. Material in the language or dialects of the countries in which the missionaries worked which was used for language learning or evangelical purposes. 5. Material on the different missions uniting (6) lantern slides, slides, photographs and pictures. 6. Audio material including a large collection of soundslides (slides with accompanying audio cassettes used in deputation work). 7. Films showing the mission's work in various fields.</p> <p>The collection contains little pre-1911 material (ie, predating the merger of EUSA and RBMU); this early material includes small amounts from the SAEM, the AEM and Help from Brazil.</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>Arrangement in progress.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>Deposited by Latin Link at the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World on 15th August 2002.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Copyright remains with Latin Link, which should be contacted at: Latin Link Britain and Ireland, 175 Tower Bridge Road, London SE1 2AB. Tel: 020 7939 9000, Fax: 020 7939 9015. </p> </userestrict> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is in progress.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World also holds the archive of the Regions Beyond Missionary Union.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Andes Evangelical Mission</emph> </corpname> <!--
<corpname>
<emph altrender = "a">EUSA</emph>
</corpname>
--> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Evangelical Union of South America </emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Help for Brazil Mission</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Latin Link</emph> </corpname> <!--
<corpname>
<emph altrender = "a">PIM </emph>
</corpname>
--> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Peru Inland Mission</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">South American Evangelical Mission</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Argentina</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Bolivia</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Brazil</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Peru</emph> </geogname> <!--
<geogname>
<emph altrender = "a">South America</emph>
</geogname>
--> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
