<?xml version="1.0"?> <!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd"> <ead> <eadheader> <eadid publicid="GB 237 Coll-1050" countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237">GB 237 Coll-1050</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="">Papers of A. W. S. Thompson M.B. (fl. 1920-1977)</titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by JavaScript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2 on <date>Fri Mar 18 12:03:46 UTC 2005</date>.</creation> </profiledesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1050"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-1050</unitid> <physloc> E2004.33</physloc> <unittitle>Papers of A. W. S. Thompson M.B. (fl. 1920-1977)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1943/1945">1943-1945</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 boxes.</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English</language> </langmaterial> <origination>Thompson, A. W. S.</origination> </did> <phystech> <p>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted</p> </phystech> <bioghist> <p>A. W. S. Thompson graduated with the degree of M.B. in 1933. During the Second World War, Thompson was sent overseas to North Africa and Italy and the Middle East from 1943 onwards with, principally, the Royal Army Medical Corps and the 8th Army. He served as a hygiene officer with the Field Hygiene Section and Mobile Hygiene Section, and was a Major then Lieutenant-Colonel. Latterly, in the late-1960s, Dr. Thompson was Director, Division of Clinical Services, at the Department of Health in Wellington, New Zealand. In the late-1970s, he was living in Dorset, England.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>Between 1943 and 1945, Thompson set about keeping a personal wartime journal hoping to register possible changes to his psychological make-up. The journal offers data on the effects of long-term overseas service amongst officers. The journal is in diary form with 9 volumes, covering the period 18 July 1943 to 15 October 1945, and written while in North Africa, Italy, Egypt, Palestine, Syria, Greece, and Austria. Within the diaries are newspaper cuttings of the period, photographs, franked envelopes, and other inserted materials. The collection also includes printed matter in the form of New Zealand Law Reports (1962, 1963), New Zealand Parliamentary Debates, press-cuttings relating to Thompson v. Turbott (1961-1965), and material relating to a Public Service Appeal.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material deposited by A.W.S. Thompson, Dorset, Accession no. E2004.33, dated 12 December 2004</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material in the collection file.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. No finding aid for this collection however.</p> </otherfindaid> <processinfo> <p>Compiled by Graeme D. Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </processinfo> <!-- Controlled Access Terms --> <controlaccess> <subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">World War, 1939-1945</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Thompson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">A. W. S. </emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1920-1977</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Doctor</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc> </ead> 