<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-756" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-756</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of the Very Rev. Dr. A. C. Craig (1888-1985)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Jan 23 11:47:06 UTC 2004</date> </item> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Oct 28 10:44:49 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-756</unitid> <physloc>MSS CRA</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Very Rev. Dr. A. C. Craig (1888-1985)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1780-1979">1780-1979</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>104 bundles letters, notes, lectures, sermons. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Craig, Archibald Campbell; Craig, Alexander McRae; Brown, James</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Archibald Campbell Craig was born on 3 December 1888. He was educated at Kelso High School, and he studied Edinburgh University, and New College, Edinburgh. During the First World War he served with the 13th Royal Scots, 1914-1918, and with the Intelligence Corps, 1914-1919. Craig held Pastorates in Galston and Glasgow from 1921 to 1930, and in 1930 he became Chaplain to Glasgow University. In 1939 he was Secretary to the Churches Commission on International Friendship and Social Responsibility, a post which he held until 1942. In 1942 he became General Secretary to the British Council of Churches, and in 1946 he was Assistant Leader, Iona Community. Craig was appointed Lecturer in Biblical Studies at Glasgow University in 1947 and he was there until 1957. He was Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland in 1961-1962. The Very Rev. Archibald Campbell Craig died in 1985.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: in Bundles 1-10, personal letters from Harry Galloway, 1925-1939, and begging letters and appeals for help, personal correspondence addressed to Craig from all over the world, 1930-1939, used and unused postcards, letters of congratulation, 1938, and verse and miscellaneous papers of the nineteenth century; in Bundles 11-26, lectures notes on Genesis, Job, Amos, Ezekiel, St. Mark's gospel, Acts, 1st Corinthians, Hebrews, Galatians, St. Paul, miracle in the Old and New Testaments, history and religion of Israel, Israel in exile, and Psalter; in Bundles 27-50, sermons, letters and notes by Craig's father, Rev. Alexander McRae Craig, from 1864 onwards, notes and quotations from books created by Archibald Campbell Craig, some sermons and prayers by the younger Craig, and letters; in Bundles 51-93, personal letters including letters of condolence on the death of his mother, 1926, his appointment as Chaplain to Glasgow University, 1929, some verse, papers on the Church, 1950s, lectures and addresses, music book and some hymn tunes, a few photographs including photographs of celebrations of the Russian Orthodox Church, some Russian volumes, some sermons and addresses and talks; in Bundles 94-100, file labelled Scottish Churches' Council containing miscellaneous talks and papers, sermons, verse and notes, broadcast talks and sermons, file containing off-prints and talks, and an analytical concordance to the Holy Bible; in Bundle 101, personal letters from James Brown, naval surgeon to Margaret Brown, his sister, 1780-1784; in Bundles 102-103, miscellaneous papers and a plan for 'a ecumenical church in a Scottish new town'; and in Bundle 104, 15 letters from Craig to Robert. C. Mackie written from St. John's, Doune, Perthshire (one exception being Bank Street, Glasgow), the content of which is mixed but with many observations on ecclesiastical politics.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who's who 1976</title>. Adam and Charles Black, 1976.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections, show reference to Craig related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter to the editor of <title>Everyman</title>, submitting a poem 'Lightning', by C. F. Meyer, translated from the German, in Sar.Coll.12. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: 1925-72: correspondence and papers, 1925-1972, Private, Ref. NRA(S)2836 NRA 30496 Craig.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Biblical scholars</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Sermons</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Craig</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Archibald Campbell</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1888-1985</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Biblical Scholar</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Craig</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander McRae</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1864 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Brown</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1780-1784</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Naval surgeon</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
