<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-54" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-54 </eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Robert Nye Manuscripts </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20061110">10 November 2006</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-54"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-54 </unitid> <physloc>MSS 2881-2916; MSS 2938-2940; MSS 3122-3123; E99.39; E2004.1; E2005.30 </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Robert Nye Manuscripts </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1969-1996">1969-2005</unitdate> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>63 archive boxes, and 1 envelope/folder (minumum 7m. shelving)</extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>The writer Robert Nye was born 15 March 1939 in London. He attended Southend High School, a traditional grammar school, and began writing when he was thirteen. Between leaving school in 1955 and starting to write full-time in 1961, he held a variety of jobs including newspaper reporter, milkman, labourer in a market-garden, and ward orderly in a sanatorium. These jobs supported him in his poetry writing. In 1961, Nye moved to North Wales to absorb himself in full-time writing. Later on he settled in Edinburgh where he lived until 1977, then he moved to Ireland. In 1961, he published his first collection of poems, <title>Juvenilia 1 </title>, and a second volume <title>Juvenilia 2 </title> was published in 1963. Around this time he became successful as a reviewer, becoming poetry editor for <title>The Scotsman </title> in 1967 and poetry critic for the <title>Times </title> in 1971. In addition to criticism and poetry, writing for children provided an outlet, <title>Taliesin </title> (1966) and <title>March has horse's ears </title> (1966) being his first books for children. These were based on a re-telling of Welsh tales. Other works for children, poetry, and short stories followed. Nye has written novels too, <title>Doubtfire </title> (1967), then <title>Falstaff </title> (1976), <title>Merlin </title> (1978) and <title>Faust </title> (1980). In 2006, Nye was still living in Ireland.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The collection includes, largely: working notes; drafts; typescripts; correspondence; source material; and, publishing house material. The collection, received at various points since the 1990s, is formed by the following components:</p> <p> MSS 2881-2916 (35 archive boxes), containing material relating to: <list> <item>- <title>Merlin</title> - working notes, drafts, typescript, copies of source material, proofs, copies of poster, and cover design</item> <item>- <title>Faust</title> - notebooks, corrected/uncorrected typescript, copies of source material</item> <item>- <title>The voyage of the Destiny</title> - typescript, proofs, copies of source material</item> <item>- <title>The memoirs of Lord Byron</title> - notes, manuscripts and typescripts</item> <item>- <title>Falstaff</title> - typescript versions for solo performance, fliers</item> <item>- various BBC scripts (late-19060s-1970s)</item> <item>- material relating to short stories and other smaller works, such as: <title>The facts of lief</title>, <title>The bird of the golden land</title>, <title>Wishing gold</title>, and <title>Owain Glendwyr</title> etc</item> <item>- correspondence (1970s-1992), files on financial matters, colour transparencies etc</item> <item>- <title>Mrs Shakespeare </title> - miscellaneous criticism, talks and essays, typescripts, proofs and reviews</item> <item>- <title>The life and death of my Lord Gilles de Rais</title> - notes, letters, typescript, proofs</item> <item>- and, other material</item> </list></p> <p>MSS 2938-2940 (3 archive boxes), which contain: <list> <item>- correspondence (1992-1996)</item> </list></p> <p> MSS 3122-3123 (2 archive boxes), containing material relating to: <list> <item>- <title>Collected poems</title> - notebooks, manuscript material, tyescript material, correspondence, proofs, dust-jacket proofs</item> <item>- <title>Henry James and other poems</title> - proofs</item> <item>- material relating to <title>Spine-chilling tales</title> or later title <title>Lord Fox and other spine chilling tales</title></item> </list></p> <p>E99.39 (10 archive boxes), containing material relating to: <list> <item>- <title>Mrs. Shakespeare</title> - a play for radio</item> <item>- drafts of book reviews for the <title>Scotsman</title>, <title>The Times</title>, the <title>Literary Review</title>, and the <title>Sunday Telegraph</title>, 1996-1999</item> <item>- obituaries (notes and drafts and texts)</item> <item>- Nye's own correspondence; and letters from correspondents</item> <item>- <title>The late Mr. Shakespeare</title> - drafts, typescript, author's proof etc</item> <item>- reviews</item> </list></p> <p> E2004.1 (1 folder/envelope), containing: <list> <item>- correspondence between Robert Graecen and Robert Nye (1970s) and relating to items (poetry) for publishing, and relating to the reviewing of poetry</item> </list></p> <p> E2005.30 (13 archive boxes), containing material relating to: <list> <item>- manuscript and typescript notes of reviews for <title>The Scotsman</title> and the <title>Times</title> 2002-2005; notes for <title>The life and death of my Lord Gilles de Rais</title>, <title>Selection of the poems of Laura Riding</title>, <title>The late Mr. Shakespeare</title>, and <title>Mr. Shakespeare: the complete works</title>; <title>Gingember: a drama in three acts</title>; also, correspondence</item> <item>- correspondence</item> <item>- <title>How delightful to meet Mr. Hodgson!</title></item> <item>- original drafts of biography of the Scottish poet Norman Cameron with related correspondence; draft of study of Seamus Heaney; typescript of unpublished autobiography of Sean Haldane and unpublished biography of Ralph Hodgson</item> <item>- notes for novels and notes toward <title>The good thief</title>; typescript of unpublished play by Bill Watson; proofs of novel <title>Tiberius</title>, by Alan Massie; proofs of <title>Bloodaxe book of contemporary women poets</title></item> <item>- manuscript and typescript drafts and correction to poems for <title>The rain and the glass: 99 poems, new and selected</title>; and, corrected proofs of <title>Sixteen poems</title></item> </list></p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Some material closed, otherwise generally open to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance of visit.</p> </accessrestrict> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Nye</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1939</emph> </persname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph> <emph altrender="y">20th century</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph> <emph altrender="x">Criticism, Textual</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H54. Within handlist is an index of correspondents and box content relevant to all parts: MSS 2881-2916; MSS 2938-2940; MSS 3122-3123; E99.39; E2004.1; and, E2005.30</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353"> <head>Related Material</head> <p>Within the Special Collections, Edinburgh University Library, and noted in the paper-format Index to Manuscripts, there are letters to Robert Nye from C.M.Grieve (Hugh MacDiarmid) 1969-1975, and a letter from Mrs.Grieve, at shelfmark Gen. 1930/16/1-7.</p> </relatedmaterial> <processinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)371"> <head>Archivist's Notes</head> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections.</p> </processinfo> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Nye</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1939</emph> </persname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph> <emph altrender="y">20th century</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph> <emph altrender="x">Criticism, Textual</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
