<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-777" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-777</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Alexander Hugh Bruce, 6th Baron Balfour of Burleigh (1849-1921)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Mar 1 12:02:13 UTC 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-777</unitid> <physloc>MSS BAL. 1.1-92</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Alexander Hugh Bruce, 6th Baron Balfour of Burleigh (1849-1921)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1904-1913">1904-1913</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>circa 75 letters, circa 20 volumes, and miscellaneous notes and newspaper cuttings and envelopes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Bruce, Alexander Hugh</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>British statesman Alexander Hugh Bruce, 6th Baron Balfour of Burleigh, was born in Kennet, Alloa, central Scotland, on 13 January 1849. He was educated at Loretto School, Musselburgh, and at Eton College, then studied at Oriel College, Oxford. He was a member of the Factory Commission, 1874-1875, and chaired many other commissions too. Bruce was a Lord-in-Waiting to the Queen, 1888-1889, Parliamentary Secretary to the Board of Trade, 1889-1892, Secretary of State for Scotland, 1895-1903, and a representative peer for Scotland in the House of Lords, 1876-1921. He was Lord Rector of Edinburgh University, 1896-1899, and Chancellor of St. Andrews University, 1900. Bruce became a Privy Councillor in1892, and was knighted in 1901, and awarded the GCMG in 1911. Alexander Hugh Bruce, 6th Baron Balfour of Burleigh, died on 6 July 1921.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of reports, memoranda, addresses, and speeches, including those from or to: the Church of Scotland, the United Free Church of Scotland, and the Christian Unity Association of Scotland, and on various subjects: annual reports, proposed pension fund for Ministers, report of church committees, spiritual calling, parish church interests, and church union. There are also letters between Bruce and various correspondents, such as: Rev. James Montgomery Campbell, 1912, Rev. Prof. James Cooper, 1912, Rev. Dr. Archibald Fleming, 1905 and 1912, Rev. Dr. Archibald Henderson, 1913, Christopher N. Johnston K.C., 1912, and the Rev. A. W. Wotherspoon, 1912. There are letters attached to a report of the Church of Scotland Committee on Church interests, 1912, and a letter from <title>Scots churchmen</title>, 1913. The collection also includes letters to Bruce from <title>The Scotsman</title> office, 1912, and a letter from Rev. James S. Stewart, 1905, with material relating to North United Free Church, Aberdeen. Finally there are drafts of speeches and miscellaneous notes, 1912-1913.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise dictionary</title>. Part 2. 1901-1970. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1982. (2) <title>Who was who 1916-1928</title>. 3rd edition. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1962.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Alexander Hugh Bruce related material.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Bruce</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander Hugh</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1849-1921</emph> <emph altrender="title">6th Baron Balfour of Burleigh</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Statesman</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
