<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-27" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-27</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Sir Robert Lorimer Papers </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections</corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-27 </unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1963/1-68; MSS 2482-2494 </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Sir Robert Lorimer Papers </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1901-1949">1901-1949 </unitdate> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>87 boxes (12 m); 1 volume; 4 folders. </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>The architect Robert Stodart Lorimer, the son of a law professor at Edinburgh University, was born in Edinburgh, 4 November 1864. He was raised in a Georgian townhouse in Edinburgh's New Town and was educated at Edinburgh Academy and Edinburgh University. In 1885 he started his career in architecture with the practice of Sir Robert Rowan Anderson in Edinburgh, and he served there for four and a half years. After travelling in England, he entered the London office of G. F. Bodley, R.A., where he remained for eighteen months before returning to Edinburgh. During his career, Lorimer became interested in the Arts and Crafts Movement and in Scottish Vernacular architecture. These interests led Lorimer to undertake the Thistle Chapel in the High Kirk of St. Giles, Edinburgh, in 1909 (the chapel of the Knights of the Thistle). Over the years he also remodelled suburban villas and built cottages in various parts of the city. Another major project was the Scottish National War Memorial within Edinburgh Castle. He also created similar memorials in Italy, Egypt and in Greece. Towards the end of his career he restored Paisley Abbey. Sir Robert Lorimer died in 1929. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The Lorimer Papers (office letters) have been sorted and numbered with a full inventory on typed sheets. The Papers relate to projects in Edinburgh and all over Scotland, and elsewhere in the United Kingdom. There are some plans of buildings and building details. Material in some boxes have been sorted but not numbered. Some Papers are still in bundles with only rudimentary sorting. </p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details </p> </accessrestrict> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Lorimer</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert Stodart</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1864-1929</emph> </persname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Architects</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Architecture</emph> <emph altrender="z">Scotland</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H27 </p> </otherfindaid> </archdesc>
</ead>
