<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-503" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-503</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Material relating to the Teaching of Professor John Stevenson LL.D. (fl. 1730-1775)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Feb 17 09:37:05 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-503</unitid> <physloc>Dc.4.54; Dk.3.2, pp.210-215</physloc><unittitle>Material relating to the Teaching of Professor John Stevenson LL.D. (fl. 1730-1775)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1737-1775">1737-1775</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 manuscript volume, 1 part volume</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="lat">Latin, </language> and <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>John Stevenson became Professor of Logic and Metaphysics at Edinburgh University in 1730. Previously he had been a tutor to the Hamilton family of Bergenie. He had not been an MA graduate of the University. Stevenson introduced the philosophy of Locke to the University and his lectures on criticism were given just at the time of a revival in literature in Scotland. Stevenson died at the age of eighty.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material includes: essays written by students in Stevenson's class, 1737-1750; and, notes from lectures on logic, 1775.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Grant, Sir Alexander. <title>The story of the University of Edinburgh during its first three hundred years</title>. Vol.2. pp. 328-330. London: Longmans, Green and Co., 1884.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Stevenson related material (check the Indexes for more details): letters to Charles Mackie, at La.II.91.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Logic</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Metaphysics</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Stevenson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1730-1775 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Logic and Metaphysics</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
