<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-89" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-89</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Sir Robert H. Matthew (1906-1975) </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-89</unitid> <physloc>MSS 2533-2578 </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Sir Robert H. Matthew (1906-1975) </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1947-1979">circa 1947-1979 </unitdate> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>48 file boxes or storage cases; 1 file (5 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>Robert Hogg Matthew was born on 12 December 1906. He was a pupil of Melville College (now Stewart's Daniel and Melville College) and then a student in the School of Architecture in the Edinburgh College of Art. His professional career began in the office of his father's firm, Messrs. Lorimer and Matthew. Between 1936 and 1946 he worked for the Department of Health for Scotland and became the Chief Architect and Planning Officer in 1945. Thereafter he was Architect to the London County Council, 1946 to1953. Matthew was involved in the Clyde Valley Regional Plan in Scotland and also in the building of the Royal Festival Hall on London's South Bank. In 1952, he was appointed Professor of Architecture at Edinburgh University and Head of the School of Architecture in the Edinburgh College of Art. From 1970 he was consultant adviser on building convservation policy to the Secretary of State for Scotland. Matthew was awarded the CBE in 1952, and was knighted in 1962. Sir Robert Hogg Matthew died on 21 June 1975. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>A first tranche of papers of Sir Robert Hogg Matthew (acquired 1980) is composed largely of office papers, but does include personal material, letters of knighthood, and speeches. Otherwise, the papers are composed of: R.I.B.A material; and, material relating to other organisations including the Scottish Civic Trust; material relating to Department of the Environment enquiries; conference material, including the Vancouver Conference on the Environment; and, material on buildings in Hong Kong, and on architectural competitions. There are also many printed publications (some on ecology) and pamphlets.</p> <p><?xm-replace_text {p}?></p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details </p> </accessrestrict> <odd encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.1"> <note encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.6.1./marc 500"> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>University of Edinburgh Journal </title>, Vol.16. 1951-1953, pp.134-135 (Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd). (2) <title>Who was who </title>, Vol.7. 1971-1980 (London: Adam and Charles Black, 1981). </p> </note> </odd> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Matthew</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert Hogg</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1906-1975</emph> </persname> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <corpname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Royal Festival Hall</emph> <emph altrender="z">England</emph> </corpname> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Royal Institute of British Architects</emph> </corpname> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Civic Trust</emph> </corpname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Architects</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Architecture</emph> </subject> <geogname encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph altrender="a">Hong Kong</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>An important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> </archdesc>
</ead>
