<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-548" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-548</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Mar 31 12:29:47 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-548</unitid> <physloc>E2000.10</physloc><unittitle>Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>7 framed photographs, 1 bag Ordnance Survey maps, 1 bag miscellaneous papers and maps. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Sandeman, Gerard L.</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Lieutenant Gerard L. Sandeman served with Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.) during the inter-war period and with the 218 Coast Battery R.A., during the Second World War. He also served in North Africa.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is comprised of: framed photograph of the 161 Heavy Battery, Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.), winners of the McIver Cup, Mackay Trophy, and Fife Cup, 1933; framed photograph of the company, Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.), 1933, when Gerard L. Sandeman was a 2nd Lieutenant; framed photograph of the company, perhaps at Whitby, Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.), 1935; framed photograph of the 9.2-inch gun, summer camp, Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.), Tynemouth 1935; framed photograph of the Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.) march past, Tynemouth 1935; framed photograph of the company, Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.), 1936; and, framed photograph of the company (probably) in the 1960s or 1970s, dressed in dinner suits, and including Bruce Alexander Stenhouse (1911-1991). The collection also includes: a copy of <title>Coast artillery in Sicily and Italy 1943-1945</title>, Colonel S. C. Tomlin, published in Rome 1945; miscellaneous maps and army papers from Algeria, Italy and Tunisia; a copy of <title>First Army Information Bulletin</title>, November 1942; photographs of 218 Coast Battery doing 6-inch gun shifts at Spurn Point, Yorkshire; illustrations of German badge ranks; and, miscellaneous other photographs of artillery and men.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material was presented to Edinburgh University Library by Mrs. Sandeman, widow, June 2002, Accession no. E2000.10.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>A related collection, the <title>Firth of Forth Defences in the 20th Century</title> is described on Archives Hub. This collection was built by Bruce Alexander Stenhouse who appears in one of the photographs within E2000.10, <title>Forth Heavy Brigade R.A. (T.A.)</title>.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Defenses</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Fortification</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Batteries (Ordnance)</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Artillery drill and tactics</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Sandeman</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Gerard L.</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1933-1945 </emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Stenhouse</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Bruce Alexander</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1911-1991</emph> </persname> <corpname role="subject"> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph altrender="x">Army</emph> <emph altrender="x">Territorial Army</emph> <emph altrender="x">Forth Heavy Brigade R.A.</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
