<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-400" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-400</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Correspondence of Alexander Dundas Ross Cochrane-Wishart-Baillie, Lord Lamington (1816-1890)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Jul 15 15:39:18 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-400</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1875, nos.6-9</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence of Alexander Dundas Ross Cochrane-Wishart-Baillie, Lord Lamington (1816-1890)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>4 manuscripts. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Alexander Dundas Ross Cochrane-Wishart-Baillie was born on 24 November 1816, the eldest son of Sir Thomas John Cochrane, G.C.B. Admiral-of-the-Fleet (1789-1872). He was educated at Eton and at Trinity College, Cambridge, where he was awarded the degree of BA in 1837. Between 1841 and 1852 he was MP for Bridport, and then MP for Lanark in 1857, for Honiton between 1859 and 1868, and for the Isle of Wight from 1870 until 1880. Cochrane-Wishart-Baillie was created a Baronet in May 1880, and he took the title Lord Lamington of Lamington, near Biggar, Lanarkshire. He was a Knight of the Order of St. Saviour of Greece. He was a Justice of the Peace and Deputy Lieutenant for the counties of East Lothian and Lanark, and was a Trustee of the National Portrait Gallery. Lord Lamington died in 15 February 1890. He was succeeded by his son Sir Charles Wallace Alexander Napier Cochrane-Baillie, 2nd Baron Lamington (1860-1940). </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of a small number of letters, mostly undated, and with content unremarkable. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Part of a purchase of miscellaneous letters, March 1971, Accession no. E71.5.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Burke, Sir Bernard. and Burke, Ashworth (eds.). <title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage, the privy council, and knightage</title>. 87th edition. p.1401. London: Burke's Peerage Ltd., 1929. (2) Walford, Edward. <title>The county families of the United Kingdom</title>. London: Chatto and Windus, 1885.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes also show a reference to material relating to Charles Wallace Alexander Napier Ross Cochrane-Baillie, 2nd Baron Lamington (1860-1940) (check the Indexes for more details): letters to Mrs. Leslie Thomson, at Gen. 1982/13-14.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Cochrane-Baillie</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander Dundas Ross Wishart</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1816-1890</emph> <emph altrender="title">1st Baron Lamington</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Politician</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Cochrane-Baillie</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Charles Wallace Alexander Napier Ross</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1860-1940</emph> <emph altrender="title">2nd Baron Lamington</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Governor of Bombay</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
