<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-767" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-767</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Henry Dunlop (1799-1867)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Feb 6 12:01:58 UTC 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-767</unitid> <physloc>MSS BOX 25.4.1-24</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Henry Dunlop (1799-1867)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1834-1841">1834-1841</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>10 letters, 3 addresses, 1 prospectus. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Dunlop, Henry; Dunlop, Alexander; Candlish, Robert Smith</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Henry Dunlop was born in Linwood, Renfrewshire, on 7 June 1799. After education at Glasgow High School and Glasgow University, he entered the family cotton trading business of James Dunlop and Sons. Better known for his political activities, Dunlop entered the town council in 1833 and in 1837 he contested a bitterly disputed election for the post of provost. He only succeeded to the post in 1838 after a judgement in the House of Lords. In 1841 and in furtherance of interested parties in the Church, he contested the parliamentary seat of Bute as a Liberal, but the election ended in defeat for him. This interest in ecclesiastical matters led to his move from the Church of Scotland to the Free Church after the Disruption of 1843. Dunlop was chairman of Glasgow Chamber of Commerce in 1841, 1850 and 1862, and in 1848 was appointed Deputy-Lieutenant of Lanarkshire. Henry Dunlop died in Edinburgh on 10 May 1867.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of correspondence and election addresses relating to Henry Dunlop as a candidate for the constituency of Bute in the election of 1841. There are letters from Henry Dunlop to Patrick Stewart and William Mure, from Robert Smith Candlish to Henry Dunlop, from Alexander Dunlop to Henry Dunlop, and from William Mure and Robert Buchanan to Henry Dunlop. There is a letter from David Landsborough to Miss Mure. The collection contains an address to the electors of Bute, an address to the Christian electors of Buteshire, and an address to the independent electors of Buteshire, as well as a prospectus for the proposed erection of Paisley South Church with a list of subscribers and drawings of the proposed chapel and school-house.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Memoirs and portraits of 100 Glasgow men</title>. Full-text [online]. <extref href="http://gdl.cdlr.strath.ac.uk/100men/gm29.htm">Henry Dunlop</extref> [Accessed 6 January 2004].</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Elections</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dunlop</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Henry</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1799-1867</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Merchant, Politician</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dunlop</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1799-1867</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Candlish</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert Smith</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Bute Island (Scotland)</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
