<?xml version="1.0"?> <!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd"> <ead> <eadheader> <eadid publicid="GB 237 Coll-887" countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237">GB 237 Coll-887</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="">Papers of Rev. Alexander Dewar (fl. 1892-1904)</titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by JavaScript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2 on <date>Fri Dec 3 10:04:09 UTC 2004</date>.</creation> </profiledesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-887</unitid> <physloc>E2004.5</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Rev. Alexander Dewar (fl. 1892-1904)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1892-1904">1892-1904</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box holding 8 volumes and 3 envelopes.</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial> <language langcode="fre">French</language> <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial> <origination>Dewar, Alexander</origination> </did> <phystech> <p>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted</p></phystech> <bioghist> <p>The Rev. Alexander Dewar served in the missionary community of the Eastern Cape, South Africa, and with the Free Church of Scotland at Livingstonia, Malawi.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of 8 volumes of notebooks containing diaries or journals covering the period 1892-1901. One of the small notebooks is headed on the inside cover, Hospital Hill, King Williams Town, and contains official stamps and franked postage stamps over the year 1904. Another is headed, Free Church of Scotland, Livingstonia Mission, 1895. Archival envelopes contain photographs and cards of people and places in Africa, and a collection of drawings and sketches of local subjects.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material purchased, accessioned 13 May 2004, Accession no. E2004.5</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987.</p> </otherfindaid> <processinfo> <p>Compiled by Graeme D. Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </processinfo> <!-- Controlled Access Terms --> <controlaccess> <subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> <emph altrender="z">Africa</emph> </subject> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Dewar</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1892-1904 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister, Missionary</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Livingstonia Mission </emph> <emph altrender="z">Livingstonia (Malawi)</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Livingstonia (Malawi)</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc> </ead> 