<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-589" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-589</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of James Kellock (1889-1968)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Nov 29 10:05:49 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-589</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 31</physloc><unittitle>Papers of James Kellock (1889-1968)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1924-1969">1924-1969</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 boxes </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Kellock, James</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> <language langcode="hin">Hindi, </language> and <language langcode="mar">Marathi.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>James Kellock, (United Free) Church of Scotland missionary in India, was born in Glasgow on 9 June 1889. He studied at Glasgow Academy then took an MA in Economic Science at Glasgow University in 1911 followed by a year at the University of Marburg. He saw war service in France between 1914 and 1919, then graduated BD in 1919. Kellock was appointed a missionary with the United Free Church of Scotland in 1919 and joined the staff of Wilson College, Bombay in 1920. He was Professor of Economics and Philosophy until 1944 when he was appointed Principal. He was noted for his ability to reconcile differences during the difficult period leading to, and after, independence. Kellock was also deeply involved in negotiations towards a united church and was the Moderator of the United Church of Northern India between 1950 and 1953. Even after he left India he continued to promote church union and to keep up with developments, in particular the 1957 Plan of Union. His <title>Break Through for Church Union</title> (India: CLS, 1965) is a comprehensive history of developments in this area. Kellock was married in December 1920 and died on 10 June 1968.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of several files relating to the United Church of Northern India and Kellock's involvement in the extension and promotion of church union including committee papers and reports, correspondence, published articles and journals, material relating to Kellock's <title>Break Through for Church Union</title>, and material on the debate over Anglican and Presbyterian union in Scotland.</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>Some of the material was deposited in files and the original file structures and (where possible) file titles have been kept despite considerable overlap in subject. The material that was not in files has been added to the appropriate files.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>The papers were presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World through Reverend Dr William Stewart.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>None expected.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material: (1) the collection itself; (2) entries in <title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scotticanae</title> and <title>Fasti of the United Free Church of Scotland</title>.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The archives of the foreign missions of the Church of Scotland are held by the National Library of Scotland and include correspondence with Kellock; Kellock also donated several pamphlets to the Centre and these have been added to the Library's collections.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Christian union</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Kellock</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James </emph> <emph altrender="dates">1889-1968</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">India</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
