<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-518" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-518</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection of Reproductions of Medallions by Phoebe Anna Traquair (1852-1936)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Mar 3 10:46:42 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-518</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 852 </physloc><unittitle>Collection of Reproductions of Medallions by Phoebe Anna Traquair (1852-1936)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1897">1897</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 bound volume in box. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Traquair, Phoebe Anna</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The artist Phoebe Anna Traquair was born in Dublin in 1852. She moved to Edinburgh in 1873. Her work included jewellery enamelling, book illuminating and binding, embroidery, and mural painting. Her murals can be found at the former Catholic and Apostolic Church, East London Street, Edinburgh, at the Song School, St. Mary's Cathedral, Edinburgh, and in the Thistle Chapel, St. Giles, Edinburgh. Traquair was the first female member of the Royal Scottish Academy. Phoebe Anna Traquair died in 1936.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of reproductions of circa 12 medallions painted by her on the walls of the Song School, St. Mary's Cathedral, Edinburgh, and it also includes a letter to C. R. Barbour. Reproductions on vellum, with gold illumination.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Reproductions, acquired January 1966, Accession no. E66.28. Letter to Barbour, Accession no. E93.10, extraction from Gen. 852, and returned in June 1996.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). <title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins, 1994.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence and papers, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 8122-29</p> </relatedmaterial> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Traquair</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Phoebe Anna Ramsey</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1852-1936</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Artist</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
