<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-491" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-491</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Notes and Publications of Dr. Shelton H. Short (fl. 1965-1974)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Feb 3 11:45:12 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-491</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1976-1977; Gen. 2000; E92.107</physloc><unittitle>Notes and Publications of Dr. Shelton H. Short (fl. 1965-1974)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1965-1974">1965-1974</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box, 2 volumes, 1 typescript</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Shelton Hardaway Short III graduated from Hampden-Sydney College, Virginia, USA, in 1948, and studied History at Edinburgh University from 1966 until 1969 obtaining his degree of Ph.D. there. Both Dr. Short and his wife, Jean Short manage nearly 5,000 acres of forest in Virginia. In 2000, the couple received honorary Doctor of Humane Letters degrees from Randolph-Macon College in Ashland, Virginia. The degrees honoured their commitment to forests and wildlife, as well as to historic preservation, education, and humanitarianism. Dr. Shelton H. Short has served for many years as a state and national representative to the United Nations. The Honourable and Mrs. Shelton H. Short Forestry Professorship has been set up the College of Natural Resources, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Short's publications include <title>A history of the Nevada livestock industry prior to 1900</title> (1965) and <title>From Elsinore to Edinburgh: echoes of a student 1962-1969</title> (1970).</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: a xeroxed collection of publications by Short or on Short, 1965-1974; student notes and personal papers, circa 1965; <title>A journal along the Meherrin from Springs in Charlotte County near Fort Michell of Lunenburg towards the Emporia Ponds</title> 1974; and, <title>A Virginian's impressions of Edinburgh</title>.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Journal received May 1975, from Shelton H. Short, Accession no. E75.26. Notes and papers received March 1976, from Short, Accession no. E76.16. Edinburgh impressions received April 1992, from Short, Accession no. E92.107.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material gleaned from collection and from notes in, (1) Short, Shelton H. 'British attitudes to the war in America'. <title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 30. No.1. June 1981. pp.51-53. Edinburgh: The University of Edinburgh Graduates' Association, 1981.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <bibliography> <p> <title>British attitudes to the Slesvig-Holsten question, 1848-50: a summary of a University of Edinburgh Doctor's Dissertation (1969)</title>. With Danish and German translations. G&#x00F6;ttingen: Dieterich University Press, 1972.</p> </bibliography> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Short</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Shelton H.</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1965-1974</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Historian</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">United States</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Virginia</emph> <emph altrender="x">Description and travel</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh (Scotland)</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
