<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-631" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-631</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection relating to Rev. Dr. A. K. H. Boyd (1825-1899)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Apr 15 11:35:46 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-631</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1429/10/8 Boyd; Gen. 1981/27</physloc><unittitle>Collection relating to Rev. Dr. A. K. H. Boyd (1825-1899)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1877-1899">1877-1899</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 letter, 1 fragment, 1 portrait photograph, 2 cuttings</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Boyd, A. K. H.</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The Rev. Dr. Andrew Kennedy Hutchison Boyd was born at Auchinleck Manse, Ayrshire, on 3 November 1825. He studied at King's College and at the Middle Temple, London, with the idea of becoming a barrister, then went to Glasgow University with the intention of entering the Church. He graduated in 1846 and in 1850 was licensed to preach by the Presbytery of Ayr. For a time he assisted at St. George's, Edinburgh, then in 1851 he was ordained Minister at Newton-on-Ayr. In 1854 Boyd became the Minister at Kirkpatrick-Irongray, near Dumfries, and while there began writing for <title>Fraser's magazine</title> under the name A.K.H.B. In 1859 he was appointed Minister at St. Bernard's, Edinburgh, and in 1864 Edinburgh University conferred on him the honorary degree of D.D. In 1865 he was appointed Minister in St. Andrews and while there began work on recommendations for improvements in the ritual of the Church of Scotland. In 1890 he was appointed Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland. Boyd's publications include the essay series <title>Recreations of a country parson</title> (1839, 1861, and 1878), <title>Graver thoughts of a country parson</title> (1862, 1865, and 1875), and <title>Scotch communion Sunday</title> (1873). One of his last public services was the re-opening of St. Cuthbert's, Edinburgh, on 11 July 1894. The Rev. Dr. Andrew Kennedy Hutchison Boyd died at Iffley, Bournemouth, on 1 March 1899. He was buried in the Cathedral grounds, St. Andrews.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material includes: a letter to Robert Cochrane, November 1886; a signed portrait photograph; a fragment of a letter; article on Boyd from <title>The Christian globe</title>, 19 July 1899; obituary from <title>Daily news</title>, 3 March 1899; and, letter to the Bishop of Grahamstown, April 1897.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Letter, fragment, cuttings, acquired January 1970, Accession no. E70.2</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.22. Supplement. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes shows a reference to Boyd in the form of a letter to Sir. C. J. Pearson, January 1892, at Gen. 756, no.49 (check the Indexes for more details). In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence with Blackwoods, 1867-1897, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 4218-4714 passim., and letters (17), 1865-1897 and undated, Ref. Acc 5373; and letters (22), 1861-1862, Huntington Library. </p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boyd</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Andrew Kennedy Hutchison</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1825-1899</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Church of Scotland Minister at St Andrews Essayist</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
