<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-59" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-59</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">The Archives of the Edinburgh Royal Choral Union </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-59</unitid> <physloc>MSS 3144-3171; E2005.25 </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">The Archives of the Edinburgh Royal Choral Union </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1866-1994">1866-1994 </unitdate> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>16 boxes (2 linear metres); 11 volumes; 1 envelope (45 cm x 36 cm); 1 seal embossing machine. </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>The Edinburgh Choral Union was instituted on 25 November 1858 at Wood's Musical Rooms, Waterloo Place, in central Edinburgh. Its first conductor was Charles J. Hargitt, the organist at St. Mary's Roman Catholic Church, Broughton Street. The choir performed before Queen Victoria on her visit to the Edinburgh International Exhibition held on the Meadows in 1886. The title 'Royal' was conferred by King George V in 1911. The Edinburgh Royal Choral Union (ERCU) sang before Queen Elizabeth II when Beethoven's <title>9th Symphony </title> was conducted by Sir Thomas Beecham at the opening concert of the 1956 Edinburgh International Festival. Many notable soloists have sung with the ERCU since it came into existence, among them Jenny Lind (1861), Isobel Baillie, Kathleen Ferrier, Peter Pears, and Dietrich Fischer-Dieskau. Over the decades, the ERCU has performed many 'firsts' in Scotland, most notably Elgar's <title>Dream of Gerontius </title> (1903), Bach's <title>Mass in B Minor </title> (1907), and Britten's <title>War Requiem </title> (1964). The ERCU is famed for its annual New Year's performances of the <title>Messiah </title>, given since 1888, and in modern times usually held in the city's Usher Hall. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The archives of the Edinburgh Royal Choral Union contain rolls of members since 1866 and including lists of patrons, officers, and directors; correspondence for the period 1877-83; correspondence with members, 1957-69; correspondence with choirs, 1857-1979; minute books from 1881; accounts ledger 1960-75; programmes from the 1940s onwards; bulletins and news-sheets for the National Federation of Musical Societies; press cuttings book; receipts; accounts; posters; and, the ERCU seal with its embossing machine. </p> <p>There is also ERCU promotional material for concerts in the Usher Hall, Methodist Central Hall, and other locations (1950s-1990s) in the form of: posters; handbills; and season programmes. The material includes programmes of the National Federation of Music Societies, Jubilee Concert, Usher Hall, 1985, and Goldsmiths Choral Union concert (L'Entente Chorale. A Revolutionary Requiem), Royal Albert Hall, 1989, as well as material relating to the ERCU centenary in 1958. Also ERCU bulletins and archive material, and musical score (Handel. Selection from the works of G.F. Handel, Edinburgh Choral Union, 9 February 1885).</p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details </p> </accessrestrict> <controlaccess> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh Royal Choral Union</emph> </corpname> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">International Festival of Music and Drama</emph> <emph altrender="z">Edinburgh</emph> </corpname> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">National Federation of Musical Societies</emph> </corpname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Choirs (Music)</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Choral music</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Choral singing</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Choral societies</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H59 </p> </otherfindaid> </archdesc>
</ead>
