<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-733" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-733</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Antony Mario Ludovici (1882-1971)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Dec 1 10:06:49 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-733</unitid> <physloc>MS 3121</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Antony Mario Ludovici (1882-1971)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1960-1969">1960-1969</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Ludovici, Anthony Mario</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Anthony Mario Ludovici was born in London on 8 January 1882. He was privately educated both in England and abroad, and he became fluent in several languages. He started working life as an artist, and served as an artillery officer during 1914-1919, fighting in Armentieres and the Somme. Ludovici married Elsie Finnimore Buckley on 20 March 1920. He was a writer and translator of over 80 works. His writing includes <title>Nietzsche: his life and works</title> (1910), <title>Woman: a vindication</title> (1923), <title>Lysistrata</title> (1924) <title>The future of woman</title> (1936), <title>Enemies of women</title> (1947), and <title>The quest of human quality</title> (1952). Captain Anthony Mario Ludovici died on 3 April 1971.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of 3 pieces of typescript material, being <title>The confessions of an antifeminist</title>, <title>The English countryside today</title>, and the considerably shorter <title>Juvenile delinquency and sex</title>.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material acquired from executors, in Diss, Norfolk, January 1997, Accession no. E97.6</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who's who 1968-1969</title>. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1968.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes these locations of Ludovici related material: letters, 1917-1932, Oxford University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western Manuscripts; correspondence in Eugenics Society papers, 1927-1947, Wellcome Library for the History and Understanding of Medicine; and, letters (32) to Francis Neilson, 1954-1961, Manchester University, John Rylands Library, Ref. Neilson</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Ludovici</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Anthony Mario</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1882-1971</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Author Eugenics Propagandist</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
