<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-341" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-341</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Records of the Round Table Club, Edinburgh</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Mar 19 11:31:52 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-341</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 175-180</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Round Table Club, Edinburgh</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1868-1908">1868-1908</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>4 volumes, 1 photograph album, 1 envelope papers. </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Cunynghame, Robert James Blair; and others </origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The Round Table Club, Edinburgh, arose out of the wish among rising medical graduates for occasional meetings &quot;simply for the purpose of good fellowship&quot;. On 8 December 1868 a party of ten men deemed likely to be &quot;suitable members&quot; met at dinner at the invitation of Dr. Robert James Blair Cunynghame, St. Colme Street, Edinburgh. The diners were: Dr. Cunynghame, Professor Alexander Dickson, Dr. Archibald Dickson, Dr. John Chiene, Dr. Thomas Annandale, Dr. John Duncan, Dr. Thomas Fraser, Dr. Joseph Bell, Dr. Claud Muirhead, and Alexander Crum Brown. These would become the original members of the Round Table Club, and an invitation was also opened to Arthur Gamgee and William Rutherford. The first meeting of the Club was held at Meikle's Hotel, Register Street, Edinburgh.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The records consist of a minute-book for the period 1868-1878, a minute-book covering 1878-1895 with photograph inserts, a notebook with poems dated 1870, an envelope containing correspondence and accounts, a bound photograph album with a few portraits of Round Table Club members, and a volume entitled <title>Annals of the Round Table Club</title>. The volume was edited by J.G.M, and was printed for private use in 1908. It was no.27 of 35 copies printed.</p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Cunynghame</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert James Blair</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Round Table Club, Edinburgh</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
