<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-514" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-514</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Dr. Alexander Burt Taylor (1904-1972)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Feb 20 12:10:33 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-514</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1927/6</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Dr. Alexander Burt Taylor (1904-1972)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1920-1930">1920-1930</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 notebooks in 1 file</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Taylor, Alexander Burt</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Alexander Burt Taylor C.B.E., M.A., D.Litt.(Edin.) was born in Earlston, Berwickshire, in 1904. He was educated at Hamilton Academy and Kirkwall Grammar School, and he studied at Edinburgh University graduating with the degree of M.A. in 1925. He taught in Stirling and Falkirk, and at Columbia University, New York, and in 1933 he joined the Schools' Inspectorate of the Scottish Education Department. At the outbreak of the Second World War, Taylor was seconded to the Department of Health for Scotland and was involved with the evacuation of school children from urban areas and with the homeless. After the war he worked on town and country planning and on the housing programme. In 1947 he was promoted to Assistant Secretary within the Department and took charge of the division responsible for administering the mental health services, specialist services, medical research and rehabilitation. These years too saw the formation of the National Health Service in Scotland. In 1959 Taylor was appointed as Registrar-General of Births, Deaths and Marriages for Scotland. During his period as Registrar-General he improved the public research facilities offered by the Registrar-General's Office, and he was responsible for two censuses of Scotland - the full census 1961 and the ten per cent sample in 1966. The 1961 census was the first in Scotland in which a computer was used. He was made a C.B.E. in 1961, and that year too he became a Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh. He retired in 1966. Taylor's publications include a translation of <title>The Orkneyinga saga: A new translation with introduction and notes</title> (1938), and geographical and historical interests gave impetus to his <title>British and Irish place-names in Old Norse literature</title> (1953). Alexander Burt Taylor died on 13 March 1972. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers consist of notes on Old Norse literature and Anglo-Saxon literature.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Rennie, A. L. 'Alexander Burt Taylor C.B.E., M.A., D.Litt.(Edin.)' <title>Year Book R.S.E., 1972-73</title>. Edinburgh.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <bibliography> <p>At Edinburgh University Library, shelfmark .8396 Ork. a copy of <title>The Orkneyinga saga</title>. Edinburgh; London: Oliver and Boyd, 1938.</p> </bibliography> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph> <emph altrender="z">Old English, ca. 450-1100</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Old Norse literature</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Taylor</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander Burt</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1904-1972</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Registrar General for Scotland</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
