<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-710" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-710</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Material relating to Professor Alfred Edward Taylor (1869-1945)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Oct 21 11:44:38 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-710</unitid> <physloc>E95.54</physloc> <unittitle>Material relating to Professor Alfred Edward Taylor (1869-1945)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1903-1910">1903-1910</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 folders.</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Taylor, Alfred Edward</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Alfred Edward Taylor was born on 22 December 1869. He was educated at Kingswood School, Bath, and he studied at New College, Oxford. He was a Fellow of Merton College, 1891-1898. He was the brother of the Rev. Ernest Wesley Taylor who studied at Oxford and at Cuddesdon Theological College (Ripon College, Cuddesdon). From 1896, Alfred Edward Taylor was an assistant lecturer in Greek at Owens College, Manchester, and in 1903 he became Professor of Philosophy at McGill University in Montreal. In 1908, Taylor returned to Britain as Professor of Moral Philosophy at St. Andrews University, and in 1924 he was appointed Professor of Moral Philosophy at Edinburgh University. He became Professor Emeritus in 1941. Taylor was an international authority on Plato and he was a strong Anglo-Catholic. His publications include <title>The problem of conduct</title> (1901, <title>Plato and Thomas Hobbes in philosophies ancient and modern</title> (1908), <title>St. Thomas Aquinas as a philosopher</title> (1924), <title>The faith of a moralist</title> (1930), and <title>Socrates</title> (1933). Professor Alfred Edward Taylor died on 31 October 1945.</p> <p>The Rev. Ernest Wesley Taylor had died at Barble Bay, New Guinea on 23 June 1903.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of: newspaper cuttings; notes; family papers including those relating to the Rev. Ernest Wesley Taylor; photograph of the Rev. E.W.Taylor; and, copies of off-prints, proceedings, journals, including <title>Truth and practice</title> reprinted from the <title>Philosophical review</title> Vol.14. No.3. May 1905, a 1908 copy of <title>College echoes</title> from St. Andrews university, a 1901 copy of <title>Missionary notes. The Australian Board of Missions</title>, and a 1905 copy of <title>West Australia Church News</title> from Perth, Australia.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material was acquired from Dr. P. Dunstan, Divinity Faculty, Cambridge University, July 1995, Accession no. E95.54</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1941-1950</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1952. (2) <title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise dictionary</title>. Part 2. 1901-1970. Oxford: OUP, 1982</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show a reference to Taylor related material (check the Indexes for more details), namely: translations from Plato and Leibnitz, 20th century, at Dc.1.92. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Taylor related material: letters (33) to Samuel Alexander, 1904-1931 and undated, Manchester University, John Rylands Library, Ref. Alexander papers NRA 25975 Alexander; letters to E. H. Blakeney (22 items), 1925-1942, Cambridge University Library, Department of Manuscripts and University Archives, Ref. Add 7509 NRA 40859 Blakeney; and, correspondence with Macmillans, 1900-1939, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 55166.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Philosophers</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Taylor</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alfred Edward</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1869-1945</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Philosopher</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
