<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-781" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-781</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of the Very Rev. William White Anderson (1888-1956)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Mar 30 10:32:06 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-781</unitid> <physloc>MSS ANDER. 1-14</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Very Rev. William White Anderson (1888-1956)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1930-1952">1930-1952</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>9 volumes, and miscellaneous. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Anderson, William White</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>William White Anderson was born on 17 March 1888. He was educated at Bo'ness Academy, and then he studied at Glasgow University. Anderson became a missioner in New Brunswick, Canada, in 1912, and during the 1914-1918 War he was a Chaplain to the Forces. He was Senior Chaplain (9th Division), served with the army of occupation in Germany, and was Senior Chaplain in the Lowland Division. He received the M.C. in 1917. He was Minister of Bellahouston Parish Church, 1919-1926, Minister of New Kilpatrick Parish, Bearsden, 1926-1931, and then from 1931 was the Junior then Senior Minister of St. Cuthbert's Parish Church, Edinburgh, and he was Chaplain too in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, 1926. During the 1939-1945 War he served with the Royal Navy and he was awarded the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve Officers' Decoration. In 1951, Anderson was appointed Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland, and in 1952 became Chaplain to the Queen in Scotland. Earlier he had been Chaplain to King George VI in Scotland, 1949-1952. The Very Rev. William White Anderson died 17 December 1956.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: sermon notebooks; lectures, mainly on Scottish subjects; prayers for public worship; miscellaneous poems, quotations from prose works, newspaper cuttings, and author and subject index, Anderson's <title>Gleanings</title>; a collection of anecdotes; and, memorabilia from the Moderatorial year, 1951-1952.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1951-1960</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1961.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Sermons</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Anderson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William White</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1888-1956</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister of St Cuthbert's Edinburgh, Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
