<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-757" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-757</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of the Very Rev. Professor Archibald Hamilton Charteris (1835-1908)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Jan 23 11:53:52 UTC 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-757</unitid> <physloc>MSS CHAR 1.1-4</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Very Rev. Professor Archibald Hamilton Charteris (1835-1908)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1880-1912">1880-1912</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>4 volumes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Charteris, Archibald Hamilton</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Archibald Hamilton Charteris was born in Wamphray, Dumfriesshire, on 13 December 1835. He was educated at the school in Wamphray and then he studied at Edinburgh University and at Tuebingen and Bonn. He was a Minister successively at St. Quivox, South Ayrshire, Newabbey, Kirkcudbrightshire, and the Park Parish, Glasgow. In 1868 he was appointed Professor of Biblical Criticism at Edinburgh University, a post which he held until 1898, after which he became Emeritus Professor. Charteris was instrumental in the setting up of the Church of Scotland's parish magazine <title>Life and work</title>, the Woman's Guild, and the Deaconess Hospital. He was Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland in 1892, and from 1901 he was Chaplain in Ordinary to King Edward VII in Scotland. His publications included <title>Life of Professor James Robertson</title> (1863) and <title>The church of Christ</title>. The Very Rev. Professor Archibald Hamilton Charteris died on 24 April 1908. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection comprises: lectures on Galatians, session 1885-1886; lecture book, prophecy in the Old testament, 1896-1897; a volume of newspaper cuttings and obituary notices, and including an address by Dr. I. Mitford Mitchell at the dedication of the Charteris Memorial Church in Edinburgh, 1912; and, <title>Canonicity</title>, a collection of early testimonies to the canonical books of the New Testament, with notes by Charteris.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who ... 1897-1916</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1920.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes on Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division, George Square, Edinburgh, show various references to Charteris related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter, 1913, at Sar. Coll.8; letter to A. Berriedale Keith about lectures on the Australian Constitution, 1929, at Gen. 145/1/63; letter to Charteris from the Secretary of <title>Everyman</title>, 1913, at Sar. Col. 8; letter to Mrs. Wauchope, at Dk.2.14, p.37; and, letter to D. Laing enclosing a letter from Miss E. Hamilton conveying the thanks of the ladies' class in biblical criticism to those responsible for arranging an exhibition of manuscripts, 1874, at La.IV.17; letter of Charteris to Sir. C. J. Pearson, 1901, at Gen. 756, no. 80.</p> <p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence with Lord Balfour of Burleigh, 1881-1889, Private, Ref. NRA(S)0923 NRA 18285 Bruce; and, correspondence with Blackwoods, 1862-1898, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 4168-4714 passim.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Biblical scholars</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Charteris</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Archibald Hamilton</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1835-1908</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Biblical Scholar</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
