<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-188" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-188</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of David Cuthbertson (1856-1935)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Dec 21 10:12:46 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-188</unitid> <physloc>Dc.10.25; Dc.2.80/1-2; Gen. 1973; Gen. 1730 Cuthbertson</physloc><unittitle>Papers of David Cuthbertson (1856-1935)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1910-1929">1910-1929</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>4 volumes, 1 letter. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>David Cuthbertson was born in Kilmarnock, Ayrshire, on 27 June 1856. He studied at Edinburgh University and was Assistant Librarian at the Philosophical Institution in Edinburgh, from 1874 until 1879. Then, in 1880 he was appointed to the staff of Edinburgh University Library, first as an Assistant Librarian, and then as Sub-Librarian. He retired in 1925. Cuthbertson was a writer too and his publications include <title>Eskside lyrics</title> (1878), <title>Rosslyn lyrics</title> (1878), <title>Edinburgh University Library</title> (1910), <title>A tragedy of the Reformation</title> (1912), <title>The Edinburgh of John Knox and John Knox in Edinburgh</title> (1914), <title>Through the fires to freedom</title> (1921), and <title>The life history of Alexander Anderson (Surfaceman)</title> (1929). He also wrote <title>Student life at Edinburgh University</title> (1884) under the pseudonym Norman Fraser. David Cuthbertson lived at Inveresk in Midlothian, and he died on 12 January 1935. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers include: typewritten scripts circa 1920 of <title>The Conservator for Scotland (Sir Thomas Cunningham) and the Thrissels Banner, (1640)</title>; essays and studies by Cuthbertson, 1920-1924; a poem in manuscript <title>To Miss Jessie Brough</title> and <title>Thirty-three years' adventures in bookland</title>; and, typed, signed correspondence about the proposed Anderson book, 1929. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Manuscript poem purchased 1975, Accession no. E75.3. Letter about Anderson book purchased April 1972, Accession no. E72.11.</p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>Cuthbertson's <title>Student life at Edinburgh University</title> published by J. and R. Parlane, Paisley, 1884, can be found in the Main Library, Special Collections, Edinburgh University Library, at shelfmark S.B. .378(41445) Cut.</p> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1929-1940</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1941.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes an item relating, separately, to Sir Thomas Cunningham: journal at Campvere, 1640-1654, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections, shelfmark La.III. 639, see Index to Manuscripts.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Cuthbertson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">David</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1856-1935</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Sub-Librarian, Edinburgh University Library</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Anderson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1845-1909</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Poet</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Cunningham</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1640-1654</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight, Scots Conservator in the Netherlands </emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University Library</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
