<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-697" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-697</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Records of Edinburgh Anti-Apartheid Group</titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Oct 8 09:11:55 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-697</unitid> <physloc> E98.73</physloc><unittitle>Records of Edinburgh Anti-Apartheid Group</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1980-1993">1980-1993</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 folder or file. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Edinburgh Anti-Apartheid Group</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>During the period for which the contents of the collection are relevant, the Honorary President of the Edinburgh Anti-Apartheid Group was the Rev. Professor Duncan B. Forrester, Professor Emeritus of Theology and Public Issues at Edinburgh University, and the Chair of the organisation was Abdou Said Bakar. The finances of the Group were handled by the Co-operative Bank in the city's South St. Andrew Street. The Edinburgh Group involved itself with the Walter Sisulu Campaign Fund and the Nelson Mandela Freedom at 70 Campaign.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material, largely financial in nature and from the 1980s and 1990s, consists of a list of office bearers, a press list, and accounts including those for the Walter Sisulu Campaign Fund and the Nelson Mandela Freedom at 70 Campaign. Accounts include statements from the Bank of Scotland, and the Co-operative Bank. Also an accounts book and miscellaneous correspondence.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material received from Edinburgh Anti-Apartheid Group, December 1998, Accession no. E98.73.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Anti-apartheid movements</emph> </subject> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh Anti-Apartheid Group</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
