<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-763" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-763</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection of Margaret Duncan Campbell (fl. 1850-1860)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Feb 6 10:56:58 UTC 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-763</unitid> <physloc>MSS BOX 36.2.1-32</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Margaret Duncan Campbell (fl. 1850-1860)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1825-1894">1825-1894</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>circa 30 letters, envelopes, or signature fragments. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Campbell, John MacLeod; Erskine, Thomas; Campbell, Margaret Duncan</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Margaret Duncan Campbell was the daughter of the Scottish divine John Macleod Campbell (1800-1872) of Kilninver, near Oban, Argyll, and Mary, daughter of John Campbell also from Kilniver. They had married in 1838.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The letters include those from the 8th Duke of Argyll to John McLeod Campbell, from G.D.Boyle, Dean of Salisbury, to Donald Campbell, from F.H.Browne, Bishop of Winchester to John McLeod Campbell, from Baron Carlingford to John McLeod Campbell, from Thomas Erskine to John McLeod Campbell, from Alexander Ewing, Bishop of Argyll and the Isles to Margaret Duncan Campbell, from Edward Irving to John McLeod Campbell, from Edmund Law Lushington to John McLeod Campbell, from Norman MacLeod to John McLeod Campbell, from John Campbell Shairp to John McLeod Campbell, from Hugh McNiele, Dean of Ripon to John McLeod Campbell, from F.D.Maurice to John McLeod Campbell, from Alexander John Scott to John McLeod Campbell, from A.C. Tait, Archbishop of Canterbury to John McLeod Campbell, from C.J.Vaughan, Dean of Llandaff, to Donald Campbell, from Frances, Countess of Waldegrave, to John McLeod Campbell, letters from John Brown, Thomas Carlyle, Thams Chalmers, Principal John Lee, and A.P. Forbes, Bishop of Brechin, to Thomas Erskine of Linlathen, from William Edward Norris to Donald Campbell, and from John Tulloch to Margaret Duncan Campbell. There is also a specimen of the hand of Barry Cornwall, an autograph signature of Edward Bouverie Pusey, part of a letter in the handwriting of John Keble, and numerous envelopes.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.3. Brown-Chaloner. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>There is also a sale catalogue of contents of authograph album belonging to Margaret Duncan Campbell, issued by the seller, N. H. Tallersfield, at time of purchase by New College Library, November 1981. folio. 27 leaves. Typescript (photocopy), at MSS BOX 36.1.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Campbell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Margaret Duncan</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1850-1860</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Daughter of John McLeod Campbell</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Campbell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John MacLeod </emph> <emph altrender="dates">1800-1872</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scottish divine</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Erskine</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1788-1870</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Advocate and Theologian</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
