<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-854" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-854</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of William Tait (1793-1864)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Aug 30 10:40:54 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-854</unitid> <physloc>Dc.4.101-103 Tait; Gen. 2041/150-151</physloc><unittitle>Letters of William Tait (1793-1864)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1832-1853">1832-1853</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Tait, William</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>William Tait was born in Edinburgh on 11 May 1793. He attended Edinburgh University briefly with the intention of following a law career and was articled to a Writer to the Signet. However he abandoned that path and became a bookseller with his brother, and began publishing. His principal works published were Brown's <title>Philosophy of the human mind</title>, Carlyle's <title>German romance</title>, and Tytler's <title>History of Scotland</title>. He is most well known for the literary and radical political <title>Tait's Edinburgh magazine</title> which first appeared in April 1832 and ran until December 1864. Contributors to the publication included John Stuart Mill, Cobden and Bright. Tait's shop was a meeting place for Edinburgh notables. William Tait retired from business in 1848 and he died at his Melrose estate of Prior Bank on 4 October 1864.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The letters are to T. Doubleday, to J. M. Ludlow written from Edinburgh, and to D. E. Milne written from Prior Bank. One to Doubleday is about <title>Tait's Edinburgh magazine</title>, another accompanies a returned article (not in collection) on Afghanistan which 'seems a very good one but too late for me', and the other along with a subscription to the Liverpool Financial Association and the note that Prior Bank is where he chiefly resides 'although I retain my Edinburgh house and reside there a good deal during the winter'.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 19. Stow-Tytler. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show various references to William Tait material which may or may not relate to William Tait, Publisher (check the Indexes for more details): letters (2) of Tait, William, to Messrs Cunningham and Mortimer, 1843, at La.II.646/242/1-2; correspondence of Tait (William) Publisher, with P. F. Tytler, at La.II.494; letter to Tait, William, from T. Aird, 1828, at La.II.336; letter to Tait (William) Publisher, from Thomas Carlyle about his <title>German romance</title>, at Gen. 1730 onwards; letter to Tait, William, from E. Elliott, 1832, at La.II.647/170; and, letter to Tait, William, from W. Howitt, 1836, at La.II.647/215.</p> <p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence, 1820-1849, National Library of Scotland, Manuscript Collections, Ref. MSS 3713, 3823, letters to John Burton, 1834-1854, Ref. MS 9406, and correspondence with Thomas De Quincey, 1834-1846, Ref. MS 1670; letters to Peter Mackenzie, 1834, East Dunbartonshire Archives, Kirkintilloch, Ref. NRA(S)0347 NRA 11630; correspondence with Richard Cobden, 1836-1853, West Sussex Record Office, Ref. Cobden papers NRA 10616 Cobden; correspondence with Richard Cobden, 1836-1853, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 43665 NRA 5927 Cobden; and, correspondence with J. A. Roebuck, 1833-1847, Liverpool University, Special Collections and Archives, Ref. D.584/6/1/ NRA 39999 Roebuck.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Publishers and publishing</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Tait</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1793-1864</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Publisher </emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
