<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-661" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-661</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of Sir Francis Powell (1833-1914)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed May 7 10:23:58 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-661</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1982/90-93</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Sir Francis Powell (1833-1914)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1875-1903">1875-1903</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 letters, 1 receipt. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Powell, Francis</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The watercolour painter Sir Francis Powell was born in Pendleton, Manchester, on 22 March 1833. He was educated at the Rev, Dr. Beard's School. He trained at Manchester School of Art. His paintings were of marine and lake views and in 1857 he went to live in Dunoon in the Clyde estuary. In 1877 he won the Haywood prize for the best watercolour exhibited in Manchester. When he was living in Glasgow in 1878 he became one of the founders of the Royal Scottish Society of Watercolour Painters. He was its first President. Works include <title>Ben Nevis from Locheil</title>, <title>The Channel tug</title>, <title>Loch Corruisk</title>, and <title>The north of Arran</title>. His work is displayed in the Victoria and Albert, in Dundee and Glasgow, in Manchester, and in Portsmouth. Powell was knighted in 1893. Sir Francis Powell died in Dunoon on 27 November 1914.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: receipt for Pounds Sterling 109. 4 shillings for three drawings, 1875; letter to Leslie Thomson about the Crystal Palace, 1893; letter to Hughes about a supper to be given, 1903; and, letter to Mr. Crawford, 1903.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) McEwan, Peter J. M. <title>Dictionary of Scottish art and architecture</title>. pp.466-467. Woodbridge, Suffolk: Antique Collectors' Club, 1994. (2) <title>Who was who ... 1897-1916</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1920.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Painters</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Artists</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Powell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Francis</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1833-1914</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Artist</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
