<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-475" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-475</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection of Material relating to Robert Rollock (c. 1555-1599)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Nov 11 11:42:56 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-475</unitid> <physloc>Dc.4.68</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Material relating to Robert Rollock (c. 1555-1599)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1601-1699">17th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>141 manuscript sides</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Robert Rollock, the first Principal of Edinburgh University, was possibly born in 1555. He was educated in Stirling and in 1574 studied at St. Salvator's College, St. Andrews University. Soon after his graduation he became a Regent (or Professor) at the University, and in 1580 he became Director of the Faculty of Arts. At this time too he was studying Divinity. In 1583 he was appointed by Edinburgh Town Council as the sole Regent at the new college in the city - later to become known as Edinburgh University. By 1585-1586 he was known as the Principal or First Master, and in 1587 he became Professor of Theology retaining his office as Principal too. In 1590, Rollock became Assessor to the Moderator of the General Assembly and in 1591 was named as one of the committee set up by the Presbytery of Edinburgh to hold a conference with King James VI on the affairs of the Church of Scotland. He was persuaded to support the King's stance towards the Church, and he was made Moderator of the General Assembly held in Dundee in May 1597. Robert Rollock died in 1599.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material bound together consists of: <title>Commentarius in primam beati Apostoli Petri Epistolam, a D. Roberto Rolloco ... inchoatus, et ab henrico Charterisio ... absolutus</title> 1627; and Latin epitaphs on Rollock by various friends and colleagues, circa 1627.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 17. Robinson-Sheares. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Rollock related material (check the Indexes for more details): signature to a discharge, 1578, at La.II.146; and, original demission of the parsonage of Forteviot, 1586, at La.II.227. </p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Rollock</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph altrender="dates">c. 1555-1599</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Principal of Edinburgh University</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
