<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-179" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-179</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Records of the English Association (Scottish Branch)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Dec 07 11:52:32 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-179</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 2121</physloc><unittitle>Records of the English Association (Scottish Branch)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1906-1959">1906-1959</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>5 volumes, 1 envelope containing papers. </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Saintsbury, George Edward Bateman; and others</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>A meeting was held at Edinburgh University on Saturday 22 September 1906 to form a branch of the English Association. Professor George Saintsbury was voted to the Chair and he moved the resolution 'That a Scottish branch of the English Association be and is hereby formed'. The resolution was seconded by Dr. H. Bellyse Baildon. The objects of the English Association were: to afford opportunities for exchange and co-operation among those interested in English language and literature; to help and maintain correct use of English; to promote the language as an essential element in national education; to discuss methods of teaching; and, to encourage and facilitate the advanced study of English language and literature. After some seventy years, in May 1976, William Aitken, Honorary Treasurer of the Association, wrote that the Edinburgh branch, or local centre, would close 'in view of the state of the declining membership and the lack of office-bearers'. Association funds would be donated to the University Library which would also keep the branch records.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The records consist of a minute-book for the period 1906-1912, a minute-book for the period 1912-1933, a minute-book for the period 1933-1943, a minute book for the period 1934-1944, a secretary's expenses book for 1948-1959, and an envelope containing programmes for the Dundee and Glasgow local centres and other printed matter. The minute-books contain various inserts, clippings, and correspondence.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Records received January 1981, Accession no. E81.8. Further records received January 2001, Accession no. E.2001.5</p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English language</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph> </subject> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Saintsbury</emph> <emph altrender="forename">George Edward Bateman</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1845-1933</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Literary Critic and Historian </emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">English Association</emph> <emph altrender="z">Scottish branch</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
