<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-636" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-636</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of Thomas Graves Law (1836-1904)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Apr 21 11:58:15 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-636</unitid> <physloc>Gen.1875/20-22</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Thomas Graves Law (1836-1904)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1880-1891">1880-1891</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 letters or notes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Law, Thomas Graves</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The Scottish historian and bibliographer Thomas Graves Law was born on 4 December 1836. He was the grandson of Edward Law, 1st Baron of Ellenborough. He was educated at Winchester, University College, London, and at Stoneyhurst. He was a Roman Catholic priest, 1860-1878, and then in 1880 he married Wilhelmina Henrietta Allen, the grand-daughter of the 1st Earl of Camperdown. Law was Keeper or Librarian of the Signet Library, 1878 until 1901. He received the degree of Honorary Doctor of Laws from Edinburgh University, 1898. Thomas Graves Law died on 12 March 1904.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The correspondence is composed of miscellaneous letters, 1880-1882; and, letter to Mr. Cotton about a 'literary piece of gossip', 1891.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Letters purchased March 1971, Accession no. E71.5.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection, and (1) Burke, Sir Bernard. Burke, Asworth P. (eds.) <title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage, the Privy Council, and knightage</title>. 87th ed. p.884. London: Burke's Peerage Ltd., 1929.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: 1878-96: letters to W. E. Gladstone, 1878-1896, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MSS 44458-524 passim; and, letters to Lord Acton, 1889-1900, Cambridge University Library, Department of Manuscripts and University Archives, Ref. Add MSS 6443, 8119 NRA 37383 Acton.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Law</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Thomas Graves</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1836-1904</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Historian and Bibliographer</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
