<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-405" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-405</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Rev. Donald Macrae, Minister of Edderton, Ross-shire (1864-1923)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Jul 16 10:05:30 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-405</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 42</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Rev. Donald Macrae, Minister of Edderton, Ross-shire (1864-1923)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box containing circa 60 notebooks. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Donald Macrae was born in Aviemore on 10 January 1864. He was educated at Raining's School, Inverness, and then studied at St. Andrews University (MA., 1887) and at Aberdeen University (BD., 1890). He was licensed to preach by the Presbytery of Dornoch and was a missionary at Ardgour. He was ordained at Lairg in September 1890, and was in Edderton, Ross-shire in 1902. Between 1915 and 1923, he was Clerk of the Presbytery. His publications include <title>Notes on the history of the parish of Lairg</title> (1898), and Latin articles in the journals <title>Vox Urbis</title> and <title>Alma Roma</title> (1895-1922). Reverend Donald Macrae died in Inverness on 5 September 1923.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers consist of translations of Zeuss's <title>Grammatica celtica: E monumentis vetustis tam hibernicae linguae quam britannicarum dialectorum, cambricae, cornicae, armoricae comparatis gallicae priscae reliquiis </title> published in Leipzig 1853, and Berlin 1871.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Scott, Hew <title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scoticanae: the succession of ministers in the Church of Scotland from the Reformation</title>. Vol. 7. New edition. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1928.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <bibliography> <p>Copies of <title>Grammatica Celtica: E monumentis vetustis tam hibernicae linguae quam britannicarum dialectorum, cambricae, cornicae, armoricae comparatis gallicae priscae reliquiis</title> by Kaspar Zeuss (1806-1856) are noted in the Edinburgh University Library Catalogue. Shelfmarks are: .4916 Zeu., and Ct.9.33 (Special Collections).</p> </bibliography> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Celtic languages</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Macrae</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Donald</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1864-1923 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister of Edderton, Ross-shire</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Zeuss</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Kaspar</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1806-1856</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
