<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-441" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-441</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures and Letters of Professor Alexander Monro
			 (1773-1859)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Sep 19 14:22:47 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-441</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.7.120, pp.199-375; Dc.3.108, pp.117-274; Dc.4.101-103 Monro
		  tertius</physloc><unittitle>Lectures and Letters of Professor Alexander Monro
		  (1773-1859)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1808-1835">1808-1835</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 volumes (part), 1 letter</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Alexander Monro was born in Edinburgh on 5 November 1773. he was the
		  son of Professor Alexander Monro (1733-1817). He was educated at the city's
		  Royal High School and then studied at Edinburgh University like his father and
		  grandfather before him. He was awarded his M.D. in 1797, writing the thesis 
		<title>De Dysphagia</title>. Between 1798 and 1808 he shared the Chair of
		Medicine, Surgery and Anatomy at Edinburgh University with his father,
		assisting with lectures, although he visited Paris in the earliest years of
		this co-occupancy. From 1808 he began delivering the whole lecture programme
		and in 1817 became the Professor, succeeding his father who died that year. His
		published works include 
		<title>Observations on crural hernia</title> (1811), 
		<title>Engravings of the thoracic and abdominal viscera</title> (1818), 
		<title>Anatomy of the pelvis of the male</title> and, 
		<title>Anatomy of the urinary bladder and perinaeum in the male</title>
		(1842). Professor Alexander Monro, tertius, died in Craiglockhart, Edinburgh,
		on 10 March 1859.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: notes on anatomy from the lectures of
		  Monro, 1808; a letter to Dr. Arnold of Beccles offering to obtain for him a
		  post as a naval surgeon, 1808; and, a pen and ink sketch of Monro, circa 1834
		  or 1835.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.13.
		Masquerier-Myles. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show references to other Monro, tertius, related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): a letter to Monro from G. H.
		  Baird in the Laing Collection, at La.II.151; and, dealings with George Lawrie,
		  resurrectionist, mentioned in a letter of Sir W. Rae, 1821, at Gen. 1429/18/2.
		  In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the
		  Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: lecture notes, Royal College of
		  Surgeons of England, see Bridson, Natural history MS resources 1980; medical
		  MSS, Exeter Cathedral Archives, see ASLIB Directory of Literary and Historical
		  Collections 1993; and, correspondence and lecture notes, 1803-1835, Royal
		  College of Physicians of Edinburgh, Ref. Monro NRA 16015 Coll of
		  Physicians.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Anatomists</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Anatomy</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Monro</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1773-1859</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Anatomist</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
