<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-196" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-196</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of John Douglas (1721-1807), Bishop of
			 Salisbury</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jan 23 11:54:56 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-196</unitid> 
		<physloc>La.II.587; Dc.4.41/19-34</physloc><unittitle>Papers of John
		  Douglas (1721-1807), Bishop of Salisbury</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1771-1801">1771-1801</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 19 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John Douglas, the Bishop of Salisbury, was born on 14 July 1721. He
		  was the son of a merchant in Pittenweem, Fife, and grandson of an Episcopalian
		  clergyman in Saltoun, East Lothian. He was educated in Dunbar, East Lothian,
		  until 1736 when he entered St. Mary's Hall, Oxford. In 1738 he was at Balliol,
		  and 1740 he graduated with the degree of B.A. After a period abroad learning
		  French, he was awarded the degree of M.A. in 1743. The following year, Douglas
		  was ordained as a deacon and was appointed chaplain to the 3rd Regiment of Foot
		  Guards. In 1745, he was at the Battle of Fontenoy. On his return from the army,
		  he was again at Balliol and in 1747 he was ordained as a priest, and was then
		  curate of Tilehurst near Reading and then at Dunstew, Oxfordshire. A post of
		  tutor to Lord Pulteney, son of the Marquis of Bath, followed, and then livings
		  at Eaton Constantine and at Uppington in Shropshire, before becoming vicar of
		  High Ercall, Shropshire. In 1758, Douglas took the degree of D.D. and he was
		  given the curacy of Kenley in Shropshire, and in 1762 a canonry at Windsor. A
		  living at St. Augustine and St. Faith, Watling Street, London, followed, and a
		  canonry at St. Paul's in 1776. In 1787 Douglas was appointed Bishop of
		  Carlisle, and in 1788 Dean of Windsor. In 1791 he became Bishop of Salisbury.
		  His publications, many of which were political papers, include a pamphlet
		  entitled 
		<title>Milton vindicated from the charge of plagiarism</title> (1751), a
		book 
		<title>Criterion</title> (1752), 
		<title>Apology for the clergy</title> (1755), 
		<title>A serious defence of some late measures of the
		  administration</title> (1756), and 
		<title>The conduct of the late Commander candidly considered</title>
		(1759). John Douglas, Bishop of Salisbury, died on 18 May 1807. He was buried
		in St. George's Chapel, Windsor on 25 May.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers consist of correspondence, and include letters to J.
		  Basire, and to some unnamed, 1790, 1794, and letters to Alexander Carlyle,
		  1771-1801.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.5. Craik-Drake.
		London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show another reference to Douglas related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): mention several times in letters from J.
		  Logan, 1780-1788, at La.II.419. In addition, the UK National Register of
		  Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes:
		  autobiography, correspondence and papers, British Library, Manuscript
		  Collections, Ref. Eg MSS 2177-86, and letters to Earl of Hardwicke, Ref. Add MS
		  35403; miscellaneous papers, Wiltshire and Swindon Record Office, see
		  Accessions to repositories 1961; 1761-68: letters to Henry Bowdler, Oxford
		  University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western Manuscripts, Ref.
		  MS Top Salop c 3, and correspondence with Richard Scrope, 1773-1775, Ref. MS
		  Clarendon 151; and, letters to Brudenell and Hayman Rooke (4), 1761-1788,
		  Gloucestershire Record Office, Ref. D1833 NRA 4949 Rooke.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Douglas</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1721-1807</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Bishop of Salisbury</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Carlyle</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1722-1805</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister of
		  Inveresk, Pamphleteer</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
