<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-125" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-125</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Dr. J. M. Caborn (d. 1986)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Nov 20 09:13:10 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-125</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS 2797-2800</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Dr. J. M. Caborn (d.
		  1986)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 boxes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Dr. J. Maurice Caborn was a member of staff of the Department of
		  Forestry and Natural Resources, Edinburgh University. During the Second World
		  War he served in India. Caborn began studying forestry at the University in
		  1948 and graduated with the degree of B.Sc. in 1951. He also carried out
		  research for the degree of Ph.D. He worked for the Forestry Commission, serving
		  in Norfolk, and also as a manager on a private forest in Argyll, Scotland. From
		  1953 he developed a research programme at Edinburgh University on shelterbelts
		  and their influence on microclimate and farm crops. Caborn then did
		  post-doctoral work in Canada with the Department of Agriculture laboratory in
		  Saskatchewan, and also with the University College of Wales. He returned to
		  Edinburgh in 1959 as a Lecturer. He was a Fellow of the Royal Meteorological
		  Society and his research interest was mainly in wind flow around obstacles and
		  wind effects on trees and crops. Dr. J. M. Caborn died on 4 September 1986.</p>
		
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: estate plans, including plan of estate
		  under the Heriot-Watt University development plan for Riccarton; landscape
		  reports; particulars of individual trees; files and notes on forest engineering
		  and forest botany; report on the Forest of Dean and Tintern Wood; and, a
		  working plan for an area of New Forest, 1951-1961.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The material was acquired from Mrs. Caborn per Dr. W. E. S. Mutch,
		  Department of Forestry and Natural Resources, September 1987, Accession no.
		  E87.86.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 33. No. 1. June
		1987. p.60. Edinburgh: University of Edinburgh Graduates' Association,
		1987.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Forests and forestry</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Caborn</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">J. Maurice </emph> <emph altrender="dates">d. 1986
		  </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Lecturer</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
