<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-734" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-734</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of material relating to Christian Science
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Dec 1 10:18:47 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-734</unitid> 
		<physloc>MS 2749</physloc><unittitle>Collection of material relating to
		  Christian Science </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1900-1928">1900-1928</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 40 newspaper cuttings, circa 40 printed items;
		  circa 15 off-prints and journals, and miscellaneous ephemera collected into a
		  scrapbook. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Alexander, Stella Hadden</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Christian Science was founded in 1879 in the USA by Mary Baker Eddy
		  (1821-1910). Chronic ill-health led her to the charismatic healer Phineas P.
		  Quimby. His suggestive therapeutics led her to believe in the mental nature of
		  her illness. In 1866 she recovered from the effects of an accident while
		  reading about the healings of Jesus in the New Testament. This prompted a
		  period in her life of intense scriptural study and writing, and in 1870 she
		  began teaching and attracting a following in Massachussetts. In 1875 she
		  published 
		<title>Science and health</title> which became the textbook for the study
		and practice of Christian Science. In 1879, she and a group of followers
		founded the Church of Christ, Scientist, in Boston, and she instructed at the
		Massachussetts Metaphysical College chartered by her in 1881. By the end of the
		1880s some one hundred congregations had been formed, mostly in the Atlantic
		states and the Midwest. By 1910 there were more than 1,200. The government of
		the church was set down in Eddy's 
		<title>Manual of the mother church</title> in 1895. Christian Science is
		widely known for its international daily newspaper published in Boston, 
		<title>The Christian Science Monitor</title>.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of material gathered together by Mrs.
		  Stella Hadden Alexander who had received the degree of CSB from the Christian
		  Science College in Boston, 1906. She had been a student of Augusta E. Stetson
		  (d. 1928) herself a student of Mary Baker Eddy. The material is composed of:
		  newspaper articles on Mary Baker Eddy, Augusta E. Stetson, and on Christian
		  Science; printed items on the church; off-prints and journals including copies
		  of 
		<title>Christian Science quarterly</title> for May 1926, and February
		1927; and, miscellaneous flyers, pamphlets and other ephemera.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Presented to Edinburgh University Library by Mrs. Stella Hadden
		  Alexander, and transferred from shelfmark Att. 20.38, May 1997, Accession no.
		  E97.32.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. 15th edition. Vol.3.
		Micropaedia. Ready Reference. pp.278-280. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica
		Inc., 1991. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Christian Science</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Alexander</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Stella Hadden </emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl.
		  1905-1928 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Christian Scientist</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Eddy</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Mary Baker</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1821-1910</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Founder of
		  Christian Science</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Stetson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Augusta E.</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d.
		  1928</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Christian Science teacher</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Christ, Scientist</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
