<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-749" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-749</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Rev. John Fleming, Professor of Natural
			 Philosophy (1785-1857)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jan 7 10:11:52 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-749</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS FLE 1-3</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rev. John Fleming,
		  Professor of Natural Philosophy (1785-1857)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1808-1931">1808-1931</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 volumes, 3 letters, 1 box, miscellaneous notes and
		  off-prints. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may
		  be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Fleming, John; Carruthers, William; Carruthers, S.
		  W.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John Fleming was born near Bathgate, West Lothian, on 10 January 1785.
		  Although he studied in preparation for the Church he was also deeply in
		  interested in natural history and science, and he managed to follow the two
		  throughout his life. By conducting a mineralogical survey of Orkney and
		  Shetland for Sir John Sinclair he became acquainted with the clergy in Shetland
		  and managed to find a vacancy in the Parish of Bressay in 1808. During this
		  time he published 
		<title>Economical mineralogy of the Orkney and Zetland islands</title>
		(1807) and 
		<title>On the narwhal or sea-unicorn</title>. In 1810 he went to the
		Parish of Flisk, Fife, and after many papers on local natural history he became
		known as Scotland's first zoologist. In 1814, Fleming was awarded the degree of
		D.D. from St. Andrews University and in 1822 he published 
		<title>The philosophy of zoology</title>. This was translated into
		Italian by Zandrini and it became a standard work in Italy in the nineteenth
		century. In 1832 he went to the Parish of Clackmannan, and in 1834 he was
		appointed to the Chair of Natural Philosophy at Aberdeen University. Fleming
		also published 
		<title>British animals</title> (1828) and 
		<title>The lithology of Edinburgh</title> (1859). In 1843 after the
		Disruption, he joined the new Free Church of Scotland. He was a Fellow of the
		Royal Society of Edinburgh. The Rev. John Fleming died on 18 November 1857.</p>
		
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: letter from Mrs Melville Fleming,
		  widow, to William Carruthers, Keeper of the Dept. of Botany, British Museum,
		  1865, within a copy of 
		<title>The lithology of Edinburgh</title>; box of scientific papers
		mainly delivered at meetings of learned societies, 1808-1857; letters of S. W.
		Carruthers to Adam Mitchell Hunter, 1930 and 1931, contained within 
		<title>Memoir of Rev. John Fleming, D.D., F.R.S.E.</title>; also loosely
		inserted within latter are, Fleming's observations on the formation of
		submarine forests in general and in the Firth of Tay in particular, material on
		the state and prospects of the Chair of Natural Science in New College,
		1856-1857, paper by William Carruthers on superficial deposits and his pencil
		notes on Fleming. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 7.
		Finch-Gloucester. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes at Edinburgh University Library (Special Collections
		  Division), George Square, Edinburgh, show various references to Fleming related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): letters to Professor R. Jameson
		  about the Wernerian Society, 1816 and undated, at Gen. 129 onwards; letters to
		  D. Laing and to C. Innes, 1827 and 1836, at La.IV.17; letter to John Murray,
		  1829, at Gen. 1971/2/12; letter to Sir C. Lyell, 1848, at Gen. 108 onwards;
		  letters to Sir. R. I. Murchison, 1855, at Gen. 523/4, and 1857, at Gen. 524;
		  letter from Sir W. Jardine, 1830, at Dk.6.20/156; mentioned in a letter of R.
		  K. Greville to Jardine, 1830, at Dk.6.20/128; and, mentioned in various letters
		  of G. Johnston to Jardine, 1837-1841, at Dk.6.20/161-186.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters to F. W. Hope, 1824-1839,
		  Oxford University, Museum of Natural History, NRA 42507 Oxford; letters (12) to
		  Gideon Algernon Mantell, 1830-1850, National Library of New Zealand, Alexander
		  Turnbull Library, Ref. MS Papers 83 Folder 41 NRA 40579 Mantell; letters to Sir
		  R. I. Murchison, 1845-1855, and undated, Geological Society of London, Ref.
		  M/F8 NRA 28354 Geological Soc; and correspondence with John Wilson (1 vol),
		  1820-1851, Leeds University Library, Special Collections.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Fleming</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1785-1857</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Naturalist and Presbyterian Minister</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Carruthers</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Keeper of
		  the Dept. of Botany, British Museum</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Carruthers</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">S. W.</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">New College (Edinburgh, Scotland)</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
