<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-845" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-845</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Leslie family of Warthill, Old
			 Rain</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Aug 13 09:28:28 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-845</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2040/124-129 </physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Leslie
		  family of Warthill, Old Rain</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1826-1842">1826-1842</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>5 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Leslie family of Warthill</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>A particularly prominent earlier member of the Leslie family of
		  Warthill was William Leslie (1657-1727) who became Bishop of Laibach in
		  Slovenia (formerly in Styria, Austria), and Metropolitan of Carniola (now in
		  Slovenia).</p> 
		<p>The home of the Leslie family at Warthill, Old Rain, was in the Parish
		  of Rayne (formerly Rane, Raine, Rain, and Rayn) near Oyne and Insch in the area
		  between Durno and Rothienorman in Central Aberdeenshire. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: a letter to 'My dear Jeanie' from
		  Inveraray, 1826, telling of travels around the Central Highlands, Breadalbane
		  and Perthshire; letter to 'My dear Mrs. Leslie' from Union Place, Aberdeen,
		  1827, from Anderson, telling of family news and expressing hope that the Mrs.
		  Leslie can come to visit; letter from Warthill, 1841, to an address in Paris
		  (Palais Bourbon); letter to Miss Thornton or Mrs Davidson at Palais Bourbon;
		  letter from Warthill, 1841, to Patrick Davidson, Malta, from his sister Miss
		  Leslie; and, letter to 'My dearest Pat and Mary Anne' from Union Street and
		  addressed to Valetta, Malta.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material
		  contained in the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show a reference to Leslie related material
		  generally (check the Indexes for more details): genealogical tables of the
		  Leslie family, sixteenth to twentieth century, in photostat format, at Phot.
		  685.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<famname> <emph altrender="surname">Leslie</emph> <emph
		  altrender="other">family</emph> <emph altrender="z">Warthill</emph> </famname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
