<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-835" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-835</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of Archibald William Montgomerie (1812-1861), 13th
			 Earl of Eglinton and 1st Earl of Winton</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jul 20 12:06:45 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date>Converted from EAD 1.0
			 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-835</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1981/88; Gen. 2040/9-12</physloc><unittitle>Letters of
		  Archibald William Montgomerie (1812-1861), 13th Earl of Eglinton and 1st Earl
		  of Winton</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1847-1853">1847-1853</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>5 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Montgomerie, Archibald William</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Archibald William Montgomerie was born in Palermo, Sicily, on 29
		  September 1812. He was educated at Eton. He succeeded to the Earldom in 1819 on
		  the death of his grandfather. He took his seat in the Lords as Baron Ardrossan.
		  He was appointed Lord-Lieutenant and Sheriff Principal of Ayrshire in 1842.
		  Eglinton was a protectionist and spoke against the Corn Importation Bill in
		  1846. In Lord Derby's government he was appointed Lord-Lieutenant of Ireland
		  (Viceroy) and conducted his business with vice-regal style, though he was not
		  popular among the Irish upper classes. Archibald William Montgomerie, 13th Earl
		  of Eglinton and 1st Earl of Winton, died on 4 October 1861.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: letter to the 'Ladies of Irvine' and
		  refers to a 'Tournament'; a note referring to an order for the 'Gallery of the
		  House of Lords'; a letter referring to 'laudable endeavours to promote the
		  Conservative Cause'; a letter referring to a 'communication - to Lord
		  Palmerston' and also about bringing a matter to 'the notice of the Queen'; and,
		  a letter to G. B. Ross regretting that he cannot assist the Scotch Rifles in
		  Ipswich, 1860.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material in Gen. 2040, among miscellaneous Scottish letters, purchased
		  E. Hall, Harrogate, October 1976, Accession no. E76.43.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.13.
		Masquerier-Myles. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Eglinton related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): franked postal cover addressed to G.
		  Foster, with biographical note, 8 April 1835, at Dk.6.19/3; letter to Eglinton
		  from J. Campbell about the Ayrshire Foxhounds, 6 March 1840, at Gen. 886/3, no.
		  4; letter about the plan of a mausoleum, 20 July 1841, at Gen. 863/8/19; and,
		  letters (2) to Sir G. Warrender, watermarked 1839, no date, at La.II.509.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Eglinton
		  related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Montgomerie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Archibald William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1812-1861</emph> <emph altrender="title">13th Earl of
		  Eglinton</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Lord Lieutenant of Ireland</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">19th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
