<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-828" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-828</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Rev. Dr. Thomas Chalmers
			 (1770-1847)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jul 20 10:44:40 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-828</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.2.57; Dk.6.19/1; Dk.7.47/86; Gen. 1429/10/22; Gen. 1730 A-C;
		  Gen. 2039/100-102</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rev. Dr. Thomas Chalmers
		  (1770-1847)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1798-1846">1798-1846</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 40 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Chalmers, Thomas</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The theologian, preacher, and philanthropist Thomas Chalmers was born
		  in Anstruther, Fife, on 17 March 1780. He was educated first at the parish
		  school and then at St. Andrews University where he became a keen mathematician
		  and scientist. He also wanted to be a preacher and when he became a Minister at
		  Kilmeny in Fife, in 1803, he also gave lectures on Chemistry at St. Andrews. As
		  a preacher he made his name at the Tron Church from 1815, and at St. John's
		  Parish, Glasgow, from 1820. In 1828, Chalmers became Professor of Divinity at
		  Edinburgh University, and Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of
		  Scotland in 1832. Within the Church, Chalmers was the leader of the Evangelical
		  party, and as such he proposed the Veto Act (1834) which gave some power to the
		  parishes to reject a minister proposed by the patron. This stand against
		  patronage contributed to the Disruption in 1843 when he led around one third of
		  Church ministers to form the Free Church of Scotland. He became the first
		  Moderator of the General Assembly of the Free Church of Scotland. The Rev. Dr.
		  Thomas Chalmers died overnight on 30-31 May 1847.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: letters to Dr. James Brown, 1798-1836,
		  at Dc.2.57; letter to Rev. Mr. Hamilton, Strathblane, 1819, and to Robert
		  Brown, 1820, and to Christopher Wilson, 1822, and letters (3) to P. Marsland,
		  Professor J. Pillans, and N. W. Senior, 1824-1832, and letter to the Rev.
		  George Lewis about an article in the 
		<title>Scottish Guardian</title>, 1834, and letter to Sir Frances
		Palgrave regretting that a Mr. Knight does not seem qualified for the ministry
		of the Church of Scotland, 1842, and letter to Sir Andrew about the Free Church
		of Scotland, 1843, at Gen. 1730 A-C; letter to J. Campbell about the manuscript
		of an article and mentioning Dr. James Wood, 1824, and a letter about the
		Prophetic Society, 1827, at Dk.6.19/1; letter to the Earl of Aberdeen about his
		pamphlet 
		<title>Remarks on the present position of the Church of Scotland</title>,
		1839, at Dk.7.47/86; and, letter to Professor James D. Forbes about
		accommodation at Cambridge, 1833, at Gen. 1429/10/22. The material at Gen.
		2039/100-102 is composed of: letter from Chalmers at Kilmany Manse, to the Rev.
		William Shingleton in Biggleswade, on scriptural matters and interpretation,
		1814; a letter dated 1843; and a short note thanking for a silver gift,
		1846.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material at Dk.7.47.86 among miscellaneous letters with Scottish
		  interest, acquired 1962, Accession no. E62.56. Material at Gen. 1429/10/22,
		  among miscellaneous letters with Scottish interest, purchased E. Hall, January
		  1970, Accession no. E70.2. Material at Gen. 1730 onwards, purchased from
		  Rendell, December 1972, Accession nos. E.72.65, from C.A.K.Fletcher, 1973,
		  Accession no. E73.4, acquired 1973, Accession no. E73.6, acquired from John
		  Wilson, Accession no. E74.34, and purchased from Carnegie Book Shop, January
		  1977, Accession no. E77.1. Material at Gen. 2039 purchased among miscellaneous
		  letters of Scottish interest, E. Hall, 1976, Accession no. E76.32.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.3. Brown-Chaloner.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Chalmers related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): letter to Robert Brown, 1822, at
		  La.II.156/i; letter to Walter Wood, 1826, at La.II.156/ii; letter to John
		  Murray, 1827, at La.II.156iii; letter to possibly Sir George Ballingall in his 
		<title>Tracts on pauperism</title>, 1834, at JA 3225; letter to the Rev.
		Daniel Wilkie, 1834, at La.II.156/iv; letter to Mrs. Marshall, 1841, at
		La.II.156v; letter from Sir R. Peel, 1830, at La.II.285/3; letter about a
		national monument to Chalmers from the Rev. Dean A. B. Ramsay to the Rev. W.
		Goold, 1869, at Gen. 1983/10; an autograph signature at Dc.3.87/21; letter of
		Sir J. Leslie about Chalmers and the Chair of Natural Philosophy, 1819, at
		Pho.1144/1, f.60; mentioned in a letter of Baillie John Veitch to Lord
		Rutherfurd as 'hurting the interest of the Church', 1840, at Gen. 1995/81; and,
		mention in a letter of Professor David Welsh to sir Alexander Gordon, 1823, at
		Gen. 1429/18/29.</p> 
		<p>Contact the New College Library (Edinburgh University Library) for
		  details of material relating to the Rev. Dr. Thomas Chalmers housed there: New
		  College, Mound, Edinburgh 0131 650 8957</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Chalmers
		  related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theologians</emph> </subject>
		
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Chalmers</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1780-1847</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Theologian</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
