<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-494" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-494</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Material on Disturbances in Kono, Sierra
			 Leone, 1957</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Feb 3 10:55:34 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-494</unitid> 
		<physloc>MS 2500.8</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Material on
		  Disturbances in Kono, Sierra Leone, 1957</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1957">1957</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 file</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Not known</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Sierra Leone in West Africa became an independent nation on 27 April
		  1961. The country has substantial mineral, agricultural, and fishery resources,
		  with minerals as diverse as diamonds, titanium ore, bauxite, iron ore, gold,
		  and chromite. Diamonds, discovered in the eastern Kono District in 1930, had
		  become the largest export earner for the country by 1938.</p> 
		<p>The diamond Kono deposits are alluvial and so heavy equipment isn't
		  necessary, and indeed manual digging can extract the material. Although mining
		  authorities had been able to control the mines, a diamond rush in the 1950s
		  brought an influx of illegal diggers into the area. Between 1953 and 1957 the
		  number of illegals had grown from 5,000 to as many as 70,000. In spite of the
		  presence of a paramilitary force with helicopter support, crime and violence
		  became a characteristic of the Kono district. Diamonds were smuggled to Liberia
		  where higher profits were to be made.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of a Sierra Leone Colonial Government file
		  on the disturbances in Kono 1957 and contains a map, cuttings and typescript
		  material.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material acquired January 1989, Accession no. E89.10.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using various
		  encyclopaedias and freely available information.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to material related to Sierra
		  Leone (check the Indexes for more details): photographs and brochures
		  commemorating Sierra Leone's independence in 1961; slavery in Sierra Leone
		  mentioned in a letter of T. Perronet Thompson to R. Watson, 1824, at
		  Dc.4.101-103; and Sierra Leone mentioned in a letter of R. Hay to Sir C.
		  Stuart, Baron de Rothesay, 1829, at Dk.6.25/77. In addition, the UK National
		  Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission,
		  notes this Sierra Leone related material: mission papers, 1803-1914, Birmingham
		  University Information Services, Special Collections Department, Ref. CMS/A1
		  NRA 7630 CMS Sierra Leone.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Kono (Sierra Leone)</emph> </geogname>    
		 <!--
<geogname>
<emph altrender = "a">Sierra Leone</emph>
</geogname>

<geogname>
<emph altrender = "a">Africa</emph>
</geogname>
-->
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
