<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-78"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-78</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of
			 Professor Gordon Donaldson (1913-1993) </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-78
		  </unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1627-1645; E2005.22; E2005.23 </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Professor Gordon Donaldson
		  (1913-1993) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1549-1993">1549-1993 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>21 boxes, 1
		  file volume, 1 folder (2 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>;
		  <language langcode="lat">Latin</language></langmaterial> 
		<origination label="Name of Creator(s)"
		 encodinganalog="isadg(2)321">Donaldson, Gordon</origination> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Gordon Donaldson was born in Leith on 13 April 1913. He was educated
		  at the Royal High School, and then he studied History at Edinburgh University
		  where he obtained a First Class Honours degree. His postgraduate study was
		  conducted at the Institute of Historical Research, University of London. After
		  graduating PhD. in 1938, and having returned to Edinburgh with medical problems
		  ruling out military service, Donaldson was appointed as an assistant in the
		  Scottish Record Office where he became skilled as a reader of difficult
		  early-medieval and late-medieval manuscripts. Throughout his life he maintained
		  an interest in the material there, making an enormous contribution to the
		  editing of historical records. In 1947 he became a Lecturer in Scottish History
		  at Edinburgh University. In 1955 he was appointed Reader, and in 1963 he was
		  awarded the Chair of Professor of Scottish History and Palaeography. In 1979,
		  Donaldson was appointed Historiographer to the Queen in Scotland. One of his
		  chief interests was the study of ecclesiastical history. His output of edited
		  texts, books, articles and reviews was immense and included 
		<title>The making of the Scottish prayer book of 1637 </title> (1954), 
		<title>Scotland - James V to James VII </title> (1965), 
		<title>Scotland - Church and nation through sixteen centuries </title>
		(1960), 
		<title>Isles of home - Sixty years of Shetland </title> (1984), 
		<title>Scottish church history </title> (1985), 
		<title>The faith of the Scots </title> (1990). Between 1972 and 1977 he
		was Editor of the 
		<title>Scottish Historical Review </title> and had also been Editor of
		the 
		<title>Register of the Privy Seal of Scotland </title>. In 1988, he was
		awarded the CBE. Gordon Donaldson died in Cameron Hospital, Windygates, Fife,
		on 16 March 1993. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>The papers of Professor Gordon Donaldson within Gen. 1627-1645 consist
		  of general and individual correspondence and correspondence with institutions
		  and publishers. There is material and notes on churches, about crofters,
		  emigration, genealogy, and the Northern Isles. There are lectures and notes;
		  personal and family papers; photographs; and, press cuttings. There is
		  manuscript material, typescript material, and proofs. These all cover the
		  period 1935-1993.</p> 
		<p>The collection also contains circa 60 manuscripts and fragments at
		  E2005.20. These are held in 23 separate folders in 2 boxes and represent
		  examples of formal legal and historical Scottish documents. They had been
		  Donaldson's private collection which he used to illustrate his Scottish
		  documents and Palaeography courses held in the 1970s. Some are dated and from
		  1549 to 1740. Some are undated and may be from the 15th century. Unlisted. A
		  few are photocopies.</p> 
		<p>Additionally, in E2005.23 there is a collection of colour and black
		  and white slides (diapositives/transparancies) contained in two boxes. The
		  slides show: houses and castles, and domestic architecture generally; views of
		  Scotland, the Scottish coast, the western and northern isles, and Scottish
		  family trees, charters, seals, other documents; Scottish towns including
		  Dysart; Faeroe Islands; Scandinavia; England; France; the Mediterranean
		  including Gibraltar, Sicily and Israel; Turkey; Greece; Dubrovnik, former
		  Yugoslavia; and the USA and Canada.</p>
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <odd encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.1"> 
		<note encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.6.1./marc 500"> 
		  <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
			 (1) Obituary, by Very Rev. Dr. Duncan Shaw, 
		  <title>The Scotsman </title>, 18 March 1993. (2) Obituary, by Tam
		  Dalyell, 
		  <title>The Independent </title>, 18 March 1993. (3) 
		  <title>University of Edinburgh Journal </title>, Vol.21. 1963-1964,
		  p.168 (Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd). </p> 
		</note> 
	 </odd> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Donaldson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Gordon</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1913-1993</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh
		  University</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">National
		  Archives of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Church history</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Historians</emph> </subject> 
		<geogname role="subject" encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>An important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held
		  at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to
		  the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
