<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-817" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-817</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Lady Helen Primrose (fl.1882-1914) and family
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jun 8 09:32:31 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-817</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1814</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Lady Helen Primrose
		  (fl.1882-1914) and family </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1880-1914">1880-1914</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Primrose, Helen; Walker, William Stuart; Primrose, H. W;
		  Prothero, George; Walker, James Montgomery</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Lady Helen Primrose (fl.1882-1914) had married firstly into the Denman
		  family, and secondly James Montgomery Walker, son of Sir William Stuart Walker
		  (1813-1896). Her children included sons Tom Denman (by the first marriage), and
		  Richard Douglas Denman (by the second marriage), and daughter Gladys Walker (by
		  the second marriage).</p> 
		<p>Co-trustee with regard to daughter Gladys, was the Rev. Canon George
		  Prothero, Whippingham, Isle of Wight (George Prothero M.A. of Brasenose
		  College, Oxford). Prothero had held Whippingham since 1857, and was sub-dean
		  and canon of Westminster, rural dean of North-east Medina on the Isle of Wight,
		  chaplain in ordinary to Her Majesty and J.P. for the county of Worcester.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of correspondence relating to a number of
		  individuals, principally that of: Lady Helen Primrose, in the form of accounts,
		  letters regarding shale oil, allowances, policies, and marriage settlement, and
		  a small illustration of 'Buttercups and bees' and a photograph card of a small
		  female child, 1882-1914; further letters and notes of Lady H. Primrose in the
		  form of solicitors letters, Tods, Murray and Jamieson, of Edinburgh; further
		  letters and notes of Lady Helen Primrose (Mrs. J. M. Walker) in the form of
		  communication with, and documents of, solicitors Lewin, Gregory and Anderson of
		  London, 1883-1887; further letters and notes of Mrs. Helen Primrose in the form
		  of communication with, and documents of, solicitors R. Jardine of Edinburgh,
		  1904-1906; Denman correspondence, the first husband of Lady Helen Primrose;
		  papers (letters and telegram) relating to Tom Denman, son of Lady Primrose by
		  her first marriage; papers relating to the Rev. George Prothero of Whippingham.
		  Isle of Wight, co-trustee with the Rev. H. W. Primrose re: Gladys Denman (or
		  Walker), daughter of Lady Helen and J. M. Walker); papers relating to Gladys
		  Walker, only daughter of Lady Helen and J. M. Walker; papers relating to Mrs.
		  Elizabeth Walker, mother of J. M. Walker; papers relating to Sir William Stuart
		  Walker, father of J. M. Walker; papers relating to James Montgomery Walker;
		  papers relating to B. F. Primrose, father of Sir H. W. Primrose KCB, CSI, ISO;
		  papers relating to Sir H. W. Primrose; papers relating to Violet Primrose,
		  sister of Sir H. W. Primrose; and, stamped (Queen Victoria, and US Presidents)
		  and addressed envelopes (28) from the USA and Great Britain, from this
		  period.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material purchased from E. Hall, February 1970, Accession no.
		  E70.8.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material
		  contained in the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes locations of Primrose, Henry William, and Walker,
		  Sir William Stuart related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Primrose</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Helen</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl
		  1882-1914</emph> <emph altrender="title">Lady</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Primrose</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Henry William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1846-1923</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight, Civil Servant</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Walker</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William Stuart</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1813-1896</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Lawyer</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Walker</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James Montgomery</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Prothero</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1880</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Reverend Canon at Whippingham, Sub-Dean of
		  Westminster</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
