<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-578" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-578</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Archives of the Regions Beyond Missionary Union
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Archivist, Centre for the Study of
				Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by
				Graeme D Eddie. </p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Nov 25 09:33:01 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-578</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 33</physloc><unittitle>Archives of the Regions Beyond
		  Missionary Union </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1870-1999">[ca. 1872-1991]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>72 boxes, 4800 slides, 30 films</extent>
		  <physfacet>The slides can be viewed without special equipment but a projector
		  is needed to view them at full size. A tape player is needed to listen to the
		  audio cassettes. Many of the films have been copied onto video, although some
		  were of very poor quality. In general the material is in good physical
		  condition.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>The Regions Beyond Missionary Union</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Regions Beyond Missionary Union originated in 1873 when the East
		  London Training Institute for Home and Foreign Missions was opened by Henry
		  Grattan Guinness (1835-1910) in Stepney Green, Clapton, London. Guinness, a
		  nephew of Arthur Guinness the founder of the brewing empire, had already made
		  his name as a revivalist preacher of some note attracting crowds of up to
		  10,000 at a time. Grattan Guinness had been strongly influenced by James Hudson
		  Taylor, the founder of the China Inland Mission, whose appeal for trained
		  missionaries for China was one of the factors which prompted Guinness, with his
		  wife Fanny, to establish the college.</p> 
		<p>The first student, Joshua Chowriappah from India, enrolled at the
		  beginning of 1873, by the end of that year the college had moved to bigger
		  premises at Harley House in Bow, and later expansion included a property in
		  Derbyshire (Cliff College 1875) and a separate college for women (Doric Lodge
		  1884). The college offered a mixture of theory with opportunity for practical
		  work around the East End. Mission halls were opened for meetings and teaching,
		  a nursing centre and medical mission were established, and the Institute
		  purchased its own mission yacht the 'Evangelist'. No fees were charged, the
		  Institute was to be run by faith alone, it accepted students from many
		  different nationalities and was interdenominational. By 1915 1500 missionaries
		  had been trained and sent around the world, some joining established missions
		  and others forming their own societies.</p> 
		<p>In 1887 Guinness handed the administration over to his son (Harry
		  Grattan Guinness 1861-1915) but remained closely involved, travelling widely to
		  attract support for the Institute. The Guinness family connection was to last
		  into the 1970s through the support of Henry Grattan Guinness's grandson, Gordon
		  Meyer Guinness (1902-1980). The first decade of the twentieth century brought
		  financial difficulties and disagreements about the type of training that was to
		  be offered. Cliff College was sold, the number of students at Harley was cut
		  and in 1915 the college closed completely. By this time, however, the work had
		  expanded in different directions.</p> 
		<p> 
		<title>Regions Beyond</title> magazine was published from 1878 describing
		the Institute and giving news of missionaries and missions around the world. In
		the same year the Guinnesses and a group of friends arranged for a number of
		missionaries to go to Congo as the Livingstone Inland Mission and the Institute
		took full responsibility for the project from 1880 until 1884. In 1888 the
		Guinnesses launched a new mission to Central Africa, the Congo Balolo Mission.
		To encourage support the Regions Beyond Helpers Union was formed in 1892 and
		membership reached 11,000 by 1897. Expansion continued: in 1897 the Institute
		took responsibility for the support of a group of Harley students working in
		Peru and later for others in Argentina and in 1899 the first missionaries were
		sent to the Bihar region of India. In the same year the name of the Institute
		was changed to the Regions Beyond Missionary Union and the RBMU was
		incorporated in 1903.</p> 
		<p>Throughout the twentieth century 
		<title>Regions Beyond</title> (from 1981 
		<title>Horizons</title>) published news of the mission's work,
		conferences were organised, and pamphlets, books, lantern slides, photographs
		and films were produced to raise awareness and increase support. The financial
		difficulties of the early twentieth century affected all areas: the mission was
		able to continue to operate in Congo and India but the South American work was
		passed to the Evangelical Union of South America in 1911. The period after the
		Second World War was, however, a time of expansion with the absorption of the
		Peru Inland Mission (1948) and entry into Kalimantan (Borneo, 1948/9), Irian
		Jaya (1954) and Nepal (1954, with the United Mission to Nepal).</p> 
		<p>Despite, and in some ways because of, the mission's successes some
		  began to question the role and purpose of the mission, especially in relation
		  to the indigenous churches and other organisations. The wide diversity of
		  fields stretched resources and administration and the idea of co-operating with
		  other similar agencies was increasingly proposed. The North American councils
		  (which had met as separate bodies since 1948) sometimes took a different view
		  on these and other issues and in 1979 the London based RBMU UK split from its
		  overseas councils, the latter operating as RBMU International. In the UK the
		  mission became more involved in joint projects and in 1980 moved to office
		  premises shared with other agencies. It still sought ways to maintain its own
		  identity and considered expanding to new areas such as Pakistan, Thailand, and
		  the Philippines. From the late 1980s, however, it became increasingly clear
		  that it was no longer suitable for the mission to continue as it was. In 1990,
		  after negotiations with other bodies, the work in each area was passed to new
		  or existing agencies, although some missionaries remained with RBMU until
		  1991.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of material relating to the mission in general
		  and to the work in Congo, Peru, India, Nepal, and Kalimantan and Irian Jaya and
		  includes: (1) minutes and reports produced in the mission offices in London and
		  in the fields; (2) correspondence with missionaries in the field, with regional
		  and national councils, with other missions operating in the same areas, and
		  with other evangelical agencies; (3) publications and printed material
		  including issues of the mission's journal 
		<title>Regions Beyond</title>, newsletters produced by missionaries in
		the field, histories of the mission and its activities, and leaflets and
		pamphlets produced for publicity or information; (4) material in the language
		or dialects of the countries in which the missionaries worked which was used
		for language learning or evangelical purposes; (5) lantern slides, slides,
		photographs and pictures; (6) audio material including a large collection of
		soundslides (slides with accompanying audio cassettes used in deputation work);
		(7) films showing the mission's work in various fields; (8) and some artefacts.
		The material dates mainly from 1880 onwards; most of the correspondence is from
		a more recent period but minutes and field reports exist from the early days of
		the mission; the photographs and other visual material date from the end of the
		19th century but the films and audio material are more recent, the earliest
		film dating from the 1950s. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>Before the material was presented to the Centre it was partially
		  sorted and arranged by the mission. This arrangement has been largely kept as
		  reflecting the order in which the records were created and the different
		  sections of the mission's activities. The collection is divided into series by
		  country and divided within the series by type of material. </p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was deposited at the Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World by the mission in 1991.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details. On the request of the mission,
		  material after a certain date, usually 1976, has been classed as restricted.
		  The date was chosen as it coincided with the hand-over from one executive
		  secretary to another and the records are stored separately.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <altformavail> 
		<p>Some copies of the publications can be found in other libraries
		  including the British Library, the National Library of Scotland and Yale
		  University in America.</p> 
	 </altformavail> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself; (2) the publications listed in the note above.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A detailed handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Some related material remains in the hands of the Guinness and Kumm
		  families. Some of the Guinness material (including early issues of 
		<title>Regions Beyond</title> were deposited at All Nations Bible
		College, Ware. RBMU International merged with World Team in 1995 and their
		offices in America and Canada hold RBMU records. Collections relating to
		individual missionaries can be found elsewhere such as the Banks photograph
		collection at the School of Oriental and African Studies in London and material
		relating to the work in Congo or created by RBMU missionaries there can be
		found among the papers of the Anti-Slavery Society in London and Oxford. The
		archives of the United Mission to Nepal are at the Centre for the Study of
		Christianity in the Non-Western World. In Congo the Centre Aequatoria has a
		large collection of documents and pamphlets, including schoolbooks and
		religious textbooks written by RBMU missionaries.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p>Several publications have drawn on the RBMU archives. Three fairly
		  recent histories of the mission as a whole have been published: Pritchard,
		  Elizabeth. 
		<title>For Such A Time</title>. Eastbourne: Victory Press, 1973; Holmes,
		Kenneth. 
		<title>The Cloud Moves</title>. London: RBMU, 1974; and, Conley, Joseph. 
		<title>Drumbeats That Changed the World</title>. Pasadena, CA: William
		Carey Library, 2000. Also, a detailed account of the origins of the mission and
		the early years is given by, Guinness, Michelle. 
		<title>The Guinness Legend</title>. London: Hodder and Stoughton,
		1989.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Guinness</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Henry Grattan</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1835-1910</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Founder of Regions
		  Beyond Missionary Union</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Guinness</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Harry Grattan</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1861-1915</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Regions Beyond Missionary Union</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Livingstone Inland Mission</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Congo Balolo Mission</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Peru Inland Mission</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Congo</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Peru</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">India</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Irian Jaya</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Kalimantan </emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nepal</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
