<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-191" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-191</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Reginald Davies (1887-1971)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Jan 10 09:55:53 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-191</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1899-1900</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Reginald Davies
		  (1887-1971)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1901-1961">1901-1961</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box, 1 diary. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Reginald Davies was born on 17 November 1887. He was educated at
		  Hymers College, Hull, and studied at St. Catherine's College, Cambridge, where
		  he was awarded the degree of B.A. (Hons. Maths) in 1909. Davies rowed for
		  Cambridge in 1910. He entered the Sudan Political Service in 1911, and was the
		  Resident at Dar Masalit in 1920. By 1927 he was Director of Intelligence, and
		  in 1929 Assistant Civil Secretary. Other steps in his career included: Deputy
		  Financial Secretary, 1930; Secretary for Economic Development, 1931; and
		  Chairman of the Board of Economics and Trade, and Member of the
		  Governor-General's Council, 1934. He retired from Sudan service in 1935. Davies
		  then went on to become Deputy Director-General of Alexandria Municipality
		  between 1935 and 1939, then Director of the Publicity Section of H.M. Embassy
		  in Cairo, 1939 until 1942. He was Finance Officer at the British Council, 1942
		  to 1947, then Assistant Director-General of the British Council, 1947. Davies
		  finally retired in 1953. His publications include 
		<title>The camel's back: service in the rural Sudan</title> (1957) and
		various contributions to 
		<title>Sudan notes and records</title>. He had been awarded the Order of
		the Nile, 3rd Class, in 1932, and in 1950 he became a Companion of St. Michael
		and St. George. Reginald Davies died on 18 December 1971. Latterly he had been
		living near Bicester, Oxfordshire.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers consist of correspondence about the Sudan between 1901 and
		  1961, and include photograph albums, loose photographs and slides, verses,
		  addresses, articles, and biographical information. Contained within is
		  correspondence with Freya Stark (1893-1993). There is also diary-based material
		  covering 1920 to 1934. The material is both in manuscript and typescript
		  form.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material acquired May 1972, Accession no. E72.21.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>Who was who 1971-1980</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black,
		1981.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: 1911-42 including papers from service in Sudan
		  and Egypt, and personal correspondence, Durham University Library, Archives and
		  Special Collections, Palace Green Section, Ref. G//S 1134, see Annual Return
		  1996; correspondence with Margery Perham, Oxford University, Rhodes House
		  Library, Ref. MSS Perham NRA 33434 Perham.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Davies</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Reginald</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1887-1971</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Colonial
		  Administrator </emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Stark</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Freya Madeline</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1893-1993</emph> <emph altrender="title">Dame</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Author and Traveller</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Sudan</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
