<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-212" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-212</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Calabar Mission</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Apr 25 10:59:13 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-212</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS CALA; MSS BOX 52.5.1-6</physloc><unittitle>Records of the
		  Calabar Mission</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1849-1969">1849-1969</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 file, 2 volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Anderson, William (1812-1895); Christie, William
		  Marshall</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="efi">Efik.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Calabar mission had its origins in Jamaica when the emancipation
		  of slaves gave weight to proposals take the Christian message to Africa. In
		  1846 a party landed in Old Calabar, now in Nigeria, led by Hope M. Waddell a
		  Scottish Missionary Society missionary. The group was backed by the United
		  Secession Church but the mission was brought under the supervision of the
		  United Presbyterians in 1847. Waddell remained at the mission until 1859. He
		  was joined by William Anderson, who had begun his career in Jamaica in 1839
		  then moved to Calabar in 1849 where he was to remain a dominant figure until
		  1891, and by Hugh Goldie who became the mission's leading Efik scholar and
		  translator. Progress was at first slow, the mission concentrated partly on
		  education and partly on preaching by which they hoped to effect both religious
		  and social change. They were particularly concerned to alter such practices as
		  ritual killing, the killing of twins and poison ordeals. Church membership
		  remained small, but in the 1880s some growth was evident and the mission began
		  a period of expansion of which the appointment of Mary Slessor to Okoyong was
		  part. The Hope Waddell Institute in Duke Town was established during this
		  period. Political changes in the early part of the twentieth century increased
		  the attraction of Christianity and young African teachers, many trained by
		  Alexander Cruickshank, as well as medical missionaries began to play a more
		  prominent role in the church. One of these, Francis Akanu Ibiam, was to become
		  a major figure in independent Nigeria. William Marshall Christie, one of the
		  Calabar missionaries during this period, was ordained in Edinburgh in 1913 and
		  immediately left for Calabar where he first became vice-principal of the Hope
		  Waddell Training Institution then concentrated on opening schools throughout
		  the area. He retired in 1945 in which year the Presbyterian Church of Nigeria
		  was formally constituted. Thomas Hart was a chartered accountant and well known
		  figure in Glasgow. He was an accountant at Calabar from 1911-1912 and again
		  from 1913-1915 when he left and joined the army audit department. The mission
		  itself was finally abandoned in 1960.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: an English Calabar dictionary by William
		  Anderson (1849-1851); material used by William Marshall Christie while
		  preparing his record of the mission including a manuscript notebook of
		  locations of missionaries (1911-1945), a note of local church and mission
		  records, notes of the work at the Slessor Memorial Home, Arochuku derived from
		  the S.M.H Record Book (1915-1930), Zenana Quarterly Records (1887-1899) and the
		  Women's Foreign Mission Annual Reports (1900-1908), and the manuscript copy of 
		<title>Annals of the Calabar Mission 1846-1945</title> by Christie,
		listing all the missionaries and other workers at Calabar; notes and
		correspondence about contacts (1914-1915) between Thomas Hart, a missionary
		accountant from Glasgow, and Mary Slessor, missionary at Calabar; letters
		including reminiscences to Hart from 'Dan' Slessor, an African adopted by Mary
		Slessor, and from Dr Francis Akanu Ibiam; 'miscellaneous' papers such as a
		tribute to Christie (1945), articles about Calabar, and a report of the Itu
		Leper Colony (1948); and correspondence about histories of the mission
		(1969).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The dictionary is stored under MSS CALA, the file and volume are
		  stored together in MSS BOX 52. </p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>The material (apart from the Anderson dictionary) was gathered
		  together by Donald McFarlan, himself a missionary. Some of it was given to
		  McFarlan by Christie while the former was working on his history of the
		  mission.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The Anderson dictionary came from David Sutherland of Leith. The
		  remaining material was presented to New College Library by Glasgow University
		  Archives in 1990.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The history of the Calabar mission was compiled using: (1) information
		  from the collection. (2) Hewat, Elizabeth. 
		<title>Vision and Achievement 1796-1956 A History of the Foreign Missions
		  of the Churches united in the Church of Scotland</title>. Edinburgh: Thomas
		Nelson and Sons Ltd., 1960.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts held at New College Library mentions the
		  collection. A handlist is filed in the New College Inventory of Manuscripts
		  under MSS BOX 52 and MSS CALA.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections has an album of
		  illustrations of the Calabar Mission (reference Gen. 827F) and the papers of
		  William Marwick (Gen. 768). Correspondence and papers of William Anderson are
		  in the National Library of Scotland (reference MSS 2981-83, 8943-51) along with
		  Church of Scotland records and other missionary papers including correspondence
		  with William Christie and Thomas Hart. Mary Slessor's papers are at Dundee.</p>
		
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p>Donald McFarlan used the Christie material for 
		<title>Calabar. The Church of Scotland Mission 1846-1946</title>. London:
		Thomas Nelson, 1946.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Efik language</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Africa</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Linguistic work</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Anderson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1812-1895</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Missionary</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Christie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William Marshall</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">Missionary</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">United Presbyterian Church</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Calabar Mission</emph> <emph
		  altrender="z">Nigeria</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Calabar (Nigeria)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
