<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GGB 237 Coll-500" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-500</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Notes of Surgical Cases arising from the
			 Military Action of British Troops in Spain</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Feb 10 12:16:17 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu May 20 11:12:42 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-500</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 596-607</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Notes of Surgical
		  Cases arising from the Military Action of British Troops in Spain</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1832-1837">1832-1837</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>12 manuscript volumes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Alcock, Rutherford</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Action by French and British legions took place in Spain in the 1830s
		  during the First Carlist War, 1833-1839. The background to the War had been the
		  death of King Ferdinand VII of Spain and the subsequent Regency of Queen
		  Cristina - his fourth wife - on behalf of their infant daughter Isabel II.
		  Spain had become split into two factions known as the Cristinos, or Isabelinos,
		  and the Carlists. Cristinos were the supporters of the Queen-Regent and the
		  government, and the Carlists were supporters of Don Carlos (Carlos Maria Isidro
		  de Borbon, 1788-1855) a Pretender to the Spanish throne and brother of
		  Ferdinand VII. Carlists had invoked the Salic Law which had been introduced to
		  Spain by King Philip V in 1713. Salic Law excluded females from royal
		  succession. There had been more to the conflict than this however. Roots lay in
		  the 1820s with the growth of an extreme political party which materialised into
		  the paramilitary Royalist Volunteers (Realistas Volunarios) in 1827. Opposed to
		  liberalism in Spain, this traditionalist group regarded Don Carlos as its
		  figurehead.</p> 
		<p>The disputed succession and the ideological current provoked the First
		  Carlist War which centred around the Carlist homelands of the Basque Country
		  and Aragon, although fighting also covered the rest of Spain at one time or
		  another. Defeated in the First Carlist War, the Carlists waged a Second War in
		  the 1840s, a coup was attempted in 1860 in support of the Don Carlos heir, and
		  a Third War was underway between 1872 and 1876. There was also an outbreak of
		  insurgency in support of the Carlist claim in 1900-1902.</p> 
		<p>In 1918 the formation of the Traditionalist Party became the principal
		  voice of Carlism but it was merged with the Falange in 1937 by General
		  Francisco Franco, although neither groups had much in common. The Carlist line
		  had become extinct in 1936 with the death of Don Alfonso Carlos, duque de San
		  Jaime, though Francis Xavier of Bourbon-Parma (styled as Charles IX) was
		  nominated as 'successor' and he in turn was succeeded by his son Carlos-Hugo,
		  Duke of Parma.</p> 
		<p>The present King of Spain, Juan Carlos, was the son of Don Juan, conde
		  de Barcelona, and grandson of King Alfonso XIII. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of notes of surgical cases arising from
		  military action of British troops in Spain, 1832-1833, and notes of cases in
		  the general military hospital of San Telmo, San Sebastian, arising from
		  military action of British troops, 1836-1837. There is also a volume of
		  statistical returns of sick and wounded admitted to the military hospitals of
		  the Legion in Spain, 1835-1837.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The items making up the collection were transferred from the Anatomy
		  Library, June 1962, Accession no. E62.45-47.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Vol.2. Micropaedia. 15th
		edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1991. (2) Other general
		reading.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgery, Military</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Military hospitals</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Alcock</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Rutherford</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1809-1897</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Surgeon and Diplomat</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Spain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">Carlist War, 1833-1840</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
