<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-499" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-499</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Manuscripts relating to the Society of
			 Friends</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Feb 10 12:09:35 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-499</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 545-548D</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Manuscripts
		  relating to the Society of Friends</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1701-1799">18th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 volumes</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Cruickshank, J</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Society of Friends, or the Friends Church, or Quakers, are a
		  Christian group which arose in the seventeenth century within the English
		  Puritan movement. The founder was George Fox (1624-1691), a shoemaker from
		  Nottingham, who began giving sermons in 1643 and formed a group called the
		  Friends of Truth, later becoming known as the Society of Friends. After 1656,
		  the Friends refused to attend Anglican services and stopped paying their
		  tithes. Fox was arrested and a judge told him that he should 'quake in the
		  presence of the Lord'. After this the Friends became known as Quakers.</p> 
		<p>The Friends believe in the immediacy of Christ's teaching and
		  guidance, the consequent irrelevance of consecrated buildings and an ordained
		  ministry, and the application of Christ's teaching to the whole of life.
		  However, in the seventeenth century these beliefs met with persecution, and
		  during the reign of Charles II over 13,000 were arrested and imprisoned and
		  some were transported. Even so, the group grew rapidly particularly in the
		  north of England and by 1660, Fox had made some 20,000 converts and
		  missionaries were at work in Ireland, Scotland, and Wales.</p> 
		<p>Persecution continued throughout the seventeenth century and many
		  emigrated to North America. In 1681 William Penn founded the American Quaker
		  Colony of Pennsylvania, and in 1683 Francis Daniel Pastorius from Germany
		  established the Quaker settlement of Germantown. During the eighteenth the
		  Friends went through a series of separations and schisms - some advocating
		  Quietism, some following the theology of John Wesley, some following the
		  teaching of Elias Hicks.</p> 
		<p>The Friends involved themselves in politics and social reform and
		  became the first religious group to denounce slavery century. In 1783, they
		  presented the first substantial anti-slavery petition to Parliament. Also in
		  Britain, Elizabeth Fry joined the prison reform movement and Joseph Lancaster
		  worked for improvements in education. The Peace Society was also formed in a
		  campaign to end war.</p> 
		<p>By the beginning of the nineteenth century there were around 25,000
		  Quakers in Britain and many proved themselves to be entrepreneurial. Under
		  Edward Pease a group helped to form the Stockton and Darlington Railway in
		  1825, and companies formed by Quakers included Cadbury, Fry, Rowntree, Huntly
		  and Palmer, Bryant and May, Barclays, and Lloyds.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of manuscripts relating to the Society of
		  Friends and copied by J. Cruickshank.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material acquired November 1961, Accession no. E61.34.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Vol.5. Micropaedia.
		Ready Reference. 15th edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1991. (2)
		Material circulated by the Society of Friends.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Quakers</emph> </subject> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Society of Friends</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
