<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-239" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-239</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Sir David Patrick Chalmers
			 (1835-1899)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Jun 04 17:41:55 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-239</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1915-1918; Gen. 1934-1935</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Sir
		  David Patrick Chalmers (1835-1899)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1850-1899">1850s-1899</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>6 boxes, 2 volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>David Patrick Chalmers was born in 1835. He was educated at the
		  Edinburgh Institution and at Edinburgh University. Chalmers was called to the
		  Scottish Bar in 1860. He was appointed Magistrate of Gambia in 1867, with full
		  powers of a Judge. In 1869, he became the Magistrate of the Gold Coast (Ghana)
		  with similar powers, and also native chief's assessor. In 1872, Chalmers was
		  appointed Queen's Advocate of Sierra Leone, then he again served on the Gold
		  Coast during the Ashantee (Asante) invasion. In 1876, he became first Chief
		  -Justice of the Gold Coast, and in 1878 Chief-Justice of British Guiana
		  (Guyana). Chalmers was appointed as the Royal Commissioner to enquire into the
		  1898 revolt in Sierra Leone which had arisen because of the imposition of a hut
		  tax and because the ruling chiefs had not been consulted about the country's
		  protectorate status which had been proclaimed by the British in 1896. Chalmers
		  also served in Jamaica on a Judicial Commission of Enquiry in 1893, and as a
		  special Judge in a prosecution for fraud in Newfoundland in 1897. He was
		  knighted in 1876. Sir David Patrick Chalmers died 5 August 1899.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection contained in Gen. 1915-1918 includes the papers from
		  1867-1899 of Sir David Patrick Chalmers in his capacity of Chief-Justice of the
		  Gold Coast (Ghana), Africa, and later of British Guiana (Guyana). The material
		  consists of manuscripts, typescripts, newspaper cuttings and printed ordinances
		  and relates to the Gambia 1867-1869, the Gold Coast 1869-1878, and Sierra Leone
		  1898-1899. There is also material relating to Enquiries on British Guiana
		  18791894, Jamaica 1895-1896, and Newfoundland 1897, and Commission material.
		  There is personal material, and address, a photograph, pamphlets and articles
		  relating to the Sierra Leone Hut Tax Enquiry in 1898, and a diary kept by W. H.
		  Campbell on an expedition from Georgetown to Upata, British Guiana, in 1857.
		  Gen. 1919 and Gen. 1920 consist of 
		<title>The law reports of British Guiana. Vol.1. 1890-1891</title>,
		published in Demerara by the Argosy press, 1892, and an album of newspaper
		cuttings. At Gen. 1934-1935 there is correspondence covering the periods
		1859-1878 and including letters to the family, and diaries.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material at Gen. 1915-1920 including the diary kept by W. H. Campbell
		  from Miss E. B. Chalmers, Anstruther, Fife, June 1972, Accession no.
		  E72.27.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Walford, Edward. 
		<title>The county families of the United Kingdom ...</title>. London:
		Chatto and Windus, 1885. (2) 
		<title>Who was who. A companion to who's who ... 1897-1916</title>.
		London: A. and C. Black, 1920.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Diplomatic and consular
		  service, British</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Chalmers</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">David Patrick</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d
		  1899</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight
		  Colonial Magistrate </emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Campbell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">W H</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Ghana</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Gold Coast</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">British Guiana</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Guyana</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Gambia</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Sierra Leone</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Jamaica</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Newfoundland</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">Colonies</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Upata (Venezuela)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
