<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-737" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-737</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Archive of the Scottish Congregational
			 College</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Dec 9 09:04:33 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-737</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS SCO 2</physloc><unittitle>Archive of the Scottish
		  Congregational College</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1864-1993">1864-1993</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>6 boxes.</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Scottish Congregational College; The Scottish
		  College</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Even before they formed a union of churches, Congregationalists had
		  come together in 1811 to found a theological hall. Later on, when the
		  Congregational Union and the Evangelical Union united, they each had their own
		  related theological institutes and together these places of learning formed a
		  college - the Scottish Congregational College. The College was never
		  denominationally-owned nor denominationally-managed. It always maintained a
		  constitutional independence. There has been a strong ecumenical dimension to
		  the College. For many years, Congregational and United Free ordinands learned
		  together. More recently, there was a close association with the Scottish
		  Episcopal college. Eric Henry Liddell, Olympic medal winner 1924, studied with
		  the Scottish Congregational College prior to his becoming a missionary in
		  China. Today the institution is known as the Scottish United Reformed and
		  Congregational College, or The Scottish College. In 1995, the stock of the
		  College library was amalgamated with the stock from the library of St Colm's
		  College (Church of Scotland) and the Theological College Library of the
		  Scottish Episcopal Church (formerly at Coates Hall) to form the United SCOC
		  Library.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The archive is composed of: in Box 1, applications for admissions,
		  miscellaneous materials and documents, and material on endowments; in Box 2,
		  material on the William Smith Bursary, the John Wemyss Bursary, the Baxter
		  Scholarship, the Whitelaw Scholarship, the Agnes Bowie Bursary, and legal
		  documents concerning Inverleith Road, Edinburgh, and Lochend Road, Edinburgh;
		  in Box 3, material relating to the John Pillans Bursary, the John Sutherland
		  Bursary, the James Smith Prize, the Ferguson Prize, the legacy from Agnes
		  Goodwin, the Sir George Harvey Bursary, the David Dunlop Deans Bursary,
		  material on bequests from Low, Macnair, Loudon, from Cambuslang, and from Hywel
		  Hughes, and material relating to the Trustees, to Thornville Terrace, Glasgow,
		  Montague Street, Edinburgh, and George Street and Gordon Street, Glasgow; in
		  Box 4, legal documents in the form of feu contracts, instruments of sasine,
		  notorial instruments, searches, and deeds, and material relating to Learmonth;
		  in Box 5, material relating to Warriston Gardens, Edinburgh, Craiglea Drive,
		  Edinburgh, and to Hope Terrace, Edinburgh; and, in Box 6, miscellaneous papers
		  relating to constitutional matters, orders of service, reports, programmes, and
		  photographs.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) History. 
		<title>The Scottish College</title>. Full-text [online]. 
		<extref href="http://www.scottishcollege.org.uk/">The Scottish College:
		  History</extref> [Accessed 6 November 2003].</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Clergy</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ordination</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Congregational College</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish College</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
