<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-380" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-380</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers relating to James VI of Scotland (James I of Great
			 Britain and Ireland) (1566-1625)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu May 9 09:11:41 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-380</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.37/1/1; Dc.3.48; Dc.4.14; De.1.12/1, 5, 8, 20;
		  Dk.1.18</physloc><unittitle>Papers relating to James VI of Scotland (James I of
		  Great Britain and Ireland) (1566-1625)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1587-1617">1587-1617</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 manuscript volumes, 6 manuscript documents (bound
		  in). </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> <language langcode="lat">Latin, </language>
		  <language langcode="fre">French, </language> and <language
		  langcode="ita">Italian.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James was born on 19 June 1566 in Edinburgh Castle. He was the son of
		  Mary, Queen of Scots and Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley. Soon after James was born,
		  Mary had been forced into abdication by her illegitimate half-brother Lord
		  James Stewart, Earl of Moray, and on 24 July 1567 the baby became King James VI
		  of Scotland, and was crowned at Stirling on 29 July. The Earl of Moray acted as
		  Regent while James grew up in Stirling Castle in the custody of the Earl and
		  Countess of Mar. His senior tutor was the historian and scholar George Buchanan
		  (1506-1582). In 1570, Moray was murdered and the Earl of Lennox, grandfather of
		  James, became the second Regent. Lennox too died in September 1571 after a
		  skirmish, and the Earl of Mar became the third Regent. When he died, James
		  Douglas, 3rd Earl of Morton, became the fourth Regent.</p> 
		<p>In 1579 change occurred yet again with the arrival from France of Esme
		  Stuart, a Catholic cousin of James. Scotland at this time was a divided country
		  with powerful nobles - Protestant and Catholic parties - seeking their own
		  control over parliament and Stuart had been sent by the Guise family to win
		  James back for France (Mary of Guise had been James' grandmother). By this time
		  James was thirteen and he created his cousin first Earl then Duke of Lennox,
		  and a companion of Stuart's, James Stewart, was made Earl of Arran. Together,
		  in 1581, they managed to have Regent Morton seized and executed for complicity
		  in the murder of Darnley. Extreme Protestants avenged this in 1582 in the
		  kidnapping of James - the Ruthven Raid organised by William Ruthven, 1st Earl
		  of Gowrie - and in the expulsion of the Duke of Lennox, who returned to France.
		  James escaped captivity in Falkland in June 1583. Gowrie was subsequently
		  executed and much later, in 1600, in an affair that still encourages debate -
		  the Gowrie Conspiracy - both John Ruthven, 3rd Earl of Gowrie, and his younger
		  brother Alexander Ruthven, were killed in a disturbance.</p> 
		<p>In 1585 negotiations began for the marriage of James to Anne, the
		  daughter of King Frederick II of Denmark. Marriage by proxy took place in
		  Copenhagen in August 1589. On her journey to Scotland, a storm drove her ship
		  towards Norway and so James sailed there to meet her. They were married in
		  Opsloe or Upslo (later the site of Christiania, then re-named Oslo) on 23
		  November 1589, and again in Denmark, at Kronenborg, before both arrived in
		  Leith on 1 May 1590.</p> 
		<p>King James and Anne, Queen Consort, had seven children, most of whom
		  died in infancy: Henry Frederick, Prince of Carrick, Prince of Wales, born
		  February 1594 (but died in 1612); Princess Elizabeth, born August 1596;
		  Princess Margaret, born December 1598 (but died in infancy); Prince Charles,
		  born November 1600; 'Duik Robert', born 1601 (died in infancy); Princess Mary,
		  born April 1605 (died in 1607); and, Princess Sophia born in June 1607, but who
		  lived only one day.</p> 
		<p>The kingship of James had doubtless been influenced by Buchanan, his
		  tutor - at times in reaction to his influence, and at times as a result of his
		  influence. James checked the power of his nobles and the aspirations of the
		  Calvinist divines who claimed Scotland for Jesus Christ and who regarded him as
		  'God's sillie vassal'. He took control of the General Assembly, deciding where
		  and when it met. His attitude to the Gaelic-speaking population of the
		  Highlands and Islands was influenced by racism and he proposed settlement of
		  these areas with English-speakers - a policy that was implemented in the north
		  of Ireland instead. Misogyny also influenced his policy and this was expressed
		  in the torture of women accused of witchcraft - although warlocks were also
		  tortured with expertise. A work by James entitled 
		<title>Demonology</title> (1597) 'proved' the malign influence of
		witchcraft which he held to be responsible for the storms that dogged the
		marriage expedition in 1589-90.</p> 
		<p>Other works by James include 
		<title>Basilikon Doron</title> (1599), 
		<title>The true law of free monarchies</title> (1603), and 
		<title>A counter-blast to tobacco</title> (1604). </p> 
		<p>James' ultimate goal was the throne of England and as early as 1586 he
		  had allied himself with Protestantism and with Queen Elizabeth of England.
		  Indeed, on the execution of his mother, Mary, Queen of Scots, also in 1586,
		  James uttered little protest (Mary had disinherited him, bequeathing her realm
		  to Philip II of Spain). On the death of Queen Elizabeth I on 24 March 1603, and
		  at the age of thirty-seven, James VI of Scotland became King James I of Great
		  Britain and Ireland.</p> 
		<p>James died on 27 March 1625 and he was buried in Westminster Abbey on
		  5 May 1625. Anne, his queen, died earlier, on 2 March 1619. James VI and I was
		  succeeded by Charles, his second son. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: letters under the Signet of James VI to
		  John Young, messenger, commanding him to summon William Stewart of Kinnaird and
		  others to appear before the Privy Council, 1595; letter from A. La Roche de
		  Chandieu, La Rochelle, 1587; letter from A. Farnese, Duke of Parma, Spanish
		  ambassador in the Netherlands, 1589; 
		<title>The offers made by Her Majesty's ambassador of England</title> to
		King James, 1588; 
		<title>Tabula consanguinitatis inter Christianam Lotharingicam,
		  Ferdinandi, Magni Hetruriae Ducis uxorem, et Jacobum Steuartum, ejusdemque
		  conjugem Annam Altiburgicam, Britannorum reges faelicissimos</title>; 
		<title>De jure successionis regni Angliae libri duo, adversus sophismata
		  cujusdam personati Dolomanni, etc</title>, 1602; document which refers to
		James' apology for the oath of allegiance; and, transcripts of documents
		relating to the reign of James, 1578-1617. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 10. Howard-Kenneth.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney
		(eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 1. Abbadie-Beadon.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (3) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various other references to material related to
		  James I in the Laimg Collection (check the Indexes for more details):
		  correspondence between Queen Elizabeth of England and James, 1583-1602, at
		  La.III.371; correspondence between James, Sir Robert Cecil and others,
		  1602-1607, at La.III.372; letter to Sir Lewis Bellenden, 1585, at La.II.517;
		  letters from Queen Elizabeth, 1587-1593, at La.III.365; letter to James about
		  the renunciation by the Duke of Lennox of the Priory of St. Andrews, circa
		  1606, La.II.539; 
		<title>A brief opinion of the state, faction, religion and power of the
		  noblemen in Scotland</title>, 1583, at La.III.510; 
		<title>A declaration of the King's majesties intention and meaning toward
		  the lait actis of Parliament</title>, 1585, at La.III.534, ff.42-55; commission
		to J. Anderson, Minister of Stirling, 1586, at La.II.14; 
		<title>An apologie of the Scottische king</title>, circa 1599-1603, at
		La.III.245; 
		<title>The historie and life of King James the Sext</title>, 1566-1594,
		at La.III.223; accounts for setting and repair of crown jewels, 1604, at
		La.II.525; a treatise for James on trade and traffic, circa 1620, at La.II.52;
		and, a warrant for paying 900 Pounds to George Heriot for jewels and presents
		to the French ambassador and his secretaries, 1621, at La.II.658.</p> 
		<p>The local Indexes also show reference to: a letter to Anne of Denmark
		  from Elizabeth, Queen of England, 18 January 1595, at De.1.12/9.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: royal letter book, 1565-1628,
		  National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD149 NRA 33875 Cuninghame, and letters
		  (23), 1590-1621, Ref. GD249/2/1 NRA 10114 Hamilton see NRA(S)0104, and letters
		  to the Dukes of Hamilton, and correspondence with the Earl of Mar, circa
		  1580-1620, Ref. GD 124/10/52 NRA 32022 Erskine, and letters (7) to Sir John
		  Ogilvy, 1593-1606, Ref. GD 205/box1 NRA 34282 Ogilvy; miscellaneous letters and
		  papers, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Sloane MSS, and
		  correspondence, 1582-1596, Ref. Add MSS 23240-41; papers, including
		  establishment lists, circa 1603-1619, Society of Antiquaries of London, Ref.
		  MSS 40, 45, 74-75, 118; miscellaneous correspondence and papers, Cambridge
		  University Library, Department of Manuscripts and University Archives;
		  miscellaneous correspondence and papers, Lambeth Palace Library, Ref. MS 929-42
		  NRA 36499 Gibson; household accounts, 1623-1624, Duchy of Cornwall Office, NRA
		  24580 Duchy of Cornwall; letters to the Boyd family (8), 1578-1618, Dick
		  Institute, NRA 29118 Boyd; letters (8) to the Earl of Huntly, West Sussex
		  Record Office, Ref. 1427/3-10 NRA 850 Gordon Lennox; letters (11) to the Earl
		  of Huntingdon, 1609-1624, Huntington Library, Ref. HU NRA 10029 Hastings; and,
		  letters (2) to the wardens of New College, Oxford and Winchester College, 1609,
		  Warwickshire County Record Office, Ref. CR 136/B/736A and B NRA 26325
		  Newdegate.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">James</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">I</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1566-1625</emph>
		  <emph altrender="title">King of Great Britain and Ireland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Anne</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1574-1619</emph> <emph altrender="title">of Denmark,
		  Queen Consort of James I</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Farnese</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alessandro</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1545-1592</emph> <emph altrender="title">Duke of Parma</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Governor General of the Netherlands</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Chandieu</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Antoine de</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1534-1591</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">16th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">17th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">16th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">17th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
