<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-495" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-495</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures of, and other material relating to Professor Sir
			 James Young Simpson (1811-1870)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Feb 3 10:48:52 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-495</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.2.58; Dc.2.85/2, 7, 10/4-5; Dc.4.101-103 Simpson; Gen. 851;
		  Gen. 1732 Simpson; Phot.516/2</physloc><unittitle>Lectures of, and other
		  material relating to Professor Sir James Young Simpson (1811-1870)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1840-1868">1840-1868</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>11 letters, 1 notebook, miscellaneous
		  photographs</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Simpson, James Young; Dickson, George</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The physician James Young Simpson was born on 7 June 1811 in Bathgate,
		  West Lothian. He was educated locally and then at Edinburgh University,
		  entering in 1825. In 1827 he began the study of medicine and graduated M.D. in
		  1832. By 1835 he was Senior President of the Royal Medical Society of Edinburgh
		  and by 1839 he was appointed to the Chair of Midwifery. Simpson first worked
		  with sulphuric ether as a form of anaesthetic in obstetric practice, but then
		  in 1847 he and his assistants came to understand the efficacy of chloroform. A
		  public trial was held at Edinburgh's Royal Infirmary in November 1847. The same
		  year he was appointed one of Her Majesty's Physician in Scotland and he became
		  a foreign Associate of the Academy of Medicine, Paris. Apart from his
		  contribution to anaesthesia, Simpson laid the foundation of gynaecology and
		  contributed to obstetrics. In 1866 he was given a Baronetcy, the first to be
		  received by a doctor practicing in Scotland. Professor Sir James Young Simpson
		  died on 6 May 1870. His family declined a grave in Westminster Abbey - though
		  there is a bust of him there - and he was buried at Edinburgh's Warriston
		  Cemetery. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material in the collection includes: lectures on midwifery and
		  diseases of women, 1862-1863; letters and photostat copy of letters to W.
		  Grindlay, father-in-law, 1840, and to mother, 1840, on election to Chair of
		  Midwifery; letter to Dr. Forbes, 1847; letter to D. R. Hay, 1854, and a letter
		  about the Aesthetic Club, 1857; letter to Duncan McLaren, 1868; letters to Adam
		  Black, 1868, about the Principalship of Edinburgh University; and, letter to W.
		  Dickson, 1862.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter to Dickson, Accession no. E62.13. Lectures, Accession no.
		  E66.27. Letter to McLaren, Accession no. E67.39. Letters to Black, Accession
		  no. E76.15.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>Note that when this record was created any associated
		  photographic/illustrative was unseen.</p> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 18.
		Shearman-Stovin. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various other references to Simpson related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): testimonial by Simpson in favour
		  of Dr. G. H. Pringle, 1854, at Dc.4.98/6, (19); mention of Simpson in a letter
		  of William Jameson, 1856, at Gen. 1996/5/21; draft letters of Mrs. Catherine
		  Torrie, 1855, at Gen. 1996/12/93; certificate in favour of Walter Somerville,
		  1861, at Da.Cyl; letters to D. Laing, at La.IV.17; certificate of Professor J.
		  Pillans in favour of Simpson, 1826, at Da.3; letter to Simpson from J. Scott
		  about medical research in Guy's Hospital and the Museum of London University,
		  1837, at Gen. 886/4, no.23; letter from Sir W. Laurence, 1847, at Dc.2.85/1;
		  mentioned in letters of T. Cunningham, at Dk.7.46/54 etc; mentioned in letters
		  of J. Cunningham, Belfast, 1849, at Dk.7.46/67, 70; and, various letters about
		  the death of Simpson, press-cuttings about Simpson and R. L. Stevenson, silver
		  medal, recommendations for his lectures, and photographs relating to
		  Simpson.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Simpson
		  related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Midwifery</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Simpson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James Young</emph> <emph
		  altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1811-1870</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Physician</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dickson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
