<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-72"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-72
		</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of William
			 Speirs Bruce (1867-1921) </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-72 </unitid>
		
		<physloc>Gen. 1646-1669; Bruce Coll. </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of William Speirs Bruce
		  (1867-1921) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1892-1923">1892-1923 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>12 boxes,
		  10 albums, 2 log-books (2 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>William Speirs Bruce, explorer and geographer, was born on 1 August
		  1867 in London, the son of a doctor. His early education was conducted at home,
		  but from the age of eleven he attended Norfolk County School at North Elmham.
		  While at school he became interested in natural history and this was his main
		  hobby. In 1883, Bruce went to University College School, London, and it was
		  intended that in the autumn of 1884 he would commence medical studies at
		  University College. In preparation for this, his father sent him to the
		  vacation course in biology at the marine station in Granton, Edinburgh, which
		  was held under the direction of Professor Patrick Geddes. This short period at
		  Granton encouraged Bruce to study medicine at Edinburgh rather than London.
		  Medicine alone failed to hold his attention however, and he developed a width
		  of outlook and range of interests across the whole field of science - natural
		  philosophy, anatomy, natural history. He also helped in the Challenger Office
		  in the city, and often assisted in dredging in the Forth or in the Clyde and in
		  laboratory work at the Office. Bruce studied at Edinburgh University between
		  1887 and 1892 but did not graduate. Before completing his course he sailed for
		  Antarctica with the 'Balaena' expedition of Dundee whalers, signing on as a
		  surgeon and naturalist. Meteorological observations taken during the expedition
		  provided the first clear evidence in favour of an Antarctic anticyclone. The
		  'Balaena' expedition re-awakened interest in the region and paved the way for
		  greater efforts there in the early years of the 20th century. In 1895, Bruce
		  was working at the meteorological observatory on Ben Nevis in Scotland. Plans
		  for a Repulse Bay Expedition in 1897 and an expedition to the Antarctic late in
		  1896 never materialised, but during 1896 and 1897 he was in Franz-Josef Land
		  with the Jackson-Harmsworth expedition. His work there was mainly zoological
		  but he took part in the survey of the western part of the archipelago. In 1898
		  he sailed to Novaya Zemlya and the Barents Sea with Major Andrew Coats, and in
		  the same year accompanied the Prince of Monaco to Spitzbergen (Svalbard).
		  Between 1899 and 1901 Bruce was a Lecturer in Geography at the then Heriot-Watt
		  College in Edinburgh (now Heriot-Watt University) and at the Church of Scotland
		  Training College in the city. In 1902, Bruce organised and led the Scottish
		  National Antarctic Expedition to the Weddell Sea, returning home in 1904. This
		  expedition took some of the earliest cine film of Antarctica and may also have
		  pioneered sound recording there. Other expeditions to Spitzbergen occurred in
		  1906, 1907, 1909, 1912, 1914, and 1919. During the visits to Spitzbergen deep
		  soundings were taken and the island was surveyed and explored. Bruce took a
		  leading part in economic developments there, and brought back samples of coal
		  for analysis before any claims to mining estates had been made by Norwegian and
		  Russian interests. His plan for a second Scottish Antarctic Expedition was
		  announced in 1910 but this was abandoned due to insufficient funds. Between
		  1914 and 1915, he was in the Seychelles in charge of a sperm-whaling venture.
		  Bruce equipped and maintained the Scottish Oceanographical Laboratory as a
		  centre for Polar research and was Director of the Laboratory, but his failing
		  health compelled him to disband it. His voyages added materially to knowledge
		  about the mammal and bird life of the islands of the Arctic region, and about
		  both the northern and southern Polar seas. Bruce died in Edinburgh on 28
		  October 1921. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>The Papers of William Speirs Bruce consist of a substantial number of
		  manuscripts and ephemera including pamphlets; notes and notebooks; annotated
		  typescripts; annotated offprints; picture postcards; photographs; examination
		  papers; sketch maps; diaries; press cuttings; correspondence; lists of
		  specimens; book catalogues; soundings; lecture engagements; lectures; and,
		  maps. The Papers handle a wide variety of subjects including the 'Balaena',
		  fish and fisheries, Franz Josef Land, the Jackson-Harmsworth Expedition,
		  meteorology, oceanography, Repulse Bay, the Seychelles, soundings, South
		  Georgia, Spitzbergen, and whaling. In addition there are circa 1000 books with
		  the shelfmark, Bruce Coll. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.5./marc 541"> 
		<p>The library of the Scottish Oceanographical Laboratory and the Bruce
		  manuscript collection was donated in 1921. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Bruce</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William
		  Speirs</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1867-1921</emph> </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Geddes</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Patrick</emph>
		  <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1854-1932</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Grimaldi</emph> <emph
		  altrender="forename">Albert-Honore-Charles</emph> <emph
		  altrender="title">H.S.H. Prince of Monaco</emph> </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Coats</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Andrew</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Jackson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Frederick</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Heriot-Watt
		  University</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish
		  Oceanographical Laboratory</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph
		  altrender="a">International Antarctic Expedition</emph> <emph
		  altrender="y">1901-1903</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Challenger Expedition</emph> <emph altrender="y">1872-1876</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Scientific expeditions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Whaling</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Zoology</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Zoologists</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Meteorologists</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Meteorology</emph> </subject> 
		<geogname encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Antarctica</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Seychelles</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph altrender="a">Arctic
		  Ocean</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph altrender="a">Spitzbergen
		  Island (Norway)</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph altrender="a">Repulse
		  Bay</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname source="aacr2" encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Svalbard (Norway)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>Handlist, H72. Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts shows, at various shelfmarks, references to
		  various letters of and to William Speirs Bruce. There is a volume of newspaper
		  cuttings relating to the Scottish National Antarctic Expedition at Gen.556.
		  Separately there is a set of album material stamped Scottish National Antarctic
		  Expedition at Gen. 1670-1696 </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
