<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-873" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-873</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of George Hamilton Gordon (1784-1860), 4th Earl of
			 Aberdeen </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Oct 28 10:29:43 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-873</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.7.47/6-7; Gen. 2039/5-6</physloc><unittitle>Letters of George
		  Hamilton Gordon (1784-1860), 4th Earl of Aberdeen </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1832-1849">1832-1849</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 letters or notes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Gordon, George Hamilton</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Prime Minister, Lord Aberdeen, was born George Gordon in Edinburgh on
		  28 January 1784. By 1795 he was an orphan and his guardians were Pitt and Lord
		  Melville. He was educated at Harrow and studied at St. John's College,
		  Cambridge. He inherited the Earldom in 1801 on the death of his grandfather and
		  travelled in Europe soon afterwards spending much of the time in Greece. Gordon
		  spoke in the House of Lords for the first time in 1807. In 1813 he became
		  Ambassador Extraordinary and Minister Plenipoteniary to Vienna, and signed an
		  alliance with Austria (Treaty of Toeplitz). In 1814 he signed the Treaty of
		  Paris, and for his diplomatic skill became Viscount Gordon. When the Duke of
		  Wellington formed an administration in 1828, Lord Aberdeen became Chancellor of
		  the Duchy of Lancaster with a seat on the Cabinet, and later that year he was
		  made Foreign Secretary. During his office, Greece became independent. Under Sir
		  Robert Peel's administration, Lord Aberdeen was Secretary for War and the
		  Colonies and then in 1841 he was Secretary for Foreign Affairs, successfully
		  concluding agreements with the Americans over boundaries in the north-east and
		  in Oregon. In 1852, Lord Aberdeen became Prime Minister within a 'coalition
		  ministry' of Lord John Russell, Palmerston, Gladstone, and the Duke of Argyll.
		  His government became embroiled in the Crimean War and he resigned in 1855. He
		  spoke for the last time in the Lords in 1858. His publications included 
		<title>An inquiry into the principles of beauty in Grecian
		  architecture</title> (1822). Aberdeen married Lady Catherine Elizabeth Hamilton
		(d. 1812), daughter of John, 1st Marquis of Abercorn, in 1805, and then
		Harriet, daughter of the Hon. John Douglas, in 1815. George Hamilton Gordon,
		4th Earl of Aberdeen, died at Argyll House, London, on 14 December 1860, and
		was buried at Stanmore, Middlesex.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The correspondence is composed of: a letter from Aberdeen, 1832,
		  declining the offer of a villa at Woolmer which, although he knew of nowhere
		  'which would more take my fancy' the distance from London was 'much greater
		  than we should find convenient'; a letter from Aberdeen at Addington Park to D.
		  C. Guthrie Esq., 1847, in which he declines to give support for a petition;
		  and, notes regretting his absence from a Lord Mayor's dinner, 1835, and from
		  the opening of the New Coal Exchange, 1849..</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Among miscellaneous letters of a Scottish interest, purchased E. Hall,
		  May 1976, Accession no. E76.21</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.8. Glover-Harriott.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Lord Aberdeen related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): letters (4) of Aberdeen,
		  mentioning the Bannatyne Club and publications, 1827-1836, at La.IV.18; letter
		  to Sir Walter Scott announcing his joint appointment (with Lockhart and Gooch)
		  to report on the Stuart Papers, 1829, at La.III.584/68; letter to Aberdeen from
		  the Rev. Dr. T. Chalmers, 1839, at Dk.7.47/86; </p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of George
		  Hamilton Gordon related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Gordon</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George Hamilton</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1784-1860</emph> <emph altrender="title">4th Earl of
		  Aberdeen</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Statesman</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
