<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-525" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-525</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Sir Edward Walker (1612-1677), Garter
			 King-of-Arms </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Mar 10 10:46:40 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date>Converted from EAD 1.0
			 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-525</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.8.111; Dk.5.21</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Sir Edward
		  Walker (1612-1677), Garter King-of-Arms </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1650">1650</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 manuscript volumes</extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Walker, Edward</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Edward Walker was born on 24 January 1612. He entered the service of
		  Thomas Howard, Earl of Arundel, the Earl Marshal, around 1633. With the help of
		  Arundel, he entered the College of Arms and was successively created Blanch
		  Lion pursuivant-at-arms extraordinary, Rouge Croix pursuivant, and Chester
		  Herald. Walker accompanied Arundel with the royal army to Scotland and took
		  part in negotiations with Scottish Commissioners at Berwick. In 1640 he was
		  appointed Paymaster of the Carlisle garrison. During the Civil War he
		  accompanied King Charles on his campaigns and in 1642 he was made
		  Secretary-at-War, then Secretary-Extraordinary to the Privy Council in 1644. He
		  was with the King at Naseby and after, and was created Norroy King-of-Arms in
		  1644, in Oxford. Walker became Garter King-of-Arms in 1645. When Oxford fell,
		  he went to France but returned in 1648 to act as the King's chief secretary. In
		  1649 he was in The Hague with the King and in 1650 accompanied the royal
		  entourage to Scotland. Sir Edward Walker died on 19 February 1677 and was
		  buried at Stratford-on-Avon.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: 
		<title>A short journal of what was transacted in Scotland from his
		  Majesty King Charles the Second's arrival there from Holland to the end of
		  October following</title>, 1650, and 
		<title>a short journal of severall Actions performed in the Kingdome of
		  Scotland after his majesties first Arrival there out of Holland, the 24th of
		  June 1650</title>. The latter is signed with the author's corrections and
		additions.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.20.
		Ubaldini-Whewell. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence and papers, 1639-1677, British
		  Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Index of MSS, X, 1986; collections,
		  College of Arms; historical discourses, Huntigndon Library; draft letters and
		  warrants, 1643-1649, House of Lords Record Office, The Parliamentary Archives,
		  Ref. Walker papers; account of progress and successes of Charles I, 1644,
		  Oxford University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western
		  Manuscripts, Ref. MS Clar 136; papers (24 items), 1653-1674, College of Arms;
		  annotated transcript by him of Rice Merrick's Morganiae Archaiographia, 1675,
		  National Library of Wales, Ref. NLW MS 11700; heraldic papers, Society of
		  Antiquaries of London, Ref. MSS 354, 455 NRA 27819 Society; and, correspondence
		  with 6th Duke of Norfolk, 1654-1656, Arundel Castle, Ref. Vol 1 pp219-20 NRA
		  12614 Fitzalan-Howard.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Walker</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Edward</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1612-1677</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Herald</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">17th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
