<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-356" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-356</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of James Hall (circa 1800-1854) and his father Sir
			 James Hall (1761-1832)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Apr 08 11:34:25 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-356</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.100/8, f.2-6, 8-9; Gen. 1981/138</physloc><unittitle>Papers
		  of James Hall (circa 1800-1854) and his father Sir James Hall
		  (1761-1832)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1817-1839">1817-1839</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 letter, 1 envelope containing miscellaneous
		  material. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Hall was born in 1761. He was the eldest son of Sir John, 3rd
		  Baronet of Dunglass, East Lothian. The younger Hall succeeded to the baronetcy
		  in 1776. In 1777 he entered Christ's College, Cambridge, but did not graduate.
		  He had developed an interest in geology and the work of James Hutton
		  (1726-1797) and tested Hutton's ideas by studying rocks in the Alps, Italy and
		  Sicily. While travelling he studied the architecture of each locality. After
		  his return to Britain in 1785 he submitted papers to the Royal Society of
		  Edinburgh on a variety of topics including basalt, carbonate of lime, and
		  strata.</p> 
		<p>In 1797 he also submitted an introductory 
		<title>Essay on the origin and principles of Gothic architecture</title>
		in which he argued that Gothic architecture was the reproduction in stone of
		simple wattle buildings. He showed how its features copied sprouting buds on
		willow-staves, curling flakes of bark on poles, and roof poles tied together as
		rafters.</p> 
		<p>Between 1807 and 1812, Hall was MP for a borough in Cornwall. A
		  machine invented by him for regulating high temperatures was described
		  posthumously to the Geological Society of London by his second son, Captain
		  Basil Hall (1788-1844). Sir James Hall died in Edinburgh on 23 June 1832.</p> 
		<p>James Hall, advocate and painter, was the youngest son of Sir James
		  Hall. James Hall was born between 1797 and 1800, and was educated for the legal
		  profession. He became better known however as an art patron and amateur
		  portrait-painter. Hall was a student of the Royal Academy and became friends
		  with Sir David Wilkie (1785-1841). He exhibited portraits and scenic works both
		  at the British Institution and the Royal Academy. His works include 
		<title>The real scenery of the bride of Lammermuir</title>, 
		<title>From Burns's monument in Ayrshire - the island of Arran in the
		  distance</title>, 
		<title>The Pentland Hills near Edinburgh</title>, 
		<title>Tantallon Castle</title>, and 
		<title>The linn at Ashiesteel, where it enters the Tweed</title>. Hall
		also attempted a political career, unsuccessfully fighting for the borough of
		Taunton in 1841 and 1842. James Hall died at Ashiesteel, Selkirkshire, on 26
		October 1854.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Material in the collection relating to James Hall, advocate and
		  painter includes: a letter to his sisters, 1817; class cards, certificates etc
		  while a student at Edinburgh University, 1817-1821; petition to undergo
		  advocate's trials, 1820; act of admission as an advocate, 1821; pencil sketch
		  of the civil law class at Edinburgh University, 1819; and, a letter probably to
		  Sir Archibald Alison, 1839.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 8. Glover-Harriott.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Hall related material in
		  the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters to James
		  Hall from T. Campbell, at La.II.426/90-91; letters of Sir James Hall to H.
		  Warrender and E. Blore, 1782-1811, at La.II.309. There is also: mention of Sir
		  James in a letter of Adam Ferguson, 1783, at Gen. 1733/93; mention in a letter
		  of James Byres, 1785, at Gen. 873/11/262-263; mention in a letter of John
		  Playfair, 1804, at Gen. 1999/1/133; note to Professor J. Black at Gen.
		  873/1/109-110; letters and notes to Sir C. Lyell, Lyell Collection and Gen.
		  1999/7/7/1-3.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes for James Hall, painter: 1838-39:
		  letters (14) to 1st Duke of Wellington, 1838-1839, Southampton University
		  Library, Ref. MS 61 NRA 20085 Wellesley. For Sir James Hall, UK NRA notes:
		  correspondence, diaries and papers, 1774-1831, National Archives of Scotland,
		  Ref. GD206 NRA 13872 Hall; notes on experiments, letters and travel journals,
		  1798-1809, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 584,
		  3220-21, 3813, 4002, 5019-20, 6324-32, and notes on perspective, circa
		  1812-1816, undated, NRA 32554 Royal Soc Edinburgh, and also letters to
		  Alexander Marcet, 1804-1813, Ref. MS 3813.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Law</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Painters</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Artists</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hall</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1797-1854</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Painter</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Hall</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1761-1832</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">4th Baronet, Geologist and Chemist</emph> </persname>
		
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
