<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-410" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-410</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor Thomas Laycock
			 (1812-1876)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Jul 29 15:27:49 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-410</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.2.58; Gen. 1813; Gen. 1960; Mic.M.82;
		  Phot.Ill.90</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor Thomas Laycock
		  (1812-1876)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>10 letters, 1 volume, 1 box. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Thomas Laycock was born in Wetherby, Yorkshire, on 10 August 1812. He
		  was educated at the Wesleyan Academy, Woodhouse Grove, Yorkshire, and studied
		  at University College London. He also studied abroad in Paris and
		  G&#x00F6;tttingen. His early works were 
		<title>The acid and alkaline reactions of the saliva</title> (1837), and 
		<title>A treatise on the nervous diseases of women, comprising an inquiry
		  into the nature, causes, and treatment of spinal and hysterical
		  disorders</title> (1840). In a paper submitted before the British Association
		in 1844, Laycock was the first to formulate the theory of the reflex action of
		the brain. In 1846 he was appointed Lecturer in Clinical Medicine at the York
		School of Medicine, and in 1855 he became Professor of the Practice of Medicine
		at Edinburgh University. It was in Edinburgh that he published 
		<title>Mind and brain, or the correlations of consciousness and
		  organisations, with their applications to philosophy, mental pathology, and the
		  practice of medicine</title> (1859). He also published 
		<title>Lectures on the principles and methods of medical observation and
		  research</title> (1856), and 
		<title>The social and political relations of drunkenness</title> (1857).
		Professor Thomas Laycock died in Edinburgh on 21 September 1876.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: papers; a journal from 1833 to 1857
		  including time spent in London as a medical student; letters to D. R. Hay with
		  a copy of one letter from Hay relating to the Aesthetic Club; and,
		  illustrations of Laycock.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Papers acquired June 1974, Accession no. E74.42.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.11. Kennett-Lluelyn.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909. (2) Cooper, Thompson. 
		<title>Men of the time: a dictionary of contemporaries containing
		  biographical notes of eminent characters of both sexes</title>. 9th edition.
		p.632. London: George Routledge and Sons, 1875.</p> 
		<p>Although its content was not drawn upon, see also: Barfoot, Michael.
		  (ed.). 
		<title>'To ask the Suffrages of the Patrons' Thomas Laycock and the
		  Edinburgh Chair of Medicine</title>. Medical History, Supplement No.15. London:
		Wellcome Institute for the History of Medicine, 1995.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show another reference to Laycock related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): a letter about a bas relief portrait of
		  Laycock, from D. Waterston to the Secretary, Royal College of Physicians, 1940,
		  at Gen. 784/9/30. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA),
		  updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: diary, lecture notes
		  and papers, circa 1850-1876, Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh, Ref.
		  Laycock NRA 16015 Coll of Physicians; correspondence with Sir Edwin Chadwick,
		  1843-1857, London University, University College London (UCL) Manuscripts Room,
		  Ref. CHADWICK] NRA 21653 Chadwick; and, correspondence with George Combe,
		  1848-1858, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS
		  7302-7393 Passim.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Laycock</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1812-1876</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of
		  Medicine, Mental Physiologist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hay</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">David Ramsay</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1798-1866</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Decorative Artist
		  and Author</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
