<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-263" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-263</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Scottish Marine Station for Scientific
			 Research, Granton, Edinburgh</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Aug 08 10:00:46 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-263</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 33; Gen. 81D-92D; Gen. 93D-96D</physloc><unittitle>Records
		  of the Scottish Marine Station for Scientific Research, Granton,
		  Edinburgh</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1883-1901">1883-1901</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes, 16 volumes of notebooks. </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Scottish Marine Station for Scientific Research was established in
		  1884 and was located on a floating barge in a drowned but tidal quarry near
		  Granton, which was then a small but growing harbour community west of Newhaven
		  harbour and the port of Leith on the Firth of Forth (each of these now part of
		  greater-Edinburgh). Behind the scheme for setting up the Station had been the
		  Meteorological Society of Scotland and the Royal Society of Edinburgh. Dr. John
		  Murray (1841-1914), later Sir John Murray K.C.B., F.R.S., LL.D., of the
		  'Challenger' Commission, and also a prominent member of both Societies, had
		  also been a leading spirit behind the project. Opened for scientific work by
		  Ernst Haeckel (1834-1919), Professor of Zoology and Natural Philosophy in Jena,
		  in April 1884, the biological station would become popularly known as the
		  Edinburgh Marine Station, and, perhaps because of the input of funds from the
		  Crown in autumn 1884, it also styled itself the Royal Scottish Marine
		  Station.</p> 
		<p>In addition to the extensive and varied biological investigations
		  which were to be carried out on the Station, a complete series of observations
		  on the temperatures of the surface water and of the bottom and intermediate
		  waters at fixed points of the Firth were to be carried out at regular intervals
		  throughout the year. The nature of the bottom and of deposits there, and a
		  record of the marine life, was also to be attempted. It was intended that the
		  Station be provided with a steam launch fitted for dredging purposes and for
		  making hydrographic observations. Indeed, the Station, known as the 'Ark' - a
		  floating laboratory with accommodation for seven biologists - was provided with
		  two small Norwegian skiffs, the 'Asymptote' and the 'Appendicularia' as well as
		  the steam yacht 'Medusa', the collecting vessel. The floating Station also
		  possessed a complete library of works on marine biology and physics. Mr.
		  Alexander Turbyne was fisherman on the 'Medusa', Mr. J. T. Cunningham was the
		  naturalist-in-charge, and H. R. Mill was the physicist and meteorologist.</p> 
		<p>In preparation for medical studies at University College, London,
		  William Speirs Bruce (1867-1921) was sent by his father to a vacation course in
		  biology at the Station in Granton in either 1884 or 1887. The biology course
		  was said to have been under the direction of Patrick Geddes (1854-1932).
		  Another student who worked at the Station for a short time in 1886 was the
		  Norwegian Fridtjof Nansen (1861-1930) who later on would achieve eminence as an
		  Arctic explorer.</p> 
		<p>Earlier, in 1882, Murray had succeeded Sir Charles Wyville Thomson
		  (1830-1882) as the Director of the Challenger Office and editor of the 
		<title>Report on the Scientific Results of the Voyage of the H.M.S.
		  Challenger</title>. The Office of the 'Challenger' Expedition were latterly at
		Challenger Lodge, slightly to the east of Granton. The 'Challenger' Expedition
		of 1872-1876 had been charged with determining deep sea physical conditions
		including depth, temperature, and ocean currents. Charting, surveying, and
		biological investigations were also carried out. Each of these activities were
		reflected in the activities and interests of the Scottish Marine Station for
		Scientific Research.</p> 
		<p>After some years of work at Granton, the floating biological Station
		  was towed to Millport on Cumbrae in the Clyde. There it was beached and became
		  an annex of the Millport biological station which went on to become the
		  headquarters of the Scottish Marine Biological Association (SMBA).</p> 
		<p>Challenger Lodge has become St. Columba's Hospice, at 15 Boswall Road,
		  Edinburgh.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The records of the Scottish Marine Station consist largely of
		  notebooks containing details about the chemical work done at Granton,
		  1888-1901. The notebooks show calculations, water and other analyses, notes on
		  chemical deposits, photographs, sketches, and tables both written and printed.
		  There is also a large amount of invoices addressed to the Station and receipts
		  for payment, 1883-1887. A few other papers relate to accounts, 1884-1901.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative history of the Station was compiled using
		  information derived from other collection descriptions, communication with
		  Geoff Swinney (Curator of Fishes, Amphibians &amp;amp; Reptiles, Geology and
		  Zoology Department, National Museums of Scotland, Chambers Street, Edinburgh),
		  and from: (1) 
		<title>The Times</title>. 17 September 1883, p.6. London: The Times,
		1883. (2) Anon. Edinburgh Marine Station. 
		<title>Nature. A weekly illustrated journal of science</title>. Vol. 29.
		Nov. 1883-April 1884. p.483. London: Macmillan and Co., 1884. (3) Herdman, Sir
		William A. 
		<title>Founders of oceanography and their work. An introduction to the
		  science of the sea</title>. London: Edward Arnold, 1923. (3) Laverack, M. S.
		Zoology. A natural history of natural historians. 
		<title>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Edinburgh</title>. Section B.
		Biological sciences. Vol. 84. Two hundred years of the biological sciences in
		Scotland. 1983. pp.353-374. Edinburgh: Royal Society of Edinburgh, 1983.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Hydrographic surveying</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Marine biology</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Marine resources</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Murray</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1841-1914</emph>
		  <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Naturalist
		  and Oceanographer</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh Marine Station for Scientific
		  Research</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Marine Station for Scientific
		  Research</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Challenger Expedition, 1872-1876</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Firth of Forth (Scotland)</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
