<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-852" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-852</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Dukes and Duchesses of Sutherland
			 (1758-1963)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Aug 30 10:19:47 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-852</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1983/162; Gen. 2041/49-92</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the
		  Dukes and Duchesses of Sutherland (1758-1963)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1800-1923">1800-1923</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>41 letters, and 4 items illustration. </extent>
		  <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Gower, Elizabeth Leveson-; Gower, George Granville Leveson-;
		  Gower, George Granville Leveson-; Gower, Harriet Elizabeth Georgiana
		  Sutherland-Leveson-; Gower, George Granville William Leveson-; Gower, Cromartie
		  Leveson-; Gower, Millicent Fanny St. Clair-Erskine Leveson-; Gower, George
		  Granville Sutherland Leveson-</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="fre">French.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>While there had been an Earldom of Sutherland in Scotland dating as
		  far back as the thirteenth century - and held by the Gordons through marriage
		  later on in the sixteenth century - the title of Duke of Sutherland was first
		  borne by the family of Leveson-Gower in 1833.</p> 
		<p>In 1771 the House of Lords agreed that the Earldom belonged to
		  Elizabeth Gordon, youngest and only surviving daughter of William, 18th Earl of
		  Sutherland who died on 16 June 1766. In 1785 she married George Granville
		  Leveson-Gower (1758-1833) who became Marquess of Stafford in 1803, and the two
		  titles and vast estates and wealth were united. Leveson-Gower was educated at
		  Westminster School, and studied at Christ Church, Oxford. He was the MP for
		  Newcastle-under-Lyme and for Staffordshire, and was the British Ambassador in
		  Paris. He held the post (jointly with another) of Postmaster-General,
		  1799-1810. Leveson-Gower was made Duke of Sutherland in January 1833 and he
		  died on 19 July 1833. The Duke and Duchess (who died on 29 January 1839) had
		  two sons and two daughters.</p> 
		<p>The eldest son George Granville (1786-1861), 2nd Duke of Sutherland
		  married Harriet Elizabeth Georgiana (d. 1868), daughter of George, 6th Earl of
		  Carlisle. She was a close personal friend of Queen Victoria and was Mistress of
		  the Robes. The Duke was MP for St. Mawes, 1808-1812, for Newcastle-under-Lyme,
		  1812-1815, and for Staffordshire, 1815-1820. He died on 22 February 1861.</p> 
		<p>Their eldest son George Granville William (1828-1892), 3rd Duke of
		  Sutherland, was MP for Sutherland, 1852-1861. He married Anne Hay-Mackenzie of
		  Newhall and Cromartie on 27 June 1849. She was created Countess of Cromartie
		  and was also Mistress of the Robes to Queen Victoria.</p> 
		<p>Their second son Cromartie (1851-1913), 4th Duke of Sutherland, was MP
		  for Sutherland, 1874-1886. He married the socialite Millicent Fanny, daughter
		  of Robert Francis, 4th Earl of Rosslyn. Their eldest son George Granville
		  Sutherland (1888-1963), 5th Duke of Sutherland, married Lady Eileen Gwladys
		  Butler, daughter of the 7th Earl of Lanesborough. She was Mistress of the Robes
		  to Queen Mary. The Duke was Under-Secretary at the Air Ministry, 1922-1924,
		  Paymaster-General, 1925-1928, and Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for
		  War, 1928-1929. The 5th Duke died without issue in 1963 and was succeeded by
		  John Sutherland Egerton, oldest son of the 4th Earl of Ellesmere.</p> 
		<p>Millicent, Dowager Duchess of Sutherland, died in August 1955. On the
		  death of the 4th Duke in 1913, she had remarried, and married again after a
		  divorce. During the First World War she served as a nurse in Namur.</p> 
		<p>The hereditary home of the Dukes of Sutherland is Dunrobin Castle in
		  Sutherland. Stafford House, facing Buckingham Palace from Green Park, became
		  Lancaster House.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers are composed of: letters signed either Gower, Stafford, or
		  Sutherland, between 1800-1838, and from either Stafford House, Trentham or
		  Brighton; letter of 1st Duke from Stafford House, 1833 and in relation to
		  'purchasing Pictures or adding to his collection'; letters of 2nd Duke,
		  1832-1857, written at either Westhill, Brighton, Stafford House, Dunrobin, and
		  London, and signed either Gower or Sutherland, and two letters in French (one
		  at Gen. 1983/162); letters (9) of Harriet, Duchess of Sutherland, largely
		  undated; letters (10) of 3rd Duke of Sutherland, one written on paper from
		  Woodlands, Clapham Common, but at Portmadoc, 1870, others from Queen Anne
		  Street, London, Stafford House, Swynnerton Park at Stone, and signed either
		  Stafford or Sutherland; letters of the 4th Duke and his Duchess Millicent, from
		  either Stafford House or Trentham, and RYS 'Sans Peur' at Swinemunde on the
		  Baltic; and, letters of the 5th Duke, 1917-1923, from Dunrobin Castle and
		  Hampden House, signed Sutherland. There are also illustrations of Trentham
		  Hall, the Rt. Hon. Harriet Elizabeth Georgiana Countess Gower, the 3rd Duke of
		  Sutherland, and a number of newspaper cuttings, two relating to Millicent,
		  Dowager Duchess.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Burke, Sir Bernard. and Burke Ashworth P. 
		<title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage,
		  the Privy Council, and knightage</title>. 87th edition. London: Burke's Peerage
		Ltd., 1929. (2) 
		<title>Who's who 1962</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1962.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Sutherland related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): a tract on the precedency of the
		  Earls of Sutherland before the Earls of Caithness, 1617, at La.II.45; letter to
		  Elizabeth Sutherland, wife of G. G. Leveson-Gower, 1st Duke of Sutherland, from
		  Sir W. Scott, at La.III.585/7; letter of G. G. Leveson-Gower, 2nd Duke of
		  Sutherland, to Sir G. Warrender, 1841, at La.II.509; franked postal cover
		  addressed to Gitter and Co., 1834, at Dk.6.19/3; letter of G. G. William
		  Sutherland-Leveson-Gower, 3rd Duke to Sir C. J. Pearson, 1892, at Gen. 756, no.
		  276; letters (19) of Millicent, Dowager Duchess, to Professor John Orr about
		  relief for Normandy, 1944-1945, at Gen. 868/1/46-61c; letters of Millicent to
		  Mrs. Howey and to Mrs. A. Tweedie, 1895-1903, at Dk.6.19/2; and, letters of
		  Millicent to Mrs. A. Tweedie, 1895-1896, at Dk.6.19/4.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Dukes and
		  Duchesses of Sutherland related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gower</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Elizabeth Leveson-</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1765-1839</emph> <emph altrender="title">Countess of
		  Sutherland</emph> <emph altrender="other">nee Sutherland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gower</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George Granville Leveson-</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1758-1833</emph> <emph altrender="title">Marquess of
		  Stafford, 1st Duke of Sutherland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gower</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George Granville Leveson-</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1786-1861</emph> <emph altrender="title">2nd Duke of
		  Sutherland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gower</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Harriet Elizabeth Georgiana
		  Sutherland-Leveson-</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1806-1868</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">wife of 2nd Duke of Sutherland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gower</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George Granville William Leveson-</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1828-1892</emph> <emph altrender="title">3rd Duke of
		  Sutherland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gower</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Cromartie Leveson-</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1851-1913</emph> <emph altrender="title">4th Duke of
		  Sutherland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gower</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Millicent Fanny St. Clair-Erskine Leveson-</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1867-1955</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">wife of 4th
		  Duke of Sutherland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gower</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George Granville Sutherland Leveson-</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1888-1963</emph> <emph altrender="title">5th Duke of
		  Sutherland</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
