<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-162" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-162</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Swan Land and Cattle Company</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Nov 23 12:12:30 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-162</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 717</physloc><unittitle>Swan Land and Cattle
		  Company</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1883-1947">1883-1947</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>6 thin bundles typescript. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Burns, Robert Homer; Gillespie, Andrew Springs</origination>
		
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The home ranch of the Swan Land and Cattle Company was sited at
		  Chugwater, Wyoming. Its corporate headquarters were in Cheyenne. This large
		  corporate cattle company, with between 50,000 and 80,000 livestock, at one time
		  controlled an area of land greater than the size of the State of Connecticut.
		  In the 1870s and 1880s, this and other very large ranches grew out of the
		  realisation that cattle could be wintered on the northern plains of America.
		  Speculative investors were promised a twenty per cent return from the new
		  industry.</p> 
		<p>In November 1882, Alexander Hamilton Swan (1831-1905), the President
		  of the firms Swan and Frank Live-Stock Co., National Cattle Co., and Swan,
		  Frank and Anthony Cattle Co., together with James Converse, Joseph Frank, and
		  Godfrey Syndacker, entered into an agreement with James Wilson of Edinburgh to
		  set up the Swan Land and Cattle Company as a British limited company.</p> 
		<p>John Clay (1851-1934) followed Swan as general manager of the
		  firm.</p> 
		<p>By 1909, the company had reduced its dependence on cattle and had
		  turned to the holding of sheep instead.</p> 
		<p>In 1926, Swan Land and Cattle was re-organised in order to avoid
		  British taxes and became an American corporation under the laws of
		  Delaware.</p> 
		<p>The corporation's assets were liquidated in 1948, and the last
		  dividend was paid in 1951.</p> 
		<p>Andrew Springs (Bud) Gillespie worked as a cowboy for Swan Land and
		  Cattle Company during the 1900s, becoming a Wyoming rancher himself, performing
		  in rodeos, and writing books about Wyoming history.</p> 
		<p>Born on 23 August 1900 on the Flag Ranch, south of Laramie, Robert
		  Homer Burns studied at the University of Wyoming from 1916-1920 and obtained
		  his M.A. from Iowa State in 1921 and a Ph.D. in 1931 at Edinburgh University.
		  He began teaching at the University of Wyoming in 1924, later serving as head
		  of the Wool Department. From 1937-1939 Burns worked with the U.S. Department of
		  Agriculture, and in 1946 he participated in a mission to China to study
		  carpet-wool. In 1949, Burns then served as consultant to the Iranian government
		  in New York. He published widely and his writing included material on Laramie
		  ranches and the wider ranching industry, articles and data on Wyoming wool,
		  wool shrinkage, pelt sizes in sheep, and breeds of sheep. Burns and Gillespie
		  collaborated in the writing of 
		<title>Steamboat. Symbol of Wyoming spirit</title> (1952), 
		<title>Wyoming's pioneer ranches</title> (1955) and some writing on the
		Swan Land and Cattle Company. Robert Homer Burns died in an automobile accident
		on 14 June 1973.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of reminiscences of the Swan Land and
		  Cattle Company. The bundles of material are entitled: 
		<title>The Swan Land and Cattle Company. Utilizers of Wyoming
		  Grass</title>; 
		<title>The Swan Company roundups</title> Parts I and II; 
		<title>The Two-Bar hands. Cowboys for the Swan Company</title>; 
		<title>Blue Grass Well. World's largest water-hole</title>; and 
		<title>Edward Held and the Swan Company</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material acquired 1963, Accession no. E63.24.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Site of the 
		<title>American Heritage Center</title>, University of Wyoming, Laramie,
		and the standard archival description of the Inventory for the Robert H. Burns
		Papers, 1910-1973. Full-text [online]. 
		<extref
		href="http://ahc.uwyo.edu/usearchives/inventories/400002.htm">American Heritage
		  Center / R. H. Burns papers</extref> [Accessed 23 September 2004]. (2) Swan
		Land and Cattle Company, Chugwater, Wyoming. 
		<title>Wyoming Photographs</title>. Full-text [online]. 
		<extref href="http://www.wyomingtalesandtrails.com/horn.html">Wyoming
		  Photographs / Swan Land and Cattle Co.</extref> [Accessed 20 November
		2001].</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Robert Burns donated his papers to the University of Wyoming Archives
		  beween 1947-1973. The collection there is to be cited as, Robert H. Burns
		  Papers. The Accession Number is: 400002, Box Number, Folder Number, University
		  of Wyoming Archives, American Heritage Center, University of Wyoming. There may
		  be Gillespie material too.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ranching</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Cowboys</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Sheep ranchers</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Burns</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert H.</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1900-1973</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">University
		  Lecturer, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Writer</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gillespie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Andrew Springs</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl.
		  1900</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Cowboy, Rancher, Writer</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Swan Land and Cattle Company</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname source="aacr2" role="subject"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Wyoming</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
