<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-610" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-610</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Church of Scotland China (Manchuria)
			 Collection</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 13:14:31 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-610</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 40</physloc><unittitle>Church of Scotland China
		  (Manchuria) Collection</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1870-1989">1870-[ca. 1986]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>5 boxes and 8 rolled items</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Foreign Mission Committees of the United Presbyterian
		  Church, the United Free Church and the Church of Scotland concerned with
		  Manchuria, China</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="chi">Chinese.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Foreign Mission Committee (later Board of World Mission and Unity)
		  of the Church of Scotland was responsible for the Church's mission work around
		  the world. In 1824 the Church's General Assembly resolved to send its first
		  missionary to India and appointed Alexander Duff who arrived in Bombay in 1830.
		  The first missionary to China arrived at I'chang in 1878 but by that time the
		  Disruption of 1843 had led to the split of the Free Church of Scotland from the
		  main Church and the United Presbyterian Church had been formed in 1847. This
		  latter Church sent its first missionary, Dr John Ross, to Manchuria in 1872
		  and, in co-operation with the Irish Presbyterian Church, the work grew steadily
		  in evangelical, medical and educational areas. The Chinese Presbytery (later
		  Synod of Manchuria) was formed in 1891 and in 1899 the Theological College was
		  established at Moukden. In 1900 the United Presbyterian Church joined with the
		  Free Church of Scotland and the missionaries became the responsibility of the
		  new United Free Church transferring to the Church of Scotland in 1929 when the
		  two Churches joined. Despite the Boxer rebellion of 1900 the mission continued
		  to flourish, there was a period of revival in 1908 and Moukden Medical College
		  was opened in 1912. Conditions were never easy for the missionaries, and they
		  suffered sever disruption during the Japanese occupation (from 1931) and the
		  Sino-Japanese War (from 1937). However in January 1941 there were over seventy
		  Church of Scotland missionaries in Manchuria but the entry of Japan into the
		  Second World War meant that the missionaries were either evacuated or interned
		  by the Japanese. After the war some of the missionaries were invited back to
		  Manchuria, the first arriving in 1946, but by the end of 1948, with the whole
		  of Manchuria in communist hands, it became increasingly difficult to work
		  effectively. The main group of missionaries withdrew during 1949 and all had
		  left by August 1950. The Church attempted to keep in touch with developments in
		  China, or with Chinese Christians who had left the country: missionaries and
		  church officials were members of various China focus groups and during the
		  1980s they took part in the first official Church visits to China.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: some early material relating to the
		  mission in Manchuria including letters from John Ross (1870) and a memoir by
		  Ethel Omelvena (1957); Moukden Medical College annual statements (1911-1948);
		  material relating to the mission after the Second World War including extracts
		  from minutes and reports and circular letters from missionaries (1946-1968);
		  reports on visits to China (1980s); photographs of Manchuria, the mission and
		  church (c 1910-1940s); maps and plans; Chinese language newspapers; hymns and
		  songs; and illustrations, sketches, wall-hangings, posters and miscellaneous
		  artwork, many used in evangelising.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged as described above. Before it was deposited
		  at the Centre it was listed in some detail by the Church of Scotland, these
		  lists are in the relevant files and boxes.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was presented to the Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World by the Church of Scotland in 1993.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) National Library of Scotland 
		<title>Catalogue of Manuscripts</title>. Vol. 6. Edinburgh: Her Majesty's
		Stationery Office, 1984, (2) Fulton, Austin. 
		<title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title>. Edinburgh: The Saint
		Andrew Press, 1967.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist and box file lists are available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the foreign missions of the Church of Scotland are
		  held by the National Library of Scotland, some of the material in that
		  collection may duplicate this material. The Centre has several other
		  collections relating to mission work in Manchuria and to the Church of
		  Scotland, including large sets of slides and lantern slides. Austin Fulton in 
		<title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title> (Edinburgh: The Saint
		Andrew Press, 1967) describes the missionary work in Manchuria and includes a
		list of sources. The Centre has many pamphlets and journals and some bound
		minutes relating to missions in China, some of which came from the Church of
		Scotland.</p> 
		<p>Also within the ArchivesHub the Edinburgh University Library
		  collection of 
		<title>Records of the Church of Scotland General Assembly</title> may be
		of interest.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland </emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Manchuria (China)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
