<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-406" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-406</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Correspondence of Daniel Maclise R.A.
			 (1806-1870)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Jul 29 14:45:40 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-406</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.4.101-103; Dc.4.102 misc., f.74; Gen.
		  1732</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence of Daniel Maclise R.A.
		  (1806-1870)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>7 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Daniel Maclise was born in Cork (Corcaigh) in 1806. He was educated at
		  an English day-school in the city, where he showed an early proficiency at
		  drawing. In 1820 he was working in a bank but soon left to devote himself to
		  art, studying at the new (in 1822) Cork Academy. An early success was a drawing
		  of Sir Walter Scott (1771-1832) which was lithographed and became very popular.
		  He then opened a studio, and he was also introduced to the Irish antiquary
		  Thomas Crofton Croker (1798-1854) whose second edition of 
		<title>Fairy legends and traditions of the south of Ireland</title>
		contained a number of illustrations by Maclise. In 1827 he went to London and
		made an early success with a sketch of actor-manager Charles (John) Kean
		(1811-1868) in the role of Norval in 
		<title>Douglas</title> at Drury Lane, which was again lithographed. In
		1828 he commenced studies at the Academy schools and in 1829 he exhibited at
		the Royal Academy. In 1830, Maclise began a series of character portraits under
		the nom de plume of Alfred Croquis, and he continued with these until 1838. He
		drew Scott, Coleridge, Thackeray, Wordsworth, Charles Lamb, Carlyle, Leigh
		Hunt, Disraeli, and Talleyrand. In 1840 he was elected to the Royal Academy and
		in 1855 he acted as a juror at the Paris Exhibition. In 1857 he put forward
		proposals for the decoration of the Royal Gallery in the House of Lords. These
		included 
		<title>Wellington and Bluecher at Waterloo</title> and 
		<title>The death of Nelson on board the Victory</title>. Daniel Maclise
		died on 25 April 1870 at his home on Cheyne Walk, Chelsea. He was buried at
		Kensal Green.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The correspondence includes: an undated letter to MacGregor; an
		  undated letter to Hall and Mrs. Hall; a letter to G. Jones, R.A.., about
		  military objects of the period of Waterloo, probably for use in the Waterloo
		  fresco in the House of Lords, 1858; letters of 1862; and, a letter to a
		  merchant about a supply of wine.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter to Jones acquired December 1966, Accession no. E67.31. Letters
		  of 1862, purchased July 1968, Accession no. E68/23. Wine letter, purchased
		  February 1973, Accession no. E73.8. Letter to Hall, purchased October 1973,
		  Accession no. E73.34. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 12. Llwyd-Mason.
		London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Maclise related material
		  in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters to W.
		  Jerdan, J. Crofton Croker, and Hall, at La.II.648/149-151; letter to an unnamed
		  correspondent objecting to a portion of a picture being engraved separately, at
		  La.II.426/302. Also, letters to J. O. Halliwell-Phillipps, 1863, at
		  L.O.A.84/42, and L.O.A. 91/17. In addition, the UK National Register of
		  Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes:
		  letters and memoranda, Trinity College, Dublin, Ref. MS 10686, see Annual
		  return 1994; autobiographical notes, circa 1846, Royal Academy of Arts, Ref.
		  MIS/MAC NRA 14837 Royal Academy; letters to J. N. Forster, 1834-1869, Victoria
		  and Albert Museum, National Art Library, Ref. Forster Collection NRA 38887
		  Forster, and letters (16), see List of Accessions 1979; and, letters (24) to
		  Charles Dickens and others, 1831-1867, Huntington Library, see Guide to
		  Literary MSS 1979.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Artists</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Maclise</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Daniel</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1806-1870</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Painter</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
