<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-392" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-392</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers relating to Sir Norman Boyd Kinnear
			 (1882-1957)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon May 27 11:27:57 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-392</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.6.22</physloc><unittitle>Papers relating to Sir Norman Boyd
		  Kinnear (1882-1957)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1900-1945">1900-1945</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box file. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The ornithologist Norman Boyd Kinnear was born on 11 August 1882. He
		  was educated at Edinburgh Academy and Trinity College, Glenalmond. In 1905 he
		  became a Volunteer Assistant with the Royal Scottish Museum, and from 1907 he
		  was Curator of Bombay Natural History Society Museum. Prior to joining the
		  Zoology Department at the British Museum, Natural History, in 1920, he
		  organised a survey of mammals in India, Myanmar, (then Burma) and Sri Lanka
		  (then Ceylon). From Assistant at the British Museum in 1920, he became
		  Assistant Keeper in 1928, Deputy Keeper in 1936, and Keeper of Zoology in 1945.
		  From 1947 until 1950 he was Director of the Museum. Between 1943 and 1948 he
		  was President of the British Ornithological Union. Kinnear was knighted in
		  1950. He published various papers on ornithology and he had been Assistant
		  Editor of the Bombay Natural History Society Journal, 1908 to 1919, and Editor
		  of the Bulletin of the British Ornithological Club, 1925 to 1930. Sir Norman
		  Boyd Kinnear died on 11 August 1957.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection contains correspondence and papers on various
		  ornithological issues, 1901-1945, and includes correspondence with William
		  Eagle Clarke (1853-1938) between 1900 and 1911, also Kinnear's obituary of W.
		  E. Clarke.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection bears the Accession no. E58.10, indicating acquisition
		  in 1958. Presented by Lady Kinnear.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>Who was who 1951-1960</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black,
		1961. (2) 
		<title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise
		  dictionary</title>. Part 2. 1901-1970. Oxford: OUP, 1982.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: letter books, journal of whaling voyage, notes,
		  1901-1935, Natural History Museum, Ref. L MSS KIN</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ornithology</emph> </subject>
		
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Kinnear</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Norman Boyd</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1882-1957</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Ornithologist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Clarke</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William Eagle</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1853-1938</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">Ornithologist</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
