<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-666" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-666</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of Thomas Faed R.A. (1826-1900)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri May 9 11:55:50 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-666</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1981/93-96; Dc.4.101-103 Faed; Gen.
		  863/8/21-22</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Thomas Faed R.A.
		  (1826-1900)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1851-1890">1851-1890</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 letters, 1 cutting. </extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Faed, Thomas</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Thomas Faed was born in Kirkcudbright on 8 June 1826. He was the
		  brother of the artists George Faed (1830-1852), John Faed (1819-1902), James
		  Faed (1821-1911), and Susan Bell Faed (1827-1909). Thomas showed talent as a
		  painter already as a boy but at the age of sixteen he was apprenticed to a
		  draper in Castle Douglas. Painting was too strong however and he went to
		  Edinburgh to work on miniatures for his brother. He entered the Trustees
		  Academy at the Royal Scottish Academy, Mound, Edinburgh and was taught by Sir
		  William Allan (1782-1850) and Thomas Duncan (1807-1845). At the age of eighteen
		  he exhibited 
		<title>A scene from the 'Old English Baron'</title>at the RSA. His
		greatest strength was the painting of scenes of rural and Scottish domestic
		life. In the 1840s he illustrated Scott's 
		<title>Heart of Midlothian</title>. Between the 1850s and the 1890s he
		exhibited at the Royal Academy. In 1855 his 
		<title>The mitherless bairn</title> received great acclaim and is now in
		the National Gallery of Victoria, Australia. He is represented at the Tate, the
		National Gallery of Scotland, the Scottish National Portrait Gallery, Aberdeen,
		and Glasgow, and at Royal Holloway College, the Ashmolean, and in Montreal,
		Vancouver, Baroda, and Durban. Thomas Faed R.A. H.R.S.A. died in St. John's
		Wood, London, on 17 August 1900. His son John Francis Faed (1859-1904) was an
		accomplished oil and watercolour painter of seascapes.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The letters are composed of: those to various correspondents 1851-1886
		  and also undated, with photographs; those about private view tickets and
		  insurance, 1866 and 1890; cutting showing illustration 
		<title>The village school</title>; letter to Mr. Nicol about a chair, and
		London fog, 1886; and, letter to L. Emanuel Jr. saying he is hanging pictures
		at the Royal Academy. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letters 1851-1886, purchased Goodspeed's, Boston, Mass., July 1968,
		  Accession no. E68.23. Letter to Mr. Holden, 1879, purchased G. H. Paton, June
		  1988, Accession no. E88.40.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) McEwan, Peter J. M. 
		<title>Dictionary of Scottish art and architecture</title>. pp.199-200.
		Woodbridge, Suffolk: Antique Collectors' Club, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show a reference to John Faed related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): letter to Lumb Stocks, engraver, with
		  detailed suggestions for the revision of some plates, 1857, at Dc.4.101-103.
		  The local Indexes also show a reference to Thomas Faed related material (check
		  the Indexes for more details): mention of a dinner in honour of Faed from
		  Professor J. S. Blackie to R. Herdman, at Gen. 1730 onwards.</p> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters to Henry Septimus Sutton, Nottingham
		  University Library, Department of Manuscripts and Special Collections, NRA
		  12432 Sutton.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Artists</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Painters</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Faed</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1826-1900</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Painter</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
