<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-577" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-577</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Joseph Ross (d. 1967)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Nov 25 09:08:33 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-577</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 3</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Joseph Ross (d.
		  1967)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1920-1962">1920-1962</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 files </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Ross, Joseph </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> <language langcode="hin">Hindi, </language> and
		  <language langcode="chi">Chinese.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Joseph Ross was Organising Officer and Deputy Camp Chief of the Boy
		  Scout Association in Central Provinces (Madhya Pradesh), India in the early
		  20th century, with his headquarters at Jubbulpore (Jabalpur). He was seconded
		  to the YMCA and involved in other forms of youth work, coming into contact with
		  many missionaries who became his friends. He had previously been Scout
		  Commissioner for Aberdeen and returned there in 1924(?) when he left India. He
		  found it difficult to find scouting work and returned to his original career as
		  an accountant but also began taking Sunday school classes at Holburn West
		  Church. He collected as much information as he could find on missionaries
		  associated with Aberdeen and encouraged these and other missionary friends to
		  write him letters and send bulletins that he could read and discuss with his
		  classes. Ross died circa 1967.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists mainly of letters from and articles about
		  missionaries who knew Ross, who were connected with the Boy Scout Association
		  or who were associated with Aberdeen. Much of the material was collected by
		  Ross for use in his Sunday school classes, but some is more personal, many of
		  the articles are cutting from 
		<title>Life and Work</title> or other missionary publications, and there
		are some photographs. There is only a small amount on each missionary: Gertrude
		Becker, Earl L. King, H. R. Ferger, C. E. Tyndale-Biscoe, Elizabeth Hewat,
		Helen Hewat, Herbert Torrance, W. Idris Jones, Robert Calderwood, W. H. Watson,
		James Dewar, Johanna Tocher, Eric Liddell and Albert Schweitzer. There is also
		correspondence with those associated with the Boy Scout Association in India
		(1922-1931) and with the Grenfell Association (1920s-1940s) and there are two
		files of general press and missionary cuttings and articles.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged as above, with annotations by Ross. </p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The material was deposited at the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World by Joseph Ross.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself.</p>
		
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Ross also donated several pamphlets and the papers of George and
		  Isabel Kerr to the Centre library.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Ross</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Joseph</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Africa</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">India</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">China</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
