<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-705" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-705</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Marjorie Rackstraw (1888-1981), Warden of Masson
			 Hall, Edinburgh University</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Oct 21 10:58:29 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-705</unitid> 
		<physloc>E95.81</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Marjorie Rackstraw
		  (1888-1981), Warden of Masson Hall, Edinburgh University</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1915-1960">1915-1960</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes, 1 large envelope, 1 box slides, 1 bundle
		  picture postcards. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile
		  condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Rackstraw, Marjorie</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Marjorie Rackstraw was born 24 June 1888. She studied at the
		  University of Birmingham and was a Postgraduate Scholar at Bryn Mawr College,
		  Pennsylvania, USA. In 1913 she became Bursar at University House, Birmingham,
		  and from 1915 until 1917 did relief and reconstruction work in France. From
		  1917 until 1921, Rackstraw was warden of the Students Hall of Residence, Moray
		  House, Edinburgh, and then in 1921 did relief work in the Soviet Union until
		  1923. In 1924 she worked at the Headquarters of the League of Nations, and from
		  1924 until 1937 was Warden of Masson Hall, Edinburgh University. During this
		  time too she was Adviser of Women Students, Edinburgh University. From 1937,
		  Rackstraw was in London doing social work and in 1939 was involved in the
		  evacuation of day nurseries and nursery schools for London City Council (LCC).
		  In 1940 she did relief work for refugees in France until the fall of France in
		  June 1940. She then did emergency war work, and in 1944 joined the United
		  Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration in Germany. There she worked
		  with refugees, community feeding, and the welfare of old people, including the
		  setting up of hostels. In 1945, Rackstraw was elected Labour Councillor for
		  Hampstead and from 1945 until her death she set up and worked with the
		  Hampstead Old peoples' Housing Trust. Rackstraw was Chair of the Hampstead
		  Committee of the Lord Mayor's National Air Raid Distress Fund, Chair of the
		  Standing Committee on Communal Feeding, Governor of St. Olave's and St.
		  Saviour's School, and Honorary President of Niddrie School Association. She was
		  awarded the OBE in the New Years Honours List, 1960. Marjorie Rackstraw OBE
		  died on 28 April 1981.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: unsorted letters, cards, newspaper
		  cuttings; a soft leather folder of unsorted letters; photographs; a file on
		  displaced persons, notes of reminiscences for broadcast; Automobile Association
		  documents; letters from Sara Margery Fry (1874-1958); book on Sara Margery Fry;
		  cassette tapes; biographical papers; pamphlets on Masson Hall, Edinburgh
		  University; a report on women students; album of photographs relating to Masson
		  Hall; newsletter of the Masson Association; several dozen foreign picture
		  postcards; a document from Buckingham Palace announcing the award of OBE; and,
		  a box of Ilford lantern slides of Russia.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The material was acquired in a suitcase from Rackstraw's executors,
		  November 1995, Accession no. E95.81.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material
		  contained within the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Rackstraw</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Marjorie</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1888-1981</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Warden of Masson
		  Hall, UNRRA Relief Worker, Labour Councillor</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Fry</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Sara Margery</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1874-1958</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Penal reformer,
		  Principal of Somerville College Oxford</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph>
		  <emph altrender="x">Masson Hall</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
