<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-438" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-438</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers on Mining in Scotland, 18th and 19th
			 centuries</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Sep 19 12:17:51 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-438</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.57; Dc.2.39/1/2; Dc.6.111, ff.106-107; Dk.6.19/1;
		  Dk.7.28/1-7; Gen. 129 (Jameson 9); Gen. 1971/2/7; Gen. 1982/35; Gen.
		  1999/1/162</physloc><unittitle>Papers on Mining in Scotland, 18th and 19th
		  centuries</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1758-1831">1758-1831</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>7 volumes, 3 documents or reports, 4 letters</extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<origination>Raspe, R. E; Dirom, A; Horner, J.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The monks of Newbattle Abbey in Midlothian have been credited with
		  starting the first coal mine in Scotland in the 13th century, and coal fields
		  in the east of Scotland generally - in Fife and Midlothian - were the first to
		  gain importance in the country. Mining was conducted with a scatter of bell
		  pits and with primitive technology, an exception being the workings at Culross
		  in Fife. There, from 1617 the colliery of George Bruce may have been the first
		  to use a wheel mechanism for drainage. With a rise of coal-using industries in
		  the 18th century - lime preparation, glass and vitriol making, and coke-fired
		  ironworks such as that at Carron - the demand for coal increased, and output
		  rose from around 400,000 tons in 1700 to 2,000,000 tons in 1800. Many of the
		  early coal mines were operated by the landed gentry, often on their own
		  estates, but with the rise of iron-making and the building of hot blast
		  furnaces, and the coming of the large coal and iron enterprises, the old estate
		  mines lost their importance.</p> 
		<p>As far as lead workings are concerned, the Romans may first have
		  exploited this mineral in Scotland. Re-discovery of the resource near the
		  village communities of Leadhills in Lanarkshire on the estates of the Earls of
		  Hopetoun and Wanlockhead in Dunfriesshire on the estates of the Dukes of
		  Buccleuch is credited to Matthew Templeton in around 1517. Lead was also worked
		  just west of Tyndrum in Perthshire. The activity was carried out in fits and
		  starts in the 18th and 19th centuries.</p> 
		<p>Gold has also been worked at Tyndrum, and gold and silver at Leadhills
		  and these minerals from the latter have been incorporated into the Scottish
		  regalia. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: 
		<title>Symtoms of a Copper myne</title> in Kirkcudbrightshire, 1758;
		state and history of the Duke of Queensberry's lead mines at Wanlockhead,
		digested into queries and answers, circa 1770; paper on the state of the mines
		in Isla, 1770; journal of the lead mine workings at Tyndrum, Perthshire,
		1775-1779, 1783-1791, with a copy of entries 1771-1787 sent at intervals from
		Tyndrum to Leadhills or Garden, in addition to 'bargain books' recording
		agreements with miners about work and wages, 1762-1772, 1785-1791; report on a
		mineralogical survey of Scottish lead and copper mines by R. E. Raspe addressed
		to the Highland Society, Edinburgh, 1790; letters of Messrs. Bogle and Scott,
		Glasgow, about shipments of lead from Tinwald Downs, Dumfries, 1796-1799;
		letter of A. Dirom about lead and antimony mines at Leadhills, 1799; letter of
		W. Burns on behalf of the Society for Preventing Accidents in Coal Mines, 1816;
		letters of Dr. J. Horner relating to the mines at Leadhills, 1830; and, journal
		of the strata penetrated through in the course of a trial for the purpose of
		discovering a workable stratum of coal on the state of Lt. Gen. Sharpe of
		Hoddom, near Ecclefechan, Dumfriesshire, 1831.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Journals of the lead mine workings, acquired probably 1958, Accession
		  no. E58.23. Mineralogical survey, Accession no. E75.45. Letters, acquired
		  October 1975, Accession no. E75.52.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper and
		Collins Publishers, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show references to mining (Scotland) related
		  material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): papers
		  relating to mining in Scotland, 1592-1664, at La.II.478; Sir George Hay of
		  Kinfauns iron mines, 1621, at La.II.541; and, coal mines in Mull, 18th century,
		  La.II.701. Also, there is a paper by J. Buddle on creeps and thrusts in coal
		  mines, 1841, at (Lyell1) Gen.108 onwards. There are references to lead mining
		  in correspondence between John Barker of Langshaw, Dumfriesshire and B. Wyatt
		  of Foolow, Derbyshire, 1821-1829, at Dk.2.41; and, an account of coal mines in
		  the Newcastle area, 1830, at Gen. 1996/8/4. The bad state of mining and
		  teaching of mining discussed in a letter of T. J. Torrie to Professor R.
		  Jameson, 1832, at Gen. 1996/9/63. There is an invitation from A. McDonald,
		  secretary to the Committee of the Miners of Scotland to J. L. Ludlow to attend
		  a meeting, 1860, at Gen. 1982/35, and material on attempts to find evidence of
		  Roman tin mining in Cornwall, 1882, at Gen. 1425/145.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Coal mines and mining</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Lead mines and mining</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Mineral industries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Raspe</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">R. E.</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dirom</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">A.</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Horner</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">J.</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Wanlockhead (Scotland)</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Leadhills (Scotland)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
