<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-790" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-790</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the F. H. McClintock Probation Studies
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Apr 12 10:16:48 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-790</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS 2581-2588</physloc><unittitle>Records of the F. H.
		  McClintock Probation Studies </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1958-1962">1958-1962</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>7 boxes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>McClintock, Frederick Hemming</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Frederick Hemming McClintock was born in 1926. In 1960 he was
		  Assistant Director of Research at the University of Cambridge, Institute of
		  Criminology. While there he worked on research for the later 
		<title>Crimes of violence: an enquiry by the Cambridge Institute of
		  Criminology into crimes of violence against the person in London</title>
		published by Macmillan in 1963. He became Professor of Criminology at Edinburgh
		University in 1974, a post from which he retired in 1993. He was Dean of the
		Faculty of Law from 1982-1985. McClintock was a council member of the Scottish
		Association for the Care and Resettlement of Offenders (SACRO) and of the
		Scottish Association of Victim Support Schemes (SAVSS), and was a member of the
		Perks Committee on Criminal Statistics. SACRO holds an annual McClintock
		Lecture. Frederick Hemming (Derick) McClintock, Professor Emeritus of
		Criminology, died in Edinburgh on 22 May 1994.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of numerous files and folders of information
		  about: non-indictable assaults; non-indictable wounding; robbery; crimes of
		  violence in the metropolis; young offenders; judicial conferences; the
		  University of Cambridge Advanced Course in Criminology; a Scottish Committee of
		  Criminal Statistics; the Magistrates Association, and its Treatment of
		  Offenders Committee; information on results of probation collected by Van
		  Dulken and McClintock; a typescript copy of 
		<title>Crimes of violence: an enquiry by the Cambridge Institute of
		  Criminology into crimes of violence against the person in London</title>;
		departmental sub-committee minutes; a seminar on long term imprisonment; the
		Prison Officer Association; crime among immigrants; material relating to
		probation; Scottish material; appendices to 
		<title>The dangerous offender</title>; and material relating to 
		<title>Crimes against the person</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material received from Professor F. H. McClintock, Faculty of Law,
		  Edinburgh University, June 1987, Accession no. E87.66.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Obituary. 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 36. 1993-1994.
		p.264. Edinburgh: University of Edinburgh Graduates' Association, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p>Edinburgh University Library (Law Library) holds a copy of 
		<title>Crimes of violence : an enquiry by the Cambridge Institute of
		  Criminology into crimes of violence against the person in London</title>,
		McClintock, F. H. (et al.). at shelfmark KC 1 McC.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Probation</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Criminology</emph> </subject>
		
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Crime analysis</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Youth and violence</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">McClintock</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Frederick Hemming</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1926-1994</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of
		  Criminology</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
