<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-594" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-594</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Karl G&#x00FC;tzlaff (1803-1851) and the Chinese
			 Union </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Nov 29 11:16:14 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-594</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 9</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Karl G&#x00FC;tzlaff
		  (1803-1851) and the Chinese Union </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1840-1849">[ca. 1844-1849]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 file (107 pp)</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>G&#x00FC;tzlaff, Karl Friedrich August </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="chi">Chinese.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Karl Friedrich August G&#x00FC;tzlaff, pioneer Protestant missionary
		  in China, was born in Pomerania, Germany in 1803. He trained in a mission
		  institute in Berlin and, having met Robert Morrison in London, began to learn
		  Chinese with a view to working amongst the Chinese people. He spent some years
		  as a missionary in Java and Thailand working with Chinese expatriates and he
		  and his wife translated the bible into Siamese. During these years
		  G&#x00FC;tzlaff also acquired some medical skill and between 1831 and 1833 he
		  made three trips along the Chinese coast acting as a medical practitioner and
		  interpreter. He finally secured entry into mainland China as a free-lance
		  missionary in 1833, by which time his wife had died. After some disputes with
		  the authorities he took a job as a Chinese language secretary in the British
		  diplomatic services but continued to do his missionary work. G&#x00FC;tzlaff
		  was convinced that the way to penetrate China was through Chinese converts, not
		  foreign missionaries. He devoted himself to recruiting and training Chinese
		  evangelists who would travel throughout the provinces preaching and
		  distributing tracts. He supported the formation of a largely Chinese led
		  evangelisation society, the Chinese Union, and appeared to achieve some success
		  with reports of thousands of converts during the 1840s. G&#x00FC;tzlaff ensured
		  that accounts of his activities were published in the West where he received an
		  enthusiastic reception during visits to raise funds. It was while he was in
		  Europe in 1848 that missionaries in Hong Kong accused G&#x00FC;tzlaff of
		  exaggerating his success and his evangelists of falsifying figures and having a
		  poor grasp of basic Christian doctrine. G&#x00FC;tzlaff returned to China but
		  the criticisms and his own ill health led to the collapse of the Union shortly
		  before he died in 1851. Accused by many of being a fanatic and eccentric, not
		  least because he insisted on wearing Chinese dress, G&#x00FC;tzlaff has also
		  been criticised in China for his role in the Nanking Treaty (1842). He was,
		  however, a pioneer in many senses. He published several books and articles on
		  Chinese history and culture and translated much of the New Testament into
		  Chinese. Although the Union collapsed it was the forerunner of the Chinese
		  Evangelisation Society which sent Hudson Taylor to China and Hudson Taylor
		  himself called G&#x00FC;tzlaff 'the grandfather of the China Inland
		  Mission.'</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of photocopies of material describing the work
		  of the Chinese Union and defending it against criticism, including: motto,
		  constitution, rules and regulations of the Chinese Union; names of Chinese
		  members and preachers and statistics relating to their activities (1849); list
		  of books published by the Union; lists and numbers of baptised (1844-1849);
		  lists of places to which preachers had been sent; finances of the Union
		  (1845-49); notes by G&#x00FC;tzlaff on China, Korea, Japan, Manchuria,
		  Mongolia, Sougaria, Tibet and Cochin-China; valedictory remarks to Theo Hamberg
		  (1849) referring to the philosophy behind and work of the Union and further
		  explanations 'to avoid some misunderstanding'; essay 
		<title>Requirements for the Foreign Preachers of the Gospel who Wish to
		  Combine Their Efforts with the Associations Now Forming for the Conversion of
		  Eastern Asia</title>; and a response to criticisms of the Union, particularly
		those by James Legge. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged as described in the Scope and Content
		  section. The pages were numbered and listed by Ralph Covell in 1992.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World by Dr A. J. Broomhall.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Anderson, Gerald (ed.). 
		<title>Biographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New York:
		Simon and Schuster Macmillan, 1998. (2) The Illuminated Lantern web site, (3)
		Christianity Today web site.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Herman Schlyter's 
		<title>Der China-Missionar Karl G&#x00FC;tzlaff und Seine
		  Heimatbasis</title> (Lund : CWK Gleerup, 1976) has a comprehensive list of
		sources. The archives of the China Inland Mission at the School of Oriental and
		African Studies, London, and Special Collections at the University of
		Birmingham hold material relating to G&#x00FC;tzlaff.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">G&#x00FC;tzlaff</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Karl
		  Friedrich August</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1803-1851</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Chinese Union</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">China</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
