<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-253" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-253</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Sir William Jardine (1800-1874)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jul 17 11:56:40 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-253</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.6.20-21</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Sir William Jardine
		  (1800-1874)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1820-1869">[ca. 1828-1861]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box, 1 volume of printed matter bound in. </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>William Jardine was born in Edinburgh on 23 February 1800. He was the
		  eldest son of Sir Alexander Jardine, 6th Baronet, of Applegarth, Dumfriesshire.
		  William Jardine was educated at home and then in York, and then he studied at
		  Edinburgh University taking literary and medical classes as well as natural
		  history and geology. In 1820, he succeeded his father as 7th Baronet. Sir
		  William Jardine was particularly devoted to the study of ornithology, and in
		  addition to his wide ornithological knowledge he was also knowledgeable about
		  many orders of vertebrates. His publications include 
		<title>The natural history of humming-birds</title> (1833), 
		<title>The natural history of fishes of the perch family</title> (1835), 
		<title>The natural history of the Nectariniadae, or sun-birds</title>
		(1843), 
		<title>Memoirs of Hugh Edwin Strickland, M.A.</title> (1858), and 
		<title>The natural history of Selborne: with observations on various
		  parts of nature, and the naturalist's calendar</title> (1836). In 1836, Jardine
		was President of the Berwickshire Naturalists' Club, and he was for some years
		a joint editor of the 
		<title>Edinburgh Philosophical Journal</title>. In 1860 he participated
		in the Royal Commission on Salmon Fisheries of England and Wales. Sir William
		Jardine died at Sandown on the Isle of Wight on 21 November 1874.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers consist of correspondence about natural history, and
		  journals, from around 1828 to 1861. More particularly there is: a journal of a
		  visit to Ireland in the form of letters from Jardine to his wife, Dk.6.20/315;
		  draft letters and replies on a variety of subjects; note; and, volume of
		  offprints on natural history.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Accession no. E58.10.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.10. Howard-Kenneth.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Sir William Jardine related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): letters to unnamed
		  correspondents; and, mention in a communication. In addition, the UK National
		  Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission,
		  notes: correspondence and papers, 1821-48, at the National Museums of Scotland,
		  Chambers Street NRA 24275 Jardine; correspondence and papers, 1826-59, at the
		  National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD472 NRA 34337 Jardine; letter book, 1852,
		  at the Natural History Museum, Ref. L MSS JAR (see Catalogue of MSS...Natural
		  History Museum, 1995); 1834-37: letters to Leonard Blomefield, 1834-37, Bath
		  Royal Literary and Scientific Institution, Ref. Jenyns Corresp NRA 41808
		  Blomefield; letters, 1838-71, to Thomas Eyton, at the American Philosophical
		  Society Library NRA 9728 American Philosophic; letters, 1830-51, to Sir William
		  Hooker, at the Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, Library and Archives; correspondence
		  with Prideaux Selby, 1825-54, at Cambridge University, Department of Zoology;
		  1827-31: letters to William Swainson, Linnean Society of London, Ref. Swainson
		  NRA 22111 Swainson; and, miscellaneous letters, 1829-52, at the National
		  Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MS 10997.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Natural history</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ornithology</emph> </subject>
		
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Jardine</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1800-1874</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">7th Baronet Naturalist </emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
