<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-237" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-237</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor Sir Robert Christison
			 (1797-1882)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Jun 04 16:46:54 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-237</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.3.108; Dc.3.110; Dk.4.56-57</physloc><unittitle>Papers of
		  Professor Sir Robert Christison (1797-1882)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1830-1879">1830s-1870s</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes, 2 notebooks (parts of). </extent> </physdesc>
		
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Robert Christison was born in Edinburgh on 18 July 1797. He was
		  educated at the Royal High School and then at Edinburgh University where he
		  followed the Arts course. Christison chose a medical career however and
		  graduated from Edinburgh in 1819, having submitted a thesis for the degree of
		  M.D., entitled 
		<title>Dissertatio medica inauguralis, de febre continua, quae nuper in
		  hac urbe epidemica fuit ...</title> on fever. This was completed while he was a
		resident medical assistant in the Royal Infirmary, 1817 to 1820. A brief period
		of study in London followed, at St. Bartholomew's Hospital, and then he went to
		Paris where he studied analytical chemistry and laid the foundations for his
		future reputation as a toxicologist. On his return to Edinburgh in 1821, he
		became involved right away in the contest for the Chair of Medical
		Jurisprudence at Edinburgh University. Christison was appointed to the
		Professorship in 1822, still in his early twenties. He then set about giving a
		scientific basis to medical jurisprudence, particularly toxicology. Christison
		learned German in order to look at his field in that language, and soon became
		known as a logical and accurate lecturer and medical witness. In his capacity
		as medical adviser to the Crown in Scotland, from 1829 to 1866, he acted as
		medical witness in nearly every prominent case in Scotland, including the trial
		of Burke and Hare (who had murdered to meet the growing demands of anatomists
		for bodies) and the trial of Madeleine Smith (a murder trial famous for its
		not-proven verdict). Christison drew up instructions for the examination of
		dead bodies for legal purposes and these became the accepted guide at the time.
		He also ascertained accurately the distinctions between signs of injuries
		inflicted before and after death, and investigated the detection and treatment
		of oxalic acid, arsenic, lead, opium and hemlock poisoning. In 1827 he was
		appointed physician to the Infirmary, and then in 1832 he resigned his Chair of
		Medical Jurisprudence and was appointed to the Chair of Materia Medica and
		Therapeutics which he held until 1877. This he had held along with the Chair of
		Clinical Medicine until 1855. In addition to his work on poisons, Christison
		investigated Bright's disease, and fevers, and he published a large number of
		papers on chemistry, medical jurisprudence, materia medica, medicine, and
		botany. Included among his publications were 
		<title>A treatise on poisons, in relation to medical jurisprudence,
		  physiology, and the practice of physic</title> (1829), 
		<title>On granular degeneration of the kidneys, and its connection with
		  dropsy, inflammations, and other diseases</title> (1839), and 
		<title>A dispensatory, or commentary on the pharmacopoeias of Great
		  Britain: comprising the natural history, description, chemistry, pharmacy,
		  actions, uses, and doses of the articles of the materia medica</title> (1842).
		He experimented with the Calabar bean from West Africa and its principal active
		ingredient, eserine, which is still one of the most important drugs in
		pharmacology. In 1848, Christison was appointed Physician in Ordinary to the
		Queen in Scotland, and in 1871 he became a Baronet. He was elected twice as
		President of the Royal College of Physicians, 1839, and 1848, and was also
		President of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, 1868-1873. Professor Sir Robert
		Christison died on 23 January 1882.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Abstracts from his lectures on materia medica, 1834-35, at Dc.3.108;
		  extracts from his lectures on clinical medicine, at Dc.3.110; notes and
		  lectures on materia medica and dietetics, c.1832-1874, at Dk.4.56; lectures on
		  medical jurisprudence delivered at EU, c.1830, at Dk.4.57. The subjects covered
		  by the lectures and notes include: metals, iron, lead, mercury, fever,
		  introduction to vegetable materia medica, ipecacuan, ranunculaceae, solanaceae
		  and atropaceae, opium, alkalis of earths, acids, pharmacopoeias, actions of
		  medicines, and mineral waters. There is also material on rape, signs of
		  pregnancy, procuring abortion, death from external injuries, infanticide,
		  concealment of pregnancy, medical reports and evidence, poisons, arsenic,
		  narcotics, asphyxia, hanging, drowning, burning, death from cold, lightning,
		  and starvation.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Stephen, Leslie, and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>The dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.4.
		Chamber-Craigie. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) 
		<title>University of Edinburgh Journal</title>. Vol.30. No.4. December
		1982. p.286. Edinburgh: The University of Edinburgh Graduates Association,
		1982. (3) 
		<title>University of Edinburgh Journal</title>. Vol.31. No.1. June 1983.
		pp.52-54. Edinburgh: The University of Edinburgh Graduates Association,
		1983.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to other Christison related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): letters and extracts from
		  letters; notes of lectures on Materia Medica at De.1-.7-8; testimonial; and
		  notices etc. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives notes: letters
		  and lectures at the Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh; correspondence at
		  the National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division; correspondence at
		  St.Andrews University Library; letters at Oxford University's Bodleian Library,
		  Special Collections and Western Manuscripts; and, miscellaneous letters at the
		  British Library, Manuscript Collection. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Medical jurisprudence</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Toxicologists</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Toxicology</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Christison</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1797-1882</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Toxicologist</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
