<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-221" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-221</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor Archibald H. Campbell
			 (1902-1989)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Nov 26 09:46:17 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-221</unitid> 
		<physloc>E89.60</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor Archibald H.
		  Campbell (1902-1989)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>81 box-files, 3 large photograph albums, miscellaneous
		  printed items (circa 9 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Archibald Hunter Campbell was born 21 May 1902 in Edinburgh. He was
		  educated at George Watson's College in the city, at Edinburgh University, and
		  then at University College, Oxford. He won a Prize fellowship at All Souls
		  College, Oxford, and was called to the English Bar. He was Barrister at Law of
		  Lincoln's Inn. In 1935 he was appointed Barber Professor of Jurisprudence at
		  Birmingham University. During the Second World War he was summoned into service
		  at Bletchley Park where he was a codebreaker, first of Italian codes, then of
		  Japanese. After the war he returned to Edinburgh and to the University's Regius
		  Chair of Public Law and the Law of Nature and the Nations which he held from
		  1945 to 1972. He was Dean of the Faculty of Law, 1958-64. He was also an
		  Emeritus Fellow of All Souls College. His scholarly work included notable
		  papers on Fascism and Legality, on Obligation and Obedience to Law, and on the
		  structures and sources of Stair's 
		<title>Institutions</title>. The friends of his youth included the poets
		Auden and Isherwood. Professor Archibald Hunter Campbell died in Edinburgh 8
		June 1989.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of personal correspondence from circa 1921
		  and Edinburgh University notes and material from circa 1919. There is also a
		  large amount of printed law journals and journal offprints. There are
		  postcards, Christmas cards, framed photographs, loose photographs, photograph
		  albums, and diploma cylinders. There are also newspapers and news-cuttings.
		  Much of the material is unsorted. One particular filing box contains letters of
		  W. H. Auden, Stephen Spender, and Humphrey Carpenter, along with many articles
		  and news-cuttings. Several items either handwritten or in typescript from Auden
		  to Campbell in Edinburgh over the period 1928 to 1960.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Professor A. H. Campbell's material acquired August 1989, Accession
		  no. E89.60. His library was presented to Edinburgh University Library in
		  1984.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Obituaries. Prof. Archibald Campbell. Winds of change
		  in Scottish legal education. 
		<title>The Times</title>. London: The Times, 8 June 1989. (2) 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol.13. 1944-1945. p71.
		Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1945. (3) 
		<title>Who's who 1987</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1987.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Campbell's library was presented to Edinburgh University Library and
		  it includes first editions, often with presentation inscriptions, of works by
		  Spender and Auden. Shelfmarks include SC 5076-SC 5339 and JA 3936-JA 3951. </p>
		
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Law</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Christmas cards</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="surname">Campbell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Archibald Hunter</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1902-1989</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Auden</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Wystan Hugh</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1907-1973</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Poet </emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Spender</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Stephen Harold</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1909-1995</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Poet and Critic</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Carpenter</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Humphrey </emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1946
		  </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Author, Broadcaster, Musician</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
