<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-168" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-168</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of John Rennie (1761-1821)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Dec 03 12:05:09 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-168</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 835; La.II.427; Dc.4.101-103
		  Rennie</physloc><unittitle>Papers of John Rennie (1761-1821)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1791-1817">1791-1817</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 45 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Rennie, John; Rennie, Sir John</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John Rennie was born at Phantassie, near East Linton, East Lothian, on
		  7 June 1761. He was the son of a farmer but showed an interest in mechanics
		  from an early age, often spending time in the workshop of Andrew Meikle
		  (1719-1811) the millwright and inventor of the threshing-machine. He was
		  educated at a local school in Prestonkirk and then in Dunbar, and studied at
		  Edinburgh University until 1783. After his education, Rennie worked as a
		  millwright and established his own business. In 1784 he went to England,
		  visiting James Watt in Staffordshire, and then took charge of the works at
		  Albion Flour Mills in Blackfriars, London, for which Boulton and Watt were
		  building a steam-engine. In 1791 he established himself as a mechanical
		  engineer, setting up in business in Blackfriars. Rennie then directed himself
		  towards canal construction, carrying out work on the Kennet and Avon Canal, the
		  Rochdale Canal, the Lancaster Canal, and the Royal Canal of Ireland. He was
		  also involved in the extensive drainage operations in the Lincolnshire Fens,
		  the construction of the London docks, the East and West India Docks, Holyhead
		  harbour, Hull docks, Ramsgate harbour, and the dockyards at Sheerness and
		  Chatham. Rennie also worked on the construction of bridges and was involved
		  with bridges in Kelso and Musselburgh in Scotland, and the former was his
		  blueprint for Waterloo Bridge. He also designed London Bridge (completed after
		  his death) and Southwark Bridge. Rennie gave advice during the construction of
		  Bell Rock Lighthouse, built between 1807 and 1810 (off the Angus coast near
		  Arbroath). His most imaginative and enduring work is probably the colossal
		  breakwater at Plymouth, constructed across the Sound in deep water. Rennie had
		  been elected a Fellow of the Royal Society on 29 March 1798. John Rennie died
		  on 4 October 1821, and was buried in St. Paul's Cathedral.</p> 
		<p>Rennie's second son, Sir John Rennie (1794-1874) was born in London.
		  He acquired his engineering skills in his father's firm and assisted in the
		  building of Southwark Bridge. He worked in partnership with his brother, George
		  Rennie. His most important undertaking was the building of London Bridge,
		  opened in 1831. Rennie was knighted the same year. Like his father, he carried
		  out work for the Admiralty, and also in the Lincolnshire Fens. He and his
		  brother also conducted some early railway work, and in 1852 he laid out a
		  system of railways for Sweden for which he received the Swedish Order of
		  Gustavus Vasa (riddare av Kungl. Vasaordern). </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Within the collection there are 19 letters from Rennie to various
		  correspondents including 11 to Firmin de Tastet and Company, 1791-1817, at
		  La.II.427. At La.III.427 (Rennie, 12-14) there are 3 letters about the proposed
		  Glasgow and Saltcoats Canal, 1803. There are also 2 letters to Jackson Mason
		  about the Wigan Petition, the Kennet and Avon Canal, 12 February and 24
		  September 1794. The collection at Gen. 835 includes 5 letters to Thomas
		  Townshend about engineering projects, 1802-1804, namely canal constructions in
		  Dublin, and 4 other letters about engineering projects, 1813-1815. There is
		  also a letter to Robert Swan about engineering dated 13 April 1814. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letters about engineering projects in Dublin, acquired 1966, Accession
		  no. E66.16. Letters to Townshend acquired 1959, Accession no. E59.27.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.16. Pocock-Robins.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show references to the papers of John Rennie's
		  second son, Sir John Rennie (1794-1874), who was also a civil engineer (check
		  the Indexes for more details): within the Laing Collection at La.II.427,
		  letters of Rennie the younger to correspondents between 1822-1843 and some
		  undated; and, letters to Thomas Townshend, 1823 and 1824, at Gen. 835.</p> 
		<p>Otherwise, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the
		  Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes this material relating to John Rennie
		  the elder: papers, drawings and reports, c.1772-1821, Institution of Civil
		  Engineers, NRA 16921 Civil Engineers; c1783-1821: correspondence, notebooks and
		  accounts, c.1783-1821, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref.
		  MSS 19771-968, and papers relating to Whiteadder Bridge, 1800-1801, Ref. MS
		  19967, and miscellaneous letters, 1791-1821, Ref. MS 2909; correspondence and
		  papers relating to Boston Bridge, 1799-1815, Lincolnshire Archives, NRA 11483
		  Boston borough, and reports and papers relating to Lincolnshire River
		  Authority, Ref. LRA, 2-3, 5 LRA NRA 9935 Lincolnshire River; correspondence and
		  papers relating to Clyde Harbour, 1798-1809, Glasgow City Archives, Ref.
		  3/11-29 NRA 13871 Clyde Port; reports on Fen drainage, 1814, Cambridgeshire
		  County Record Office, Huntingdon, Ref. Acc 235 NRA 9006 Cambs RO, Hunts; ms
		  plans, British Waterways Archive, see British Archives (3rd ed); report on the
		  Kennet and Avon Canal, 1795, Bath and North East Somerset Record Office; report
		  on the Leek Canal, c.1800, Staffordshire and Stoke-on-Trent Archive Service,
		  Staffordshire Record Office; specification for rebuilding London Bridge, 1823,
		  London University Library, Ref. MS 158; report on Northfleet New Arsenal, 1807,
		  British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 27884 and letter and
		  reports to Viscounts Melville, 1810-1819, Ref. Add MS 41345; correspondence and
		  reports on Rochester Bridge, Rochester Bridge Trust, NRA 10539 Rochester
		  Bridge; MS opinion on the Shardlow and Nottingham Canal, 1793, Birmingham
		  University Information Services, Special Collections Department, Ref. Canal
		  collection NRA 13208 Midlands canals; reports on Southampton Docks, Southampton
		  Archives Office, Ref. D/PM NRA 20055 Page; report and correspondence relating
		  to Tamar Navigation Canal, 1795-1797, Devon Record Office, Ref. W1258 T1258M
		  NRA 9813 Russell; correspondence with Boulton family, Birmingham City Archives,
		  Ref. Matthew Boulton Papers NRA 9497 Boulton, and letters to Boulton and Watt,
		  1784-1820, Ref. Box 23 NRA 14609 Boulton &amp;amp; Watt, and also letters to
		  James Watt, 1792-1794, Ref. James Watt Papers NRA 22549 Watt; letters to Sir
		  Roger Newdigate, 1778-1807, Warwickshire County Record Office, Ref. CR
		  136/B1310-97 NRA 26325 Newdegate; letters (10) to Samuel Whitbread,
		  Bedfordshire and Luton Archives and Record Service, Ref. W NRA 1123 Whitbread;
		  and, letters, 1795-1804, Public Record Office, Ref. RAIL1008/87 NRA 28797 PRO
		  railway.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Canals</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Civil engineers</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Civil engineering</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Rennie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1794-1874</emph>
		  <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Civil
		  Engineer</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Rennie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1761-1821</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Civil Engineer</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Townshend</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl
		  1794-1843</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Engineer</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
