<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-429" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-429</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Material relating to Andrew Melville
			 (1545-1622)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Aug 28 16:19:11 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-429</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.4.68, f.141; Dc.5.50/2, p.3; Dc.6.45; Dc.8.5; De.1.12/10, 11,
		  13-14; De.2.63; Df.7.72; JA 3817</physloc><unittitle>Material relating to
		  Andrew Melville (1545-1622)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1574-1613">1574-1613</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>7 poems or notes or miscellaneous, 3 manuscript
		  volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The scholar and reformer Andrew Melville was born at Baldovie in Angus
		  on 1 August 1545. He was educated in Montrose and then studied at St. Mary's
		  College, St. Andrews, from 1559, and in Paris from 1564 and Poitiers from 1566.
		  Now versed in Latin, Greek, and law, he went to Geneva where he was appointed
		  to the Chair of Humanity by Theodore de Beze (1519-1605), Calvin's successor.
		  While in Switzerland he published his first volume of Latin verse 
		<title>Carmen Mosis</title>, Basel (1573). On his return to Scotland in
		1574 he found that his reputation had gone before him, and such had been his
		involvement in Geneva among the reformation movement he was made Principal of
		Glasgow University. Melville then set about revising and enlarging the
		curriculum and the University was re-established with a new charter - Nova
		Erectio - in 1577. Earlier, in 1575 he assisted in the formation of a new
		constitution for King's College, Aberdeen. In 1580 he became Principal of St.
		Mary's College (or New College), St. Andrews. Melville was an active leader in
		ecclesiastical affairs and was opposed to episcopacy and absolute authority. He
		was Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland several times,
		and was involved in the publication of the 
		<title>Second book of discipline</title> (1578) which set the shape of
		Presbyterian government for the Church in Scotland. Because he believed in the
		separation of Church and State with God above both &quot;kingdoms&quot;,
		Melville was always on a collision course with King James VI and I, and lived
		under the threat of imprisonment. He was in every way, Knox's successor. In
		1606 he attended the Hampton Court Conference out of which came the proposal
		for the King James Version of the Bible. While in England he ridiculed Church
		of England worship and was sent to the Tower of London. He was released in 1611
		and then went into exile and became Professor of Biblical Theology at the
		University of Sedan, in France. Andrew Melville died at Sedan in 1622.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: Latin verses 
		<title>Melvinus ad H. Rollocum</title>; 
		<title>Praefatio Magistri Andreae Melvini in poema de gestis Scotorum ad
		  Henricum Principem</title>; Latin poems in the hand of Melville written in fly
		leaves of 
		<title>Jvlii Caesaris Scaligeri Poemata</title>; 
		<title>Epitaphium Alexandri Arbuthneti</title>; 
		<title>Epitaphium D. Thomas Smetonii</title> on fly leaf; letter to D.
		Hume of Godscroft about 
		<title>De unione insulae Britannicae tractatus</title>; 
		<title>Epistolae Londino e turri carceris ad Jacobum Melvinum Novocastri
		  exulentem scriptae, cum ejusdem Jacobi nonullis</title>; and, 
		<title>A short confutation of Dr. Downames apologetick sermon maid for
		  the dignitie of the episcopall office</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>28 August 2002, item noted as at De.2.63 was not found.</p> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994. (2) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 13.
		Masquerier-Myles. London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Melville related material
		  in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details) and include: 
		<title>Commentarius in divinam Pauli epistolam ad Romanos auctore Andrea
		  melvino Scoto</title>, 1601, and a translation and notes on 
		<title>Odyssey</title> at La.III.94; transcript of 
		<title>Epistolae Londino e turri carceris ad Jacobum Melvinum Novocastri
		  exulentem scriptae, cum ejusdem Jacobi nonullis</title>, at La.III.373, and
		La.III.374; an acknowledgement signed by Melville while Professor at Sedan,
		1612, at La.II.148; and a letter, 1873, about 
		<title>Anti-tami-cami-categoria</title>, at La.IV.17. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Melville</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Andrew</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1545-1611
		  </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Reformer, Theologian, Writer</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">16th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">17th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
