<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-245" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-245</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures and Correspondence of Sir Herbert J. C. Grierson
			 (1866-1960)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Jun 22 10:41:11 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-245</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS 2645-2646; MSS 2694-2695; Gen. 1948/9/1-13; Gen. 2002/4-6;
		  Gen. 2096-2103D; Dk.3.35; E97.40</physloc><unittitle>Lectures and
		  Correspondence of Sir Herbert J. C. Grierson (1866-1960)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>18 volumes, circa 21 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Grierson, Sir Herbert John Clifford; Caird, Janet H.; Low,
		  Margaret; Robbie, Herbert James Liddell; Stuart, M. M. Wedderburn</origination>
		
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Herbert John Clifford Grierson was born in 1866 in Shetland. He
		  studied at Aberdeen University (King's College) and was awarded the degree of
		  MA. He also studied at Christ Church, Oxford. In 1894, Grierson was appointed
		  Chalmers Professor of English at Aberdeen University, and in 1915 he was
		  elected Professor of Rhetoric and English Literature. His publications include 
		<title>The first half of the sevententh century (Periods of European
		  literature)</title> (1906), 
		<title>The poems of John Donne edited from the old editions and numerous
		  manuscripts, with introductions and commentary</title> (1912), and 
		<title>Metaphysical lyrics and poems of the seventeenth century: Donne to
		  Butler</title> (1921). In addition, his twelve volume edition of 
		<title>The letters of Sir Walter Scott</title> (1932-1937) was said to be
		'one of the monuments of 20th-century erudition'. Grierson also maintained an
		interest in modern Scottish poetry. Professor Herbert J. C. Grierson retired in
		1935 and was knighted in 1936. He was Rector of Edinburgh University from 1936
		to 1939, and was the first holder of a Chair there to be elected by the student
		body as Rector. He died on 19 February 1960.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The lectures of Sir Herbert J. C. Grierson on English literature were
		  taken down 1916-1919; 1922-1925, 1925-1926 and 1934-1935. The lectures include
		  poetry, Shakespeare, and seventeenth century literature generally. There are
		  various letters to William Fraser Mitchell between 1919 and 1956 at Gen.
		  1948/9/1-13, and to Professor O. L. Richmond (1881-1977), 1924-1955. There is
		  also a list of contributors to a fund commemorating Grierson's retirement in
		  1935 and his seventieth birthday in 1936, at Dk.3.35.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Notes of Grierson's lectures were acquired from: Miss M.M.Wedderburn,
		  Edinburgh, 21 August 1979, Accession no. E79.53; Mrs. E.B.Robbie, Edinburgh,
		  1976, Accession no. E76.28; Dr. W.R.Aitken, Dunblane, 4 March 1986, Accession
		  no. E.86.11; and, Mrs. Janet H. Caird, Inverness, 22 April 1988, Accession no.
		  E88.29. Letters to Richmond were purchased in July 1997, Accession E97.40. </p>
		
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Rice, D. Talbot. 
		<title>The university portraits</title>. Edinburgh: The University Press,
		1957. (2) 
		<title>Who was who 1951-1960. A companion to Who's who ...</title>
		London: Adam and Charles Black, 1961.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to other letters to or from
		  Grierson (check the Indexes for more details): to Charles Sarolea (1870-1953);
		  from J. Masefield; and, from Augustus Muir. In addition, the UK National
		  Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission,
		  notes: correspondence and papers at the National Library of Scotland,
		  Manuscripts Division, with Reference MSS 9320-49, Ch 8482-85, letters with
		  Reference Acc 5001 5109 NRA 29131 MacIver, and letters to DN Smith, Reference
		  MS 19604; correspondence and papers relating to John Donne at Oxford
		  University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western Manuscripts,
		  Reference MSS Eng poet e 92-93, Eng lett d 363; correspondence with Sir Sydney
		  Cockerell, at British Library, Manuscript Collections, Reference Add MS 52717;
		  correspondence and miscellaneous papers at Aberdeen University, Special
		  Libraries and Archives, NRA 22901 Grierson; and, letters to G.H.W. Rylands, at
		  Cambridge University, King's College Archive Centre, Reference Rylands
		  Papers/3/181 NRA 42463 Rylands.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Grierson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Herbert J. C.</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1866-1960</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Rhetoric and English Literature</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Caird</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Janet H.</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Low</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Margaret</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Robbie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Herbert James Liddell</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Stuart</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">M. M. Wedderburn</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
