<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-87"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-87</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of
			 Professor Robert Wallace (1853-1939) </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-87</unitid>
		
		<physloc>Gen. 554-555; Gen.867F</physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Professor Robert Wallace
		  (1853-1939) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1914-1920">circa 1914-1920 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>1 volume; 2
		  small bundles. </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Robert Wallace was born into a farming family at Wallace Hall,
		  Glencairn, Dumfries and Galloway, on 24 June 1853. He was educated at Tynron
		  School and Hutton Academy. He studied at Edinburgh University and was awarded
		  the degree of M.A. in December 1920, and thereafter managed farms for his
		  father and farmed for himself and his brother. He was interested in every
		  aspect of farm livestock recognising the importance of scientific agriculture,
		  and throughout his career he sought to improve the standard of agriculture in
		  Britain and the Commonwealth. In 1882 he was appointed Professor of Agriculture
		  at the Royal Agricultural College in Cirencester and then in 1885 he returned
		  to Edinburgh University as Professor of Agriculture and Rural Economy. In the
		  early years of his office a course in Forestry was added to the curriculum for
		  students, then a course in Agricultural Entomology, and in 1892 and an Ordinary
		  B.Sc. was instituted. He also established the Edinburgh Incorporated School of
		  Agriculture and this led to the official recognition of Edinburgh by the then
		  Board of Agriculture as an agricultural teaching centre. Later on, the East of
		  Scotland College of Agriculture, founded in 1907, merged with the University
		  School to form the basis of the modern School of Agriculture. Wallace occupied
		  the Chair of Agriculture and Rural Economy until 1922. In that year too, an
		  Honours degree in Agriculture was instituted. He was also the Garton Lecturer
		  in Colonial and Indian Agriculture, 1900-1922. In the pursuit of his study and
		  interests, he travelled to Canada, Australia, New Zealand, India, Southern
		  Africa and Malaysia, as well as the United States of America, Egypt, Greece,
		  Mexico, and Japan. Towards the end of his career, between 1914 and 1917,
		  Wallace engaged in correspondence with Woodrow Wilson, President of the USA.
		  The subject of his concern was the treatment of prisoners and hostages in
		  Germany. His publications include 
		<title>Farm live stock of Great Britain </title> (1889), 
		<title>The rural economy and agriculture of Australia and New Zealand
		  </title> (1891), 
		<title>Argentine shows and live stock </title> (1904), and, 
		<title>Heather and moor burning for grouse and sheep </title> (1917).
		Professor Robert Wallace died on 17 January 1939. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>The papers of Professor Wallace include a collection of letters to
		  President Wilson of the United States by Wallace, at shelfmark Gen. 867F. These
		  are contained in a binding along with numerous selected newspaper cuttings of
		  the period. Included are letters of acknowledgement sent by Private Secretaries
		  instructed from the White House. At shelfmark Gen. 554-555 are bundles of notes
		  both manuscript and typescript, leaflets, pamphlets, and cuttings on
		  agriculture between 1900 and 1920. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <odd encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.1"> 
		<note encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.6.1./marc 500"> 
		  <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
			 (1) 
		  <title>The university portraits </title>, Second series, compiled by
		  John H. Burnett [et al.], Edinburgh: Eyre &amp;amp; Spottiswoode Ltd., 1986.
		  (2) 
		  <title>Who was who </title>, Vol.3. 1929-1940, 2nd edition (London:
		  Adam and Charles Black, 1967). (3) Obituary notices, 
		  <title>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Edinburgh </title>, Vol.59.
		  1938-1939, pp.284-285 (Edinburgh: Neill and Co., 1940). </p> 
		</note> 
	 </odd> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Wallace</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1853-1939</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Wilson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Thomas
		  Woodrow</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1856-1924</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Wilson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Woodrow</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1856-1924</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh
		  University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh School
		  of Agriculture</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Agriculture</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>An important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held
		  at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to
		  the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts shows a reference to a letter from Professor
		  Wallace to Sir C. J. Pearson at Gen. 756, no.285. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
