<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-778" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-778</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers relating to Robert Baillie
			 (1599-1662)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Mar 2 10:44:08 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-778</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS BAILL. 1-5</physloc><unittitle>Papers relating to Robert
		  Baillie (1599-1662)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1627-1710">1627-1710</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 530 leaves, 11 volumes, miscellaneous. </extent>
		  <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Baillie, Robert</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Robert Baillie was born in Glasgow in 1599. He studied at Glasgow
		  University acquiring an M.A., and then studied theology. He was ordained by
		  Archbishop Law of Glasgow, and in around 1622 he became a Regent (Professor) of
		  Philosophy at Glasgow University. Although his had been an Episcopal ordination
		  and he had been in favour of episcopacy, he became a Minister of the Parish of
		  Kilwinning, Ayrshire, within the Church of Scotland. Baillie had been opposed
		  to the 1637 Book of Common Prayer and by the late 1630s, and the beginning of
		  the civil war, he was being drawn into the covenanting side. He was a member of
		  the 1638 General Assembly. In 1639 he became Chaplain to Lord Eglinton's
		  regiment and was with the Covenanter army under Leslie. In 1642 he was
		  appointed Professor of Divinity at Glasgow University. Baillie attended the
		  Westminster Assembly from 1643 and in 1649 he went to the Netherlands with
		  others to persuade Charles II to accept the Covenant and the Crown. In 1661 he
		  was appointed Principal of Glasgow University. Robert Baillie died in July
		  1662. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: a conference by letters with a
		  Canterburian Minister anent the Arminian tenet of the Saint's apostasie; Duorum
		  studiosorum de geniculatione ... collatio; A peaceable consideration of a paper
		  against kneeling; Commentariolus de praecipius Pontificorum armoribus;
		  Tractatus de forma et causa justificationis; Oratio in Academia Glasguensis
		  comitiis habita a R.B. anno 1627; Oratio in laudem linguae Hebraeae in Academia
		  comitiis ... 1629; and, My brothers books . There is also a list of Baillie's
		  books at Carnbrue, 22 July 1708, a list of books wanting, a list of books lent,
		  Carnbrue, 26 August 1710. The collection includes: letters and journals,
		  1637-1662, and copies 1710 and 1728, and undated; and, sermons from January
		  1648 to January 1652. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 1. Abbadie-Beadon.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) Keay, Julia. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encylopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes, Special Collections Division, Edinburgh University
		  Library, George Square show various references to Baillie related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): mention of Baillie in a letter of J.
		  Smith, Minister of Avoch, to W. Laing, Bookseller, 15 March 1820, at La.IV.17;
		  letter of Madame Racchia replying to enquiries by D. Laing about a portrait,
		  papers etc., of Baillie, in 1846, at La.IV (Douglas); mention of Baillie in
		  letters from T. Miller D.D. Minister of Cumnock, to D. Laing, 1817 and 1818, at
		  La.IV.17; mention in letters of J. S. Reid to D. Laing, 1836-1851, at La.IV.17;
		  mention in letters of W. Duncan to D. Laing, 1841, at La.IV.17; and, mention in
		  a letter of J. Richardson to D. Laing, 1842, at La.IV.17.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters and journals (3 volumes)
		  relating to affairs in Scotland, 1637-1662, (18th century transcript), Glasgow
		  University Library, Special Collections Department, Ref. MS Gen 1239-41;
		  correspondence with William Spang (copies), 1637-1643, National Library of
		  Scotland, Ref. MS 1908, and correspondence and sermons, 1637-1639, Ref. Adv MSS
		  20 6 4, 32 3 12.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Sermons</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Church history</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Baillie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1599-1662</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Presbyterian
		  Minister Principal of Glasgow University</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">17th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
