<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-218" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-218</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection relating to Eric Henry Liddell
			 (1902-1945)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Apr 23 12:05:13 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-218</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS BOX 49.5.1-6; E94.6-7;
		  E2006.34</physloc><unittitle>Collection relating to Eric Henry Liddell
		  (1902-1945)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1923-1945">1923-1945</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library; Edinburgh
		  University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 files. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Eric Henry Liddell, Olympic runner and missionary, was born in 1902 in
		  China, the son of Scottish missionaries. He was educated in Blackheath and
		  Eltham, London, then studied at Edinburgh University where he was a rugby blue
		  and gained his B.Sc. in 1924. He was outstanding as a runner and was selected
		  for the British team in the Paris Olympics of 1924. He refused to run in the
		  heats for the 100 meters as they were held on a Sunday and instead entered the
		  400 meters which he won in a world record time. Liddell's story was later made
		  into the film 
		<title>Chariots of Fire</title>. He went on to study at the Scottish
		Congregational College and in 1925 went to China as a missionary with the
		London Missionary Society. He began by teaching science at the Anglo-Chinese
		College in Tientsin then moved to rural Siochang where he worked despite the
		difficult conditions caused by poverty and war. He married Florence Mackenzie
		in March 1934 in Tientsin but he last saw his wife and children in 1940 when,
		for safety, they went to Canada to live with family. Liddell was interned by
		the Japanese in 1943 in Weihsien prison camp, Shantung where he died of a brain
		tumour in 1945. His death was widely mourned not least in the camp itself where
		he had become a teacher, friend and guide to scores of imprisoned children.</p>
		
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection at New College Library consists of 
		<title>Eric Liddell</title> by D.P. Thomson (1945) and a letter (30 June
		1940) from Liddell to Mary and George Cameron, Heriot, Midlothian describing
		his movements during his last trip with his family. There is also a photograph
		of the letter and an accompanying exhibition captions. Material at Edinburgh
		University Library, Special Collections Division, consists of the annual sports
		programmes of Edinburgh University Athletic Club, 1923-1925, and an annotated
		Scottish Inter-Universities programme, 1923. There are also two photographs of
		a memorial stone in China. </p> 
		<p>At E2006.34 there is an original invitation to the wedding of the Rev.
		  Eric H. Liddell to Florence Jean Mackenzie at the Union Church, Tientsin, on 27
		  March 1934. The invitation was sent to Margaret Irene Brown (later Nichols),
		  b.1912, of Peterborough, Ontario, Canada, who was a friend of Florence.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The material was presented to New College Library by the Reverend
		  George C. Cameron in 1985. The letter was found in the Thomson booklet.
		  Liddell's Olympic medals were donated to Edinburgh University by his daughter
		  Mrs. Patricia Russell, 20 May 1992. The wedding invitation was gifted to
		  Edinburgh University Library by Mary MacPherson and John Nichols, Peterborough,
		  Ontario, Canada.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using: (1) Anderson, G. H.
		  (ed.). 
		<title>Bibliographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New
		York: Macmillan Reference USA, 1998. (2) Cameron, Nigel M. de S. (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of Scottish Church History and Theology</title>.
		Edinburgh: T&amp;T Clark, 1993.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts held at New College Library mentions the
		  collection. A handlist is filed in the New College Inventory of Manuscripts
		  under BOX 49.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Two Olympic medals won by Liddell in Paris, 1924 - gold and bronze -
		  and a third medal for participation are on public display at the Old College,
		  Edinburgh University.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">China</emph> </subject> 
		<subject><emph altrender="a"><?xm-replace_text {subject}?></emph></subject>
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Liddell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Eric Henry</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1902-1945</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Olympic Athlete
		  and Missionary</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">London Missionary Society</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
