<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-355" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-355</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Anna Maria Hall (1800-1881)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Mar 26 11:46:50 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-355</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1731 Hall</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Anna Maria Hall
		  (1800-1881)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1841-1846">1841-1846</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>5 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The novelist and miscellaneous writer Anna Maria Hall was born in
		  Dublin on 6 January 1800. Her own family name was Fielding. On the death of her
		  father, she and her mother went to live in Wexford and they stayed there until
		  1815 when they came to England. On 20 September she married author and editor
		  Samuel Carter Hall (1800-1889). Her first recorded writing was an Irish piece
		  called 
		<title>Master Ben</title> (1829). Other tales quickly followed and these
		were collected together and published as 
		<title>Sketches of Irish character</title> (1829). Her first novel was 
		<title>The buccaneer</title> (1832) a story from the Civil War and
		Commonwealth period with Cromwell as one of the characters. Articles for her
		husband's magazine followed and these were republished in three volumes as 
		<title>Lights and shadows of Irish life</title> (1838). Hall also wrote
		for the stage and 
		<title>The French refugee</title> was produced at the St. James's Theatre
		in 1836. Another of her dramas was in the possession of Irish comedian Tyrone
		Power (1797-1841) when he was lost with the 'SS President' when it went down in
		April 1841. Around this time Hall contributed to 
		<title>Chambers's Edinburgh Journal</title> and her stories in that were
		collected and published as 
		<title>Tales of the Irish peasantry</title> (1840). She also assisted her
		husband with 
		<title>Ireland, its scenery, characters</title> (1841-1843), 
		<title>The book of south Wales</title> (1861), and 
		<title>A companion to Killarney</title> (1878). Other writing included 
		<title>Pilgrimages to English shrines</title> (1849), 
		<title>Stories of the governess</title> (1852), 
		<title>Daddy Dacre's school</title> (1859), and 
		<title>The playfellow and other stories</title> (1866). Hall was
		instrumental in the founding of a hospital for consumption in Brompton, an
		institution for governesses, and the Nightingale Fund. She also supported the
		temperance movement and her work 
		<title>Boons and blessings: stories of temperance</title> (1875) was
		dedicated to Lord Shaftesbury. In her lifetime, Hall's writing had never been
		particularly popular in Ireland chiefly because on each side of the historical
		divide there she saw both the negative and the positive and failed to please
		either Catholic or Protestant. Anna Maria Hall died at East Moulsey on 30
		January 1881.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers consist of correspondence, including: a letter of Hall to a
		  Mrs. Finlay about her literary work and fashions etc, 1841; a letter to Miss
		  Catmar in Musselburgh, circa 1843; a letter to James Montgomery asking for a
		  contribution to a women's magazine, 1844; and, a letter to W. C. Macready
		  requesting his autograph, 1846. There is also a portrait of Hall.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter to Catmar purchased November 1972, Accession no. E72.60. Letter
		  to Finlay and Montgomery, and portrait, purchased 1973, Accession no. E73.56.
		  Letter to Macready, purchased February 1975, Accession no. E75.7. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 8. Glover-Harriott.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Hall related material at
		  shelfmark L.O.A. among the Halliwell-Phillipps collection (check the Indexes
		  for more details): letters of Hall to J. O. Halliwell-Phillipps, L.O.A. 71/65,
		  79/7, 82/32, 209/41. There is also correspondence to Hall at Gen. 1730, and at
		  L.O.A. 91/60.</p> 
		<p>There is also material relating to Samuel Carter Hall, including:
		  letters, 1852, at Dc.2.59; letter, 1855, at Gen1731; letters in the
		  Halliwell-Phillipps collection at L.O.A. 71/22 and L.O.A. 80/52; and, letter in
		  the Laing Collection at La.IV.17. There are also letters to S. C. Hall (check
		  the Indexes for more details).</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes for Anna Maria Hall:
		  correspondence and papers, University of Iowa Libraries, Special Collections,
		  see NUC MS 72-926; personal and professional correspondence, Knox College, see
		  NUC MS 78-1208; papers, Historical Society of Pennsylvania, see NUC MS 61-352;
		  letters to Lord Lytton, 1840-1859, Hertfordshire Archives and Local Studies,
		  Ref. D/EK NRA 4598 Bulwer-Lytton; letters (24) to the Milner-Gibsons and
		  others, 1867-1880, Cambridge University, Trinity College Library, Ref. Cullum
		  N1:8-46; and letters, as sponsor, to the Royal Literary Fund, 1842-1879,
		  British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Loan no.96.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">19th century</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Hall</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Samuel Carter</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1800-1889</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Author and
		  Editor</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hall</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Anna Maria</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1800-1881</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Novelist,
		  Playwright, Miscellaneous writer</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
