<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid publicid="GB 237 Coll-1021" countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237">GB
		237 Coll-1021</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="">Papers of Gregory Peter Lubkin (fl.
			 1972-1975)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by JavaScript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2 on 
		  <date>Fri Dec 3 10:28:03 UTC 2004</date>.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1021"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-1021</unitid> 
		<physloc>E2003.6</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Gregory Peter Lubkin (fl.
		  1972-1975)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1972/1975">1972-1975</unitdate> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 boxes with 8 archive folders, 3 envelopes.</extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
		
		<origination>Lubkin, Gregory Peter</origination> 
	 </did> 
	 <phystech> 
		<p>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted</p></phystech> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Gregory P. Lubkin was a student at Edinburgh University from October
		  1972, with the Faculty of Arts. He graduated with the degree of MA (Hons) in
		  1975. At the time of his matriculation in 1972 his home was in East Lansing,
		  Michigan. Lubkin has taught at Wellesley College, Massachusetts, USA, and the
		  University of California, Berkeley. He has written many works on Renaissance
		  Milan, including 
		<title>A Renaissance Court - Milan under Galleazzo Maria Sforza</title>
		(March 1994).</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of notes, essays, and examination papers, and
		  consists of: folder relating to British History I, European History 2, and
		  Celtic I, 1972-1973; Medieval aristocracies and society, Medieval and early
		  renaissance thought, and Theory and history of history, 1973-1974; and,
		  Literature, war and society in France, England, and the Iberian Peninsula, and
		  Studies in Italian Renaissance history, 1974-1975. There are also 3 archival
		  envelopes containing: communication between Lubkin and the University relevant
		  to his chosen course, the documents, letters, and class certificates; material
		  relating to student activities; and material on the theatre company and
		  dramatic society he was involved with, 1972-1975. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material received from Gregory Lubkin, April 2003, Accession no.
		  E2003.6.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material
		  contained in the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <processinfo> 
		<p>Compiled by Graeme D. Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
		  Collections Division.</p> 
	 </processinfo>
    <!-- Controlled Access Terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Students</emph> </subject> 
		<subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Note-taking</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Lubkin</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Gregory Peter </emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl.
		  1972-1975 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Writer on Italian
		  Renaissance</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Edinburgh (Scotland)</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
