<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-48"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-48</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Alexander Gillon Macalpine. Malawi missionary papers and
			 linguistic studies </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-48</unitid>
		
		<physloc>MSS 3086-3090 </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Alexander Gillon Macalpine. Malawi
		  missionary papers and linguistic studies </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1893-1964">1893-1964 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>5 boxes (1
		  m). </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Alexander Gillon Macalpine was born 11 June 1869 in Linlithgow. He was
		  educated in Linlithgow and at George Watson's College in Edinburgh, then went
		  to Edinburgh University and Glasgow Free Church College. He was ordained in
		  1893. With the exception of 1914-21 when he was Minister of Monquhitter and New
		  Byth, Aberdeenshire, he was a missionary in Nyasaland (Malawi), mainly at
		  Bandawe, Chintechi, and later on Livingstonia. In his earliest years in the
		  country Macalpine did some administrative and postal work. He became the first
		  Clerk of the Synod of the Church of Central Africa Presbyterian. He prepared a
		  dictionary of the Chitonga language, and translated and revised the New
		  Testament in Chitonga. Two manuscript copies of the dictionary are said to be
		  in the libraries of Glasgow and Witwatersrand Universities. Macalpine died in
		  Glasgow, 8 September 1957. The material constituting the Macalpine Malawi
		  missionary papers and linguistic studies, was presented by the Rev. Alexander
		  Gillon Macalpine, jr., in 1964 and 1993, and by Dr. H. B. Auld in 1993. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>The papers consist of biographical notes on African and missionary
		  colleagues dating from 1893; diaries from 1897 onwards; wayside and journey
		  notes and jottings; extracts from newspapers; notes on folklore; letters; film
		  strip showing pictures of missionary work; notebooks; and, correspondence with
		  church ministers in Scotland. There are printed items, including the catechism
		  and hymns in the Chitonga language; psalms in Tonga; dictionaries; the grammar
		  of the Bemba language; notes on Tumbuka syntax; notes for a Tonga grammar, and
		  notes of Chitonga grammar; Tonga-English vocabulary; and, items on the building
		  of Nyasaland and on the Church in the region. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Macalpine</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander
		  Gillon</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1869-1957</emph> </persname> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Malawi</emph> <emph altrender="x">Languages</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Linguistics</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Linguists</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>Handlist, H48 </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
