<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-223" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-223</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of David Clement Ruffell Scott
			 (1853-1907)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Apr 23 10:46:54 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-223</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 717/10</physloc><unittitle>Papers of David Clement Ruffell
		  Scott (1853-1907)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1881-1895">1881-1895</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 file. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>David Clement Ruffell Scott, Church of Scotland missionary in Malawi
		  and Kenya, was born in Edinburgh in 1853. He attended school in Edinburgh then
		  spent some time working in an actuary's office before a calling to the church
		  led him to study Arts and Divinity at the University of Edinburgh. He was a
		  brilliant student graduating M.A. (1878) and B.D. (1881). Scott was ordained in
		  1881 and immediately sent to be head of the Church of Scotland mission at
		  Blantyre in Nyasaland (now Malawi). He was responsible for virtually restarting
		  the mission as all the previous staff had either resigned or been dismissed.
		  Scott was a brilliant linguist, his interest in African culture and closeness
		  to African people can be seen from his 
		<title> Cyclopaedic Dictionary of the Mang'anja Language</title> (1892).
		Much of the periodical 
		<title>Life and Work in Central Africa</title> between 1886 and 1898 was
		written by Scott. His efforts created a mission that was regarded as highly
		successful. Scott suffered a series of personal setbacks in 1895 with the
		deaths of his wife, brother-in-law and brother, and later of the daughter of
		his second wife. This, coupled with the Church of Scotland's decision to side
		with white settler critics, led him to resign in 1898. In 1901 Scott returned
		to Africa, to head the Kikuyu mission in British East Africa (Kenya) which had
		just been taken over by the Church of Scotland. However his work at Kikuyu was
		not as successful as his work at Blantyre. The death of his second wife in
		1902, a series of illnesses, and criticism of his methods of running the
		mission marred the final years of his life. Despite this, his ability to relate
		to Africans remained unchanged and he attracted a number of outstanding Kikuyus
		to the mission. Scott died at Kikuyu on 13 October 1907. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of nineteen letters from Scott to his close
		  friend the Reverend James Robertson written mainly from Blantyre, Nyasaland
		  (Malawi) from the time of his arrival in 1881 to 1895, the year in which his
		  wife and brother died. They describe in some detail the work of the mission and
		  his experiences in Africa. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The letters are arranged chronologically in one file.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to Edinburgh University in 1964 by the
		  Reverend Neil Bernard of Edinburgh.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <altformavail> 
		<p>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections has a microfilm of
		  the collection (Mic. Dup. 405). A copy was sent to the Kenyan High Commission
		  in 1982 and the National Archives of Malawi in 1984.</p> 
	 </altformavail> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Anderson, Gerald H. (ed.). 
		<title>Biographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New York:
		Macmillan Reference USA, 1998. (2) Macpherson, Robert. 
		<title>The Presbyterian Church in Kenya</title>. Nairobi: Presbyterian
		Church of East Africa, 1970.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University
		  Library, Special Collections and Archives. The collection is mentioned in the
		  Edinburgh University Library subject checklist (C3) 
		<title>Manuscripts on Africa</title>.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The papers of John William Arthur, who was also at the mission at
		  Kikuyu, at Edinburgh University Library contain references to Scott and his
		  death. A list filed with the Arthur collection mentions some Scott material
		  that is not amongst the material now in the Library. The papers of Arthur
		  Ruffell Barlow, Scott's nephew who was at Kikuyu from 1903, are also at
		  Edinburgh and include material about the history of the mission during Scott's
		  time and some pamphlets and reports produced by Scott. Dr Brian McIntosh in his
		  doctoral thesis 
		<title>The Scottish Mission in Kenya 1891-1923</title> (Edinburgh
		University 1969) has a comprehensive list of sources for the history of the
		Kikuyu mission. Material on the mission at Blantyre is in the National Archives
		in Malawi and the Synod offices at Blantyre. These sources are described in 
		<title>Blantyre Mission and the Making of Modern Malawi</title> by Andrew
		Ross (Blantyre, Malawi: CLAIM, 1996). There is also relevant material at the
		National Library of Scotland which has the records of the Church of Scotland
		and some Scott correspondence. The papers of George Shepperson at Edinburgh
		University Library contain a collection of photographs, some of which are of
		Blantyre.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Africa</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Nyanja language</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="x">Linguistic work</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Scott</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">David Clement Ruffell</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1853-1907</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scottish
		  Missionary</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Blantyre Mission</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Malawi</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Kikuyu Mission</emph> <emph
		  altrender="z">Kenya</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Blantyre (Malawi)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
