<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-747" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-747</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Rev. James King Hewison
			 (1853-1941)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jan 7 09:54:44 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-747</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS HEW 1-26</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rev. James King
		  Hewison (1853-1941)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1874-1938">1874-1938</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>19 longer manuscripts and books, 5 volumes scrapbooks,
		  1 box containing 13 notebooks newspaper cuttings, 4 boxes notebooks of
		  manuscript drafts, miscellaneous photographs and prints, miscellaneous letters
		  and addresses. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition
		  may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Hewison, James King</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James King Hewison was born in 1853. He studied at Edinburgh
		  University. He was Minister of the Church of Scotland, first at Stair and then
		  at Rothesay, Isle of Bute, from 1884 to 1925. Hewison was an eminent researcher
		  and writer on Scottish seventeenth century ecclesiastical history, and his work
		  included the two volume 
		<title>The covenanters</title>. He also edited the works of Ninian Winzet
		for the Scottish Text Society, and he wrote many papers on the local history
		and archaeology of Bute. Hewison was a Grand Chaplain of the Masonic Order in
		Scotland. The Rev. James King Hewison died at Thornhill, Dumfriesshire on 23
		January 1941.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: books and longer manuscripts, including
		  interleaved and annotated sets and additional notebooks and photographic
		  material relating to 
		<title>The covenanters</title>, correspondence relating to a work on
		Ninian Winzet and the volumes themselves, material on Dumfriesshire and the
		saints and heroes of Dalgarnoc, material on the geography of Dumfriesshire and
		on church lands there, an index of books, brochures, articles, and verses,
		typescript work on Scotland's debt of gratitude to its parish schools and
		universities, and an essay on Shakespeare's character of Coriolanus, 1874, for
		an English class at Edinburgh University; scrapbooks of newspaper cuttings of
		articles, personal documents, photographs, and letters, including articles on
		Ferguson the Poet, the Sir Patrick Spens myth, scholars of Nithsdale, Ailsa and
		its sea-birds, runic roods, St. Columba's Day, St. Patrick's Day, clerical
		attire, Pontius Pilate at Fortingall, the Benedictines, and much more; cuttings
		from the 
		<title>Dumfries and Galloway standard</title> 1923, cuttings of articles
		from 
		<title>The Scotsman</title> 1904-1938; photographs by John Cunninghame
		Montgomerie of Dalmore, Ayr, and including those of the Ruthwell and Bewcastle
		Crosses; notebooks containing manuscript drafts of articles; and, biographical
		material including letters describing a tour round the world, 1895, and
		congratulatory address on the 50th anniversary of Hewison's admission as
		Minister of the High Kirk of Rothesay.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 11. 1940-1942.
		pp.117-118. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1942.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hewison</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James King</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1853-1941</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister,
		  Writer</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
