<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-782" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-782</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Rev. John Anderson (1668-1721)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Mar 30 10:42:05 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-782</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS AND. 1-4</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Rev. John Anderson
		  (1668-1721)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1705-1913">1705-1913</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 volumes, circa 340 sheets or leaves in typescript.
		  </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Anderson, John; Anderson, A. Whitford</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The theologian John Anderson was born in 1668. He was tutor to John,
		  Duke of Argyll and Greenwich. Anderson became Minister of Dumbarton in 1698 and
		  was involved in the battle lines drawn around Episcopacy and Presbyterianism.
		  At the time there was a great deal of worry among the Presbyterian clergy in
		  connection with the use of the English liturgy in Episcopalian congregations.
		  In 1720 he was appointed Minister of the Ramshorn Church (later St. David's) in
		  Glasgow. His published works included 
		<title>A dialogue between a curate and a countryman</title> (1710), 
		<title>The second dialogue between the curate and the countryman
		  respecting the English service</title> (1711), and then 
		<title>The countryman's letter to the curate, wherein, besides an
		  historical view of the English Liturgy, the assertions of Sage, the author of
		  the Fundamental Character of Presbytery, concerning its universal usage in
		  Scotland at the time of the Reformation ... are examined and proved to be
		  false</title>, and also 
		<title>Defence of the Church government, faith, worship, and spirit of
		  the Presbyterians</title> (1714). The Rev. John Anderson died in 1721.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: correspondence in typescript; a diary
		  from 1 January 1705 to 25 March 1705, in typescript, transcribed from the
		  original manuscript, 1910; 
		<title>The history of the introducing the usage of the Lord's Prayer in
		  Dumbarton</title>, 1705, from an unpublished manuscript account; and, records
		of the Rev. John Anderson, transcribed from documents by A. Whitford Anderson,
		1913, in typescript</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 1. Abbadie-Beadon.
		London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes at New College also show reference to other A.
		  Whitford Anderson material (check the Indexes for more details): general index
		  to the four volumes of transcripts of the papers (of the Rev. John Anderson),
		  circa 130 leaves; and, records of a Scots parish and its minister, 1670-1721
		  (John Anderson of Dumbarton). Material at MSS ANDE. 1-2.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Anderson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1668-1721
		  </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister of Dumbarton</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Anderson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">A. Whitford </emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl
		  1914</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Dumbarton (Scotland)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
