<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-752" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-752</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Rev. Marcus Dods (1786-1838)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jan 7 10:39:43 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-752</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS DODS 1-23</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rev. Marcus Dods
		  (1786-1838)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1810-1835">1810-1835</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 18 boxes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records
		  in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Dods, Marcus</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The theological writer Marcus Dods was born near Gifford, East
		  Lothian, in 1786. He was educated in Edinburgh and was ordained as a
		  Presbyterian Minister at Belford, Northumberland, in 1810. He was a leading
		  contributor to the 
		<title>Edinburgh Christian instructor</title> under the editorship of Dr.
		Andrew Thomson. The Rev. Marcus Dods died in 1838.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: sermons, lectures, address etc. on Old
		  Testament books and themes, including 21 on Ezekial, 31 on Acts and the Gospel
		  of John, and on miscellaneous New Testament books and themes; thematic sermons;
		  miscellaneous thematic lectures, address etc; Biblical canon, Bross lectures on
		  the Bible, history of biblical criticism, the Authorised version, Bible
		  compared with other sacred books, development of biblical interpretation in the
		  eighteenth century; material on Paul, and on Hebrews and the background of the
		  New Testament; material on the teaching of Jesus, and on the life, death and
		  resurrection of Jesus; notebooks on the New Testament, including Synoptics,
		  Gospels, Matthew, Mark, Luke, John, Galatians, I Peter, II Peter, James, Jude,
		  I John, Colossians, and Revelation, many with interfiled loose sheets; further
		  notebooks on the New Testament, including the chronology of life of Jesus, the
		  appointment of the Apostles, the Corinthian abuse of the Lord's Supper and the
		  Agapae, textual criticism, sects of Christendom, history of the primitive
		  church, Greek mysteries, divisions of the Lord's ministry, language of the New
		  Testament, and notebooks on Greek language; and, fragments. There is also a
		  commonplace book, a copy of 
		<title>Novum Testamentum Graece</title> (1886), an annotated copy of 
		<title>The parallel New Testament</title> (1882), an annotated copy of 
		<title>Synopse der drei ersten Evangelien</title> (1892), and Charles
		Edward Hammond's 
		<title>Outlines of textual criticism applied to the New testament</title>
		also annotated by Dods.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 5. Craik-Drake.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes at Special Collections Division, Edinburgh
		  University Library, George Square, show a reference to Dods related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): the death of Dods mentioned in a letter
		  of G. Johnston to Sir W. Jardine, undated, postmarked 1 October 1838, at
		  Dk.6.20/169. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated
		  by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters (58) to May Crum,
		  Cambridge University Library, Department of Manuscripts and University
		  Archives, Ref. Add MS 7671 NRA 34421 HF Stewart; and, correspondence with Henry
		  Drummond, circa 1872-1895, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division,
		  Ref. Acc 5890 NRA 27275 Drummond</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">New Testament scholars</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Church history</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Sermons</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dods</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Marcus</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1834-1909</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">New Testament
		  Scholar</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
