<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-481" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-481</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers and Reports relating to Albert Schweitzer
			 (1875-1965)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Oct 21 12:04:23 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-481</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 79; Phot.P.25-26F</physloc><unittitle>Papers and Reports
		  relating to Albert Schweitzer (1875-1965)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1934-1961">1934-1961</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box with circa 11 essays</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The German theologian, philosopher, and mission doctor Albert
		  Schweitzer was born in Kaysersberg, Upper Alsace, France, on 41 January 1875.
		  He studied philosophy and theology in Strasbourg. While he established himself
		  in the field of theological studies he also became an accomplished organist,
		  taught by Charles-Marie Widor. In 1913 he became a doctor of medicine and at
		  Lambarene in Gabon, on the shores of the Ogowe River, he set up a mission
		  hospital which he equipped from his own income and maintained with funds from
		  around the world. During a period of internment while the First World War was
		  underway, Schweitzer turned himself towards international problems, setting out
		  a philosophy of the reverence for life and an ethical principle involving all
		  living things. He returned to the hospital in 1924 to rebuild it from the
		  derelict state into which it had fallen. This time a leper colony was added. By
		  1963, his hospital had around 500 patients. His works include 
		<title>J. S. Bach: le musicien-poete</title> (1905), 
		<title>Von Reimarus zu Wrede</title> (1906), 
		<title>The quest for the historical Jesus</title> (1910), 
		<title>Kulturphilosophie</title> (1923), and 
		<title>Die mystik des Apostels Paulus</title> (1930). In 1952 Schweitzer
		was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize. Albert Schweitzer died on 4 September
		1965.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: reports of the Gifford Lectures delivered
		  by Albert Schweitzer at Edinburgh University in November 1934 and November
		  1935; and, papers relating to Schweitzer produced by the Albert Schweitzer
		  Foundation, Chicago, 1960-1961.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Albert Schweitzer Foundation papers, acquired 1961, Accession no.
		  E61.12.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>Note that when this record was created any associated
		  photographic/illustrative material was unseen.</p> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. 15th edition. Vol.10.
		Micropaedia. Ready Reference. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1991. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Schweitzer</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Albert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1875-1965</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Theologian,
		  Philosopher, Organist, and Mission Doctor</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Albert Schweitzer Foundation</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
