<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-69"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-69</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Manuscripts of
			 Norman MacCaig (1910-1996) </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20061222">22 December 2006</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-69</unitid>
		
		<physloc>MSS 3198-3210; E2006.40 </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Manuscripts of Norman MacCaig
		  (1910-1996) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1939-1995">1939-1995 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>13 boxes (1
		  linear metre); 1 folder containing letter. </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>The Scottish poet, Norman MacCaig, was born in Edinburgh on 14
		  November 1910. He was educated at the city's Royal High School and studied at
		  Edinburgh University, graduating with an honours degree (MA) in Classics in
		  1932. Throughout much of his life until 1970, MacCaig held various teaching
		  positions, mostly in Edinburgh, but this was interrupted by a two-year period
		  as Fellow in Creative Writing at Edinburgh University, 1967-69. He was the
		  first person to be given such a post of Writer in Residence at the University.
		  Between the years 1970 and 1972 he was Lecturer in English Studies at the
		  University of Stirling, and Reader in Poetry between 1972 and 1977. MacCaig's
		  father had been a Lowlander while his mother was from the island of Scalpay,
		  and he had felt the rich cultural inheritances from both connections. Except
		  for a few foreign settings, his poetry is set in Edinburgh or Assynt in the
		  North West Highlands. His early works included 
		<title>Far cry </title> (1943), 
		<title>The inward eye </title> (1946) and 
		<title>Riding lights </title> (1955). He exploited the natural world for
		many of the images in his work, and his poetry contained wit, humour, and keen
		observation. His command of metaphor was also evident. His volumes of verse
		looked at life on a small scale, these volumes being 
		<title>The Sinai sort </title> (1957), 
		<title>A common grace </title> (1960), 
		<title>A round of applause </title> (1962), 
		<title>Measures </title> (1965), and 
		<title>A man in my position </title> 1969). Later works included 
		<title>Tree of strings </title> (1977) and 
		<title>A world of difference </title> (1983). A volume of collected poems
		was published, 
		<title>Collected poems </title> (1985, and new edition 1990). MacCaig was
		awarded the OBE in 1979. One of the foremost Scottish men of letters of the
		20th century, MacCaig died in Edinburgh on 23 January 1996. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>Within the Norman MacCaig collection, MSS 3198-3199 consist of single
		  sheets of poetic manuscripts and drafts. From MSS 3200 onwards there are
		  folders containing miscellaneous early material. Also, proofs and typescripts;
		  notes and newscuttings; notes on other poets; broadcast transcriptions, reviews
		  and notes; translations by MacCaig; correspondence; critical material on
		  MacCaig's poetry; dissertations; literary material by other people;
		  certificates of birth and marriage etc., and material relating to drawing up of
		  will; invoices and statements and other financial material; pocket diaries and
		  address book; and, published books of poems. </p> 
		<p>At E2006.40 there is a letter to Norman MacCaig from person unknown
		  (letter signed Ian S.). At letter heading is 5 Mackenzie Place, Friday. 11th
		  May. The year is unknown. The letter content is a fairly involved review of a
		  book. The letter-writer is clearly a good friend of MacCaig because he writes,
		  referring to the letter: 'I don't expect to be able to wait long at the pub, so
		  I will leave this for you there' (see shelfmark SD 9105 for the book).</p> 
		<p>E2006.45 includes: portrait photograph of MacCaig as an infant, 1911;
		  passport 1964-1974; passport 1975-1985; Christmas and New Year card from
		  Christopher (Grieve) and Valda to Norman and Isabel; printed copy of 
		<title>The close brethren of the SNP Junta</title>; OS map, Sheet 13,
		Loch Inver, Loch Assynt; circa 100 assorted colour and black and white
		photographs of MacCaig and friends; large black and white portrait of MacCaig;
		and, a note to MacCaig from Gavin Ewart found in a copy of 
		<title>Twelve apostles</title> (see shelfmark SD 9152 for the book). </p>
		
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.5./marc 541"> 
		<p>MSS 3198-3210 are those manuscripts acquired in 1997 with the help of
		  the National Lottery Fund, the National Fund for Acquisitions, the Friends of
		  Edinburgh University Library, and other sources. </p> 
		<p>E2006.40 was found in the book 
		<title>In memoriam James Joyce: from a vision of world language</title>,
		by Hugh MacDiarmid, 1955. This book can be found at shelfmark SD 9105.</p> 
		<p>Within E2006.45 is a note to MacCaig from Gavin Ewart found in a copy
		  of 
		<title>Twelve apostles</title>. This item can be found at shelfmark SD
		9152. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">MacCaig</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Norman</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1910-1996</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh
		  University</emph> </corpname> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Scottish poetry</emph> <emph altrender="y">20th century</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Poets, Scottish</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>Handlist, H69; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts shows, at various shelfmarks, references to
		  MSS of poems, and letters. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
