<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-238" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-238</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor Albert Venn Dicey
			 (1835-1922)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jun 05 17:31:34 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-238</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 531-541</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor Albert Venn
		  Dicey (1835-1922)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1999">19th century and 20th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>14 assorted volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Albert Venn Dicey was born in 1835. He studied at Balliol College
		  Oxford where he was President of the Union. He was a Fellow of Trinity College,
		  Oxford, from 1860 until 1872. Dicey was called to the Bar at Inner Temple in
		  1863. From 1876 until 1890, he was Junior Counsel to the Commissioners of the
		  Inland Revenue, and between 1882 and 1909 he was the Vinerian Professor of
		  English Law and a Fellow of All Souls College, Oxford. He became a QC in 1890.
		  His publications include: 
		<title>Introduction to the study of the law of the constitution</title>
		(1885), 
		<title>Digest of the law of England</title> (1896), 
		<title>Law and public opinion in England</title> (1905). An ardent
		Unionist, Dicey also wrote 
		<title>England's case against home rule</title> (1886), and collaborated
		on 
		<title>Thoughts on the union between England And Scotland</title> (1920).
		Albert Venn Dicey died on 7 April 1922.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of notebooks containing: notes on the law of
		  domicil (domicile) with a list of cases to 1890; notes on jurisdiction
		  procedure; notes on contracts to 1891; notes on changeability of immovables,
		  and land or immovables; notes on the conflict of laws from 1907 to 1911; and,
		  notes on private international law.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) 
		<title>Who was who 1916-1928. A companion to Who's who ...</title>.
		Vol.2. 3rd ed. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1962. (2) 
		<title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise
		  dictionary</title>. Part 2. 1901-1970. Oxford: OUP, 1982.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to A. V. Dicey
		  correspondence (check the Indexes for more details). In addition, the UK
		  National Register of Archives notes: miscellaneous correspondence and papers at
		  Glasgow University Library, Special Collections Department; correspondence and
		  papers at London Metropolitan Archives; correspondence at Cambridge University
		  Library, Department of Manuscripts and University Archives, and letters at
		  Gonville and Caius College Library, Cambridge, and King's College Archive
		  Centre, Cambridge; letters at Oxford University, All Souls College, and at
		  Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western Manuscripts, and at Balliol
		  College Library; letters at British Library, Manuscript Collections; letters at
		  Manchester University, John Rylands Library; correspondence at House of Lords
		  Records Office, the Parliamentary Archives; and letters at Trinity College
		  Dublin.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Conflict of laws</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Jurisdiction</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Domicile</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Contracts</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Dicey</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Albert Venn</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1835-1922</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Jurist and
		  Historian</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
