<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-393" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-393</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of papers relating to Rudyard Kipling
			 (1865-1936)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon May 27 10:45:24 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-393</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.2.8; Gen.1733/20</physloc><unittitle>Collection of papers
		  relating to Rudyard Kipling (1865-1936)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 volume (182 pp. of manuscripts), 1 letter. </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The author Joseph Rudyard Kipling was born in Bombay on 30 December
		  1865. He was the son of the architectural sculptor and designer John Lockwood
		  Kipling (1837-1911) and a cousin of Stanley Baldwin (1867-1947). He was
		  educated at United Services College, Westward Ho! North Devon. In 1882, he
		  joined the staff of the 
		<title>Civil and military gazette and pioneer</title> in Lahore, and
		became Assistant Editor serving until 1889. He then settled in London though
		travelled widely in China, Japan, America, Africa, and Australia. From 1902 he
		lived in Burwash. His early writing included 
		<title>Plain tales from the hills</title> (1887), 
		<title>Soldiers three</title> and 
		<title>Wee Willie Winkie</title>. Other stories and verse such as 
		<title>The light that failed</title> (1891), 
		<title>The jungle book</title> (1894), 
		<title>Second jungle book</title> (1895), and 
		<title>Captains Courageous</title> (1897) brought him to the height of
		his fame. His publications also included 
		<title>Barrack-room ballads</title> (1897), 
		<title>Kim</title> (1901), the 
		<title>Just so stories for little children</title> (1902), 
		<title>Puck of Pook's hill</title> (1906), and 
		<title>A school history of England</title> (1911). In 1907 Kipling was
		awarded the Nobel Prize for Literature. Rudyard Kipling, who was a cousin of
		Stanley Baldwin, died on 18 January 1936.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The manuscript material is composed of sheets of verse from 
		<title>The diversity of creatures</title> (1917) and 
		<title>The eyes of Asia</title>. There is also a letter from Kipling to
		James Couper H. Brash and A. Christian Gillan declining an invitation to be
		nominated as a candidate in the Edinburgh University rectorial election,
		1935.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>In local Index, volume original manuscripts gifted by Rudyard Kipling
		  to Edinburgh University and transmitted through Mrs. Kipling, 1936, noted
		  Acc.23034. Letter, acquired from J. C. H. Brash, April 1982, Accession no.
		  E82.25.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>Who was who 1929-1940</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black,
		1941. (2) 
		<title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise
		  dictionary</title>. Part 2. 1901-1970. Oxford: OUP, 1982.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes material in the UK: correspondence, literary MSS
		  and papers, c. 1880-1947, Sussex University Library Special Collections, Ref.
		  SxMs 38 NRA 22631 Kipling, and correspondence and papers relating to school
		  life and friends in particular George Beresford, Ref. SxMs 69, and letters (9)
		  to L. C. Dunsterville, 1886-1928, Ref. SxMs67 NRA 41274 Sussex Uni Misc, and
		  letters (51) to Harry Lewin, 1920-1935, and correspondence and literary MSS
		  kept by Miss Parker, his secretary, 1902-1904, Ref. SxMs66 NRA 41274 Sussex Uni
		  Misc; literary MSS, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MSS
		  44481, 45540-42, 59840, and correspondence with Macmillans, corrected proofs,
		  1890-1936, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MSS 54940,
		  55846-75, and correspondence with Society of Authors, 1909-1922, Ref. Add MSS
		  56734; MS of Puck of Pook's Hill, 1906, and letters, 1902-1912, Oxford
		  University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western manuscripts, Ref.
		  MS Eng misc c 127; MS Autogr b 11/453-467, and correspondence with Lady Milner
		  (127 items), 1902-1938, Ref. MS Violet Milner NRA 20659 Milner, and MS of
		  Rewards and Fairies, 1910, Ref. Add 6850; letters (19), 1882-1935, and literary
		  MSS, Huntington Library; correspondence and papers relating to Imperial War
		  Graves Commission, Commonwealth War Graves Commission, Ref. passim NRA 40692
		  Commonwealth; letters to Sir Percy Bates, 1924-1936, National Maritime Museum,
		  Manuscripts Section, Ref. MS 82/158 NRA 20623 Nat Maritime Mus, and letters to
		  Leslie Cope-Cornford, 1903-1928, Ref. CPC NRA 30121; letters from Lord
		  Bathurst, 1910-1935, Leeds University, Brotherton Library, Ref. Ms Dep 1990/1
		  part II NRA 35050 Glenesk; correspondence with Lord Beaverbrook, 1910-1918,
		  House of Lords Record Office, The Parliamentary Archives, Ref. BBK C/197-9 NRA
		  19284 Aitken, and correspondence with John St. Loe Strachey, 1898-1924, Ref.
		  Strachey 33/1; letters to Samuel Levi Bensusan, Essex University Library;
		  letters (24) to J. H. C. Brooking, 1907-1935, Kipling Society; correspondence
		  with Edward Carson, Public Record Office of Northern Ireland, Ref. D1507 NRA
		  17985 Carson; letters to Sir Henry Rider Haggard, Norfolk Record Office, NRA
		  22737 Haggard; letters to the Leonard family, Hagley Hall, NRA 14545 Lyttelton;
		  and, correspondence with Douglas Sladen, 1895-1919, Richmond Local Studies
		  Library, Ref. SLA/6-8, 17, 31, 58, 68 NRA 14252 Sladen.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">20th century</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Kipling</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Rudyard</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1865-1936</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Author</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
