<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-571" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-571</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Edward McKillop Young (1873-1942)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University and re-edited by Graeme D Eddie,
				Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Nov 19 10:28:00 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-571</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 8</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Edward McKillop Young
		  (1873-1942)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1900-1941">1900-1941</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 vol. (c 513 pp)</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Young, Edward McKillop</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Edward McKillop Young, (United Presbyterian and United Free) Church of
		  Scotland Missionary in Manchuria, China, was born in 1873 in Kinross, Scotland.
		  He attended the University of Edinburgh where he graduated MB, ChB in 1899. He
		  was appointed by the mission in 1899 and left for China in the same year. In
		  1900 he was ordained by the United Presbytery of Edinburgh and in 1902 he
		  married Dr Katharine Constance Sampson. He retired in 1932 but spent many years
		  in Shanghai and died there in 1942.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of circa 1026 sides of Young's closely written
		  commentary on the Bible, Christianity and God in modern society, with some
		  reference to books read by him. The material is arranged as diary entries but
		  there seem to be very few personal references apart from December 1941 when
		  Japanese occupation of the area in which Young was living is mentioned. The
		  material begins with page 833 and is obviously only part of a larger collection
		  of notes. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The pages are all numbered and dated. They are kept in the covers of a
		  book which was owned by Young on his way to China.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The Church of Scotland deposited with the Centre several collections
		  relating to missionaries in China and these papers probably formed part of this
		  deposit.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself, (2) Fulton, Austin. 
		<title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title>. Edinburgh: The Saint
		Andrew Press, 1967. (3) Lamb, J. A. (ed.). 
		<title>Fasti of the United Free Church of Scotland</title>. Edinburgh:
		Oliver and Boyd, 1956.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the Church of Scotland foreign missions are held by
		  the National Library of Scotland and include correspondence with Young. Papers
		  of other missionaries working in Manchuria are held by the Centre for the Study
		  of Christianity in the Non-Western World as are several books on the
		  development of missionary work in Manchuria. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Young</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Edward McKillop |</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1873-1942 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Church of
		  Scotland Missionary in Manchuria</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Manchuria (China) </emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
