<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-264" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-264</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of William Cullen M.D. (1710-1790)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Aug 08 10:15:39 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-264</unitid> 
		<physloc>MS 3143; Gen. 1860-1861; Dk.3.49; Dk.3.54-62; Dc.1.49; Dc.4.101
		  Cullen; Dc.3.70; Dc.5.109-112; Dc.7.55; Dc.10.10; Da.2.1, p.60; E90.128;
		  E95.04</physloc><unittitle>Papers of William Cullen M.D.
		  (1710-1790)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1701-1799">18th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>24 volumes of notebooks, 2 letters (manuscript).
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Cullen, William; Remmett, Robert Butler; Johnson, James;
		  Hope, Thomas Charles</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>William Cullen was born in Hamilton, Lanarkshire, on 15 April 1710. He
		  studied at Glasgow University and in 1729 went to London and became a surgeon
		  on a merchant ship sailing to the West Indies. On returning to London he
		  assisted in an apothecary in Henrietta Street and continued with his studies.
		  In the early 1730s, Cullen returned to Scotland to provide for his family after
		  the death of his father and eldest brother. After two years of practicing in
		  Auchinlee near Hamilton, he began studying again this time at the Edinburgh
		  Medical School under Alexander Monro primus (1697-1767) between the years 1734
		  and 1736. In 1736 he began practicing as a surgeon in Hamilton and was chief
		  magistrate in the town too, between 1739 and 1740. In 1740, Cullen obtained the
		  degree of M.D. at Glasgow and from 1744 he moved to the city and became
		  occupied with founding a medical school there, and lectured on medicine and
		  other subjects. One of his students was Joseph Black (1728-1799). In 1751,
		  Cullen became Professor of Medicine at Glasgow University, and then in 1755 he
		  was elected joint and then sole Professor of Chemistry at Edinburgh University.
		  In 1757 he began to give clinical lectures at Edinburgh Royal Infirmary with
		  great success, and in 1766 he was elected Professor of the Theory (or
		  Institutes) of Physic. From 1768 he and his rival, Dr. John Gregory
		  (1724-1773), lectured in the Theory and the Practice of Physic in alternate
		  years, but on the death of Gregory in 1773 Cullen succeeded him and lectured
		  both, and became the mainstay of the Medical School for many years.</p> 
		<p>In the 1740s, Cullen made some discoveries on the evolution of heat in
		  chemical combination and the cooling of solutions which were published in 1755,
		  
		<title>Essay on the cold produced by evaporating fluids</title>. Other
		discoveries helped Black to reach his conclusions in relation to latent heat.
		Cullen took an active part in preparing a new edition of the 
		<title>Edinburgh Pharmacopoeia</title> (1774), and other principal works
		included 
		<title>Synopsis nosologiae methodicae</title> (1769), 
		<title>First lines of the practice of physic</title> (1776-1784), and 
		<title>The substance of nine lectures on vegetation and agriculture
		  delivered privately in 1768</title> (1796)</p> 
		<p>William Cullen resigned his Chair on 30 December 1789, and he died on
		  5 February 1790. He was buried at Kirknewton near his estate of Ormiston
		  Hill.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection of material around William Cullen M.D. cover the period
		  from his admission to the use of Edinburgh University Library, 1735, at Da.2.1,
		  p.60, to 1785-1787 and notes of lectures on the practice of physic at Dc.10.10.
		  The material also includes: correspondence at Dc.4.101 Cullen; correspondence
		  at E90.128 in the form of a postal prescription dated March 1780; lectures on
		  the practice of medicine, at Dk.3.54-62; chemistry lectures, 1757, at E95.04;
		  physiological and therapeutical observations, 1766-1767, at Dc.7.55; an
		  abstract of Cullen's lectures on agriculture, from around 1768, at Dc.3.70;
		  clinical lectures, 1772-1773, at Dk.3.49; notes of lectures from 1773, at
		  Dc.5.109-112; lectures on chemistry and pharmacy, at MS 3143; lectures from
		  1775, at Dc.1.49; and, commentaries on his 
		<title>First lines of the practice of physic</title>, 1783-1784, at Gen.
		1860-1861.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter at Dc.4.101-103 purchased July 1963, Accession no. E63.4/1.
		  Lectures at Dk.3.54-62 presented by Allen Thomson, 1866. Commentaries at
		  Gen.1860-1861 purchased from Mrs. Barnes, November 1970, Accession no. E70.53.
		  Notes at Dc.10.10 received from the Hope Bequest.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Leslie, Stephen, and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.5. Craik-Drake.
		London: Smith, Elder &amp;amp; Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Cullen related material
		  in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters or
		  signature in La.II.158; La.II.239, La.II.492, La.II.647/176, La.II.647/98,
		  La.III.375/49; and his being mentioned in letters of others, Dc.4.41/69,
		  Dc.4.101-103, Dk.7.52/78, Gen. 873/1/93-96, Gen. 874/V/17-18. Letter draft at
		  Gen. 873/111/61. Letter to Cullen at JA3452. There is also an account of Cullen
		  in Benjamin Rush's journal, 1766-1768, in Mic.M.28 ff.55-69, 74. In addition,
		  the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence and papers, 1737-1790, Royal
		  College of Physicians of Edinburgh, Ref. Cullen NRA 16015 Coll of Physicians;
		  correspondence, lectures and notes, Glasgow University Library, Special
		  Collections Department, NRA 20977 Glasgow Univ L; medical papers, ca.
		  1763-1772, Royal College of Physicians of London; medical MSS, Exeter Cathedral
		  Archives; lecture notes, Oxford University, Bodleian Library, Special
		  Collections and Western Manuscripts, Ref. MSS Eng misc d 298-306; lecture
		  notes, 1760-1775, Wellcome Library for the History and Understanding of
		  Medicine, Ref. MSS 1918-71; lecture notes, 1760, Northwestern University
		  Medical School Library; lecture notes, 1762-1763, Manchester University, John
		  Rylands Library, NRA 9194 Manchester scientif; lecture notes, 1763-1764,
		  Wellcome Library for the History and Understanding of Medicine, Ref. MS 5487;
		  1767-68: lecture notes, 1767-1768, University of Kansas, Clendening History of
		  Medicine Library; lecture notes, 1762-1772, National Library of Scotland,
		  Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 2078-83, 3472, 3535-37, 3543, 3759; lecture
		  notes, 1772-1773, National Library of Wales, Department of Manuscripts and
		  Records, Ref. JE Griffith MSS 19064 NRA 40906 Griffith; lecture notes, National
		  Library of Medicine.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physicians</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Cullen</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1710-1790</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physician </emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Remmett</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert Butler</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Hope</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas Charles</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1766-1844</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Chemist</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Johnson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Glasgow University</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
