<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-189 " countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-189 </eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor Andrew Dalzel
			 (1742-1806)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Dec 21 10:01:00 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-189 </unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 842; Gen. 1731 Dalzel; Dk.7.52; Dc.4.41/124; Dc.4.95/2,
		  f.4; La.II.185; La.II.583; La.II.648/285 </physloc><unittitle>Papers of
		  Professor Andrew Dalzel (1742-1806)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1763-1804">1763-1804</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box-file (circa 108 letters), 6 letters. </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The classical scholar Andrew Dalzel was born at Gateside on the
		  Newliston estate, Kirkliston, West Lothian, on 6 October 1742. He was educated
		  at the parish school in Kirkliston and then at Edinburgh University where he
		  graduated with an M.A. It was intended that Dalzel then enter the church but
		  after studying divinity he did not become licensed. On leaving the University
		  he became the tutor to the Lauderdale family. Dalzel and his pupils attended
		  lectures on civil law at Glasgow University and he assisted Alexander Adam,
		  Rector of the Royal High School, in the preparation of a Latin grammar. In 1772
		  he was appointed joint Professor of Greek at Edinburgh University, and in 1779
		  he became sole Professor on the death of the co-holder Robert Hunter. When
		  Dalzel was appointed, the teaching of Greek had reached a low point but he was
		  soon successful in turning standards around and attracting students. In 1783 he
		  assisted in the founding of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, and in 1789 he
		  obtained a grant of arms and a common seal for Edinburgh University which it
		  had never previously possessed. Dalzel resigned his chair in 1805 and was
		  succeeded by his assistant, George Dunbar (1774-1851). Professor Andrew Dalzel
		  died on 8 December 1806.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers consist of: lectures on Greek, 1803-1804; a large amount of
		  correspondence between Dalzel and his brother Archibald, 1763-1789; other
		  correspondence, 1800, 1802, 1804, and undated; and a note. There are also class
		  certificates, 1787, 1798, 1802, and 1804.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Lectures purchased 1966, Accession no. E66.18. Certificate purchased
		  March 1970, Accession no. E70.11. Certificate received February 1987, Accession
		  no. E87.24.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. London: Smith, Elder and
		Co., 1908. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Dalzel material (check the
		  Indexes for more details): mention of a play written by him, 1771, at
		  Dk.7.52/20-22; mention of his play, a prologue to Tamerlane, 1774, at
		  Dk.7.52/43, 50; mention of the change in spelling of surname, at Dk.7.52/70; a
		  mention of, 1784, at Dc.6.111, ff.17-18; a letter about his widow and children,
		  1809, at Dc.4.101-103. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA),
		  updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence with
		  Robert Liston, 1765-1794, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division,
		  Ref. MSS 5513-89.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Dalzel</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Andrew</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1742-1806</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Classical Scholar,
		  Historian</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
