<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-617" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-617</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Rt. Rev. Stanley Booth-Clibborn
			 (1924-1996)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Grame D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 16:50:21 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-617</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 44</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rt. Rev. Stanley
		  Booth-Clibborn (1924-1996)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1972-1993">1972-1993</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 files</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Booth-Clibborn, Stanley </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="swa">Swahili.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Stanley Eric Francis Booth-Clibborn, Church Missionary Society
		  missionary in Kenya and Bishop of Manchester, was born on 20 October 1924 into
		  the family that founded the Salvation Army. Throughout his life he sought to
		  combine his belief in Christianity with the promotion of social justice and the
		  support of the poor and oppressed. He spent four years in the army, including
		  two in India, then went to Oriel College, Oxford graduating BA (1951) and MA
		  (1956). In 1950 he had studied at Westcott House in Cambridge and in 1952 he
		  was ordained a deacon and a year later a priest. His first posts as a curate
		  were in Sheffield (1952-56) but he was then accepted as a missionary to
		  Kenya.</p> 
		<p>Booth-Clibborn arrived in Africa in 1956 where he was to have varied
		  ecumenical responsibilities included editing 
		<title>Rock</title> and 
		<title>Target</title>, influential church newspapers in East Africa. He
		was especially concerned to promote church unity and the development of the
		African church leadership during the political upheaval around the time of the
		Mau Mau rebellion.</p> 
		<p>On returning to England in 1967 Booth-Clibborn became a minister in
		  Lincoln but was also involved with the International Affairs Department of the
		  British Council of Churches, and his wife Anne (nee Forrester) was Vice-Chair
		  of Christian Aid for a time. He then moved to Cambridge in 1970 spending 9
		  years at St Mary the Great. From 1979 he was Bishop of Manchester and regarded
		  with great affection and respect even by those who disagreed with his with his
		  views, he was, for example, a strong supporter of women's ordination. He
		  retired in 1992 and went, with his wife, to live in Edinburgh. His interest in
		  Africa had continued and the Booth-Clibborns were invited by the National
		  Council of Churches in Kenya (NCCK), in co-operation with Christian Aid, to
		  monitor the 1992 Kenyan elections. He died on 6 March 1996. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists mainly of material relating to the
		  Booth-Clibborns' visit to Kenya to monitor the 1992 elections with reports,
		  briefings, press releases and cuttings and correspondence (1992-1993); also
		  includes other press cuttings and articles about Kenya (1972-1993); and some
		  material on the Africa Christian Press.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged as described above.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was presented to the Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World in the 1990s.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using (1) an obituary in 
		<title>The Guardian</title> that appeared shortly after Booth-Clibborn's
		death and (2) the entry in 
		<title>Crockford's Clerical Directory</title>. London, 1995-1996
		edition.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<head>Related Material</head> 
		<p>Coll-1063 containing 
		<title>Collection of Stanley Booth-Clibborn (1924-1996)</title> is
		located at Edinburgh University Library (Special Collections).</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial><!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Booth-Clibborn</emph> <emph
		  altrender="forename">Stanley</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1924-1996</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church Missionary Society</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Kenya</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
