<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-575" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-575</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Ragnhild Whiting (b. 1912) and Sister Marjorie
			 Raphael (b. 1923), Society of St Margaret, Haiti</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Nov 22 11:54:02 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-575</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 21</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Ragnhild Whiting (b.
		  1912) and Sister Marjorie Raphael (b. 1923), Society of St Margaret,
		  Haiti</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1956-1992">1956-1992</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Whiting, Ragnhild; Raphael, Marjorie</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> <language langcode="fre">French, </language> and
		  <language langcode="cpf">Other French-based Creoles and pidgins.</language>
		  </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Ragnhild Almquist Whiting (Rhon), Anglican physiotherapist and
		  missionary in Haiti, was born in Norway in 1912 and trained as a
		  physiotherapist there. She settled permanently in Canada in 1933 where she
		  married and raised two daughters. In 1962 she took a year's physiotherapy
		  course at McGill University and then worked as a physiotherapist until her
		  retirement in 1977, a year after the death of her husband. At that time she was
		  living in Windsor, Ontario and, in 1980, was sent by the Huron Diocese of the
		  Anglican church to Haiti to help in the orthopaedic clinic of St Vincent's
		  School for handicapped children in Port-au-Prince. The school was started by
		  the Society of St Margaret, an Episcopal religious community of women based in
		  Boston that first went to Haiti in 1927. Whiting returned to Haiti every year
		  for six to eight months at her own expense and from 1985 was an associate of St
		  Margaret's. During the remaining months she was in Canada giving talks and
		  attending events to raise money and interest in the Society and the work. In
		  1984 she helped to organise a Physiotherapy Association in Haiti and throughout
		  her time there she was involved in training and encouraging rehabilitation
		  workers. She was in Haiti during a period of political upheaval and was working
		  at the Hospital Sainte Croix, Leogane during the election of Aristide in 1990.
		  Whiting left Haiti for the last time in 1991. She was awarded an honorary
		  degree from the University of Windsor in 1990. Sister Marjorie Raphael was born
		  on 17 October 1923. She was a member of the Society of St Margaret and worked
		  in Haiti from 1955 to 1963 and from 1978 to 1994, often based at St Margaret's
		  convent in Port-au-Prince. Both Whiting and Raphael were still alive in
		  2001.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of two main series: (1) Ragnhild Whiting
		  material which includes: biographical information on Whiting (1986-1990); diary
		  and journal entries by Whiting describing her work in Haiti (1980-1991); notes
		  for talks and addresses given by Whiting on Haiti (1985-1990); material for a
		  biography of Whiting by her daughter mainly abstracts from journals and letters
		  (1980-1992); letters to Whiting about her work (1986-1991); newsletters,
		  pamphlets and circulars relating to St Margaret's and Haiti (1986-1991); and
		  press cuttings on Haiti (1986-1991); and (2) Sister Marjorie Raphael material:
		  newsletters and circular letters from Raphael at St Margaret's Convent in Haiti
		  (1956-1989).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is in three files arranged as described above.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>The material was collected by Kari Morris, daughter of Ragnhild
		  Whiting, either from material sent to her by her mother or from material sent
		  by Sister Raphael.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was donated to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World circa early 1990s by Kari Morris from Aberdeen.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself, (2) the web pages of the Society of St Margaret, and
		  (3) information from Sister Marjorie Raphael.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The main offices of the Society of St Margaret are in Boston, America,
		  where they hold a great deal of material about Haiti.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p>Some of Whiting's journal entries were used by her daughter as a basis
		  for a draft biography, the manuscript of which is in the collection.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Whiting</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Ragnhild A</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b
		  1912</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Raphael</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Marjorie </emph> <emph altrender="dates">b
		  1923</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Society of St Margaret</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Haiti</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
