<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-71"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-71
		</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Certificates,
			 Diplomas, etc of Principal William Robertson (1721-1793) </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-71</unitid>
		
		<physloc>PC 2.1-9; PC 3.10-14 </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Certificates, Diplomas, etc of
		  Principal William Robertson (1721-1793) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1743-1783">1743-1783 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>14 items, 1
		  pair spectacles (in 2 plan chest drawers). </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Principal of Edinburgh University and historian, Sir William
		  Robertson, was born on 19 September 1721 at the manse in Borthwick, Midlothian,
		  where his father was minister. He received his early education at the parish
		  school in Borthwick and then at the Burgh School in Dalkeith. In the autumn of
		  1733, Robertson entered the University of Edinburgh studying Arts and Divinity.
		  After completion of his studies and earning his license to preach, he became
		  minister of Gladsmuir in East Lothian in 1743. With the approach to Edinburgh
		  of the Jacobite army in 1745, Robertson left his manse to offer his services,
		  with some others, to Sir John Cope against the Rebellion. However, Cope
		  declined to admit them. In 1746, Robertson was elected as member to the General
		  Assembly of the Church of Scotland. This indicated steady advancement in his
		  career. In 1753 he began work on a long writing project on the history of
		  Scotland which culminated in his 
		<title>History of Scotland </title> (1759). The work was a great success
		and shortly before its publication he received the degree of Doctor of Divinity
		from Edinburgh University. Shortly after publication of his work he was
		successively appointed Chaplain of Stirling Castle and Chaplain Royal in 1759,
		elected joint-minister of Greyfriars Church in Edinburgh in 1761, became
		Principal of the University in 1762, and in 1764 was appointed Historiographer
		Royal for Scotland. His next literary work was the 
		<title>History of Charles V </title> (1769) which enhanced his reputation
		in Europe and earned him praise from Voltaire and the Empress Catherine of
		Russia. His last great work was the 
		<title>History of America </title> (1777). His life was also filled by
		his work with the affairs of the General Assembly and with those of Edinburgh
		University. The initiative to rebuild the University - Old College - owed its
		origins to the influence of Robertson. He had launched a public appeal which
		won the support of successive Town Councils and Lords Provost, and he managed
		to secure the services of the architect Robert Adam. In 1791, Robertson's
		health began to decline and he died of jaundice on 11 June 1793 </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>Among a number of interesting certificates and diplomas, the
		  collection includes Robertson's commission as Principal of the University,
		  1762; his Royal appointment as Historiographer, 1763; a diploma of foreign
		  membership of the St. Petersburg Academy of Sciences, 1783; and, his
		  spectacles. The items are in vellum of various sizes, and often with paper or
		  wax seals. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.5./marc 541"> 
		<p>Deposited in 1989 by Lt.-Commander David Robertson-Macdonald, April
		  1989 and made a gift in 1992. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Robertson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1721-1793</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh
		  University</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Church of
		  Scotland</emph> <emph altrender="x">General Assembly</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Greyfriars
		  Church</emph> <emph altrender="z">Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Historians</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">History</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>Handlist, H71; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts shows at various shelfmarks letters of
		  William Robertson to different individuals; and, accounts of his stipend at
		  Gladsmuir. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
