<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-606" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-606</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Thomas Colvin (1925-2000)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 08:52:58 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-606</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 39</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Thomas Colvin
		  (1925-2000)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1890-2001">[ca. 1890]-2001</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 boxes and 1 file </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Colvin, Thomas Stevenson</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="nya"> Chichewa or Chewa or
		  Nyanja.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Thomas Stevenson Colvin (Tom), Church of Scotland missionary in Malawi
		  and Ghana, was born in Glasgow on 16 April 1925. He attended the Royal
		  Technical College, Glasgow (now Strathclyde University) where he was chairman
		  of the Student Christian Movement and from where he graduated B.Sc. in 1945.
		  After a period with the Royal Engineers in Burma and Singapore, Colvin returned
		  to Scotland in 1948 to become student assistant minister at Fallin Parish
		  Church in Stirling. Later in the same year he began a three year course in
		  divinity at Trinity College, Glasgow, was again an active member of student
		  bodies, and held the post of president of the SCM. He spent a year after
		  leaving Glasgow as the Travelling Secretary of the SCM, then between 1952 and
		  1954 was Youth Secretary of the Iona Community.</p> 
		<p>In 1954 Colvin was ordained as a minister and appointed a missionary
		  to Malawi (Nyasaland) where he was headmaster of Henry Henderson Institute,
		  associate minister of Blantyre church and education secretary of Blantyre
		  Synod. On the integration of Blantyre mission into the Synod in 1958 Colvin was
		  appointed General Secretary but was unable to take up the post as the Welensky
		  government declared him a prohibited immigrant. Colvin and his wife Patricia
		  (Patsy, n&#x00E9;e McGregor), whom he had married in 1955, were forced to leave
		  Malawi. In 1959 they went to Ghana with the Church of Scotland where Colvin was
		  district pastor at Tamale, Northern Ghana. In Ghana Colvin was noted for his
		  pioneering ecumenical programme of community development which he saw as a
		  complement to evangelistic outreach and he was Organising Secretary of the
		  Christian Service Committee of Northern Ghana.</p> 
		<p>In 1964 the Colvins were recalled to Malawi and Tom Colvin became
		  development adviser to the Synod, being responsible for programmes to develop
		  lay and clerical leadership training and directing the formation and growth of
		  the Christian Service Committee. The CSC in Malawi, which from 1968 included
		  the Roman Catholic church, was an attempt to encourage community development by
		  Christians and to involve them in all levels of society and social planning and
		  aid, in co-operation with secular bodies. Colvin was also involved in MEND (the
		  movement of ecumenical action in national development), held the post of
		  Secretary of the Christian Council of Malawi (1965-1967), and undertook many
		  pastoral duties such as the chaplaincy of the University of Malawi. In 1974 the
		  Colvins retired from Malawi but during 1975 Colvin made several return trips to
		  Africa on a survey for the All Africa Conference.</p> 
		<p>From 1976 to 1984 he was warden and leader of ministry at Sydenham
		  United Free Church in south-east London and particularly involved in urban
		  community development. His experience and skills meant that he was frequently
		  called on to give advice about the church in Africa and in 1984 he was
		  appointed by the World Council of Churches and seconded to the Zimbabwe
		  Christian Council as development consultant. The Colvins returned to Malawi
		  with the Church of Scotland for three years in 1987 and, despite retiring in
		  1990, Colvin continued to advise on development projects throughout Africa and
		  spent short periods in various countries. He revisited Malawi several times in
		  the 1990s to advise on policy making and provide training for church leaders
		  involved in relief and development. Colvin's promotion of the role of the
		  church in development was not restricted to writing reports or organising
		  committees. He was involved in many practical projects, organising relief for
		  victims of famine and refugees and initiating various building, agriculture and
		  health projects in villages and urban communities. Colvin was also noted for
		  his interest in African music and hymns. He was concerned with helping the
		  African church to use their own musical heritage in worship and to write hymns
		  arising from the African context.</p> 
		<p>His publications on Africa include several books of hymns as well as
		  books on the mission and church in Africa. Colvin died in Edinburgh on 24
		  February 2000.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of three main sections (1) personal items and
		  early mission history; (2) Colvins in Malawi 1954-1958; and (3) Colvins in
		  Malawi 1964-1974. Section (1) includes: personal items on Colvin such as his
		  c.v.; and material on early mission and church history including publications
		  and early accounts and photographs (1890s-1976). Section (2) includes: mission
		  and church reports and papers (1950s); letters to the Colvins around the time
		  that they were excluded from Malawi, including letters from Hastings Banda in
		  Ghana (1957-1960); photographs (c 1952-1959); and publications on Nyasaland
		  (1951-1956). Section (3) includes: material relating to Colvin's role as
		  Blantyre Synod Development Adviser covering the training of ministers, church
		  funding, Synod committees and early Christian Service schemes (1962-1966); some
		  material relating to Presbyteries and schools (1964-1967); papers and
		  photographs recording the development of the Christian Service Committee, the
		  Utumiki Project and the MEND seminars (1966-1975); notes, publications and
		  other material on liturgy and hymns (1958-1976); photographs (1960s-1970s); and
		  general publications on Malawi and Africa. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material was partly arranged and annotated by Patricia Colvin
		  before she deposited it and the papers relating to Colvin's role as Blantyre
		  Synod development adviser were in his original files. The items have been
		  removed from their original folders and the photographs from their albums for
		  reasons of preservation but the arrangements, captions and file titles have
		  been kept.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The material was presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World by Patricia Colvin in 2001. Mrs Colvin spent some time
		  arranging and annotating the material before depositing it.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using (1) the collection itself,
		  and (2) information supplied by Patricia Colvin.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the foreign missions of the Church of Scotland are
		  held by the National Library of Scotland. Edinburgh University Special
		  Collections has some collections relating to the early years of the Malawi
		  missions. The Centre also holds the papers of Richard Baxter, Church of
		  Scotland missionary in Malawi.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Colvin</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas S.</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1925-2000</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland </emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
