<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-447" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-447</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of James Nasmyth (1808-1890)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Sep 20 14:26:38 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-447</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen.1732 Nasmyth; Dc.4.101-103
		  Nasmyth</physloc><unittitle>Letters of James Nasmyth (1808-1890)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1845-1855">1845-1855</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 letters</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Nasmyth, the inventor of the steam hammer, was born at York
		  Place, Edinburgh, on 19 August 1808. He was educated privately and, for a time,
		  at the Royal High School. He was taught drawing by his father and he became
		  skilled at handling tools. He made a small steam-engine and made models of
		  steam-engines to be used for illustrative purposes by mechanics institutes. In
		  1821 he became a student and his model-making business supported him in his
		  studies. Nasmyth was commissioned to build a steam-carriage and in 1827-1828 it
		  was tried out on roads in and around Edinburgh. In 1829 he went to London - to
		  Lambeth - to work for the engineers Henry Maudslay (inventor of the metal
		  lathe) and Joshua Field, and stayed there until 1831. While in the employment
		  of Maudslay he invented the nut-shaping machine. He returned to Edinburgh and
		  made tools and machines before setting up in business in Manchester, laying the
		  foundations of what became Bridgewater Foundry. His steam-hammer came about in
		  1839 in association with his work for the new steamship 'Great Britain' under
		  construction at Bristol. Nasmyth also suggested the use of a submerged chain
		  for towing boats on rivers and canals, and contrived a hydraulic
		  punching-machine capable of making a hole in a block of iron five inches thick.
		  He was also interested in astronomy and in 1827 constructed a small reflecting
		  telescope. James Nasmyth died in South Kensington, London, on 7 May 1890. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The correspondence is composed of: a letter of Nasmyth to the Duc du
		  Roussillon about astronomical papers, cuneiform script etc, 1855; and, a letter
		  to Haigh Foundry Co., about the method of working the hammer, 1845.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter to Haigh Foundry, noted as acquired March 1966, but note
		  subsequently crossed out, Accession no. E66.13. Letter to Roussillon, purchased
		  June 1968, Accession no. E68.21.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 14. Myllar-Owen.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: autobiography, Unknown location, see A microfilm
		  is in Eccles Central Library; correspondence and drawings, Edinburgh Central
		  Library; correspondence and sketchbook, Institution of Mechanical Engineers
		  Library, NRA 9515 Mechanical Engineers; correspondence and drawings among
		  papers of Samuel Smiles, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MSS
		  71070-93; sketches, 1821-1885, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts
		  Division, Ref. MSS 3241-43, and letters (17) to Henry Bicknell, 1859-1879, Ref.
		  MS 11000; letters (4 vols) to Sir John Anderson, 1872-1880, Aberdeen Central
		  Library, Ref. NRA(S)3542 NRA 38831 Aberdeen CL; letters (13) to Sir John
		  Herschel, 1845-1871, Royal Society, Ref. HS NRA 8803 Herschel; and,
		  correspondence 1848-1889, Salford City Archives, Ref. U312 NRA 33747
		  Nasmyth.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Nasmyth</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1808-1890</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Engineer </emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
