<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid publicid="GB 237 Coll-894" countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237">GB
		237 Coll-894</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt>
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="">Notes on the Practice of
			 Physic</titleproper>
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by JavaScript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2 on 
		  <date>Thu Jan 20 09:45:43 UTC 2005</date>.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-894</unitid> 
		<physloc>E2003.12</physloc><unittitle>Notes on the Practice of
		  Physic</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1850-1851">1850-1851</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 volume mss, 1 sheaf supporting notes in
		  typescript.</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English</language>
		  </langmaterial> 
		<origination>Graves, William H. Y; Fotherby, Henry Isaac; Burditt,
		  William Fotherby</origination> 
	 </did> 
	 <phystech> 
		<p>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted</p> 
	 </phystech> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Physic was the art of healing diseases; the science of medicine; the
		  theory or practice of medicine. The medical 
		<title>Notes on the Practice of Physic</title> in question here were
		written in Edinburgh in 1850-1851. The item has eight printed pages, being 
		<title>Syllabus of examinations on medical subjects</title>, printed by
		John Muir, West Register Street, in Edinburgh. The remainder of the book
		contains pages of handwritten notes covering the practice of physic which was
		section 3 of the syllabus.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The medical notes were written 1850-1851. The lecturers were Sellers,
		  Alison, and Home, though one lecture was by Southwood Smith. The notes are
		  unsigned and there are two different sets of handwriting. The volume of
		  manuscript is supported with a transcript - typescript document.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>The material belonged to William Fotherby Burditt who lived in
		  Lincolnshire and Leicestershire, England. His father was the Rev. Thomas
		  Burditt, a Baptist minister from Tenby in Wales. William Fotherby Burditt
		  emigrated to Canada in 1868, settling in St. John, New Burnswick. he became a
		  businessman, selling farm machinery. There had been two doctors in the family
		  earlier however. William H. Y. Graves and Henry Isaac Fotherby. These men were
		  the uncle and brother of Burditt's mother, Anne Maria Fotherby. It is entirely
		  possible that some of the notes were written by the younger of these two
		  men.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material gifted by Anna Mary Burditt, May 2002, Accession no.
		  E2003.12.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material
		  contained in the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <processinfo> 
		<p>Compiled by Graeme D. Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
		  Collections Division.</p> 
	 </processinfo>
    <!-- Controlled Access Terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Medicine</emph> </subject> 
		<subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Note-taking</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Burditt</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William Fotherby</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1849-1931</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">New Brunswick
		  businessman</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Fotherby</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Henry Isaac</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1822-1905
		  </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Doctor</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Graves</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William H. Y.</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1799-1853</emph> <emph altrender="epithet"> Doctor</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
