<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-776" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-776</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Henry Barker (d. 1948)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Mar 2 10:52:14 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-776</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS BAR. 1.1-23; MSS BAR. 2.1-20</physloc><unittitle>Papers of
		  Henry Barker (d. 1948)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1899-1935">1899-1935</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 410 leaves or sheets, 8 bundles notes, 5
		  volumes, and miscellaneous. </extent> <physfacet> Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Barker, Henry</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Henry Barker had been an Assistant and Lecturer in Moral Philosophy at
		  Edinburgh University, 1898-1934, and Lecturer in Social Ethics 1919-1934. He
		  held the degrees of MA, from Edinburgh University, 1891, and from Cambridge.
		  Henry Barker died on 19 December 1948.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: a dissertation on the problem of
		  theological method in its bearing on philosophy; items on the connection
		  between ethical theory and a religious view of the world, and the science of
		  ethics from the standpoint of realism; material on philosophy and theology,
		  Ritschlian theology, the religious consciousness, faith, and the nature and
		  origin of Christian experience; an unpublished article on anthropomorphism;
		  material on the moral teaching of the Gospels; Kemp Smith material on spiritual
		  values; material on the Church and state; Balfour's 
		<title>Foundations of belief</title>; material on contrasts between
		philosophy and religion, the duty of religious inquiry, and belief; a lecture
		course to theological students 
		<title>The state in philosophical and Christian ethics</title> 1919-1920;
		the seat of authority in religion, the Church, the authority of the Church, and
		the basis of the Church's authority; Schism; and, the idela of the Church.
		There is also: lecture notes for Summer and Honours ethics, 1919-1926; lecture
		notes on the moral standard and its problems; material on Butler; material on
		hedonism, the definition of philosophy, Berkeley's theory of vision, psychology
		of will, psychology of belief, and St. Paul's view of the Christian life;
		material on the difficulties of a teleological conception of the universe,
		examination of objections to the teleological argument, difficulties in forming
		a system of Christian ethics; and, notes and annotations on Isaiah, factors in
		the efficiency of religious belief, and Christian dogmatics.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Obituary 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 14. 1946-1949.
		p.272. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1949.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes of Special Collections Division, Edinburgh
		  University library, George Square, show various references to Barker related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): correspondence with J.B.
		  Baillie, B. Bosanquet, C.D. Broad, A.C. Fraser, G.D. Hicks, J.H. Muirhead, H.
		  Sidgwick, G.F. Stout and J. Ward, 1898-1932, at Dc.6.118; Shaw Fellowship
		  lectures, circa 1897, entitled 
		<title>The present relations of theology and philosophy. A critical
		  examination of theological methods</title>, at Dc.6.117, and lectures on Kant
		and Hegel, delivered at Edinburgh University 1898-1906. Also some papers on
		miscellaneous philosophical topics, circa 1900-1910, at Dk.6.9/1-2.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ethics</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Philosophy</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theology</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Barker</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Henry</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d. 1948</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Lecturer in Moral Philosophy</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
