<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-269" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-269</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Scottish Council for African
			 Questions</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Aug 15 11:32:18 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-269</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS 2495-2497</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Scottish
		  Council for African Questions</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1950-1979">1950s-1970s</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Scottish Council for African Questions was founded in 1952 at a
		  time when many countries administered by Britain were achieving independence.
		  The Council was a secular body and was not affiliated to any political party.
		  Anyone resident in Scotland or with a Scottish connection was entitled to
		  become a member. The aims of the Council were to strengthen and further the
		  best traditions of Britain's policy in relation to Africa, to promote in
		  Scotland a fuller understanding of the aspirations of the people of Africa, and
		  to promote in Britain policies ensuring the economic and social development and
		  the equitable political rights of all communities in Africa. Honorary
		  Presidents of the Council have been Sir John Boyd-Orr (1880-1971), Nobel Peace
		  Laureate, and Sir Jo Grimond (1913-1993). The Scottish Council for African
		  Questions was wound up on 6 November 1976. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The unsorted records of the Scottish Council for African Questions
		  includes, in MS 2495, typescript and manuscript documents on Central Africa,
		  copies of the 
		<title>Newsletter. The Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland</title>, and
		newspapers and newspaper clippings. In MS 2496 there is a selection of
		journals, government reports, parliamentary debates, and colonial reports, for
		example 
		<title>Northern Rhodesia</title> 1951, 
		<title>Nyasaland</title> 1957, 
		<title>Northern Rhodesia. Proposals for constitutional change</title>
		Cmnd 530. 1958, and 
		<title>Report of the Nyasaland commission of enquiry</title> Cmnd 814.
		1959. In MS 2497 there are bundles of correspondence, newspaper cuttings,
		typescript and manuscript documents on southern Africa, Rhodesia, and other
		parts of Africa. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative history was compiled using material contained
		  within the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Council for African
		  Questions</emph> <emph altrender="y">1952 - 1976</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Zimbabwe</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
