<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-551" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-551</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters and Papers of Professor James Lorrain Smith
			 (1912-1931)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Apr 7 11:10:23 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-551</unitid> 
		<physloc>E93.17; E98.20; E98.22</physloc><unittitle>Letters and Papers of
		  Professor James Lorrain Smith (1912-1931)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1880-1926">1880-1926</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 12 letters, 1 bundle typescript notes. </extent>
		  <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Smith, James Lorrain</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Lorrain Smith was born in 1912. He took the degree of D.Sc. at
		  Manchester and the degrees of M.A. and M.D. at Edinburgh. He also studied at
		  Oxford and became associated with John Scott Haldane (1860-1936) and his work
		  on respiration and allied subjects. Smith was Professor of Pathology and Dean
		  of the Faculty of Medicine, Edinburgh University. While at Edinburgh he made
		  observations on fatty degeneration. He had also been Professor of Pathology at
		  Queen's College, Belfast, and Professor of Pathology at Manchester University.
		  With John Scott Haldane (1860-1936), he was involved in the publication of 
		<title>The absorption of oxygen by the lungs</title> (1897). Professor
		James Lorrain Smith died on 18 April 1931.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material consists of: copies of letters to James Thomas Wilson,
		  1880-1891; letters to James Thomas Wilson, 1888-1891, also the memorandum 
		<title>An inquiry into pathology</title>; and, copy of the transcript of
		autobiography entitled 
		<title>Boyhood in Half Morton House</title> notes of which were written
		in 1926.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Wilson letters, acquired from Dr. Max Wilson, 1993, Accession no.
		  E93.17. Wilson letters, acquired from Dr. J. M. G. Wilson, 1998, Accession no.
		  E98.20. Autobiography transcript, acquired from Dr. J. M. G. Wilson, Accession
		  no. E98.22.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>Who was who 1929-1940</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black,
		1941. (2) 'Obituary'. 
		<title>Edinburgh University journal</title>. Vol. 4. 1930-1931.
		pp.170-173.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The Division also has material relating to the Faculty of Science at
		  shelfmark Da.45.12 and Da.45.15, being the Faculty of Science Minute book for
		  1918-1921, which includes letters and reports, covering subjects such as
		  courses, students, research grants and appointments. Those present at meetings
		  included Sir Thomas Hudson Beare, James Lorrain Smith, James Cossar Ewart and
		  Thomas John Jehu. Also, the Faculty of Science Minute Book, 1929-1932, which
		  includes letters and reports, covering subjects such as courses, students,
		  research grants and appointments. Those present at meetings included Sir Thomas
		  Hudson Beare, Sir William Wright Smith, James Lorrain Smith, Henry Briggs and
		  Thomas John Jehu. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Pathologists</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Smith</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James Lorrain </emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1912-1931</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of
		  Pathology</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
