<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-433" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-433</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Correspondence relating to Robert Saunders Dundas, 2nd
			 Viscount Melville (1771-1851)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Sep 5 12:06:32 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-433</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.8.4/3; Gen. 1790, nos.78-81; Gen. 1875, nos.77-79; Gen.
		  1982/46</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence relating to Robert Saunders Dundas,
		  2nd Viscount Melville (1771-1851)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1816-1834">1816-1834</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>6 letters, 2 engravings</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Robert Saunders Dundas was born on 14 March 1771. He was the only son
		  of Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742-1811) - 'Henry the Ninth, the
		  uncrowned King of Scotland'. He was educated at the Royal High School. Dundas
		  entered Parliament as M.P. for Hastings in 1794, and had received his first
		  taste of political life as Private Secretary to his father who was Secretary of
		  State for War and the Colonies and President of the Board of Control for the
		  Affairs of India, 1794-1801. In 1796 he became M.P. for Rye. His first official
		  appointment was that of Keeper of the Signet for Scotland in 1800. In 1801
		  Dundas was M.P. for Midlothian, his father's former constituency. He began to
		  make his mark in the Commons in 1805 and 1806 when he spoke up in support of
		  his father who was criticised and impeached for 'high crimes and misdemeanours'
		  while Treasurer of the Navy. In 1807 he became a member of the Privy Council
		  and President of the Board of Control in the Cabinet formed by the Duke of
		  Portland. In 1809 he was Secretary for Ireland for a brief period and then was
		  back at the Board of Control during the Perceval administration. In 1811,
		  Dundas succeeded his father as 2nd Viscount Melville, and the same year he
		  became Lord Privy Seal in Scotland. In 1812, he was appointed First Lord of the
		  Admiralty by Lord Liverpool. While at the Admiralty he became particularly
		  interested in Arctic affairs which was acknowledged when Melville Sound was
		  named after him. After the death of Lord Liverpool he refused to serve in
		  Canning's government, but was re-appointed to the Admiralty when the Duke of
		  Wellington took office. He retired from political life in 1830. Earlier, in
		  1821, Dundas had been made a Knight of the Thistle. Robert Dundas, 2nd Viscount
		  Melville, died at Melville Castle, Edinburgh, on 10 June 1851. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The correspondence is composed of: a letter to N. Auld, 1816; a letter
		  to Capt. Dillon, 1819; a letter to Sir Patrick Walker requesting him to call at
		  the Admiralty, 1820; a letter to Rear-Admiral Otway with instructions of what
		  to do in case of the death of Queen Caroline, 1821; letter to T. Dench, 1821;
		  and, a letter to Messrs. Spottiswoode and Robertson about coal-weighing, 1834.
		  There is also an engraving, and a franked postal cover to Messrs. Drummond,
		  1823, with a signed engraving of Viscount Melville.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Micellaneous letters, purchased 1964, Accession no. E64.6.
		  Miscellaneous letters, purchased June 1971, Accession no. E71.17.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.6. Drant-Finan.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Robert Dundas related
		  material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters
		  to H. Warrender, 1808, 1809, at La.II.294/7-8; letter to Capt. J. Ross R.N.
		  about his remuneration for expenses incurred during his last voyage to the
		  north coast of America, 1834, at La.II.647/275; and, letter to Sir G.
		  Warrender, at La.II.509. There are also letters to Robert Dundas from A.
		  Lindsay, 6th Earl of Balcarres, at Dk.7.63, nos.6-8.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes the following collections in
		  Scottish public and academic institutions: correspondence and papers, National
		  Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD51 NRA 10188 Dundas, and family and personal
		  correspondence, 1783-1849, Ref. GD235/10 NRA 34965 Bonar Mackenzie, and
		  correspondence with Sir George Clerk, 1831-1848, Ref. GD18 NRA 29182 Clerk, and
		  letters to Thomas, Lord Cochrane, Ref. GD233 NRA 8150 Cochrane, and letters
		  (14) to Lord Dalhousie, 1835-1847, Ref. GD45 NRA 17164 Ramsay, see NRA(S)0805,
		  and letters to Sir Alexander Hope, 1810-1825, Ref. GD364 NRA 10172 Hope, see
		  NRA(S)1021, and correspondence with J. A. Stewart-Mackenzie, 1821-1828, Ref.
		  GD46 NRA 30101 Stewart-Mackenzie, and correspondence with Duke of Wellington,
		  see Annual report 1983; correspondence and papers, National Library of
		  Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. passim, and miscellaneous correspondence,
		  1807-1830, Ref. MSS 6524, 7199 Passim, and correspondence, mostly on Indian
		  affairs, 1790-1838, Ref. Acc 12001, and correspondence with Sir Alexander
		  Cochrane, 1812-1825, Ref. MSS 2264-68, 2574-76, and letters (29) from Frederick
		  Augustus, Duke of York to him and his father, 1798-1823, see Accessions to
		  repositories 1990, and correspondence with Lord Keith, 1812-1815, Ref. MSS
		  9733-34, and correspondence with John Lee, 1811-1846, Ref. MSS 3433-45 passim,
		  and correspondence with Sir David Milne and Earl of Seafield, 1818-1820, Ref.
		  MS 9735, and correspondence with Lord Minto, 1807-1812, Ref. MSS 11289-90,
		  11302-03 NRA 10476 Minto, and correspondence with Sir Walter Scott, 1806-1829,
		  Ref. MSS 3875-910 passim, and miscellaneous correspondence including Lord
		  Rutherfurd, Thomas Graham Stirling and John Borthwick of Crookston, 1808-1851,
		  Ref. MSS 9697-10683, 10218-10958 Passim; correspondence as Governor of the Bank
		  of Scotland, Bank of Scotland Archives, Ref. BS 20/32 NRA 41517 Dundas;
		  correspondence and papers relating to Scotland, St Andrews University Library,
		  NRA 14799 Dundas; correspondence with Balfour family, 1820-1837, Orkney
		  Archives, Ref. NRA(S)0627 NRA 16075 Balfour; and letters to Robert Christie,
		  1833-1837, Edinburgh Central Library, Ref. NRA(S)3563 NRA 38890 Edinburgh
		  CL.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Saunders-Dundas</emph> <emph
		  altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1771-1851</emph>
		  <emph altrender="title">2nd Viscount Melville</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">statesman</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">19th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
