<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-207" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-207</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of John William Arthur (1881-1952)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Apr 26 10:59:39 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-207</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 762-765, Phot.Ill.92-97</physloc><unittitle>Papers of John
		  William Arthur (1881-1952)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1902-1954">1902-1954</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 boxes, 6 volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="kik">Kikuyu or Gikuyu.</language>
		  </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John William Arthur, Church of Scotland medical missionary in East
		  Africa, was born in Glasgow in 1881 the son of John W. Arthur, a Glasgow
		  businessman. He was educated at Glasgow Academy and at Glasgow University from
		  where he graduated M.B. Ch.B. in 1903 and took his M.D. in 1906. He was
		  appointed to the post of medical missionary at the Kikuyu Mission, British East
		  Africa (Kenya), in 1906, arriving at the mission on 1 January 1907. He opened
		  the mission's first hospital and also became involved with its evangelical and
		  educational work. Arthur succeeded Dr Henry E. Scott as head of the mission on
		  the latter's death in 1911 and, after his ordination in 1915, he concentrated
		  increasingly on ministerial rather than medical practice. He oversaw the
		  mission during a period of notable growth, when he joined the mission staff
		  there were no baptised Christians among the Kikuyu, by the time of his
		  retirement the members of the Christian community numbered nearly 11,000. One
		  of the many Africans influenced by Arthur and the mission was Jomo Kenyatta.
		  During the First World War Arthur organised the Kikuyu Missions' Volunteer
		  Carrier Corps for service in German East Africa and became the commanding
		  officer. He was awarded the OBE in 1920 for his services. Arthur came to be
		  accepted as one of the foremost spokesmen of missionary opinion in East Africa
		  and worked enthusiastically for inter-mission co-operation. He also worked with
		  the colonial government, applying pressure from within for reforms. He was a
		  close advisor of J.H. Oldham and was involved in the conference in London in
		  1923 that declared the paramountcy of African interests in Kenya. He sat on
		  various councils and served, from 1924-1926, as representative of African
		  interests on the Legislative Council of Kenya and from 1928-1929 on the Kenyan
		  Executive Council. Arthur was particularly concerned with problems of
		  education, land ownership and labour reforms, and was involved in debates over
		  the practice of female circumcision. From 1929 Arthur sought to strengthen the
		  mission's resistance to the practice but his call for sanctions against
		  Christians who practised it caused a Kikuyu reaction which adversely affected
		  the membership of the church. Arthur resigned from the Legislative Council and
		  his reputation as a voice of African interests was damaged. He retired in April
		  1937 and acted for a period as personal assistant at St Columba's (Church of
		  Scotland), Pont Street, London. He then served as minister of Dunbog, Fife, a
		  post which he held for around ten years. When he retired from Dunbog, Arthur
		  took up residence in Edinburgh acting as locum tenes at the Tron Church for a
		  year and spent the last year of his life as chaplain to the Astley-Ainslie
		  Hospital. During his later years Arthur gave a number of interviews and papers
		  on Kenya and East Africa, writing, for example, 
		<title>East Africa in Transition</title> in 1942. He returned to Kenya
		briefly in 1948 for the jubilee celebrations of the Church of Scotland mission.
		Arthur was a noted athlete and mountaineer. Whilst in Kenya he devoted most of
		his spare time to mountaineering and became president of the mountain club of
		East Africa. He married in 1921. He received an honorary degree of D.D. from
		the University of St Andrews in 1946. John William Arthur died in Edinburgh in
		1952 at the age of 71.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists mainly of correspondence and papers
		  (1907-1949) including letters from Arthur to his mother; circular letters and
		  newsletters from the Kikuyu mission; sections from Arthur's diaries and notes
		  on his travels throughout East Africa; reports on missionary conferences;
		  memoranda by Arthur and others on native affairs such as the labour question,
		  land tenure, education and female circumcision; minutes, memoranda and papers
		  of the Kikuyu Association and the Kikuyu Mission Council; and papers relating
		  to parliamentary commissions and court cases, and to Arthur's position as an
		  unofficial member of the Kenyan Executive Council. The collection also includes
		  printed pamphlets, journals, articles and ordinances on native questions, the
		  mission and East Africa in general (1902-1954); press cuttings (1918-1952); and
		  photographs of Kenya, the mission, and individuals (1907-1916). </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged in four boxes, the first two (Gen. 762-763)
		  contain most of the papers and correspondence arranged in roughly chronological
		  order with a file of 'undated' material (Gen. 763/45-66), the third box (Gen.
		  764) consists mainly of printed pamphlets and articles, and the fourth box
		  (Gen. 765) of press cuttings. Six albums of photographs (Photo. ill. 92-97) are
		  stored separately.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>After Arthur's death the Reverend Robert Macpherson, also a missionary
		  in Kenya, reported that Arthur had left two large boxes of papers. Macpherson
		  separated these into personal and mission papers, and arranged the latter into
		  four groups and listed them (see Gen. 762 and Gen. 763/45-46). A decision as to
		  the eventual disposal of the documents was postponed. Very few of the items on
		  Macpherson's list seem to be in the collection at Edinburgh University. It is
		  likely that the original collection, some of which related to the mission
		  before the arrival of Arthur, including the Kibwezi phase, and to other
		  missionaries, such as to David Clement Scott, was split either before or after
		  its arrival at Edinburgh. According to Dr Brian McIntosh in his doctoral thesis
		  
		<title>The Scottish Mission in Kenya 1891-1923</title> (Edinburgh
		University, 1969) the Arthur papers were shorn of any document of a
		controversial or personal nature before they were deposited.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to Edinburgh University by Arthur's wife in
		  1964 through Professor George Shepperson, Professor of Commonwealth and
		  American History at the University of Edinburgh.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <altformavail> 
		<p>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections has microfilm copies
		  of the collection (Mic. Dup. 82, 355, 1275 and 1740) and a copy was sent to the
		  Kenyan High Commission in 1982.</p> 
	 </altformavail> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) an undated newspaper obituary (Gen. 765/51). (2) Church of Scotland Foreign
		  Missionary Council resolution, 19 July 1938 (Gen. 763/25). (3) 
		<title>Bibliographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>,
		Anderson, G.H. (ed.). New York: Macmillan Reference USA, 1998.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University
		  Library, Special Collections and Archives. A list of Arthur Papers is filed in
		  Gen. 763 but does not relate to the papers surviving in this collection. Also
		  in Gen. 763 is 
		<title>Documents on East African Social and Political Affairs</title>.
		This lists (not in order) most of the reports, memoranda and other items
		concerning Africa in the collection. The collection is mentioned in the
		Edinburgh University Library subject checklist (C3) 
		<title>Manuscripts on Africa</title>.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Mrs Arthur also presented to Edinburgh University Library in 1963 a
		  printed bound collection of her husband's circular letters from the mission
		  (1907-1914, reference SD 1059). Other collections at Edinburgh University
		  Library with some relevance are the papers of George A. Grieve (Gen. 766/3-5)
		  and Arthur Ruffell Barlow (Gen. 1785-1786) both missionaries at Kikuyu, and the
		  Berriedale Keith papers (Gen. 145/2/51-2) which include Arthur material. The
		  Library's African Studies (CAS) collection has a collection of pamphlets and
		  printed materials relating to the church at Kikuyu. The National Library of
		  Scotland has a large collection of missionary records, including some letters
		  from Arthur. Dr Brian McIntosh in his doctoral thesis 
		<title>The Scottish Mission in Kenya 1891-1923</title> (Edinburgh
		University, 1969) lists sources for the history of the Kikuyu mission. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Female circumcision</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Kenya</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Africa</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Arthur</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1881-1952</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Medical Missionary
		  in Kenya</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Kikuyu Mission</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Kikuyu Association</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
