<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-746" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-746</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Rev. James Hog (c. 1658-1734)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jan 7 09:44:31 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> GB 0237 MSS HOG 1-4
			 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-746</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS HOG 1-4</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rev. James Hog (c.
		  1658-1734)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1694-1733">1694-1733</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 40 letters, 1 diary, and miscellaneous items.
		  </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Hog, James</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Hog was born around 1658. He graduated from Edinburgh University
		  with an M.A. in 1677, and then studied theology in the Netherlands. He was
		  ordained as Minister of Dalserf parish in the Presbytery of Hamilton in 1691.
		  Hog was elected as a member of the General Assembly in 1695. In 1699 he became
		  Minister of Carnock, Fife. He belonged to a stricter wing of the Church of
		  Scotland that took a stand against the more tolerant attitudes that had begun
		  to arise within the Church. With his re-publication of the 
		<title>Marrow of modern divinity</title> (1718), he started the 'Marrow'
		controversy. The book was denounced by the Assembly in 1720. Rev. James Hog
		died on 14 May 1734. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: copies of several letters from Hog to
		  friends in Edinburgh, 1725-1733; sermons by James Webster and others,
		  1697-1721; diary while at Carnock, 1702-1703, and also while at Dalserf,
		  1694-1695; memorial written by Philomathes; and, letters concerning the
		  absoluteness of the covenant of grace, 1712-1713, letter of William Stuart to
		  James Cuthbert, letter of James Cuthbert to William Stuart, undated letter, and
		  items by Thomas Gilbert and James Fraser of Brea.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 9. Harris-Hovenden.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes of Edinburgh University Library, George Square, show
		  references to Hog related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter
		  of Hog to John Gibb, Minister of Cliesh, 30 October 1708, at La.III.355,
		  f.201v; and, remarks on W. Stuart's account of Thomas Hog of Kiltearn. Remarks
		  mainly casuistical pertaining to the life of Thomas Hog, and letter from Hog to
		  Lord Grange concerning John Card, queries of the Synod of Fife to Hog, with his
		  answers, in La.III.263. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives
		  (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: copies of
		  autobiography, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Adv MSS
		  22 7 10, 32 3 8</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hog</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1658-1734</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scottish Minister
		  and Controversialist</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
