<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-608" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-608</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Church of Scotland India and Nepal
			 Collection</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 11:05:53 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-608</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 41</physloc><unittitle>Church of Scotland India and Nepal
		  Collection</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1868-1985">1868-1985</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Foreign Mission Committees of the United Presbyterian
		  Church, the United Free Church and the Church of Scotland concerned with
		  India</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="hin">Hindi.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Foreign Mission Committee (later Board of World Mission and Unity)
		  of the Church of Scotland was responsible for the Church's mission work around
		  the world. In 1824 the Church's General Assembly resolved to become involved in
		  educational work in India. In 1829 Alexander Duff, the first Church of Scotland
		  missionary, was appointed and he arrived in India in 1830. He founded the
		  General Assembly's Institution to be run on western principles of higher
		  education using the English language and the work was an immediate success with
		  a number of Indians from high caste families being converted. With the
		  Disruption of 1843 Duff joined the Free Church of Scotland and founded another
		  college in Calcutta which, after his death, was named Duff College. After some
		  years of tension between the two churches in Bengal there was an increasing
		  desire for co-operation, an example of which was the merger of the two colleges
		  in 1908 to form the Scottish Churches College. Both the Church of Scotland and
		  the Free Church had by this time established mission stations in other areas of
		  India. In Madras a similar college to the one founded by Duff had been opened
		  in 1837 by John Anderson. Originally the Central Institution it was later named
		  the Madras Christian College and became an outstanding centre of Christian
		  higher education. Its success was due largely to William Miller, a Free Church
		  missionary, who took charge of the school in 1862 and in 1887 persuaded the
		  Church Missionary Society and the Weslyans to join to make the College
		  interdenominational. The Free Church did not concentrate just on education, it
		  tried to establish Christian communities and churches amongst Indians and
		  amongst various other tribes. In the 1870s the Free Church began working among
		  the Santal (Santhal) people of Bengal and Bihar, an undertaking which expanded
		  to several stations with churches, schools and medical care. In Rajputana the
		  United Presbyterian Church of Scotland, which had been formed in 1847, had been
		  working since the 1860s and when the Church joined with the Free Church in 1900
		  this work was continued under the United Free Church. In 1929 all missionaries
		  became once again the responsibility of the Foreign Mission Committee of the
		  Church of Scotland when the United Free Church joined with the Church of
		  Scotland.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: (1) volume giving details of the
		  missionaries and mission council in Rajputana, north-west India (1868-1976);
		  (2) papers, reports and correspondence relating to the work in Calcutta in
		  particular to the Scottish Churches Mission and educational work (1880-1930);
		  (3) minutes of the Santal (Santhal) missionaries' committee (1950-1976); (4)
		  minutes of the meetings of the Madras Christian College governing board in
		  Edinburgh (1909-1949); (5) material relating to the constitution and building
		  work at Wilson College, Bombay (1958-1968); (6) lists of goods sent to
		  missionaries in the Central Provinces (Madyha Pradesh, 1941-1956); (7)
		  correspondence concerning the visit of the Moderator to India and Nepal (1985);
		  (8) maps; (9) Laubach wall charts; and (10) a photograph album of typical
		  Indian scenes.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged as described above.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was presented to the Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World by the Church of Scotland in the
		  1990s.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself, (2) Latourette, K. S. 
		<title>A History of the Expansion of Christianity</title>. Vol.6. London:
		Eyre and Spottiswoode, 1945.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the foreign missions of the Church of Scotland are
		  held by the National Library of Scotland, some of the material in that
		  collection may duplicate this material. The Centre has many pamphlets and
		  journals and some bound minutes relating to missions in India, some of which
		  came from the Church of Scotland and has other collections of archives relating
		  to the Church of Scotland, including large sets of slides and lantern
		  slides.</p> 
		<p>Also within the ArchivesHub the Edinburgh University Library
		  collection of 
		<title>Records of the Church of Scotland General Assembly</title> may be
		of interest.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">India</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nepal</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
