<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-463" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-463</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Material relating to Early Railways in
			 Britain</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Oct 15 09:18:12 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-463</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.6.19/2; Dk.7.46/56; Gen. 715/8; Gen. 1697-1715; Gen. 1790,
		  no.259; Gen. 1939/3/iii; Gen. 1956/7/8; Gen.
		  2169/142</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Material relating to Early Railways
		  in Britain</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1999">19th century - 20th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>7 letters or documents, 19 albums containing several
		  hundred photographs (1.5 linear metre)</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The first railroad built in Great Britain was the Stockton and
		  Darlington railroad, opened in 1825. It used a steam locomotive built by George
		  Stephenson but was practical only for hauling mineral trains. In order to help
		  exploit rich veins of coal in the area, the original plan had been to employ
		  draft horses for the pulling of wagons along the railroad. Instead, the
		  promoter of the plan - Edward Pease - commissioned Stephenson to build a steam
		  locomotive for the line. Railway transportation began on 27 September 1825 when
		  the first public passenger train pulled by the engine 'Active' (later renamed
		  'Locomotion'), ran from Darlington to Stockton carrying 450 persons at 15 miles
		  (24 km) per hour.</p> 
		<p>Interested parties in the cities of Liverpool and Manchester then
		  called on Stephenson to build a 40-mile (64-kilometre) railway line to connect
		  the two cities. The Liverpool and Manchester Railway opened in 1830, and was
		  the first modern railroad. It was a public carrier of both passengers and
		  freight.</p> 
		<p>When the Liverpool-Manchester line was nearing completion in 1829, a
		  competition was held for locomotives. Stephenson's new engine, the 'Rocket',
		  which he built with the assistance of his son, Robert, won with a speed of 36
		  miles (58 km) per hour. Eight locomotives were used when the
		  Liverpool-Manchester line opened on 15 September 1830, and all of them had been
		  built in Stephenson's Newcastle works. From this time on, railway building
		  spread rapidly throughout Britain, Europe, and North America.</p> 
		<p>In Scotland, it had been coalmining that stimulated the first railway
		  or waggonway building. In the eighteenth century tracks existed in East Lothian
		  between Tranent and Cockenzie and at Inveresk near Musselburgh. Indeed part of
		  the land upon which the Battle of Prestonpans took place in 1745 was taken up
		  by one of these early tracks. These waggonways also connected canals with
		  collieries. The first line in Scotland to experiment with steam power was the
		  Kilmarnock and Troon Railway in Ayrshire in 1816 or 1817.</p> 
		<p>The North British Railway begun in 1846 had become, by 1922, the
		  largest Scottish railway, although the Caledonian Railway linking with England
		  regarded itself as the principal railway in Scotland. Others were the Glasgow
		  and South Western Railway, the Highland Railway, and the Great North of
		  Scotland Railway.</p> 
		<p>By 1870 Britain had about 13,500 miles (21,700 km) of railway. At
		  their greatest extent in 1914, there were about 20,000 miles (32,000 km) of
		  track, run by 120 competing companies. The British government combined all
		  these companies into four main groups in 1923 as an economy measure. When the
		  Second World War began in 1939, Britain's railways were placed under government
		  control and in 1947 the Transport Act nationalised them. The railways were
		  taken over by the British Transport Commission (BTC) in 1948 and given the name
		  British Railways. The BTC divided Britain's rail network into six (later five)
		  regions on a geographic basis.</p> 
		<p>A 1962 law replaced the BTC with the British Railways Board in 1963.
		  The board's management emphasized mass movement over major trunk lines and the
		  closing of money-losing branch lines and depots - the so-called Beeching cuts.
		  Between 1963 and 1975 the board shortened its routes from 17,500 miles (28,000
		  km) to 11,000 miles (17,000 km) and cut personnel from about 475,000 to about
		  250,000. As part of a modernization program, steam locomotives began to be
		  replaced by diesels in the 1950s, and this was followed in the 1960s by
		  electrification. A programme of reconstruction included the installation of
		  long, continuously welded rails, and new signalling systems. By the 1970s,
		  electrification had extended to Glasgow. With track improvements and high speed
		  trains (the InterCity services) travel times between the major conurbations
		  were cut.</p> 
		<p>In 1993, the British government passed legislation that restructured
		  British Rail prior to its sale to the private sector. A new state-owned
		  company, Railtrack, was created in 1994 to own and manage the system's track,
		  signals, land, and stations while British Rail itself was split up into about
		  25 train-operating units that could be franchised to private-sector operators.
		  In 2002 Railtrack was replaced by yet another authority - Network Rail. Current
		  train operators (in 2002) include: Connex, GNER, Virgin trains, Midland
		  Mainline, South West TrainsArriva Trains Northern, Anglia Railways, Central
		  Trains, and Scot Rail.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: instructions by T. Telford 'respecting
		  the Glasgow and Berwick line of Railways', 1809; letter about land for the
		  Edinburgh and Glasgow railway, 1840; letter from the Directors of the North
		  British Railway with a proposal to extend the proposed line from Edinburgh to
		  Dunbar as far as Berwick to link up with the English railways, 1843; letter of
		  Adam Black to Bailie Gray about the Atmospheric Railway, Trinity Hospital,
		  Edinburgh, 1846; an account of the laying of the foundation stone of the
		  Caledonian Railway Terminus in Edinburgh, 1847; measurement of work at Peebles
		  Railway Station, 1854; letter about a proposed light railway in the Cairn
		  Valley, Dumfriesshire, 1896; and, several albums of photographs of British
		  steam locomotives from the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Telford instructions, purchased November 1968, Accession no. E68.36.
		  Atmospheric Railway, acquired November 1973, Accession no. E73.42. NBR letter,
		  purchased 1974, Accession no. E74.14.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>Item at Dk.6.19/2 not examined (October 2002). The
		  biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994. (2) 
		<title>Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. 
		<extref href="http://search.eb.com/eb/article?eu=16770">British
		  Railways</extref> [Accessed October 8, 2002].</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to railway related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): a pencil note on 'Railway traveling' by
		  'JB' on folios 1-2v of ledger of Professor J. Black, 13 December 1799, at Gen.
		  874/XI; the Glasgow and Paisley line referred to in a commonplace book, 1828,
		  at Gen. 567D, p.78; new railway at Malines, France, mentioned in a letter of T.
		  J. Torrie, 1835, at Gen. 1996/9/90; progress on the railway to Preston and
		  Lancaster mentioned in a letter from Babington to Jardine, 1838, at Dk.6.20/4;
		  meetings about the Caledonian railway in Dumfriesshire mentioned in a letter,
		  at Dk.20/254; propesed railway in southern Scotland mentioned in letters, 1841,
		  at Gen. 886/2, nos.19-10; travel by railway mentioned in letters of T. J.
		  Torrie, 1841, at Gen. 1996/8/31, 37; and, letter of Cooke to Torrie suggesting
		  she should 'bespeak the invalids carriage', 1847, at Gen. 1996/12/42.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Railroads</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Locomotives</emph> </subject>
		
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">North British Railway Co</emph>
		  <emph altrender="y">1842 - 1948</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Caledonian Railway Company</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
