<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-804" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-804</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Rolland J. B. Munro relating to James Hutton
			 (1726-1797)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed May 19 10:22:58 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-804</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2234</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Rolland J. B. Munro
		  relating to James Hutton (1726-1797)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1939-1947">1939-1947</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Munro, Rolland J. B.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Hutton was most well known for achievements in geology. He was
		  born in Edinburgh on 3 June 1726. He was educated at the city's Royal High
		  School and he studied at Edinburgh University first matriculating there in
		  1740. His most important contribution to science was the 
		<title>Theory of the Earth</title> (1785) which earned him the accolade
		of 'founder of modern geology'. In his work, he noted: &quot;with respect to
		Human observation, this world has neither a beginning nor an end&quot; - a
		principle now accepted as axiomatic. Hutton also had interests in the physical
		sciences, in particular, chemistry, physics and meteorology. Toward the end of
		his life he published a three-part book entitled 
		<title>Dissertations on Different Subjects in Natural Philosophy</title>
		(1792) where he discussed mostly meteorology, phlogiston, and the theory of
		matter. Hutton also engaged in more philosophical concerns of the time. He
		published a three volume treatise on metaphysics and moral philosophy entitled 
		<title>An Investigation of the Principles of Knowledge and of the
		  Progress of Reason, From Sense to Science and Philosophy</title> ( 1794). James
		Hutton died on 26 March 1797.</p> 
		<p>On his death, Hutton's sister Isabella gave his collection of fossils
		  to Dr. Joseph Black (1728-1799), Professor of Chemistry at Edinburgh
		  University, and he in turn presented them to the Royal Society of Edinburgh.
		  Trace of the fossil collection was then lost, and this became a research
		  interest of Rolland J. B. Munro working in the 1930s and 1940s. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection contained in two files, six notebooks and one envelope
		  within an archive box is composed of: copies in typescript of 
		<title>On the loss of James Hutton's geological collection</title>, an
		address given on 12 March 1941; notes on James Hutton and the wider Hutton
		family; correspondence 1939; correspondence 1942-1947; notes on Hutton and
		Isaac Newton; and address delivered by Munro to the Edinburgh Geological
		Society, 19 March 1947; genealogical notes; and, assorted notes and
		correspondence.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material acquired from Munro, May 1986, Accession no. E86.31.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 10. Howard-Kenneth.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) 
		<title>Biographies D-N</title>. Full-text [online]. 
		<extref href="http://www.nahste.ac.uk/biographies/d-n.html"> Hutton,
		  James 1726-1797. Geologist</extref> [Accessed 12 March 2004].</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Geology</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Geologists</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Munro</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Rolland J. B.</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl
		  1939-1947</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Researcher of James Hutton</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hutton</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1726-1797</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Geologist</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
