<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-315" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-315</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Boswell family of Auchinleck and
			 Balmuto</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Nov 23 14:05:11 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> May 08 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-315</unitid> 
		<physloc>MS 2671; Gen. 2212/2; Gen.750D; Dk.7.52/52; La.II; La.III;
		  La.IV; La.Add; E90.96; E90.97</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Boswell family
		  of Auchinleck and Balmuto</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1722-1823">1722-1823</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 bound volume, 1 boxed volume, miscellaneous
		  manuscript letters and documents, notebooks and bundles. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Boswell, Alexander; Boswell, Claud Irvine; Boswell, James;
		  Boswell, Sir Alexander; Boswell, Robert</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Auchinleck is situated in Ayrshire, in Scotland's large Strathclyde
		  region, 21 kilometres east of the town of Ayr. The town has a population (based
		  on 1991 figures at least) of 4,160.</p> 
		<p>Auchinleck is associated with the Boswell family through the granting
		  of the estate to Thomas Boswell, a 'cadet' of the Balmuto line, on his marriage
		  to the daughter and co-heiress of Sir John Auchinleck in 1504. Thomas had been
		  one of the court favourites of James IV and he died with the king at the Battle
		  of Flodden in 1513.</p>
		<p>On his appointment as Lord of Session in 1754, Alexander Boswell
		  (1706-1782) took the title of Lord Auchinleck. It was Alexander Boswell who had
		  Auchinleck House built. His son, James Boswell, the diarist and biographer of
		  Samuel Johnson, was born at nearby Auchinleck House, and is buried in the
		  churchyard in Auchinleck</p>
		<p>Balmuto in the parish of Kinghorn, in Fife, was an estate with a
		  mansion, the latter just over 4 kilometres northwest of Burntisland.</p> 
		<p>On his appointment as Lord of Session in 1754, Alexander Boswell
		  (1706-1782) took the title of Lord Auchinleck. It was Alexander Boswell who had
		  Auchinleck House built. His son, James Boswell, the diarist and biographer of
		  Samuel Johnson, was born at nearby Auchinleck House, and is buried in the
		  churchyard in Auchinleck.</p> 
		<p>Thomas Boswell had been one of the court favourites of James IV and he
		  died with the king at the Battle of Flodden in 1513.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers of the various members of the Boswell family consist almost
		  entirely of the manuscript correspondence of Alexander Boswell, Lord Auchinleck
		  (1706-1782), Claud Irvine Boswell (1742-1824), James Boswell (1740-1795), Sir
		  Alexander Boswell, 1st Baronet (1775-1822), and Robert Boswell (1746-1804) a
		  descendant of the Auchinleck Boswells. There is also a transcript of a history
		  of Edinburgh University, and poems. There are also petitions and other letters,
		  as well as description of the family circumstances. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (ed.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. p.46. London: Harper
		Collins, 1994. (2) Seltzer, Leon E. (ed.). 
		<title>The Columbia Lippincott gazetteer of the world</title>.
		Morningside Heights, N.Y: Columbia University Press, 1962. (3) Groome, Francis
		H. (ed.). 
		<title>Ordnance gazetteer of Scotland: a survey of Scottish topography,
		  statistical, biographical, and historical</title>. Vol.1. Edinburgh: Thomas C.
		Jack, 1882. (4) </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to material related to the
		  Boswell family in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details):
		  mention in a letter of the poverty and misfortune of the Boswell family of
		  Balmuto, 1802, at La.II.500; a letter of a Miss Boswell of Auchinleck, 1823, at
		  La.IV.6; preamble to the will of an Alexander Boswell, 18th century at
		  La.IV.417/23; and, a letter of Lady G. Boswell, 1823, at La.IV.6.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1707-1782</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Lord Auchinleck
		  Judge </emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Claude Irvine</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1742-1824</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Lord Balmuto
		  Judge</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1740-1795</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Biographer of
		  Samuel Johnson Diarist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1775-1822</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Poet and Antiquary </emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1746-1804</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Psalmist</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Auchinleck (Scotland)</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Balmuto (Scotland)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess>    <!-- sub fonds level descriptions in dsc tag -->
	 <dsc type="analyticover"> 
		<c01 otherlevel="subfonds" level="otherlevel"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>GB 0237 MS 2671; Gen. 2212/2; La.II.91; La.II.176;
				La.III.331; La.III.619/1; La.Add.6/75-76; E90.96</unitid> 
			 <unittitle>Boswell family. Papers of Alexander Boswell, Lord
				Auchinleck (1706-1782)</unittitle> 
			 <unitdate normal="1701-1799">18th century</unitdate> 
			 <physdesc> <extent>Miscellaneous manuscripts</extent> </physdesc> 
			 <langmaterial/> 
		  </did> 
		  <bioghist> 
			 <p>Alexander Boswell, Lord Auchinleck, was born in 1706. His father
				was the advocate James Boswell of Auchinleck and his mother was Lady Elizabeth
				Bruce, the third daughter of Alexander 2nd Earl of Kincardine. He studied at
				the University of Leiden, in the Netherlands, graduating on 29 December 1727.
				Earlier, in July 1727, he was admitted to the Faculty of Advocates in Scotland.
				In 1748 he was appointed Sheriff-Depute of Wigtownshire and in 1754 he became
				an ordinary Lord of Session. In July 1755 he was also appointed as a Lord
				Justiciary. Lord Auchinleck was twice married. His first wife was Euphemia
				Erskine, and they had three sons one of whom was James Boswell who would become
				renowned as a diarist and the biographer of Samuel Johnson. His second wife was
				his cousin Elizabeth, daughter of John Boswell of Balmuto. Alexander Boswell
				died in Edinburgh on 25 August 1782.</p> 
		  </bioghist> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>The papers of Alexander Boswell consist of manuscript
				correspondence and transcripts including: a copy made by himself of the
				manuscript by William Scott, Professor of Greek, entitled 
			 <title>Annotata in libros A et B Homeri Iliados</title>, at MS 2671;
			 and, a transcript of a history of the University of Edinburgh, 1580-1646, but
			 ending with the year 1623. There is a tranche of 17 letters from 1741 at
			 E90.96. Papers held within the Laing Collection include: letters to Professor
			 C. Mackie, at La.II.91; and La.II.176; transfer of bonds, at La.Add.6/75 and
			 76; manuscript notes on 
			 <title>De verborum significatione</title> with a letter to James
			 Boswell, at La.II.619/1; a volume of extracts from a manuscript entitled 
			 <title>Several things relating to the bishoprics and religious
				foundations in Scotland</title>, 1732, at La.III.331; a mention in a letter,
			 1754, at La.II.91; letters about printing, 1813-1818, at La.IV.6.</p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		  <acqinfo> 
			 <p>Boswell's copy of 
			 <title>Annotata</title>, purchased January 1983, Accession no. E83.9.
			 Boswell's transcript of the history, purchased June 1985, Accession no.
			 E85.33.</p> 
		  </acqinfo> 
		  <relatedmaterial> 
			 <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the
				Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: notes on logic lectures, 1723,
				National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MS 3938; and, notes on
				Mackenzie's Institutions, 1727, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts
				Division, Ref. Adv MS 17 22 1.</p> 
		  </relatedmaterial>        <!-- control access terms -->
		  <controlaccess> 
			 <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
				<emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph
				altrender="dates">1707-1782</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Lord Auchinleck
				Judge </emph> </persname> 
			 <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Scott</emph>
				<emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph
				altrender="title">fl.1720</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of
				Greek</emph> </persname> 
			 <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph>
				</corpname> 
		  </controlaccess> 
		</c01> 
		<c01 otherlevel="subfonds" level="otherlevel"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>GB 0237 La.II.509</unitid> 
			 <unittitle>Boswell family. Papers of Claud Irvine Boswell, Lord
				Balmuto (1742-1824) </unittitle> 
			 <unitdate normal="1780">1780</unitdate> 
			 <physdesc> <extent>Manuscript</extent> </physdesc> 
			 <langmaterial/> 
		  </did> 
		  <bioghist> 
			 <p>Claud Irvine Boswell, Lord Balmuto, was born in 1742. His father
				was John Boswell of Balmuto, and he was a cousin of Alexander Boswell
				(1706-1782). He was educated in Dalkeith and then studied at Edinburgh
				University, after which he was admitted as a member of the Faculty of Advocates
				on 2 August 1766. In 1780 he was appointed Sheriff-Depute of Fife and Kinross,
				and in 1799 he was appointed as an ordinary Lord of Session taking his seat as
				Lord Balmuto. After receiving a shock on the death of Sir Alexander Boswell
				(1775-1822) at his family home in March 1822, Claud Irvine Boswell died at
				Balmuto on 22 July 1824.</p> 
		  </bioghist> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>Within the Laing Collection there is a letter of Boswell, from
				Balmuto, in 1780, to H. Warrender.</p> 
		  </scopecontent>        <!-- control access terms -->
		  <controlaccess> 
			 <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
				<emph altrender="forename">Claude Irvine</emph> <emph
				altrender="dates">1742-1824</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Lord Balmuto
				Judge</emph> </persname> 
		  </controlaccess> 
		</c01> 
		<c01 otherlevel="subfonds" level="otherlevel"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>GB 0237 Gen. 750D, f.14; La.II.81-82; La.II.180;
				La.II.417/23; La.II.603; La.II.619</unitid> 
			 <unittitle>Boswell family. Papers of James Boswell
				(1740-1795)</unittitle> 
			 <unitdate normal="1769-1795">1769-1795</unitdate> 
			 <physdesc> <extent>Manuscripts</extent> </physdesc> 
			 <langmaterial/> 
		  </did> 
		  <bioghist> 
			 <p>James Boswell was born in Edinburgh in 1740. He was educated first
				privately by a tutor and then at James Mundell's school in Edinburgh, and then
				at the Royal High School in the city. He studied law at Edinburgh, Glasgow and
				Utrecht universities and although these studies were interrupted by a period in
				London pursuing his other interests of literature, politics and the army he was
				admitted to the Scottish Bar in 1766. It was in London, 16 May 1763, that
				Boswell first met Samuel Johnson (1709-1784).</p> 
			 <p> In addition to studying in the Netherlands, Boswell toured
				Germany and met Rousseau and Voltaire during a visit to Geneva. In 1765, he was
				permitted by his father to visit Italy. After a period in Rome and Florence, he
				travelled to Corsica from Livorno (Leghorn) and was introduced, through
				Rousseau, to Pasquale Paoli, the Corsican patriot (1725-1807) responsible for
				ending Genoese rule of the island. Boswell returned to Britain in 1766, first
				staying in London and then proceeding to Scotland where he applied himself to
				legal work in Edinburgh and writing an account of his visit to Corsica. In 1769
				he married his cousin, Margaret Montgomerie.</p> 
			 <p>The attraction of London society, his friendship with Johnson, and
				his strong political interests frequently drew Boswell away from Edinburgh, and
				in 1773 he persuaded Johnson to undertake an extensive tour of Scotland and the
				Hebrides.</p> 
			 <p>Boswell's publications include<title>An account of Corsica</title>
			 (1768), 
			 <title>Journal of a tour to the Hebrides</title> (1785) and 
			 <title>The life of Johnson</title> (1791).</p> 
			 <p>Boswell succeeded to the family estate on the death of his father
				in 1782 and James Boswell himself died at his home in Great Portland Street,
				London, on 19 May 1795.</p> 
			 <p>He had two sons, Alexander and James, and three daughters,
				Veronica, Euphemia, and Elizabeth.</p> 
		  </bioghist> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>Within the Laing Collection there are letters both from and to
				James Boswell including: correspondence with J. Cumming, April 1785, and
				extracts from a letter made by J. Cumming, October 1769, at La.II.82;
				correspondence with Sir David Dalrymple, Lord Hailes, at La.II.180 and
				La.II.603; and, correspondence with Isabella Strange, 1769, at La.II.81. There
				is also a note with an autograph statement at La.III.619, a copy of a will of
				James Boswell, and an epitaph at La.II.417/23 and at Gen. 750D, f.14.</p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		  <acqinfo> 
			 <p>Epitaph presented August 1964, Accession no. E64.23.</p> 
		  </acqinfo> 
		  <odd> 
			 <note> 
				<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
				  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
				<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.2.
				Beal-Browell. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) Keay, John. and Keay,
				Julia (eds.). 
				<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper
				Collins, 1994.</p> 
			 </note> 
		  </odd> 
		  <relatedmaterial> 
			 <p>The local Indexes show another reference to James Boswell in the
				form of a mention in a letter at Dk.7.52/52.</p> 
		  </relatedmaterial>        <!-- control access terms -->
		  <controlaccess> 
			 <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
				<emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
				altrender="dates">1740-1795</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Biographer of
				Samuel Johnson Diarist</emph> </persname> 
		  </controlaccess> 
		</c01> 
		<c01 otherlevel="subfonds" level="otherlevel"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>GB 0237 Gen. 750D; La.IV.6; La.III.584/21; La.II.343;
				E90.97</unitid> 
			 <unittitle>Boswell family. Papers of Sir Alexander Boswell
				(1775-1822)</unittitle> 
			 <unitdate normal="1782-1818">1782-1818</unitdate> 
			 <physdesc> <extent>9 letters, 3 poems</extent> </physdesc> 
			 <langmaterial/> 
		  </did> 
		  <bioghist> 
			 <p>Alexander Boswell was born on 9 October 1775 at Auchinleck House
				on the Boswell estate in Ayrshire. Alexander and his brother James were
				educated at Westminster and at Oxford. In 1795, Alexander succeeded his father,
				James Boswell the elder, and began a tour of Europe. On his return, he settled
				at Auchinleck and studied literature, writing and composing poems and songs in
				Scots. In 1815, he established a printing press at Auchinleck. Boswell was also
				noted for moving a public subscription for the construction of a monument to
				Robert Burns on the banks of the River Doon. In 1816 and 1820 he was elected as
				the MP for Plympton in Devonshire. He was created a Baronet in 1821.</p> 
			 <p>Arising from scurrilous articles written by Boswell about James
				Stuart of Dunearn (1775-1849) in 
			 <title>The Glasgow Sentinel</title> and after an interrupted legal
			 action for libel, Boswell was challenged to a dual with pistols on 25 March
			 1822. The dual was fought the following day at a farm near the village of
			 Auchtertool, near to Kirkcaldy. Although Boswell shot into the air, Stuart
			 wounded his opponent fatally. Sir Alexander Boswell died at Balmuto on the 27
			 March 1822.</p> 
		  </bioghist> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>Boswell's papers held within the Laing Collection include: eight
				letters from Alexander Boswell to David Laing about printing, 1813-1818; a
				letter to Sir Walter Scott, 15 June 1811; and, a poem entitled 
			 <title>The Brig's answer. To John Gibson</title>. There are also
			 three of Alexander Boswell's poems in a notebook at Gen. 750D, and a letter to
			 Miss Campbell dated 1821 at E90.97.</p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		  <acqinfo> 
			 <p>Poems in Gen. 750D presented August 1964, Accession no.
				E64.23.</p> 
		  </acqinfo> 
		  <odd> 
			 <note> 
				<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
				  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
				<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.2.
				Beal-Browell. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
				<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.19.
				Stow-Tytler. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
			 </note> 
		  </odd> 
		  <relatedmaterial> 
			 <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the
				Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence with James Boswell and
				miscellaneous papers, 1786-1795, Yale University Libraries, Beinecke Library,
				Ref. L73-124, C233-303 NRA 22146 Boswell; letters (36) to James Skene,
				1797-1817, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MS 3854,
				and letters to Sir William Forbes, 1795-1805, Ref. Acc 4796 NRA 29136; and,
				letters to G. Thomson, with songs, 1801-1821, British Library, Manuscript
				Collections Ref. Add MSS 35263-65 passim.</p> 
		  </relatedmaterial>        <!-- control access terms -->
		  <controlaccess> 
			 <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
				<emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph
				altrender="dates">1775-1822</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
				<emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Poet and Antiquary </emph> </persname> 
			 <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Laing</emph>
				<emph altrender="forename">David</emph> <emph
				altrender="dates">1793-1878</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scottish Antiquary
				</emph> </persname> 
			 <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Scott</emph>
				<emph altrender="forename">Walter</emph> <emph
				altrender="dates">1771-1832</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
				<emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Novelist Poet Antiquary Barrister</emph>
				</persname> 
		  </controlaccess> 
		</c01> 
		<c01 otherlevel="subfonds" level="otherlevel"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>GB 0237 Gen. 750D; La.II.82; La.II.511</unitid> 
			 <unittitle>Boswell family. Papers of Robert Boswell
				(1746-1804)</unittitle> 
			 <unitdate normal="1765-1797">1765-1797</unitdate> 
			 <physdesc> <extent>Notebook and correspondence</extent> </physdesc> 
			 <langmaterial/> 
		  </did> 
		  <bioghist> 
			 <p>The psalmist Robert Boswell , a descendant of the Boswells of
				Auchinleck, was born in 1746. He received a classical education and became a
				Writer to the Signet in Edinburgh. Boswell was a Glasite or Sandemanian ( a
				member of the Christian sect founded around 1730 by John Glas and built on by
				Robert Sandeman) and was a teaching elder of the Church in Edinburgh . Robert
				Boswell died on 1 April 1804 during the middle of a sermon he was preaching in
				London, probably at the Barbican chapel. </p> 
		  </bioghist> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>The papers include a notebook containing verses written by Boswell
				between 1782 and 1797. Within the Laing Collection are letters to Mr and Mrs J.
				Cumming and to Miss Cumming between 1765-1785, and a letter to J. McRitchie, 20
				April 1795.</p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		  <acqinfo> 
			 <p>Notebook presented August 1964, Accession no. E64.23.</p> 
		  </acqinfo> 
		  <relatedmaterial> 
			 <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the
				Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence with James Boswell,
				1775-1794, Yale University Libraries: Beinecke Library, Ref. L196-260 NRA 22146
				Boswell</p> 
		  </relatedmaterial>        <!-- control access terms -->
		  <controlaccess> 
			 <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph>
				<emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph
				altrender="dates">1746-1804</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Psalmist</emph>
				</persname> 
		  </controlaccess> 
		</c01> 
	 </dsc> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
