<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-621" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-621</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Interserve Scotland</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown and edited by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh
				University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Dec 10 11:57:56 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-621</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 50</physloc><unittitle>Interserve Scotland</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1880-1988">1880- 1988</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes of minute books, 2 boxes of
		  correspondence</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Interserve Scotland</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Interserve Scotland, also known as the Bible and Missionary Fellowship
		  (Scotland), was founded in 1965. It is a registered trust domiciled in Scotland
		  and is one of 17 National Councils of Interserve.</p> 
		<p>Interserve is an evangelical, interdenominational and multi-cultural
		  mission agency which with over 500 partners from more than 17 countries
		  including 30 from Scotland. It serves in 23 countries across Asia, the Middle
		  East and North Africa, and among Asian ethnic groups in Britain.</p> 
		<p>Interserve states that it 'serves Christ in word and action. Partners
		  use their professional skills to share the love of Christ' and that Interserve
		  'recognizes that God's concern is for every aspect of His creation'. Its aims
		  are to 'preach the Gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ to the peoples of Asia and
		  the Middle East. To assist national churches in their growth and training. To
		  prepare Scotland for cross-cultural Christian service'.</p> 
		<p>Its registered address in Scotland is 12 Elm Avenue, Lenzie, Glasgow
		  G66 4HJ.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection comprises the archives of Interserve Scotland. Minute
		  books of the Indian Female Normal Schools and Instruction Society, Edinburgh
		  Auxiliary , the Zenana Bible and Medical Mision, subsequently the Bible and
		  Medical Missionary Fellowship and now Interserve from 1880-1975.
		  Correspondence, papers and 73 lantern slides. The society was principally
		  concerned with medical and educational work in Asia. The collection also
		  includes society publications: 
		<title>Annual Reports of the Bible and Medical Missionary Fellowship
		  1956-1959</title>, 
		<title>Annual Reports of the Zenana Bible and Medical Mission
		  1930-1947</title>, and 
		<title>Bible and Medical Missionary Fellowship prayer calendar 1978-1983,
		  1985- 1988</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The collection is arranged by type of material.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was deposited at the Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World by the mission in 2001.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>None. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Records of Interserve England and Wales are held at the Interserve
		  England and Wales headquarters. Records of Interserve Ireland are held at 14
		  Glencregagh Court, Belfast BT6 0PA. The National Library of Scotland holds
		  copies of the society's journal publications such as 
		<title>The Indian Female Evangelist</title>.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">BMMF International</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">BMMF Interserve</emph> </corpname>      <!--
<corpname>
<emph altrender = "a">Bible and Medical Missionary Fellowship</emph>
</corpname>
-->
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Indian Female Normal School and
		  Instruction Society</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Interserve</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Interserve England and Wales</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Interserve Scotland</emph> </corpname>    
		 <!--
<corpname>
<emph altrender = "a">Zenana Bible and Medical Mission</emph>
</corpname>
-->
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Asia</emph> </geogname>      <!--
<geogname>
<emph altrender = "a">South Asia</emph>
</geogname>
-->
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">India</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
