<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-592" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-592</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of John David Hayes (1888-1957)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Nov 29 11:49:25 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-592</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 13</physloc><unittitle>Papers of John David Hayes
		  (1888-1957)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1946-1973">1946-1973</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 file (c 195 pp)</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Hayes, John D; Hayes, Barbara M.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John David Hayes, American Presbyterian missionary in China and
		  Indonesia, was born in 1888 in Shantung Province, China, the son of American
		  missionaries. He was educated at Princeton then won a Rhodes Scholarship to
		  study at Oxford, England after which he studied at New College, Edinburgh and
		  Princeton Theological College, graduating from the latter in 1917. He went to
		  China in the same year accompanied by his wife, Barbara (nee Kelman) whom he
		  had met at Oxford and had married in 1916. Hayes was based in Peking where he
		  was in charge of student Christian work, and, being keen to promote unity, was
		  largely instrumental in the formation of a nation-wide Chinese Student
		  Christian Union. From the mid 1920s he was also involved with language teaching
		  at the College of Chinese Studies in Peking. He was an active member of many
		  Church, community and mission councils and was particularly involved with
		  organising the mission's response to famine in the surrounding provinces and
		  acting as a spokesman for the mission in its dealings with the authorities
		  after Japanese occupation. Barbara Hayes did mission work with women and with
		  the children of missionaries as well as raising five children herself. The
		  Hayes were on furlough from 1923-24 and from 1936-37 when Hayes studied in
		  London and at New York and Yale. In 1941 Barbara Hayes and her two youngest
		  children were sent to the Philippines then repatriated to America in 1943.
		  Hayes himself stayed on in China, he was interned in 1943, with his parents, at
		  Weihsien and was returned to America in September 1945. He worked for a while
		  as assistant pastor in a church in Washington, received his DD degree in 1948
		  from Wooster College and returned to China in the same year at the invitation
		  of the Church of Christ in China. The Hayes were assigned to the province of
		  Kweichow in the south-west. In 1949, with the approach of the communists,
		  Barbara Hayes was evacuated to Hong Kong where she worked for 18 months in the
		  Church of Christ in China liaison office. John Hayes remained in Kweichow
		  teaching in a government university and school until he was arrested in 1951
		  charged with being a spy. On his release in September 1952 he returned to
		  America and spent the next two years travelling and speaking about his
		  experiences. In 1955 he was appointed to Indonesia where again he worked with
		  students and built up the Christian Normal College at Salatiga. On March 4 1957
		  he died as a result of injuries received in a car accident. After his death
		  Barbara Hayes travelled throughout America speaking on behalf of the mission
		  until her retirement in 1959 in New York. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of copies of material assembled by Barbara
		  Hayes to illustrate her husband's life. It includes biographical data on the
		  Hayes family; a series of articles written by Barbara Hayes about her life in
		  China and focussing particularly on her husband's activities and work; some
		  memoirs or articles written by Hayes himself or articles about him; transcripts
		  of Hayes' 'Confessions' written for his trial in 1951; letters or extracts of
		  letters written by Hayes and his wife; memorials and comments on Hayes by
		  friends and colleagues after his death; and 
		<title>The Invincible</title> a play by Hayes.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged in chronological order relating to phases in
		  the life of Hayes, as it was presented to the Centre.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>The collection was created in 1973 when Barbara Hayes was asked to
		  deposit her husband's papers with the Presbyterian Historical Society in
		  Philadelphia. As she could find little original material she created a
		  biographical sketch and added additional material where appropriate. </p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Not clear.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <altformavail> 
		<p>See under existence and location of originals. </p> 
	 </altformavail> 
	 <odd> 
		<head>Existence/Location of Originals</head> 
		<p>The papers at CSCNWW are copies of originals held in America. Barbara
		  Hayes gave copies to the Presbyterian Historical Society Philadelphia, the
		  University of Oregon (Special Collections) and Yale University (Divinity
		  Library Special Collections): these institutions hold a mixture of copies and
		  originals.</p> 
	 </odd> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself
		  .</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>See under existence and location of originals for information about
		  material at Philadelphia, Oregon and Yale, these repositories may hold
		  additional material to that at CSCNWW. Barbara Hayes referred to 
		<title>Men for Others</title> by Stanley Rowland as containing relevant
		information.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hayes</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John David</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1888-1957</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hayes</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Barbara M</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b
		  1893</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">American Presbyterian Mission</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">China</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Indonesia</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
