<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-431" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-431</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Material relating to James Melville
			 (1556-1614)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Sep 5 11:51:40 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-431</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.4.10; Dc.4.75/2, pp.1-219; Dc.6.45,
		  pp.199-274</physloc><unittitle>Material relating to James Melville
		  (1556-1614)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1608-1610">1608-1610</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 manuscript volume, 2 part volumes</extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<origination>Melville, James; Dunlop, Niniane; Logan, George; Glasgow,
		  James</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="lat">Latin,
		  </language> and <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Melville was born near Montrose, Angus, on 26 July 1556. He was
		  the nephew of the scholar and reformer Andrew Melville (1545-1622). He was
		  educated locally at Logie and at Montrose before studying at St. Leonard's
		  College, St. Andrews. While there he heard John Knox preach. Although it was
		  originally intended that he follow law as a career, his studies were directed
		  towards entering the church and he was instructed in Greek and Hebrew by Andrew
		  Melville. When his uncle became Principal of Glasgow University in 1574, the
		  young Melville accompanied him, becoming a Regent (or Professor) in 1575,
		  teaching Greek, logic and mathematics. When his uncle then became Principal of
		  St. Mary's College (or New College), St. Andrews, in 1580, he again accompanied
		  him, this time as Professor of Hebrew and Oriental Languages. Melville
		  supported his uncle in his views on the authority of the new Presbyterian
		  church and so he too would always be on a collision course with the King,
		  living under the threat of imprisonment. In 1586 he took charge of the Parish
		  of Anstruther Wester in Fife, later reduced to Anstruther Easter and Kilrenny.
		  In 1589 he was appointed Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of
		  Scotland. In 1606 Melville accompanied his uncle to the Hampton Court
		  Conference out of which came the proposal for the King James Version of the
		  Bible. When Andrew Melville was later imprisoned in the Tower of London, the
		  younger Melville was permitted to leave London but ordered not to go further
		  north than Newcastle-upon-Tyne. James Melville died in Berwick-upon-Tweed on 13
		  January 1614. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: 
		<title>Epistolae ... ad Jacobum Melvinum ... scriptae, cum ejusdem Jacobi
		  nonullis ad eundem ... 1608-1611</title>; 
		<title>Ecclesiae Scoticanae oratio apologetica sive libellus supplex ad
		  serenissimum Jacobum primum Britanniarum regem</title>, 1610; 
		<title>True narration of the declyning state of the Kirk of Scotland,
		  from 1590-1610</title>; and 
		<title>The Zodiac of lyff</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.13.
		Masquerier-Myles. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to James Melville related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): fragment of a letter to Andrew
		  Hart, bookseller, 1606, at La.II.663; notes of the Acts of the General
		  Assemblies, 156-1605, at La.III.335; and, 19th century transcripts of 
		<title>Epistolae ... ad Jacobum Melvinum ... scriptae, cum ejusdem Jacobi
		  nonullis ad eundem ... 1608-1611</title> at La.III.373, 374. In addition, the
		UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts
		Commission, notes: diary and poems, 1583-1611, National Library of Scotland,
		Manuscripts Division, Ref. Adv MSS 19 2 7, 34 4 11, 34 2 15</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Melville</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1556-1614</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scottish
		  Reformer</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dunlop</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Niniane</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Logan</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Glasgow</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">17th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
