<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-336" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-336</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of William Scoresby (1789-1857)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Feb 19 12:06:58 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-336</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 129/198-203; Gen. 1730; Gen.
		  1999/1/141</physloc><unittitle>Papers of William Scoresby
		  (1789-1857)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1814-1854">1814-1854</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>8 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>William Scoresby was born at Cropton, near Whitby, on 5 October 1789.
		  He was the son of the Arctic navigator William Scoresby (1760-1829). In 1800 he
		  accompanied his father to the whale fishing grounds, and in 1803 was aboard the
		  whaler 'Resolution' as his father's apprentice on voyages to Greenland.
		  Scoresby entered Edinburgh University in 1806, studying chemistry and natural
		  philosophy. In 1807 he surveyed Balta Sound in Shetland, and later that year
		  volunteered for service with the British fleet at Copenhagen (after the
		  Napoleonic Wars) and to assist in sailing prize vessels from the Danish fleet
		  to England. Around this time he made the acquaintance of Sir Joseph Banks
		  (1743-1820), and probably at Banks suggestion began observations of natural
		  phenomena and a study of the natural history of the polar regions. Scoresby
		  resumed his studies at Edinburgh University in November 1809 and made the
		  acquaintance there of Professor Robert Jameson (1774-1854). In 1810 he took
		  command of the 'Resolution' as captain, but in 1813 he changed to a new and
		  larger vessel, the 'Esk'. Invention of an apparatus for the measurement of deep
		  sea temperatures followed, along with the discovery that bottom sea level
		  temperatures in the Arctic were higher than surface temperatures. In 1819,
		  Scoresby was elected a Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, and the same
		  year he sent a paper on the variations of the magnetic needle to the Royal
		  Society of London. Also in 1819 he and his family moved from Whitby to
		  Liverpool where he superintended the construction of the 'Baffin', specially
		  fitted for the Greenland trade. Voyages were made in 1820, 1821, and 1822. On
		  his return from the 1823 voyage he planned to prepare himself for the ministry,
		  his religious convictions having been intensified by the death of his wife the
		  previous year. He entered Queen's College, Cambridge, also studying Latin and
		  Greek. Scoresby was ordained by the Archbishop of York in July 1825 and
		  obtained the curacy of Bessingby near Bridlington Quay. In May 1827 he became
		  chaplain of the mariner's church at Liverpool, and in 1832 was elected to
		  Bedford chapel, Exeter. In 1834 he obtained the degree of B.D. and in 1839 the
		  degree of D.D., and around the same time he came to the parish of Bradford. Ill
		  health followed in the 1840s and after a long visit to the USA and a search for
		  a cure, he resigned in 1847. He then took up voluntary clerical work and
		  continued occupying himself with science and literature. In his lifetime,
		  Scoresby contributed numerous papers to the Wernerian Society of which he was a
		  member, and his other publications include 
		<title>Account of the Arctic regions and northern whale fishery</title>
		(1820), 
		<title>Journal of a voyage to the northern whale fishery and discoveries
		  on the east coast of Greenland</title> (1823), 
		<title>Memorials of the sea</title> (1833), 
		<title>Magnetical investigations</title> (1839-1852), 
		<title>The Franklin expedition</title> (1850), 
		<title>Zoistic magnetism</title> (1850), and 
		<title>My father, being records of the adventurous life of the late W.
		  Scoresby</title> (1851). His 
		<title>Journal of a voyage to Australia for magnetical research</title>
		(1859) was edited by Archibald Smith. William Scoresby died in Torquay on 21
		March 1857. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers include: a letter from Scoresby to Patrick Neill, Secretary
		  of the Wernerian Society about a meteorological journal, 1814; a number of
		  letters to Professor Robert Jameson about polar ice, whales etc, 1814-1821, and
		  asking if he will read some proofs; a letter about a great telescope, 1846;
		  and, a letter to D. Hodgson, 1854.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter to Neill, and those to Jameson, Accession no. E74.30. Telescope
		  letter, Accession no.E72.37.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 17.
		Robinson-Sheares. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show references to Scoresby related material in the
		  Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letter to S. Hope
		  containing suggestions for the Council considering the loan of testaments to
		  the poor, 1832, in La.II.643/53. There are also references to a portrait and an
		  engraving of Scoresby, at La.II.643/53, and Dc.4.101-103, misc., f.97., and
		  material at Dc.4.101-103 misc.,f.79-80.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Scoresby</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1789-1857
		  </emph> <emph altrender="epithet"> Master Mariner, Author, Divine</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Neill</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Patrick</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1776-1851</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Naturalist,
		  Secretary of Wernerian Natural History Society</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Wernerian Natural History Society</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
