<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-52"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-52</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Douglas
			 Guthrie (1885-1975) </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20070427">27 April 2007</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-52</unitid>
		
		<physloc>Gen. 1727; Gen. 1991</physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Douglas Guthrie (1885-1975)
		  </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1864-1967">1864-1967 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>17 boxes, 1
		  notebook (2 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Douglas Guthrie was born 8 September 1885. He was the son of the Rev.
		  William Guthrie, Dysart, in Fife, a Free Church minister. Guthrie was educated
		  at Kirkcaldy High School and at the Royal High School, Edinburgh. He studied at
		  Edinburgh University, and at Jena and Paris, and was awarded the degrees of
		  Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery in 1907. Postgraduate study was
		  carried out in Hamburg, Jena, Berlin and Paris. He was awarded the degree of
		  M.D. in 1909. His specialisation was Otolaryngology. He became a Fellow of the
		  Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh in 1913, and Fellow of the Royal College
		  of Physicians of Edinburgh in 1961. Guthrie spent six years in general practice
		  in Lanark, and during the First World War he served in the Royal Army Medical
		  Corps and then as Commandant of a Royal Air Force officer's hospital. In 1919
		  he became ear and throat surgeon to the Royal Hospital for Sick Children in
		  Edinburgh, and surgeon to the Ear and Throat Infirmary. From 1920 he was
		  Lecturer on Diseases of Ear, Nose and Throat at the School of Medicine of Royal
		  Colleges, Edinburgh. He was also aural specialist to the Scottish Command. On
		  his retiral from practice in 1945, Guthrie was appointed Lecturer on History of
		  Medicine at Edinburgh University in succession to Dr. John Comrie (1875-1939).
		  He held the post until 1956. Guthrie's publication record included 
		<title>A history of medicine </title> (1945), 
		<title>Lord Lister: His life and doctrine </title> (1949), 
		<title>The Royal Edinburgh Hospital for Sick Children, 1860-1960 </title>
		(1960), 
		<title>Janus in the doorway </title> (1964), and 
		<title>Dr. John Leyden , 1775-1811 </title> (1964). In 1948, Guthrie
		founded the Scottish Society of History of Medicine. He died in Edinburgh on 8
		June 1975. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>Within the collection of Guthrie Papers, Gen. 1727 contains notes of
		  lectures on clinical surgery in Edinburgh University taken down by Douglas
		  Guthrie, 1903-1904. The material at Gen. 1991, in folders and envelopes,
		  contains newspaper cuttings and offprints of articles relating to Dr. John
		  Leyden; notes, typescripts and articles on antiseptics and Joseph Lister;
		  typescripts of lectures; photographs; correspondence with academics; catalogues
		  of libraries holding early medical books; and, articles, typescripts, notebooks
		  on a range of topics. </p> 
		<p>Additionally, there is a scrapbook of letters relating to the
		  publication of - and reviews of - 
		<title>A history of medicine</title> published by Nelson in 1945. The
		scrapbook maintained by Guthrie contains over sixty letters and over
		twenty-five reviews received or collected by him over 1945 and 1946. The
		scrapbook and its contents is supported by an essay which describes Guthrie's
		collection of letters and reviews and which is entitled 
		<title>The value of reviews</title> by David Wright, 2006.</p>
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Guthrie</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Douglas</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1885-1975</emph> </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Comrie</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John D.</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forname">(John Dixon)</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1875-1939</emph> </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Lister</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Joseph</emph>
		  <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1827-1912</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Leyden</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1775-1811</emph> </persname> 
		<persname><emph altrender="surname">Wright</emph><emph
		  altrender="forename">David</emph></persname>
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh
		  University</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Great Britain. Royal Army Medical Corps</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Royal College of
		  Physicians of Edinburgh</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Royal College of
		  Surgeons of Edinburgh</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Royal Edinburgh
		  Hospital for Sick Children</emph> </corpname> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Otolaryngology</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Medicine</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>Handlist, H52; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts shows synopses of lectures on the history of
		  medicine delivered in Edinburgh University, 1946-56, see Dc.4.98/4. Also, for a
		  letter of, and letters to Douglas Guthrie, see Dk.7.54/1 and Dk.7.60/12-14.
		  </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
