<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-605" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-605</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Louie Cowie (fl. 1933-1965)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 09:00:27 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-605</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 27</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Louie Cowie (fl.
		  1933-1965)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1933-1969">1933-1969</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes</extent> <physfacet>The slides can be seen
		  without special equipment but a projector is needed to see them at full
		  size.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Cowie, Louie J. F.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="ara">Arabic.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Louie J. F. Cowie, Church of Scotland missionary in Yemen and South
		  Arabia, came from Aberdeen. She went to Aden as a missionary nurse in 1933
		  after first spending time in Jerusalem studying Arabic. In Aden she was based
		  in Sheikh Othman working in the mission's hospital until 1937 when she went to
		  San'a the capital of Yemen. There she joined a small group working in the
		  medical department of the Iman and stayed there for six years, with breaks for
		  furlough and enforced leave after contracting typhus in 1942. In late 1943 the
		  mission withdrew from San'a and Cowie returned to Aden and the work in the
		  hospital and rural dispensaries. She was also involved in a training programme
		  to teach young men how to set up and run dispensaries in their own areas. In
		  early 1951 Cowie spent some time in Beihan then in 1952 moved there to set up a
		  permanent clinic. She remained there for three years before returning to Sheikh
		  Othman in 1955 to take charge of the hospital. She was in Aden for the birth of
		  the Arab Church of South Arabia in 1961 and was also awarded an MBE. She
		  finally retired and returned to Scotland in 1965.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: circular letters from Cowie describing her
		  work and the mission in Yemen and some holidays taken in retirement
		  (1933-1969); a medal given to Cowie for her services in Yemen; a Church of
		  Scotland pamphlet on the mission (1964); Cowie's New Testament in Arabic; and a
		  set of slides of scenes and mission work in Yemen.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The items are arranged as above. The letters are in chronological
		  order and the slides in number order.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The material was presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World in the late 1990s by Gladys Farquhar.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself.</p>
		
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available and the slides are indexed separately.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the foreign missions of the Church of Scotland are
		  held by the National Library of Scotland. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Cowie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Louie </emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Yemen</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
