<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-209" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-209</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of David Bogue (1750-1825)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation encodinganalog="jisc-hub24">This document was generated by
		  Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the
		  elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Apr 26 10:07:00 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc encodinganalog="jisc-hub04" level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-209</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS BOG</physloc><unittitle>Papers of David Bogue
		  (1750-1825)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1771-1825">[ca. 1771-1825]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent encodinganalog="jisc-hub05">9 boxes, 11 volumes.
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>David Bogue, mission promoter and missionary educator, was born in
		  1750 in Coldingham, Berwickshire, Scotland. The son of John Bogue, a small
		  landowner and magistrate, he studied divinity at Edinburgh University with a
		  view to entering the ministry. As an opponent of the system of church patronage
		  he was unable to find a ministry in Scotland and eventually, in 1777 after some
		  time in London, became pastor at a Congregational church in Gosport, Hampshire.
		  In 1789 he opened a small seminary for training ministers. Bogue has been
		  described as the architect of the modern missionary movement. He was a
		  prominent supporter of evangelism in Hampshire and the Scottish Highlands but,
		  more importantly, was a pioneer of the London Missionary Society (LMS).
		  Sermons, meetings and articles initiated by Bogue led directly to the formation
		  of the LMS in 1785 and he became a long-serving director of the Society. Unable
		  to go to India as a missionary himself he set about training and educating
		  missionaries in his seminary, convinced that such preparation was vital for
		  success. He trained at least 115 missionaries for the LMS, nearly half of them
		  for India, and his lectures were used for training indigenous ministers in the
		  field. Bogue was part of a mission to France in 1802, he was active in
		  establishing the Religious Tract Society and the British and Foreign Bible
		  Society and was a proponent of Jewish missions. With James Bennett he wrote a
		  four volume 
		<title>History of Dissenters</title> which became a standard. He received
		a D.D. from Yale in 1815. Bogue died in 1825 in Brighton while on a preaching
		tour on behalf of the LMS.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of notes on Bogue's lectures at Gosport
		  College (c 1790-1825); notes on Bogue's sermons (1771-1825); notes on missions;
		  addresses to students and ordination charges; and an occasional diary
		  (1793-1797; 1799-1802; 1814-1817).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The collection is arranged as 11 volumes of lecture notes (MSS BOG
		  1-6); 3 boxes of lecture notes (MSS BOG 7); 4 boxes of sermons (MSS BOG 8); and
		  2 boxes of miscellaneous items including diaries (MSS BOG 9).</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>The papers originally included 
		<title>A meditation occasion'd by the earthquake, at London Febr. 8
		  1749</title> and 
		<title>Thoughts on the Last Judgement</title> (1753) bound in one volume.
		This was removed from the Bogue papers and is stored separately at New College
		Library reference MSS MED 2 (see Index to Manuscripts, New College).</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Not clear</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Anderson, G. H. (ed.). 
		<title>Bibliographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New
		York: Macmillan Reference USA, 1998. (2) Cameron, Nigel M. de S. (ed.) 
		<title>Dictionary of Scottish Church History and Theology</title>.
		Edinburgh: T. and T. Clark, 1993. (3) Stephen, L. (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of National Biography</title>. London: Smith, Elder and
		Co., 1886.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts held at New College Library mentions the
		  collection. A handlist is filed in the New College Inventory of Manuscripts
		  under MSS BOG.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>New College also holds a collection relating to Bogue's son, David
		  Bogue, consisting mainly of lecture notes from the University of Glasgow (MSS
		  BOGU). An item removed from the Bogue collection is now New College Library
		  reference MSS MED2. New College also holds separately some of Bogue's sermons
		  and sermons by others on the occasion of his funeral.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="jisc-hub43"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Evangelicalism</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="jisc-hub43"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> <emph altrender="x">Training of</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="jisc-hub43"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<persname encodinganalog="jisc-hub40"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Bogue</emph> <emph altrender="forename">David</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1750-1825</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">Congregational Minister, Historian and Educationist</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="jisc-hub41"> <emph altrender="a">London
		  Missionary Society</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="jisc-hub41"> <emph altrender="a">Gosport
		  College</emph> <emph altrender="z">England</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
