<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-170" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-170</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Sir Robert Carswell (1793-1857)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Dec 03 11:45:18 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-170</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen.590-592</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Sir Robert Carswell
		  (1793-1857)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1817-1825">1817-1825</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 volumes, 1 envelope miscellaneous papers. </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The physician and pathologist Sir Robert Carswell was born in Paisley
		  on 3 February 1793. He studied medicine at Glasgow University. As a student he
		  showed a talent for anatomical drawing and illustrating, and went to the
		  hospitals of Paris and Lyons to pursue this in 1822. On his return to Scotland
		  he took the degree of M.D. at Marischall College, Aberdeen, in 1826. He then
		  returned to Paris to resume studies there. In 1828, Carswell was nominated as
		  Professor of Pathological Anatomy at University College, London, but he
		  remained in France until the completion of a commission for 2,000 water-colour
		  drawings of diseased structures. When he came to London to take up his post, he
		  was also appointed as a Physician to the University College Hospital. He did
		  immediately take up this practice, but involved himself in the preparation of a
		  huge work on pathological anatomy - the 
		<title>Illustrations of the elementary forms of disease</title> (1837).
		Prior to that, in 1836, Carswell went into private practice, and in 1840 he
		resigned his professorship and accepted the postion of physician to Leopold I,
		King of the Belgians, and lived at Laeken the home of the Belgian royal family.
		For his services to Louis-Philippe of France when in exile in Britain, Carswell
		was knighted in July 1850 by Queen Victoria. Sir Robert Carswell died on 15
		June 1857.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers contain descriptions of medical cases from around 1817 to
		  1823 with some later additions, and notes of medical cases made in France (his
		  case books) along with a few letters and other miscellaneous papers, 1822 to
		  1825.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Notes and case books acquired June 1962, Accession nos. E62.40 and
		  E62.41.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 3. Brown-Chalonier.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: anatomical drawings and notes, 1827-1838, London
		  University, University College London (UCL), Manuscripts Room, Ref. Clin Sci
		  MS/unof/1.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physicians</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="othersource"> <emph altrender="surname">Carswell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1793-1857</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Physician </emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
