<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-173" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-173</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Church of Scotland General
			 Assembly</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Dec 07 10:20:13 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-173</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.3.54; Dc.4.57; Dk.8.9-25; Dc.1.37(2)/116; La.II.17/3;
		  La.II.511; La.III.207; La.III.335; La.III.341;
		  La.III.344</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Church of Scotland General
		  Assembly</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1560-1805">1560-1805</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>23 volumes, 1 manuscript address (1 linear metre).
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="sco">Scots,
		  </language> and <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Church of Scotland is the established Church in Scotland. Through
		  the General Assembly - the supreme court, legislative body and debating chamber
		  - the Church expresses the country's concerns from a Christian and Protestant
		  perspective. The first General Assembly met in December 1560 after the
		  Reformation led by John Knox. Today, it is the top tier of Church government
		  and authority. Items of Assembly business are referred from synods,
		  presbyteries, committees, and individuals. The Assembly sits for a week-long
		  session annually in May at the debating-chamber on the Mound, Edinburgh. The
		  monarch may attend, but usually she/he is represented by a Lord High
		  Commissioner. Each session is chaired by a Moderator, chosen annually. The
		  General Assembly is also a social occasion with one of its high points being a
		  garden party held in Holyrood Palace, Edinburgh, with the monarch or Lord High
		  Commissioner in residence. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection contains notes on the proceedings of the General
		  Assemblies held between 1560 and 1605, at La.III.335; acts of the Assembly,
		  1560 to 1618, at Dc.3.54; a history of the General Assembly, 1638, at Dc.4.57;
		  a letter about the Assembly, 1679, at La.III.344; and, a register of the acts
		  and proceedings of the General Assembly, 1690, 1692, 1702-1736, and 1741 to
		  1774, at Dk.8.9-25. In addition, there is an overture of the commission of the
		  General Assembly concerning a petition to repeal an act passed in 1720, at
		  La.II/17/3; an address by the Duke of Atholl to the General Assembly, 1746, at
		  Dc.1.37(2)/116; and, a letter about the emoluments of the High Commissioner,
		  1805, at La.II.511. The collection also includes records of a General Assembly
		  committee on funds for Gaelic speaking students, 1763-1787, at La.III.341; and,
		  minutes from 1638, at La.III.207. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins,
		1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various other references to Church of Scotland
		  related material (check the Indexes for more details). Also, Edinburgh
		  University Library's New College Library can provide access to: 
		<title>General Assembly reports. Church of Scotland</title>. Published:
		Edinburgh, Church of Scotland, [15--]. The New College Library has year 1840
		onwards, at Shelfmark: sLX 50 B</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph>
		  <emph altrender="x">General Assembly</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
