<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-720" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-720</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Clermiston Estate Papers</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Nov 5 10:29:47 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-720</unitid> 
		<physloc>E92.44</physloc><unittitle>Clermiston Estate Papers</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1741-1850">1741-1850</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box, 2 envelopes, containing circa 70 legal
		  documents. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Scott, Walter; Dick, Alexander</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Edinburgh suburb of Clermiston which lies to the west of
		  Corstorphine Hill and the city's Zoological Gardens was originally the
		  Clermiston Estate. Earliest mention of the land is recorded circa 1250 in the 
		<title>Dunfermline register</title>. In these earlier days it was
		referred to variously as Clerbaudiston and terram de Clerribaldi and
		Clerembald's toun. By 1754, the estate had been subdivided into North
		Clermiston and South Clermiston, and Clermiston House had been built in 1792.
		North Clermiston was also referred to as Nether Clermiston, and South
		Clermiston has been referred to as Mid Clermiston, and later Clermiston
		Mains.</p> 
		<p>In 1774, Sir Walter Scott's father had raised a loan on security of
		  part of the Clermiston Estate.</p> 
		<p>As the city expanded in all directions into the near countryside in
		  the 19th and early 20th centuries, references to Clermiston were drawn into
		  city street names in the area: Clermiston Terrace by 1912, Clermiston Avenue by
		  1937, and Clermiston Crescent, Drive, Gardens, Green, Grove, Hill, Loan,
		  Medway, Park, Place and View by 1953. The Clermiston Mains area together with
		  part of Cramond Muir began to be developed for housing in 1957 and street names
		  there were borrowed from 
		<title>Kidnapped </title> by Robert Louis Stevenson.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>This archive relates to the Clermiston Estate and to the Dick family
		  and includes papers particular to, and signed by, Sir Alexander Dick
		  (1703-1785), a notable medical man of the time. The papers, mostly legal,
		  include: instruments of sasine, heritable bonds, bonds of corroboration,
		  documents of discharge and renunciation, searches of incumbrances, a plan of
		  Cramond Muir Road, a sketch of parts of Cramond Moor, a description of
		  Clermiston House, measurement of turnips sold on the Estate, and pages from
		  accounts books. Three of the legal documents relate to dealings of Walter Scott
		  (1729-1799) - father of Sir Walter Scott - who had been raising a loan of one
		  thousand pounds on security of part of the Clermiston Estate.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material purchased from K. W. Jacob, Bourne Books, Bourne, Lincs.,
		  June 1992, Accession no. E92.44</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Harris, Stuart. 
		<title>The place names of Edinburgh their origins and history</title>.
		Edinburgh: Gordon Wright Publishing, 1996.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Family archives</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Family records</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Scott</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Walter</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1729-1799</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Writer to the
		  Signet, Father of the Scottish Writer</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Dick</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1703-1785</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">3rd Baronet Physician</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Clermiston Estate (Edinburgh,
		  Scotland)</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Clermiston (Edinburgh, Scotland)</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
