<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-841" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-841</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of Charles Grant (1778-1866), Baron Glenelg
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Jul 30 09:34:16 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-841</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1801/5/7; Gen. 2040/53-54; Gen.
		  2040/72-73</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Charles Grant (1778-1866), Baron
		  Glenelg </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1807-1856">1807-1856</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>9 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Grant, Charles</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Charles Grant was born on 26 October 1778 at Kidderpore in Bengal. He
		  was the son of the statesman and philanthropist Charles Grant (1746-1823) who
		  had been Chairman of the East India Company in 1805, and was the brother of Sir
		  Robert Grant (1779-1838), Governor of Bombay. Both the younger Grants were
		  educated at Magdalene College, Cambridge. Charles was called to the Bar at
		  Lincoln's Inn, 1807, but he did not practise. He became MP for the Inverness
		  and Fortrose Burghs from 1811 to 1818, and from 1818 he represented Inverness
		  County until 1835 when he became a Peer. He distinguished himself in the
		  Commons first in support of Lord Castlereagh's Preservation of Public Peace
		  Bill in 1812, and also in his support of the East India Company. In 1813 he
		  became a Lord of the Treasury in Lord Liverpool's administration. In 1819 he
		  was Chief Secretary for Ireland, and then in 1827 he was President of the Board
		  of Trade in Canning's government. He also served under Earl Grey and Lord
		  Melbourne. Under Melbourne, in 1835, he was made Colonial Secretary, but his
		  policies were sharply criticised and in 1839 he resigned. On his elevation to
		  the House of Lords in 1835, Grant had taken the title Baron Glenelg, the name
		  of his estate in Scotland. Charles Grant, Baron Glenelg, died in Cannes on 23
		  April 1866</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: letter from Charles Grant at Russell
		  Square, 1807, to the Rt. Hon. Robert Dundas seeking his help in obtaining the
		  post of District Paymaster in the County of Inverness; letter from Grant in
		  London, 1819, to Hay presumably at the Admiralty seeking help for a
		  constituent; undated letters (2) from Glenelg to Lyall and to James Colquhoun;
		  and, letters (5) of Glenelg, 1831-1856.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letters at Gen. 1801/5/7, acquired January 1970, Accession no.
		  E70.3.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 8. Glover-Harriott.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Grant related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): letter to Messrs. Gurney and Hudson
		  regretting he will not be able to attend a meeting of the Westminster Auxiliary
		  Bible Society, 1823, at La.II.647/181; letter to an unnamed correspondent
		  addressed as 'Lord', 1834, at La.II.423/131; franked postal covers addressed to
		  Mrs. Haven, 1829, and to T. B. Bingley, at Dk.6.19/3; and, letter of G. Grey to
		  J. Cochrane informing him that 'there is no situation vacant in the department
		  over which Lord Glenelg presides', 1837, at La.II.647/184.</p> 
		<p>At Gen. 2040/69 there is a letter of Robert Grant at Russell
		  Square.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Grant related
		  material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Grant</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Charles</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1778-1866</emph> <emph altrender="title">Baron Glenelg</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">politician</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
