<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-874" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-874</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of Sir Algernon Hawkins Thomond Keith-Falconer
			 (1852-1930), 9th Earl of Kintore</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Oct 28 11:54:33 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-874</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1952/3/2; Gen. 1982/10; Gen.
		  2040/117</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Sir Algernon Hawkins Thomond
		  Keith-Falconer (1852-1930), 9th Earl of Kintore</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1896-1914">1896-1914</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Keith-Falconer, Algernon Hawkins Thomond</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Algernon Hawkins Thomond Keith-Falconer was born in Edinburgh on 12
		  August 1852. He was the eldest son of Francis Alexander (1828-1880), 8th Earl
		  of Kintore, and Louisa Madaleine Hawkins. He was educated at Eton, and he
		  studied at Trinity College, Cambridge. He succeeded his father as 9th Earl of
		  Kintore in 1880. He was Lord-in-Waiting to Queen Victoria, 1885-1886, and then
		  Captain of the Yeoman Guard, 1886-1889. The Earl was appointed as Governor and
		  Commander-in-Chief of South Australia in 1889, and served until 1895 when he
		  became Lord-in-Waiting to Queen Victoria until her death in 1901. He was then
		  Lord-in-Waiting to King Edward VII until 1905, and then Aide De Camp. He was
		  Deputy Speaker in the House of Lords in 1913. Sir Algernon Hawkins Thomond
		  Keith-Falconer, 9th Earl of Kintore, died on 3 March 1930.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: a letter written on the notepaper of a
		  dwelling in Lower Berkeley Street, W., and signed Kintore, pointing out that
		  'the best thing now to be done with my lad Arthur is to establish him somewhere
		  abroad where he can have facilities for learning the language' and asking for
		  recommendations about accommodation for him; a letter to Captain Walcot about a
		  shooting permit at Strathalbyn, 1890; and, a letter written on the mid-Atlantic
		  on the steamship Kaiserin Auguste Victoria (and written on Hamburg-Amerika Line
		  notepaper) in February 1914, also signed Kintore. The letter is a small written
		  snapshot describing the service and passengers on what was once the largest
		  ship in the world (when launched in 1905). The vessel later became the Canadian
		  Pacific ship Empress of Scotland.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter to Walcot, among purchases 13 May 1977, Accession no.
		  E77.19</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Burke, Sir Bernard. and Burke Ashworth P. 
		<title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage,
		  the Privy Council, and knightage</title>. 87th edition. London: Burke's Peerage
		Ltd., 1929. (2) 
		<title>Who was who 1929-1940</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black,
		1941.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Passenger ships</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ocean liners</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Falconer</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Algernon Hawkins Thomond Keith-</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1852-1930</emph> <emph altrender="title">9th Earl of
		  Kintore</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
