<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-70"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-70</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Colin Cameron
			 Collection of Nyasaland / Malawi Government Documents </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-70</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1061-1069 </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Colin Cameron Collection of Nyasaland
		  / Malawi Government Documents </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1952-1969">1952-1969 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>9 boxes (1
		  linear metre). </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Colin Cameron was born in Lanark on 24 August 1933. He was educated at
		  Uddingston Grammar School and then studied Law at Glasgow University graduating
		  in May 1957 with the degree of Bachelor of Law. While at University he
		  represented the Law Faculty on the Students' Representative Council. He was
		  resident in Uddingston, Glasgow, when his application for entry as an immigrant
		  to the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland was approved in June 1957. In
		  Nyasaland (now Malawi), Cameron took up an appointment as a Solicitor with
		  Messrs Wilson and Morgan, Legal Practitioners, Blantyre, a law concern strongly
		  connected to the United Federal Party - the party of Sir Roy Welensky, Prime
		  Minister of the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, 1956-63. During a state
		  of emergency in 1959, Cameron gave legal help to Africans who had been arrested
		  and detained, and this led to objections from his employers and to ostracism by
		  the white community. Cameron was a paid-up member of the African National
		  Congress. In 1959, he also became a member of the Church of Central Africa
		  Presbyterian and three of his children were baptised into the local church. On
		  the expiry of his contract, he returned to Scotland in late 1960, but at the
		  request of Dr. Hastings K. Banda he returned to Africa to stand in the 1961
		  General Election against the United Federal Party. In this Election for the
		  Nyasaland Legislative Council held on 15 August 1961, Cameron, then aged 27,
		  campaigned as an independent candidate in the Soche Constituency, receiving
		  support in his campaign from the Malawi Congress Party headed by Banda. Cameron
		  voiced his sympathy with the African Nationalist movement and expressly
		  denounced apartheid. He indicated too that he was against the federal structure
		  in Central Africa at that time. A daring challenge to Welensky to debate
		  election issues with him met with the answer that the Prime Minister was fully
		  committed. Cameron was elected to the Council along with the first Africans
		  elected to government in Malawi, and in September 1961, he became Minister of
		  Works and Transport with responsibility for Works, Transport, Water Supply and
		  Sewerage across the country. Thereafter he was Minister of Transport and
		  Communications with the responsibility of transferring the federal functions of
		  Road, Rail, Air, and the Post Office back to the Malawi Government. The Central
		  African Federation to which Cameron indicated his opposition was dissolved in
		  1963. In August 1964, Cameron resigned from the Cabinet on the issue of the
		  introduction by Banda of an amendment to the Constitution allowing detention
		  without trial as part of the law of the newly independent Malawi. On the
		  resumption of private legal practice in Blantyre he represented the former
		  Minister of Education, Henry Chipembere, in a constitutional case which
		  challenged Banda in the High Court, but this resulted in him having to leave
		  Malawi with his family on forty-eight hours notice. During the next thirty
		  years, Cameron established his own legal practice in Irvine, Scotland, and
		  although unable to return to Malawi he continued to support and take an active
		  interest in refugees from Malawi who were then living in Zambia, Tanzania,
		  Zimbabwe, and the United Kingdom. After the first multi-party elections in
		  Malawi in May 1994, Cameron and his wife were invited back to the country and
		  he was offered the position of Honorary Consul for the Republic of Malawi in
		  Scotland by the new President of the country, Bakili Muluzi. Colin Cameron was,
		  for six years, a member of the Council of the Law Society of Scotland, is an
		  active member of Amnesty International, and is an active member of the Scottish
		  National Party. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>Contained in the Colin Cameron Collection are personal letters of
		  congratulation on his election and his appointment as Minister; various
		  personal documents including his letter of appointment as Minister; personal
		  and private correspondence; business, correspondence, and questions and answers
		  of the Legislative assembly, 1963-64; material for speeches; ministerial
		  material; and, constituency material. The Collection also includes material on
		  housing rentals policy; passenger transport; main and district council roads;
		  road safety; air services; lake services; and, material relating to various
		  agencies and institutions in the country. There is also material on Cameron's
		  invitations, tours and visits. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Cameron</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Colin</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1933-</emph> </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Welensky</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Roy</emph>
		  <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1907-1991</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Banda</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Hastings
		  Kamuzu</emph> <emph altrender="dates">c1902-1997</emph> </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Muluzi</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Bakili</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">African National
		  Congress</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Central African
		  Federation</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Federation of
		  Rhodesia and Nyasaland</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Malawi Congress
		  Party</emph> </corpname> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Malawi</emph> <emph altrender="x">Politics and government</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Transportation</emph> </subject> 
		<geogname encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph altrender="z">Rhodesia</emph>
		  </geogname> 
		<geogname encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph>
		  </geogname> 
		<geogname role="subject" encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Malawi</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph>
		  <emph altrender="y">1953-1964</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname role="subject" encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Malawi</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph>
		  <emph altrender="y">1964-</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>Handlist, H70 </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
