<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-247" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-247</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures of Professor David Mather Masson
			 (1822-1907)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jul 11 09:37:51 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-247</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1401-1403; Gen. 1863-1864; Gen. 2076; Dk.1.3/2/2;
		  Dk.4.28-31; Dc.5.100-102</physloc><unittitle>Lectures of Professor David Mather
		  Masson (1822-1907)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1868-1889">1868-1889</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>11 volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Masson, David Mather; Gray, James Allan; Watson, Penelope
		  Gordon; Dickson, W. K; Lumsden, G. J; Sloan, A.D.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>David Mather Masson was born in Aberdeen in 1822. He was educated at
		  Aberdeen Grammar School and then he studied at Marischal College, Aberdeen,
		  where he graduated with degree of MA in 1839. He then went to Edinburgh
		  University to study Divinity with the intention of entering the Church, but he
		  gave up his studies. Masson then pursued a literary career, first in Aberdeen,
		  then Edinburgh, then in London. He became Professor of English Literature at
		  University College, London, in 1853, a post which he held for some twelve
		  years. Then, in 1865, he was elected to the Regius Chair of Rhetoric and
		  English Literature at Edinburgh University. While at Edinburgh University,
		  Masson took a prominent part in the fight for the university education of women
		  and he was the first professor to lecture to classes organised by the Edinburgh
		  Ladies' Educational Association.</p> 
		<p>Masson's publications include 
		<title>British novelists and their styles: being a critical sketch of the
		  history of British prose fiction</title> (1859), and the multi-volume 
		<title>The life of John Milton: narrated in connexion with the political,
		  ecclesiastical, and literary history of his time</title> (1859-1894).</p> 
		<p>In 1893, Masson was appointed Historiographer Royal for Scotland. He
		  resigned his Chair at the University in 1895. Professor David Mather Masson
		  died in 1907.</p> 
		<p>Offering a glimpse of Masson's well-attended lectures are the notes
		  taken in 1868 by the Physician, James Allan Gray, born in 1854. Gray was
		  awarded the degree of MA in 1872 and obtained a Bachelor of Medicine and Master
		  in Surgery in 1876 and became registered in Scotland in that year, on August 2.
		  He was awarded the degree of Doctor of Medicine with a gold medal in 1880. Gray
		  became a Fellow of the Royal College of Physicans of Edinburgh in 1881. James
		  Allan Gray practised in Leith for 51 years and died in 1930.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Notebooks in the collection record earlier lectures by Masson on
		  Rhetoric and English Literature while at the University. The notes cover
		  lectures on the Mythical period, the Roman, Anglo-Saxon and Anglo-Norman
		  periods, influences on English literature, the history of English language, and
		  style etc., given between 1868-1869. There are lectures on English Literature
		  taken down 1878-1879, 1880, and 1887-1889, and on Rhetoric and English
		  Literature, 1881-1882 and 1882-1883.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Lectures taken down by James Allan Gray were received from J. D. Allan
		  Gray, January 1968, Accession no. E68.5. Those taken down by Miss Penelope
		  Gordon Watson were received from P. Haig Ferguson in January 1971, Accession
		  no. E71.1. Notes at Gen. 2076 received from Keele University, April 1978,
		  Accession no. E78.17</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Rice, D. Talbot (compiler). 
		<title>The university portraits</title>. pp.145-147. Edinburgh: The
		University Press, 1957.</p> 
		<p>Edited by J. D. Allan Gray, extracts from the diary of James Allan
		  Gray were published in the 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>, Vol.25. 1971-1972.
		pp.45-51.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Masson related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): his commission of appointment as
		  Professor, DK.2.20/5; letters to others; mention in letter(s); copy of his
		  essays, JA 3097; testimonial; and, more recently acquired correspondence. In
		  addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters to Edward Arber, 1879, at Birmingham
		  University Information Services, Special Collections Department, Ref. Arber NRA
		  13205 Arber; correspondence with Thomas Carlyle, 1848-78, Ref. MSS 1766-78, and
		  letters (100) to Alexander Campbell, Fraser, 1842-1904, Ref. Dep 208 NRA 27273
		  Fraser, and correspondence mainly with Lord Rosebery, 1841-1906, Ref. MSS 9657,
		  10087-10131, 10997 Passim, at the National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts
		  Division; correspondence with Macmillans, 1856-95, at the British Library,
		  Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 54792; letters to Hew Morrison from Masson
		  and members of his family, 1887-1913, Edinburgh Central Library, Ref.
		  NRA(S)3563 NRA 38890 Edinburgh CL; and, letters to GC Robertson, at London
		  University, University College London (UCL) Manuscripts Room, Ref. MS ADD 88
		  NRA 14256 Robertson.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Rhetoric</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English language</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Masson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">David</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1822-1907</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of
		  Rhetoric and English Literature, Biographer and Editor </emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Gray</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James Allan</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1854-1930</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physician</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh Association for the University
		  Education of Women</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
