<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-496" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-496</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers relating to Dr Robert Scot Skirving
			 (1859-1956)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Feb 3 10:40:37 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-496</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.87; Dc.4.94/117-137</physloc><unittitle>Papers relating to
		  Dr Robert Scot Skirving (1859-1956)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1889-1892">1889-1892</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 folder, 15 letters</extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Dr Robert Scot Skirving (1859-1956)</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Robert Scot Skirving was born in Campton, near Haddington, East
		  Lothian, on 18 December 1859. He was educated locally in Haddington and then at
		  Edinburgh Academy. He then went to Eastman's Royal Naval Academy in Southsea,
		  near Portsmouth, before joining the Merchant Navy. He made voyages to Iceland,
		  served as a cadet on the training ship 'Conway', and served as an apprentice on
		  the 'Tantallon Castle' on a voyage to Adelaide, Australia. On his way back
		  Skirving fell ill and had to leave the navy, so he decided to study medicine at
		  Edinburgh University. On graduation, he discovered that at just under the age
		  of twenty-one he was unable to take up the post of House Physician at Edinburgh
		  Royal Infirmary for which he had applied. Until he met this stipulation he
		  studied additionally in Dublin and Vienna before taking up the post. In his
		  early twenties, Skirving started a new life in Australia taking up work
		  initially as a locum before accepting a position as Medical Superintendent at
		  the Prince Alfred Hospital, Sydney, in November 1883. Then, in 1884 he started
		  a private practice in Sidney though remained as an Honorary Physician at Prince
		  Alfred Hospital until 1911 when he became Honorary Consulting Physician. He
		  also joined the surgical staff of St. Vincent's Hospital, Sidney, retaining his
		  position until 1923. Earlier, at the turn of the century, he served in the
		  South African war, and he served during the First World War too. Throughout his
		  career, Skirving published widely in Australian and British medical journals on
		  subjects as diverse as diseases of the tongue, sore throats in anaemic persons,
		  facial anaesthesia, treatment of fractures, sea-faring doctors, surgery at sea,
		  and fits and faints. Dr. Robert Scot Skirving died in Australia on 15 July
		  1956. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: correspondence from Skirving to D. G.
		  Ritchie in April, May and June 1889; and, his account of the 'Snowball Riot' of
		  1838 in which his father had been a participant.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Macintosh, Ann (ed.). 
		<title>Memoirs of Dr Robert Scot Skirving 1859-1956</title>. Sydney:
		Foreland Press, 1988. (2) 
		<title>Robert Scot Skirving Obit, July 15, 1956</title>. Sydney:
		Australasian Medical Publishing Co. Ltd.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physicians</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Skirving</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert Scot</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1859-1956</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physician</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
