<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-687" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-687</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Correspondence relating to Sir Roy Welensky
			 (1907-1991)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Aug 18 09:24:25 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-687</unitid> 
		<physloc>E92.76; E93.121 </physloc><unittitle>Correspondence relating to
		  Sir Roy Welensky (1907-1991)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1952/1976">1952-1976</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 folder containing: circa 25 letters; circa 5
		  invitation and menu cards; miscellaneous cuttings.</extent> <physfacet>Access
		  to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Welensky, Roy</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Roy (Roland) Welensky was born in Harare (then Salisbury), Zimbabwe
		  (then Southern Rhodesia), in 1907. His father was an emigrant from Poland,
		  first to the United States, then to South Africa and finally a pioneer trekker
		  to Rhodesia. Welensky was educated in Harare and left school at the age of
		  fourteen finding a variety of employment across Africa. In 1924, he turned to
		  the railway for work - and to prize-fighting - in Kabwe (Broken Hill), Zambia
		  (then Northern Rhodesia). In Broken Hill he entered the trade union movement as
		  a member of the Railway Workers' Union. Around this time too he became
		  heavy-weight boxing champion of the Rhodesias, 1926-1928. He rose rapidly as a
		  labour leader and in 1933, at the age of 26, he was elected chairman of the
		  Broken Hill branch of the RWU and a National Councillor holding both positions
		  until his retirement from the railways 20 years later. By the early-1930s,
		  Welensky was an engine driver on the main line. His political career began in
		  1938 with his election to the Northern Rhodesian Legislative Council. Between
		  1941-1946 he was Director of Manpower for Northern Rhodesia, and in 1941 he
		  formed the Northern Rhodesia Labour Party. Welensky participated in the
		  Commission set up under Sir John Forster to investigate the riots in the
		  Zambian Copperbelt in 1940. He was also a member of the Strauss Railway
		  Arbitration Tribunal in 1943, and the Grant Railway Arbitration Tribunal in
		  1946. He was made Companion of the Order of St. Michael and St. George (CMG) in
		  1946. Welensky was a member of delegations to London to discuss mineral
		  royalties, 1949, and the constitution in 1950 and 1951. He continued to serve
		  unopposed on the Legislative Council until the Federation of Northern and
		  Southern Rhodesia and Nyasaland was formed in 1953. Welensky was a strong
		  supporter of - and was instrumental in the creation of - this Central African
		  Federation. He was elected to the first Assembly of the Federation in 1953 and
		  became the right hand man of its architect, Sir Godfrey Huggins, later Lord
		  Markham. Welensky was knighted in that year and on Sir Godfrey's retirement in
		  1956 he succeeded him as Prime Minister. He was made Knight Commander of the
		  Order of St. Michael and St. George (KCMG) in 1959. He continued to head the
		  Federation until it was dismantled in 1963. His Southern Rhodesian Federal
		  Party was defeated by the Rhodesian Front of Ian Smith in 1964. After Smith's
		  unilateral declaration of independence in 1965, Welensky left politics.
		  Latterly he lived in Blandford Forum, Dorset, England. The Rt. Hon. Sir Roy
		  Welensky KCMG died in 1991.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The correspondence is composed of: letters to and from E. R. Wright,
		  1952-1976, along with some miscellaneous material; and, typescript letter to A.
		  Wallace, 29 March 1961. In addition, among miscellaneous invitations and menu
		  cards there is a copy of the Rhodesian unilateral declaration of independence
		  11 November 1965. There are also two war newspaper reports: one from the 
		<title>Rhodesia Herald</title> dated Salisbury, 1 September 1939,
		relating to German troops having invaded Poland; and, a free special news-sheet
		of the 
		<title>Rhodesia Herlad</title> dated Salisbury, 14 August 1945.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Wright letters, purchased October 1992, Quaritch, Bloomsbury,
		  Accession no. E92.76. Wallace letter, purchased December 1993, S. Dupre,
		  Accession no. E93.121. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled largely using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>Who's who 1987</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1987.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Material relating to the Federation and its resources, and described
		  within the Archives Hub service, are the Edinburgh University Library (Special
		  Collections Division) 
		<title>Papers relating to Kenneth David Kaunda</title> the 
		<title>Colin Cameron Collection of Nyasaland / Malawi Government
		  Documents</title>, the 
		<title>Collection of Kenneth Mackenzie</title>, and the 
		<title>Correspondence relating to Copper Mining in Northern Rhodesia
		  (Zambia), 1960-1962</title>.</p> 
		<p>Check the Index to Manuscripts, Special Collections Divison, for other
		  material, indexed by subject.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Welensky
		  related material: correspondence and papers, National Archives of Zimbabwe,
		  Ref. WE7; correspondence and papers, 1940s-1990, Oxford University, Bodleian
		  Library of Commonwealth and African Studies at Rhodes House, Ref. MSS Welensky,
		  NRA 39191 Welensky, and letters to R. T. Hungerford, 1953-1965, and
		  correspondence with Sir Albert Robinson, 1953-1963, Ref. MSS.Afr.s.2164 NRA
		  40207 Robinson; correspondence with Lord and Lady Avon, 1961-1978, Birmingham
		  University Information Services, Special Collections Department, Ref. AP 23/66
		  NRA 28779 Eden; correspondence with P. V. Emrys-Evans, 1953-1967, British
		  Library, manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 58251, and letters to Col.
		  O'Donovan, 1962-1979, Ref. Deposit 9437; correspondence with Sir Ian Wilson,
		  circa 1963-1964, York University, Borthwick Institute of Historical Research;
		  and, correspondence (69 items) with Desmond Donnelly, 1969-1974, National
		  Library of Wales, Ref. Desmond Donnelly Papers/A1041 NRA 41723 Donnelly.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381"> 
		<subject source="lcsh"><emph altrender="a">World War,
		  1939-1945</emph></subject> 
	 </controlaccess>
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Welensky</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Roy Roland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1907-1991</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight, Rhodesian Statesman, Former Prime Minister of
		  Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Zambia</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
