<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-242" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-242</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor John Lee (1779-1859)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Jun 15 10:01:41 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-242</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.8.7-8; Dc.8.140-165; Gen. 186D;
		  CHA4</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor John Lee (1779-1859)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1794-1858">1794-1858</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division;
		  and Edinburgh University, New College Library</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John Lee was born at Torwoodlee Mains, near Stow, in Midlothian, on 22
		  November 1779. He began studies at Edinburgh University in 1794 taking full
		  courses in Arts, Medicine and Divinity and graduated with the degree of MD in
		  1801. His thesis was entitled 
		<title>De viribus animi in corpus agentibus</title>. After a brief period
		with the army hospital service, he began to study law. He became licensed as a
		preacher and was a pastor in London for a brief period before being ordained in
		1808 as a Minister in Peebles. In 1812, Lee was appointed Professor of Church
		History at St. Mary's College, St. Andrews, and became Rector of the College.
		In 1820, he was appointed Professor of Moral Philosophy at King's College,
		Aberdeen. A year later he resigned both Professorships, and after he was
		awarded the degree of Doctor of Divinity by St. Andrews University he became
		Minister of Canongate Church in Edinburgh, and then Minister of Lady Yester's
		Church. In 1827, Lee was made principal clerk of the General Assembly of the
		Church of Scotland, and in 1832 he unsuccessfully contested the Moderatorship
		of the Assembly with Dr. Thomas Chalmers. In 1834, he became Minister of the
		Old Kirk of St. Giles in Edinburgh, and in 1837 he was Principal of the United
		College at St. Andrews. Lee was appointed Principal of Edinburgh University in
		1840 and by 1843 he held the office along with the Chair of Divinity in
		succession to Chalmers. He was appointed Moderator of the General Assembly in
		1844. This occurred just after the Disruption within the Church in 1843, when
		Chalmers demitted office to lead the Free Church of Scotland. Lee's
		publications include 
		<title>Memorial for the bible societies in Scotland. Remarks on the
		  complaint of His Majesty's printers against the Marquis of Huntly and
		  others</title> (1824), 
		<title>Dr. Lee's refutation of the charges brought against him by the
		  Rev. Dr. Chalmers and others ...</title> (1837), 
		<title>Dr. Lee's additional refutation of the charges brought against him
		  by the Rev. Dr. Chalmers and others</title> (1837), 
		<title>Lectures on the history of the Church of Scotland, from the
		  reformation to the revolution settlement</title> (1860), and 
		<title> The University of Edinburgh from its foundation in 1583 to the
		  year 1839: a historical sketch</title> (1884). Lee served on the Royal
		Commission on the Universities and Colleges of Scotland, 1826, the
		recommendations of which were incorporated in an Act of 1858. Among its
		provisions was that the office of Principal would be no longer considered an
		ecclesiastical office attached to the Church of Scotland but would be open lay
		persons and members of any Church. In 1830, Lee had been appointed as a
		Chaplain in ordinary to the King, and in 1840 he was Dean of the Chapel Royal
		in Stirling. Dr. John Lee died in Edinburgh University on 2 May 1859.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Within the collection, at Dk.8.7-8, are papers, chiefly lectures and
		  notes on theology, philosophy, biblical criticism, and rhetoric, c.1812-1854.
		  At Dc.8.140-165 are notebooks written as a student at Edinburgh University,
		  chiefly notes of lectures, 1794-1801, and a Latin vocabulary. At Gen. 186D are
		  diplomas, commissions etc, 1801-1858, along with a list of items which include
		  diplomas from St. Andrews University 1801 and the Masonic Lodge 1818, as well
		  as the Freedom of Aberdeen 1827, and Commissions by King George IV, King
		  William IV, and Queen Victoria appointing Lee as Chaplain in Ordinary. At CHA4
		  are 1829-43 letters to Thomas Chalmers.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Lee's papers at Dk.8.7-8 were presented by W. E. Lee, 1927.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Lee, Sydney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.11. Kennett-Lluelyn.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909. (2) Rice, D. Talbot (comp.). 
		<title>The university portraits</title>. pp.126-128. Edinburgh: The
		University Press, 1957. (3) Grant, Alexander. 
		<title>The story of the University of Edinburgh during its first three
		  hundred years</title>. Vol.2. pp.271-274. London: Longmans, Green and Co.,
		1884.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to material related to
		  Principal John Lee (check the Indexes for more details): correspondence to and
		  from Lee; address book at Dc.3.99/5; class cards and class certificates;
		  matriculation cards; receipts; and, testimonials. In addition, the UK National
		  Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission,
		  notes: correspondence and papers at the National Library of Scotland,
		  Manuscripts Division; papers relating to St. Andrews University and other
		  correspondence at St. Andrews University Library; and, letters at the National
		  Archives of Scotland.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theology</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Lee</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1779-1859</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Principal of Edinburgh University </emph> </persname>
		
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland: General
		  Assembly</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
