<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-231" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-231</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor Otto Schlapp (1859-1939)</titleproper>
		  
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed May 02 10:56:19 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-231</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2187</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor Otto Schlapp
		  (1859-1939)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1880-1939">1880-[193-]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English</language>; <language langcode="ger">German</language>
		  </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Otto Schlapp was born in Erfurt, in Thuringia, Germany, on 15 May
		  1859. Schlapp was educated first in his native town and then, at the age of
		  twenty, at the University of Jena. In 1880, the second year of his studies, he
		  came to Scotland to study English and Sanskrit at Edinburgh University. In
		  1881, Schlapp returned to Germany to continue his studies at Berlin, Leipzig,
		  and Strasbourg universities. Later on, he obtained the degree of Dr.Philos from
		  Kaiser-Wilhelms-Universitaet zu Strassburg (Strasbourg), with a thesis entitled
		  
		<title>Die Anfaenge von Kants Kritik des Geschmacks und des Genies, 1764
		  bis 1775: erster Teil einer Untersuchung ueber Kants Lehre vom Genie und die
		  Entstehung der Kritik der Urteilskraft</title>. Returning to Edinburgh in 1887,
		he taught German at George Watson's College, Edinburgh, and at Edinburgh
		Ladies' College until 1894. Schlapp became a Lecturer in German at Edinburgh
		University in 1894, and in 1920 he was appointed Reader. In 1926, Schlapp
		became Professor of German at the University. His publications include 
		<title>Bilder aus Sizilien</title> (1885), 
		<title>Kants Lehre vom Genie und die Entstehung der 'Kritik der
		  Urteilskraft'</title> (1901), a revision and enlargement of 
		<title>Chamber's elementary German grammar</title> (1904), and a revision
		and enlargement of 
		<title>Chambers's advanced German grammar</title> (1905). Earlier in his
		life, in 1899, Schlapp gave up his German nationality, and he became a British
		subject in 1914. He retired through ill-health in 1929, and received an
		honorary Doctorate of Laws from his University in 1930. Professor Otto Schlapp
		died on 26 December 1939.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers of Professor Otto Schlapp include: class certificates,
		  session 1880-81, for Rhetoric and English Literature, and Sanskrit and
		  Comparative Philology; a medal, session 1880-81, for Sanskrit; LL.D diploma
		  dated 1930; letters, tributes and a decorated formal address on retirement, 11
		  July 1929; a copy of Schlapp's thesis; a copy of his letter of application to
		  the Chair along with testimonials and other documents; an address on the place
		  of modern languages in examinations for bursaries to Scottish universities,
		  1900; certificates of renunciation of German citizenship and of British
		  naturalisation; invitations and photographs; cuttings relating to Scott and
		  Carlyle medallions; and, etchings of the University etc.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The immediate source of the Schlapp papers was Dr. Robert Schlapp
		  (1899-1991), son of Professor Otto Schlapp and Senior Lecturer in Mathematical
		  Physics at Edinburgh University. The papers were received in August 1984.
		  Accession no. E84.27.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) 
		<title>Who was who 1929-1940</title>. Vol.3. London: Adam and Charles
		Black, 1941. (2) 
		<title>University of Edinburgh Journal</title>. Vol.3. 1929-1930. p.38.
		Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd. (3) Burnett, John H. (et al.). 
		<title>The university portraits</title>. Second series. pp.169-171.
		Edinburgh: Eyre and Spottiswoode, 1986.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Otto Schlapp material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): various letters of Schlapp, including his
		  application for the German Chair, in Sar.Coll.33. and Sar.Coll.142/1 (Gen. 202
		  and Gen. 237); a book presented to Schlapp at Df.4.67, and a mention in a
		  letter at Gen. 767/10; and, some 21 notebooks of notes of his lectures in
		  German taken down 1913-1914, at Gen. 1862. The Library, Special Collections
		  Division, also holds another copy of Schlapp's thesis 
		<title>Die Anfaenge von Kants Kritik des Geschmacks und des Genies, 1764
		  bis 1775: erster Teil einer Untersuchung ueber Kants Lehre vom Genie und die
		  Entstehung der Kritik der Urteilskraft</title> (1899) at shelfmark Zm.6.18.
		</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">German language</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">German literature</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Schlapp</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Otto</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1859-1939</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of German, Edinburgh University</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Kant</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Immanuel</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1724-1804</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Philosopher</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
