<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-304 " countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-304 </eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Sir Henry Rowley Bishop
			 (1786-1855)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Nov 08 09:38:16 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-304 </unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1730/1 Bishop; La.III.366 </physloc><unittitle>Papers of
		  Sir Henry Rowley Bishop (1786-1855)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1822-1853">1822-1853</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>23 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Henry Rowley Bishop was born in Great Portland Street, London, on 18
		  November 1786. He received his early musical instruction from the Italian
		  composer and teacher Francesco Bianchi. Rowley's first operatic work was 
		<title>Angelina</title> (1804) which was played at the Theatre Royal,
		Margate, and soon after this he began writing ballet music for the King's
		Theatre in Haymarket, and for Drury Lane. The success of 
		<title>Tamerlan et Bajazet</title> (1806) at the King's led to a
		permanent engagement. Rowley's first important opera 
		<title>The Circassian bride</title> was accepted by Drury Lane and
		performed there on 23 February 1809. On the following night the theatre was
		burned down and the score was lost, but he re-wrote it from memory. When the
		Drury Lane company moved to the Lyceum Theatre, Rowley continued to write for
		them. He was then engaged as composer and director of music at Covent Garden,
		and his first work there was 
		<title>The Knight of Snowdoun</title>, a musical drama based on Scott's 
		<title>Lady of the lake</title>. A rapid succession of original
		compositions and compilations and music for plays and operas followed. In
		addition to his post at Covent Garden, Rowley was director of music at the
		King's Theatre in 1816 and 1817. His connection with Covent Garden ended in
		1824, and in 1825 he was engaged by Drury Lane where he produced 
		<title>The fall of Algiers</title> (1825). His permanent connection with
		Drury Lane ended in 1830. He continued writing of course, and his work was
		performed at the Haymarket, Drury Lane and Vauxhall Gardens Theatres. Rowley
		was for a time Professor of Harmony and Composition at the Royal Academy of
		Music, and in November 1841 he was elected as the Reid Professor of Music at
		Edinburgh University, a post which he held until December 1843. The year
		previously, in 1842, Rowley was knighted by Queen Victoria. In 1848, he became
		Professor of Music at Oxford University. Sir Henry Rowley Bishop died at his
		home in Cambridge Street, Hyde Park, on 30 April 1855. He was buried at
		Marylebone Cemetery, Finchley Road, in May 1855.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers of Sir Henry Rowley Bishop consist of correspondence
		  including those about: the Royal Academy of Music, 21 November 1822; an
		  oratorio, 1835; the Reid Commemoration Concert, Edinburgh, 1842; the Society of
		  British Musicians, 1847; and, suggestions for future operatic productions,
		  Covent Garden, 1853. Material in the Laing Collection includes: letters to R.
		  Stephenson, Remington, and Stephenson and Co., 1827, 1847, and undated, letters
		  to H. B. Peacock, 1836-1853, letters, 1843, 1844, and letter to Mons. Jullien,
		  1847, at La.III.366;</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter about the Royal Academy of Music purchased 1972, Accession no.
		  E73.3. letter about an oratorio purchased November 1972, Accession no. E72.61.
		  Letter about the Reid Commemoration Concert purchased April 1979, Accession no.
		  E79.35. Letter about the Society of British Musicians purchased April 1977,
		  Accession no. E77.17. Letter about future Covent Garden productions purchased
		  April 1978, Accession no. E78.8.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.2. Beal-Browell.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show another referencs to Bishop related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): a request for support for Bishop as a
		  candidate for the Chair of Music at Edinburgh University, 1841, at Dk.6.20/97.
		  In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the
		  Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: compositions, 1810-1836, British
		  Library, Music Collections, Ref. Add MSS 36938-68; and, letters to Charles
		  Mackay, 1851-1853, British Library, Music Collections, Ref. Add MS 29905.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Opera</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Bishop</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Henry Rowley</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1786-1855</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Composer</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Royal Opera House (London, England)</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Royal Academy of Music (London, England :
		  1822- )</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Society of British Musicians</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
