<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-580" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-580</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Joseph H. Oldham (1874-1969) and Betty Gibson
			 (fl. 1928-1960)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Nov 27 17:11:55 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-580</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 2</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Joseph H. Oldham
		  (1874-1969) and Betty Gibson (fl. 1928-1960)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1912-1975">1912-1975</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Oldham, Joseph Houldsworth; Gibson, Betty D.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="ger">German.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Joseph Houldsworth Oldham, pioneer of ecumenical missionary and social
		  concern, was born in 1874 of Scottish parents in India. He was educated in
		  Edinburgh and at Oxford, from where he graduated in 1896. A religious
		  conversion prompted Oldham to travel to India in 1897 to work with the YMCA
		  where he stayed for three years, marrying Mary Fraser in 1898. Illness forced
		  them to return in 1901 and Oldham went on to study theology at New College,
		  Edinburgh and in Germany. On his return to Scotland he was twice an assistant
		  minister but was unable to secure his own ministry. In 1908 he became
		  organising secretary for the 1910 World Missionary Conference at Edinburgh,
		  regarded by many as the starting point of the modern ecumenical movement, and
		  he was subsequently secretary of the Conference Continuation committee. In 1912
		  Oldham founded the 
		<title>International Review of Missions</title> which, under Oldham's
		editorship until 1927, established itself as the most prominent missionary
		periodical in the world.</p> 
		<p>During World War 1 Oldham worked to keep the spirit of
		  internationalism alive through his writings and became a trusted adviser of the
		  government on missions and German missionaries in particular. With the return
		  of peace Oldham continued to promote the cause of co-operation between mission
		  boards. He became the founder and secretary in 1921 of the International
		  Missionary Council. He also travelled widely (often with his secretary Betty
		  Gibson) and was especially concerned with education and the issues raised by
		  colonial administration in Africa. His knowledge of both India and Africa
		  thrust him into the role of mediator between Europeans, Africans and Indians in
		  Kenya and his principle that African native interests should be paramount was
		  embodied in government policy in 1923. Also in that year Oldham was a key
		  figure in the establishment of a committee on Native Education in Tropical
		  Africa. His 
		<title>Christianity and the Race Problem</title> was published in 1924
		and was his most substantial and successful book. After organising the first
		conference of missionary educators and colonial administrators in 1926, he was
		instrumental in securing funds for the founding of the International Institute
		of African Languages and Cultures.</p> 
		<p>From 1931 to 1938 he was its administrative director and responsible
		  for much of the work which made Lord Hailey's 
		<title>African Survey</title> possible. Oldham continued, often in
		partnership with Lord Lugard, to advise on government and administration in
		Kenya, however he also remained concerned about the future of the Christian
		missions and the church. As a layperson Oldham grew more convinced of role of
		the laity in this future and the need for a co-operative relationship between
		religious and secular groups and, to this end, encouraged small study groups as
		a means of research. He was, from 1934, chairman of the research committee of
		the Universal Christian Council for Life and Work and a key figure at the 1937
		Oxford conference. His efforts were to influence Christian thinking for a
		generation and lead to the formation of the World Council of Churches. During
		the Second World War he continued to encourage debate about lay responsibility
		in society. Through the meetings of his 'Moot' with such figures as T.S. Eliot
		and John Baillie and through his 
		<title>Christian Newsletter</title> he initiated much new thinking about
		Christian responsibility in modern society. From his efforts the Christian
		Frontier Council developed. Oldham retired from public life to Dunford, Sussex
		but continued to write, particularly about Africa, and was involved with the
		formation of the Capricorn Africa Movement. He was awarded honorary degrees
		from Edinburgh (1931) and Oxford (1937) and appointed CBE in 1951. Oldham's
		wife died in 1965 and Oldham himself died in 1969 at St Leonards-on-Sea,
		Sussex.</p> 
		<p>Betty D. Gibson was one of the secretarial staff of the International
		  Missionary Council in which she played a significant role acting as secretary
		  and administrator for both the IMC and for Joseph Oldham. A graduate in French
		  and German, in 1916 she joined the staff of Oldham's Continuation Committee
		  which had been set up after the 1910 World Missionary Conference. She made
		  several trips overseas for missionary conferences or to investigate the state
		  and extent of missionary activity in various countries and kept in close
		  contact with Oldham throughout.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: correspondence and reports relating to the
		  difficulties faced by German and German speaking missionaries after the war
		  (1914-c 1923); reports on the history and activities of German missions, in
		  particular the Basel Mission (1912-1951); correspondence between Oldham and
		  Gibson about Gibson's visit to Africa and Oldham's IMC work (1933); and papers
		  and correspondence collected by Gibson on missions and churches (including some
		  German missions) in Congo, Rwanda, Tanzania, Sierra Leone, Cameroon, Ghana,
		  Nigeria, Portugal and Portuguese Africa (1917-1975).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The files have been kept as found.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were obtained for the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World by Professor Andrew Walls.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself, (2) Clements, Keith. 
		<title>Faith on the Frontier</title>. Edinburgh: T. and T. Clark, 1999.
		(3) Anderson, G. H. (ed.). 
		<title>Bibliographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New
		York: Macmillan Reference USA, 1998. (4) Williams, E. T. and Nicholls, C. S.
		(eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of National Biography 1961-1970</title>. Oxford: Oxford
		University Press, 1981.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>There are also Oldham and Gibson papers in New College Library,
		  Edinburgh University and in the Neil Bernard collection at the Centre. The
		  National Library of Scotland has an extensive missionary collection including
		  some correspondence with Oldham and Gibson. The archives of the various
		  organisations with which Oldham was associated such as the International
		  Missionary Council and World Council of Churches (in Geneva) are also relevant.
		  Refer to the Archives Hub descriptions entitled 
		<title>Oldham Papers</title>, 
		<title>Papers of Betty D. Gibson </title> and the collection relating to 
		<title>John Baillie</title>.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Oldham</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Joseph Houldsworth</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1874-1969</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Missionary</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gibson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Betty D</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl
		  1928-1960</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Missionary</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">International Missionary Council</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Africa</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Germany</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
