<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-584" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-584</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Helen B. K. Maclean (fl.
			 1921-1954)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Nov 28 09:17:48 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-584</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 14</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Helen B. K. Maclean (fl.
		  1921-1954)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1930-1984">[ca. 1930]-1984</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 volumes</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Maclean, Helen B. K.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="chi">Chinese.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Helen B. K. Maclean (known as Nell), (United Free) Church of Scotland
		  missionary in China, was born in a village in the highlands of Scotland. Her
		  father was a schoolmaster and elder in the village kirk and she graduated from
		  Edinburgh University (MA) in 1916. She was accepted for China by the by the
		  mission in 1921 and spent her first six months in Peking learning the language.
		  Further language training and an introduction to evangelising followed in
		  Kaiyuan in Manchuria where she first met Fragrant Tree (Wang Su Fen) who was to
		  become her lifelong friend. In 1923 she moved to Shenyang to teach in the
		  mission's girls school, became the school's principal missionary in 1925 and
		  was also involved in developing youth work in the area. She remained at the
		  school for the rest of her time in China, appointing a Chinese principal,
		  encouraging the Church to take more responsibility from the mission and seeing
		  the school through a difficult period when the Japanese occupied Manchuria. She
		  returned to Scotland on furlough three times: 1926-28, 1933-34 when she took
		  Fragrant Tree with her, and 1939 part of which she spent in Japan. After Pearl
		  Harbour in December 1941 Maclean was put under house arrest for six months and
		  the school was closed. With other colleagues she was sent to Japan for
		  internment but was returned home as an exchange prisoner before the end of
		  1942. The Church of Scotland sent her to work in Ghana from 1944 until 1946
		  when she was able to return to Manchuria and the school. When the communists
		  entered Shenyang in November 1948 her position became more difficult, she
		  suffered from bouts of dysentery and after the school was closed in 1949 she
		  was ordered home. From 1951 until 1954 she worked in Jamaica then returned to
		  Inverness in Scotland. She kept in touch with Fragrant Tree who secured
		  permission to leave China in 1963 and joined Maclean in Scotland. Fragrant Tree
		  looked after Maclean during her final illness and after Maclean's death moved
		  to an old people's home where she died.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of two version of an unpublished manuscript 
		<title>Memories of a Missionary</title> by Maclean, the first dates from
		1967 or just after, the second is the same version but amended and annotated at
		a later date and including photographs and pictures dating from c 1930s to
		1984. It is an account of the relationship between Maclean and her friend
		Fragrant Tree, describing their backgrounds, their work for the mission and
		church in Manchuria and events in China during the period that Maclean was
		there (1921-1949). The manuscript has a foreword by Rev. Professor William
		Barclay of the University of Glasgow.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The collection consists of two items only.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>The collection was briefly listed by Ralph Covell in 1992.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World either by Mrs I. P. D. McCulloch who presented a
		  pamphlet of plays by Maclean or through the China section of the Church of
		  Scotland, along with other Manchurian material.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself.</p>
		
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the foreign missions of Church of Scotland are held at
		  the National Library of Scotland and include correspondence with Maclean dating
		  from 1921. The library of the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the
		  Non-Western World has a pamphlet of five short plays by Maclean 
		<title>Proud to Belong to China</title> (n.d. c 1947?) which was
		presented by Mrs I. P. D. McCulloch. The Centre also holds other collections of
		missionary papers relating to Manchuria.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Maclean</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Helen B. K.</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Manchuria (China)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
