<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid publicid="GB 237 Coll-1030" countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237">GB
		237 Coll-1030</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="">Papers, plans and drawings of Edward
			 Taylor, Architect and Planning Consultant</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by JavaScript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2 on 
		  <date>Fri Dec 3 10:55:37 UTC 2004</date>.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1030"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-1030</unitid> 
		<physloc>E2004.3</physloc><unittitle>Papers, plans and drawings of Edward
		  Taylor, Architect and Planning Consultant</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1985/2000">1985-2000</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>5 boxes; 6 drawing or plan-boxes; 2 wrapped piles
		  board-mounted drawings.</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
		
		<origination>Edward Taylor</origination> 
	 </did> 
	 <phystech> 
		<p>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted</p></phystech> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Edward Taylor, an Architect and Planning Consultant, Tourism and
		  Leisure Projects, in Edinburgh.</p> 
		<p>The McEwan Hall is situated in Bristo Square, adjacent to Edinburgh
		  University's Medical School. It was built by Sir Robert Rowand Anderson
		  (1834-1921) between 1888 and 1897 in Italian Renaissance style, and originally
		  planned as part of the University's new Medical School. It was funded by
		  William McEwan, the brewer, and is used as a graduation, concert, meeting and
		  examination hall.</p> 
		<p>From the early-1990s there had been a study into the refurbishment of
		  the Hall and into the extension of its functions.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material in the collection is centred on three artifical
		  sub-divisions: material in archive boxes; rolled drawing material in plan
		  boxes; and, board-mounted-material.</p>
		<p>In archive boxes, there is: in Box 1 - a Feasibility Study, 1985, and,
		  Feasibility report, 1994; in Box 2 - McEwan hall Improvement Phase 1, Minutes
		  File, and letters and planning applications etc; in Box 3 - Reiach and Hall
		  letters, Irons Foulner letters, Robertson and Dawson letters, Sandy Brown study
		  and letters, and assorted plans, drawings, reports and letters; in Box 4 -
		  drawings, letters, notes of meetings, and material on lighting; and in Box 5 -
		  drawings and letters relating to the McEwan Hall Millenium Scheme, a
		  presentation given on 24 March 1999, an application to the Heritage Lottery
		  Fund, 1998, a Final Report to the University, 1998, an Historic Scotland
		  condition report into the interior decoration, an Historic Scotland report on
		  stonework cleaning trials, a market overview, and a dissertation on the
		  Hall.</p> 
		<p>In plan boxes, there is: in Box 1 - drawings relating to the proposed
		  incremental programme, McEwan Hall, presented at meeting 21 February 2000, and
		  McEwan listed building consent; in Box 2 - University of Edinburgh, Old Medical
		  School, drawings relating to 1925, 1929, 1958, and 1971 warrants for
		  alterations to various components including gangway at Wilkie, lecture
		  theatres, stair, Anatomy Museum, Dissecting Room, and mezzanine under the
		  Anatomy Theatre, and Works Dept. drawings; in Box 3 - copies of McEwan Hall
		  original drawings, and copies of original drawings of University buildings
		  generally; in Box 4 - copies of University Library holdings of original McEwan
		  Hall drawings; in Box 5 - roll of plans of the Medical School; and, in Box 6 -
		  large roll of McEwan Hall architect's drawings, McEwan Hall drawings and plans
		  1998-to July, drawings of Old Medical School extension, and 1994 coloured
		  feasibility study.</p>
		<p>Board-mounted material consists of: 8 display drawings of the McEwan
		  Hall improvements, job T/198, dated 3 July 1997, in scales 1:100 and 1:200 on
		  thick light-foam-board, and 2 display drawings on thinner card; 2 loose
		  axonometric drawings and 1 spiral bound sketch book with drawings and
		  plans.</p>
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement encodinganalog="isadg(2)334"> 
		<p>Three artifical sub-divisions: material in archive boxes; rolled
		  drawing material in plan-boxes; and, board-mounted-material.</p> 
	 </arrangement>
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Accession no. E2004.3, gifted, deposited by Edward Taylor, accessioned
		  21 April 2004</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance. Some material may have DPA
		  restrictions.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material
		  contained in the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The Edinburgh University Library collection 
		<title>Work of William M. Palin (1862-1947)</title> is also described on
		the Hub. This consists of cartoon drawings for the murals at McEwan Hall.
		Another collection 
		<title>The Edinburgh Collection of Drawings from the Office of Sir Rowand
		  Anderson</title> also includes McEwan Hall material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <processinfo> 
		<p>Compiled by Graeme D. Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
		  Collections Division.</p> 
	 </processinfo>    <!-- Controlled Access Terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Architecture</emph> <emph altrender="x">Designs and plans</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edward Tayor, Architect and Planning
		  Consultant </emph> <emph altrender="z">Edinburgh</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">McEwan Hall, Edinburgh, Scotland</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
