<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-332" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-332</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of papers relating to Mary, Queen of Scots
			 (1542-1587)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Feb 12 11:53:24 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-332</unitid> 
		<physloc>De.1.12/6; De.1.12/22; Dc.7.93; Dc.4.83/1;
		  Dc.6.79</physloc><unittitle>Collection of papers relating to Mary, Queen of
		  Scots (1542-1587)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1501-1699">16th century-17th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 volumes manuscripts, 3 separate manuscripts.
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Buchanan, George</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> <language langcode="sco">Scots, </language>
		  <language langcode="fre">French, </language> and <language
		  langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Mary was born at Linlithgow Palace on either 7 or 8 December 1542. She
		  was the daughter of James V (1512-1542) and his second wife Mary of Guise
		  (1515-1560). On the death of her father from fever at Falkland Palace on 14
		  December 1542, after an armed encounter with a body of English Borderers at
		  Solway Moss, Mary became Queen when she was barely a week old. Under the
		  regency of James Hamilton, 2nd Earl of Arran, and with the support of the
		  pro-English and reforming party, she was promised in marriage to Prince Edward
		  of England, son of Henry VIII, and half-brother of Princess Elizabeth.</p> 
		<p>The promise of betrothal was frustrated by Cardinal Beaton who removed
		  Mary and her mother to Stirling Castle where the infant Queen was crowned on 9
		  September 1543. With the repudiation of Arran's agreement by the Estates (the
		  Scottish Parliament) now under the control of the Catholic party, war with
		  England followed. The war - the 'Rough Wooing' of Scotland by Henry VIII - led
		  to much devastation in south-eastern Scotland and to a Scottish defeat at
		  Pinkie Cleugh on 10 September 1547. After the battle, Mary was removed to the
		  island priory of Inchmahome on the Lake of Menteith for her security, and then
		  to Dumbarton Castle.</p> 
		<p>In July 1548, the Estates ratified an agreement for Mary's marriage to
		  Francis, the French Dauphin (son of Henry II and Catharine de' Medici), and she
		  sailed for France from Dumbarton in August 1548, barely six years old. Mary was
		  then educated at the French court in St. Germains-en-Laye acquiring a knowledge
		  of Latin, Greek, Italian, and of course French. Scots and English would come
		  later. Her political and religious instruction was given by the Guises,
		  especially the Cardinal of Lorraine and Antoinette de Bourbon. Meanwhile, in
		  Scotland the Catholic party gained its strength among the nobility and Mary of
		  Guise became Regent in Scotland in 1554.</p> 
		<p>On 24 April 1558, Mary was married to Francis at Notre-Dame in Paris.
		  Later, in November 1558, came the death in England of Mary Tudor and the
		  subsequent ascension of Elizabeth. In France, Mary, as great-grandaughter of
		  England's Henry VII (his daughter Margaret married Scotland's James IV) laid
		  claim to the English throne and she and Francis assumed the titles of King and
		  Queen of England, Scotland, and Ireland. On the death of Henry II on 10 July
		  1559, Francis and Mary continued to use these titles when they succeeded to the
		  French throne in their late teens.</p> 
		<p>Barely a year later, on 11 June 1560, Mary of Guise died in Scotland
		  and power there began to pass to the pro-English party again, and Catholicism
		  was proscribed. Then, on 5 December 1560 came the death of Mary's young
		  husband, Francis II. Power in France passed from the Guises to Catharine de'
		  Medici. Mary lost her position in the French court. On 19 August 1561, not yet
		  nineteen years old, she returned to Scotland, landing at Leith.</p> 
		<p>Almost immediately, Mary gave official recognition to the reformed
		  church but stipulated that she had the liberty to retain the Mass in her
		  private chapel at Holyrood. This took her into conflict with John Knox
		  (c.1513-1572), preacher and key figure in the Scottish Reformation.</p> 
		<p>In preference to suggestions of re-marriage with either the Kings of
		  Sweden, Denmark, and France, the Archduke Charles of Austria, Don Carlos of
		  Spain, the Dukes of Ferrara, Nemours, and Anjou, or the Earl of Arran and the
		  Earl of Leicester, Mary chose her cousin Henry Stewart, Lord Darnley. They were
		  married on 29 July 1565. Described variously as handsome, weak, needy,
		  insolent, vicious, and worthless, Mary herself was alarmed by his debauchery
		  and arrogance and was soon estranged from him. Alarm turned to disgust when he
		  and other Protestant nobles burst into her apartments on 9 March 1566 and
		  murdered the Italian courtier and musician David Rizzio, her adviser and
		  private foreign secretary. Although Mary was six months pregnant at the time,
		  she survived the shocking ordeal and Prince James was born on 19 June 1566.</p>
		
		<p>Mary's abhorrence and contempt for Darnley was accompanied by a
		  growing affection for James Hepburn, 4th Earl of Bothwell (c. 1535-1578) and
		  when her husband was murdered in the destruction of the house of Kirk o' Field
		  just outside the city walls on 10 February 1567 (Darnley was lying sick there
		  with smallpox), there was a suspicion that Mary was not completely ignorant of
		  the plot. On 12 April however, a mock-trial acquitted Bothwell and on 24 April
		  he abducted the Queen, perhaps with her approval and certainly without much
		  resistance from her, and carried her to Dunbar. Bothwell then obtained a
		  divorce from his recently married wife on 7 May, received a public pardon on 12
		  May from Mary for her seizure and was created Duke of Orkney, and then was
		  married to the Queen on 15 May 1567. It was at this point that Mary was faced
		  with a confederacy of nobles who stood against her and she surrendered at
		  Carberry on 15 June 1567. Imprisoned on an island castle in Loch Leven, Mary
		  was compelled to abdicate in favour of her infant son. She was now aged
		  twenty-four.</p> 
		<p>After escaping from Loch Leven on 2 May 1568, and in spite of
		  receiving much support and massing an army of six thousand, she was defeated by
		  the Regent, James Stewart, Earl of Moray, at Langside on 13 May 1568. Mary then
		  crossed the Solway into England and sought the help of Elizabeth I only to
		  remain under house arrest - a prisoner - for just over twenty years - variously
		  at Carlisle, Bolton, Tutbury, Wingfield, Coventry, Chatsworth, Sheffield,
		  Buxton, and Chartley. In England she became the focus of plots by English
		  Catholics and foreign agents. Through the efforts of Sir Francis Walsingham
		  (1530-1590) and his state security system, the 1586 Babington Plot against
		  Elizabeth was revealed, implicating Mary who was then housed at Chartley in
		  Staffordshire. She was brought to trial in September 1586, a sentence of death
		  was passed in October 1586, and with the consent of Elizabeth she was executed
		  at Fotheringay Castle on 8 February 1587. She was succeeded by her son, James
		  VI, who would later become King James I of England and Ireland on the death of
		  Elizabeth. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers include: a copy, in French, of a letter to Queen Elizabeth
		  of England, 8 November 1582; the draft of a document, in French, regarding the
		  marriage of Mary with the Dauphin of France and the succession to the kingdom
		  of Scotland, 1549; 
		<title>The declaration of the will of the most mychty and werteous
		  prencess Marie Quene of Scotland, dowarure of France, during the tyme of hir
		  extreme maladie, with the preirs and exhortations maid be hir</title>, 1566; 
		<title>Detectio Mariae, sive de Maria, Scotorum regina, totaque ejus
		  contra Regem conjuratione, fedo cum Bithuelio adulterio ... tragica plane
		  historia</title>; and, a 
		<title>Journal of affairs transacted anent Mary, Queen of Scots, begun at
		  York, October 4th, 1568, and ended at Hampton Court, January 15th
		  following</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Thorne, J. O. and Collocott, T. C. (eds.). 
		<title>Chambers biographical dictionary</title>. Revised ed. with supp.
		Edinburgh: W. and R. Chambers, 1982. (2) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney
		(eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.12. Llwyd-Mason.
		London: Smith, Elder and co., 1909. (3) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Micropedia, 15th ed.
		Chicago and London: Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1991.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to material related to Mary,
		  Queen of Scots, in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details):
		  and these include letters to Mary from James Beaton, Archbishop of Glasgow,
		  1567-68, in La.III.825/2, pp.48-62; letter, in French, from De Pierceville to
		  the Cardinal of Lorraine about preparations for the marriage of Mary to the
		  Dauphin, at La.II.524; 
		<title>Detectio Mariae</title> by George Buchanan, at La.III.241; 
		<title>A treatise concerning the righte title and interest of ...
		  Marie</title> by John Leslie, Bishop of Ross, at La.III.392, ff.12-48, and
		other at La.III.392, ff.102-125; and other letters, notes, and mentions of Mary
		in letters. There is also a copy of a letter of Charles Paget to Mary, 29 May
		1586, with a copy of part of her answer, 27 July 1586, at Dk.7.32, f.3.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters and papers, Hatfield
		  House, Ref. HMC NRA 32925 Gascoyne-Cecil; letters and papers, British Library,
		  Manuscript Collections, Ref. Cotton MSS; letters and papers (mainly copies)
		  British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Sloane MSS; letters (7), circa
		  1557-1576, Pierpont Morgan Library, Ref. RE; letters, 1554-1587, National
		  Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Adv MSS 29 2 1, 54 1 1-8;
		  letters to Archbishop James Beaton, 1562-1582, Scottish Catholic Archives, Ref.
		  JB NRA 7865 Scottish Catholic, see NRA(S)0018; and letters to Elizabeth I, West
		  Sussex Record Office, see Timothy J McCann, Goodwood Royal Letters 1977. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="othersource"> <emph altrender="surname">Mary</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1542-1587</emph> <emph altrender="title">Queen of
		  Scotland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="othersource"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Elizabeth</emph> <emph altrender="forename">I</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1533-1603</emph> <emph altrender="title">Queen of
		  England and Ireland</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Francis II</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1544-1560</emph> <emph altrender="title">King of
		  France</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="othersource"> <emph altrender="surname">Buchanan</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1506-1582</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Historian and
		  Scholar</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">16th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
