<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-879" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-879</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Material relating to Thomas Bruce (1766-1841), 7th Earl of
			 Elgin</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Nov 9 08:58:44 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-879</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1995/23-24, Gen. 748&#x002A;</physloc><unittitle>Material
		  relating to Thomas Bruce (1766-1841), 7th Earl of Elgin</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1833">1801-1833</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 letters; 1 card. </extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Bruce, Thomas</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Thomas Bruce was born on 20 July 1766, and on the death of his elder
		  brother, William Robert, in 1771 he became 7th Earl of Elgin and 11th Earl of
		  Kincardine. He was educated at Harrow and Westminster and studied at St.
		  Andrews University and in Paris. He entered the army in 1785 and by 1837 had
		  become a General. In 1799 he had been appointed to the embassy in Istanbul
		  (then Constantinople), and his mission began the study and examination of
		  Grecian remains within Turkish jurisdiction including those in Athens. A
		  collection of ornamental sculpture removed from the Parthenon began to be
		  shipped to Britain in 1803, and they became known as the Elgin Marbles. They
		  were bought for the nation in 1816. Thomas Bruce, 7th Earl of Elgin, died on 14
		  November 1841.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The correspondence is composed of: letter to J. S. Smythe, former
		  ambassador to the Porte (Istanbul), requesting him to hand over official
		  papers, written Pera, 1801; admission card for the Assembly Rooms signed by the
		  Earl, 1822; and, letter to J. Cleland, LL.D., Broomhall, Dunfermline, 1833.</p>
		
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Leslie, Stephen. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. London: Smith, Elder and
		Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Elgin related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): note from the Rev. J. Duncan to Messrs.
		  Cadell and Davis, requesting books to be delivered to him, circa 1799, at
		  Dc.4.102; letter of Mr. Roe to Mr. Wyatt about customs examination of packages
		  brought from Malta addressed to Lord Elgin, Custom House, 1812, at
		  La.II.648/208; and, mentioned in a letter from J. A. Cheque to A. Rolland W.S.,
		  with a proposal for a loan in connection with coalfields, 1831, at Gen. 886/2,
		  no.8.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Thomas Bruce,
		  7th Earl of Elgin related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Bruce</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1766-1841</emph> <emph altrender="title">7th Earl of
		  Elgin</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
