<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-282" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-282</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>The Scottish National Expedition to the
			 Antarctic</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Oct 09 10:49:04 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-282</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 556</physloc><unittitle>The Scottish National Expedition to
		  the Antarctic</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1900-1903">1900-1903</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 85 cuttings. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Scottish National Antarctic Expedition (1902-1904) was undertaken
		  with the sole aim of increasing and improving knowledge of polar science.
		  Success was achieved by the production of high quality scientific results,
		  particularly in the areas of polar oceanography, meteorology and wildlife
		  observation.</p> 
		<p>The Scottish National Antarctic Expedition was conceived and led by
		  William Speirs Bruce (1867-1921) who had training and experience in all areas
		  of the natural sciences, and a considerable background in polar observation. He
		  regarded the Expedition as a Scottish response to the recent 'Discovery'
		  Expedition, on which he had turned down the position of naturalist, due to its
		  emphasis on exploration rather than scientific observation.</p> 
		<p>After failing to gain funding from the British Government, Bruce
		  raised the cost of the expedition by private subscription. Two of the Coats
		  brothers of Paisley donated generously providing two-thirds of the overall
		  budget. In 1901, Bruce purchased the Norwegian whaler 'Hekla'. This was
		  repaired and altered at Ailsa Shipbuilding Company's yard in Troon, under the
		  free direction of the naval architect G. L. Watson. Following alteration the
		  ship was renamed the SY 'Scotia'.</p> 
		<p>SY 'Scotia' departed from Troon on 2 November 1902. On board were a
		  crew of 25 and an impressive team of scientists recruited from amongst Bruce's
		  friends and colleagues. These included a zoologist, a botanist, a
		  meteorologist, a geologist, a taxidermist and a bacteriologist. The SY 'Scotia'
		  sailed south, via Madeira and the Falkland Islands. On the way, meteorological
		  surveys were carried out every 4 hours and the oceanographic instruments
		  tested. Scientific studies were also undertaken at the Cape Verde Islands and
		  St Paul's Rock. Bruce recorded events throughout the trip using a variety of
		  methods. These included cinematography, phonography and photography using a
		  variety of cameras.</p> 
		<p>On 3 February 1903, the SY 'Scotia' arrived at Saddle Island in the
		  South Orkney Islands, where the scientific team made their first Antarctic
		  landing. Afterwards the SY 'Scotia' continued to progress southwards until a
		  drop in temperature saw a short period beset in pack ice. After breaking free,
		  the trip south was abandoned for the season. The ship progressed NNE along the
		  pack ice before anchoring for the winter in Scotia Bay on the south side of
		  Laurie Island in the South Orkney Islands. A wooden meteorological observation
		  station, named Omond House, and a cairn, as a reference point for topographic
		  survey work, were constructed immediately. Over the winter, observations and
		  collections of specimens were undertaken in a number of scientific disciplines.
		  Small parties were sent out for short periods to enhance these. In addition, a
		  considerable amount of topographic survey work was undertaken allowing the
		  first map of Laurie Island to be draughted.</p> 
		<p>After breaking free from the ice in Scotia Bay, on 22 November 1903,
		  the SY 'Scotia' sailed to Argentina via the Falkland Islands. A team of 6 men
		  were left ashore to continue scientific observations, particularly on penguins.
		  Negotiations with the Argentine Government, to assume the responsibility for
		  meteorological observations, were successful, and 3 Argentines returned with
		  the ship to staff Omond House along with Robert Cockburn Mossman (1870-1940).
		  This team was left on Laurie Island to be collected by the 'Uruguay' in
		  December 1904.</p> 
		<p>The SY 'Scotia' proceeded south into the Weddell Sea to undertake
		  oceanographic observations. Previously undiscovered land was sighted on 3 March
		  1904. This was named Coats Land in honour of the Coats brothers' support of the
		  expedition. The ship continued to edge south until meeting the ice shelf.
		  Following a storm the ship became stuck in the pack ice at 74<emph
		  render="super">o</emph> 01'S 22<emph render="super">o</emph>00'W, the furthest
		  latitude south achieved by the expedition, where it remained for 6 days.
		  Following liberation, further oceanographic soundings were taken to compare
		  with those recorded by James Clark Ross in 1843.</p> 
		<p>The SY 'Scotia' arrived back in Scotland on 21 July 1904, having
		  travelled via Gough Island, south-west Africa, Saint Helena, Ascension Island,
		  Cape Verde Islands and the Azores. During the journey a number of trips ashore
		  were taken for scientific observation and collecting, as well as
		  recreation.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of newspaper cuttings relating to the
		  Expedition, 1900-1903.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Brown, Robert Neal Rudmose. 
		<title>The voyage of the 'Scotia': being the record of a voyage of
		  exploration in Antarctic seas</title>. Edinburgh: W Blackwood 1906. (2)
		American Society of Polar Philatelists. 
		<title>Antarctic Philately: William S. Bruce</title>. Full-text [online].
		http://www.south-pole.com/ [Accessed 26 June 2001]. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Explorers</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Bruce</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William Speirs</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1867-1921</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Polar Explorer and
		  Oceanographer</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish National Antarctic
		  Expedition</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Antarctica</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">Discovery and exploration</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
