<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-761" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-761</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of John Johnstone, Printer and Publisher
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Jan 26 09:04:07 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-761</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS BOX 49.10.1-57</physloc><unittitle>Papers of John Johnstone,
		  Printer and Publisher </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1837-1857">1837-1857</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 30 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>John Johnstone, Printer and Publisher</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The firm of John Johnstone, printer, publisher, bookbinder and
		  bookseller, had been long established in Edinburgh, conducting business as
		  early as 1796 in the city's High Street. The Scottish Book Trade Index records
		  the printer at the office of 
		<title>Scots chronicle</title> in Murdoch's Close in the High Street,
		then between 1803-1811 at Strichen's Close. From 1812 there was also a premises
		at 104 High Street, and from 1824 these were the premises of John Johnstone and
		Son. The following year, Buchanan's Court was a business address, with the
		printing office in Strichen's Close. By the 1830s and into the 1840s printing,
		publishing, and bookbinding was being carried out at 2 Hunter Square and at 104
		High Street, and by 1846 bookselling at both Hunter Square and 15 Princes
		Street. In 1848 the High Street premises were those of Johnstone and Ballantyne
		and Company, and in 1850 of Johnstone and Hunter. Later on in the nineteenth
		century, premises at Melbourne Place (George IV Bridge) and at India Buildings,
		and then London Street, were recorded for Johnstone and Hunter.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers are composed of correspondence with John Johnstone from
		  Lindsay Alexander, J.H. Balfour, Lewis Balfour, James Begg, Andrew A. Bonar,
		  Horatius Bonar, John J. Bonar, John Brown, Alexander Brunton, John Bruce, James
		  Buchanan, Islay Burns, Robert S. Candlish, Thomas Chalmers, George Cook, Jean
		  Henri Merle d'Aubigne, Alexander Duff, Emily Faithfull, Thomas Guthrie, William
		  M. Hetherington, Robert Murray McCheyne, Thomas McCrie, Mackintosh Mackay,
		  Thomas McLauchlan, Norman McLeod, Hugh Miller, Frederic Monod, Robert Rainy,
		  Catherine Sinclair, Sir George Sinclair, William K. Tweedie, and a letter to
		  Andrew Cameron from Robert Vaughan.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  Scottish Book Trade Index which represents an index of printers, publishers,
		  booksellers, bookbinders, printmakers, stationers and papermakers based in
		  Scotland, from the beginnings of Scottish printing to ca. 1850.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">John Johnstone, Printer and Publisher
		  (Edinburgh, Scotland)</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
