<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-386" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-386</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers relating to Kenneth David Kaunda (b.
			 1924)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed May 22 12:07:53 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-386</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1975/1-2; Gen. 2129/1-2</physloc><unittitle>Papers relating
		  to Kenneth David Kaunda (b. 1924)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1959-1973">1959-1973</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 volumes, 2 letters, 1 typescript statement.
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Kaunda, Kenneth David; Macpherson, Fergus</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Kenneth David Kaunda - political leader and former President of Zambia
		  - was born in 1924 in Lubwa, near Chinsali, Zambia (then called Northern
		  Rhodesia). His parents were both teachers - his father was from Malawi (then
		  called Nyasaland), and his mother was the first African woman to teach in
		  colonial Zambia. After his own education, Kaunda too became a teacher, working
		  in Tanzania (then Tanganyika) as well as Zambia. He was then a welfare officer
		  at Chingoal Copper Mine, 1948, before becoming an interpreter and advisor on
		  African affairs to Sir Stewart Gore-Brown - a member of the Northern Rhodesian
		  Legislative Council - in 1949. By 1953, Kaunda's political career had been
		  founded and he was already Secretary-General of Northern Rhodesia's African
		  National Congress. Kaunda opposed the formation of the Federation of Rhodesia
		  and Nyasaland (which would have comprised modern Zambia, Zimbabwe, and Malawi)
		  and he formed the Zambia African National Congress in 1958. His party was
		  banned in 1959 and he was imprisoned, but on release in 1960 he became
		  President of the new United National Independence Party (UNIP), a post he would
		  hold until 1992. Kaunda opposed a constitution for Northern Rhodesia proposed
		  by Britain in 1962, believing that white supremacy would be built in to the new
		  country, but he participated in the elections of October 1962 and won a
		  parliamentary seat. He became the Minister of Local Government and Social
		  Welfare, 1962 to 1964. Dissolution of the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland
		  was achieved in 1963, and he became Prime Minister of Northern Rhodesia in
		  1964. The country became independent in 1964, and Kenneth Kaunda was its first
		  President. In 1969, Zambia's copper mines were nationalised and in 1972 the
		  country became a one-party state. Kaunda's Zambia played a key role in the
		  opposition to white-supremacist rule in Southern Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe), in
		  South Africa, and in South-West Africa (now Namibia). In 1990 however, he was
		  forced to restore the multiparty system in his own country and UNIP was
		  defeated in the 1991 elections by Frederick Chiluba and the Movement for
		  Multiparty Democracy. By 1995, and after repeated arrests, Kaunda headed the
		  main opposition party in Zambia, but changes to the constitution prevented him
		  from standing in the 1996 presidential election. In 2000 Kenneth David Kaunda
		  retired from politics. His published works include 
		<title> Black government</title> (1960) and 
		<title>Zambia shall be free</title> (1962).</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers are composed of: manuscript letters of Kaunda to C. T. Leys
		  about the banning of the Zambia African National Congress and his detention,
		  1959, written from the Detention Camp, Kabompo; other material relating to
		  pre-independence Zambia, 1956-1959; and, the typescript to 
		<title>Kenneth Kaunda of Zambia: the times and the man</title> by Fergus
		Macpherson, 1973.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Typescript deposited by Prof. G. Shepperson, May 1975, Accession no.
		  E75.25. Letters transferred from African Studies, June 1981, Accession no.
		  E81.64.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance, and note that Macpherson typescript
		  is noted in the accession index as 'For restricted use only'.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Micropaedia. Ready
		Reference. 15th edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., 1991. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p> 
		<title>Kenneth Kaunda of Zambia: the times and the man</title> / Fergus
		Macpherson. Published: Lusaka ; New York : Oxford University Press, 1974. ISBN
		0195723384. Held at Edinburgh University Library, shelfmarks .9(6894) Kau.
		Macp. and C.A.S. Zam. Macp.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="othersource"> <emph altrender="surname">Kaunda</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Kenneth David</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1924-
		  </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">African politician, former President of
		  Zambia</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Macpherson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Fergus</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Zambia African National Congress</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Zambia</emph> <emph altrender="x">Politics
		  and government </emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Africa</emph> <emph altrender="x">Politics
		  and government </emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
