<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-232" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-232</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Scottish International Review
			 Ltd.</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed May 02 11:47:24 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-232</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2159</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Scottish
		  International Review Ltd.</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1966-1979">1966-[197-]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Scottish International Review Ltd.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Scottish International Review Ltd. was incorporated on 22 January
		  1968. It had the aim of advancing education in the UK through the promotion and
		  encouragement of the development and study of the arts through the publication
		  of the 
		<title>Scottish International Review</title>. It aimed to compile and
		prepare, print, publish and issue, circulate and distribute papers, magazines,
		periodicals, books, circulars and other matter. It planned to promote and
		encourage the arts by organising, presenting, producing, managing and promoting
		plays, dramas, concerts, recitals, films, lectures, competitions, exhibitions
		and other presentations, activities or entertainment of an educational and
		artistic nature. The 
		<title>Scottish International Review</title> was published on a quarterly
		basis in January, April, August and December, and the first issue appeared in
		January 1968 with the actual title 
		<title>Scottish International. Review incorporating Feedback</title>, and
		ISSN 00369268. It was published with support of the Scottish Arts Council, and
		the support of Scottish Television Ltd. and the Saltire Society was also
		acknowledged. The publication continued until early-1974 and its contents
		included items as diverse as: articles on Perth Theatre, new Gaelic writing,
		the Scottish National Party and the arts, publishing and the Scottish writer,
		Antonioni, contemporary Italian poetry, Czech poetry; and, writing and poetry
		by Alasdair Gray, Norman MacCaig, Edwin Morgan and Pier Paolo Pasolini. The
		official addresses for 
		<title>Scottish International Review</title> were, in Edinburgh, 23
		George Street, and in Glasgow, 530 Great Western Road.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The records of the Scottish International Review Ltd. consist of:
		  correspondence prior to incorporation; minutes of Directors' meetings;
		  estimates of income and expenditure; bank statements for 1969-1973; general
		  correspondence and mailing lists; correspondence with publishers and printers;
		  copy for the 
		<title>Scottish International Review</title>, such as poems and articles
		and reviews; and, photographs.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Papers acquired from Father A. Ross, January 1983. Accession no.
		  E83.6. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using: (1) Material within the
		  collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>At Edinburgh University Library, copies of 
		<title>Scottish International Review</title> between 1968-1974 can be
		found in the Main Library, George Square, at shelfmark Per. 0 Sco.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish International Review Ltd</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
