<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-444" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-444</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records and Papers relating to the French West Africa
			 Company (CFAO)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Sep 20 15:03:11 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-444</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 837-840 </physloc><unittitle>Records and Papers relating to
		  the French West Africa Company (CFAO)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1900-1924">1900-1924</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 boxes </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Messrs. Donnison and Edwards</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="fre">French.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Along with the Portuguese, the Spanish, the Dutch, and the British,
		  the French began to establish themselves in coastal West Africa in the latter
		  part of the fifteenth century. The primary interest was missionary work,
		  exploration and trading in slaves, sugar, pepper, ivory, wax, and gold. Indeed,
		  in the sixteenth century gold from West Africa - from Ghana in particular -
		  accounted for one tenth of the world's gold reserves. However, from the late
		  sixteenth century until the mid-nineteenth century it was the slave trade that
		  saw huge expansion. To satisfy the emerging plantation economies of the New
		  World, the trading and transfer of African peoples became the principal
		  economic activity of the Europeans in West Africa - first the Portuguese, then
		  the Dutch, then the British and French, and of course some segments of the
		  African population themselves who participated in the capture, transport and
		  marketing of captives.</p> 
		<p>French participation in the trans-Atlantic slave trade was probably
		  less significant than the activities of the Portuguese, Dutch and British.
		  Trading by the French was focussed on gum arabic, groundnuts (or peanuts) and
		  other raw materials from the interior, particularly the Senegal River area and
		  its hinterland. In Saint-Louis, Senegal, established as a trading post in 1659,
		  the French began what would eventually become their colonial project to
		  assimilate West Africa as a part of France.</p> 
		<p>By the late nineteenth century, when industrialisation and economic
		  conditions in Europe came to influence the expansion of European interests in
		  West Africa, a 'scramble for Africa' occurred. In February 1885, the Berlin Act
		  was signed by the principal European powers looking for control and partition
		  of the continent. The Act provided the guidelines by which each power then
		  defined their territories and by the early twentieth century the French held
		  most of what would come to be their colonial territory in West Africa,
		  including: present day Senegal, Mali (formerly French Sudan), Mauritania,
		  Burkina Faso (formerly Upper Volta), Benin (formerly Dahomey), Guinea (formerly
		  French Guinea), Ivory Coast and Niger.</p> 
		<p>Meanwhile, Compagnie Fran&#x00E7;aise de l'Afrique Occidentale (CFAO)
		  was founded in Marseilles in 1887. In 1888 the Company opened its first African
		  agency in Saint-Louis, and from 1888 to 1902 began to expand across Senegal,
		  and into Guinea, Gambia, Sierra Leone, Ivory Coast and Nigeria. This coincided
		  with the creation of the federation of French West Africa in 1895 to
		  consolidate French holdings. The federation was definitively constituted in
		  1904 and was ruled by a Governor-General with a residence in Saint-Louis
		  (capital of the federation from 1895 until 1902, and capital of Senegal and
		  Mauritania from 1902 until 1958) then in Dakar.</p> 
		<p>After the Second World War, the process of de-colonisation began in
		  Africa and between 1955 and 1961 the headquarters of CFAO transferred from
		  Marseilles to Paris and the Company mutated into a multinational service
		  company and becoming a leader in specialist distribution in sub-Saharan Africa.
		  This coincided with constituent parts of the African federation becoming
		  autonomous republics. CFAO then began to diversify its activities outside
		  Africa and in the late 1950s the CICA group (marketing Ford, Opel,
		  Mercedes-Benz and Fiat automobiles in France) entered CFAO. In 1990, CFAO
		  itself entered the Pinault group, today called Pinault-Printemps-Redoute. After
		  the devaluation of the CFA franc in 1994, CFAO was able to consolidate its
		  position in Africa and acquired the activities of SCOA and Optorg, two large
		  vehicle distributors with interests in, for the former, Cameroon, Gabon,
		  Madagascar and Niger, and for the latter, Mali and Senegal. In 1996, CFAO
		  became established in the health sector through the acquisition of Eurapharma
		  which had been a subsidiary of SCOA.</p> 
		<p>By 1997 CFAO and SCOA had merged and expanded into Mauritius and
		  Equatorial Guinea, and in 1999 Eurapharma became established in Kenya. In 2000
		  CFAO had developed its activities in Algeria, Morocco, Kenya, Tanzania and
		  Zambia, and more recently in the Democratic Republic of Congo, Egypt and
		  Malawi. Today the multinational CFAO has a strong position in motor
		  distribution, pharmaceutical distribution, trading, telecommunications,
		  networks, and office automation across Africa and in the French overseas
		  departements and territories (Dom-Tom).</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material consists of the correspondence and papers of Messrs.
		  Donnison and Edwards, Castle Street, Liverpool, who appear to have been legal
		  agents for CFAO. The items are mainly about property in Lagos Oshogbo, and Port
		  Harcourt in Nigeria, Sekondi and Cape Coast Castle in Ghana, and Freetown in
		  Sierra Leone. There is also material related to litigation in the matter of
		  captured German vessels and personnel. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Acquired from Nichael Katanka (Books) Ltd., Edgeware, Middx., April
		  1966, Accession no. E66.17.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) History of CFAO. 
		<title>CFAO</title>. Full-text [online]. 
		<extref href="http://www.cfaogroup.com/cfao/uk/index.htm">CFAO</extref>
		[Accessed 30 August 2002]. (2) Background to French West Africa 
		<title>Columbia Encyclopaedia</title>. 6th edition, 2001. Full-text
		[online]. 
		<extref href="http://www.bartleby.com/65/fr/frenchwaf.html">Columbia
		  Encyclopaedia</extref> [Accessed 30 August 2002]. (3) Wooten, Stephen. 
		<title>The French in West Africa: Early Contact to Independence</title>.
		Full-text [online]. 
		<extref
		 href="http://polyglot.lss.wisc.edu/afrst/outreach/units/french.html">The French
		  in West Africa: Early Contact to Independence</extref> [Accessed 30 August
		2002].</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Compagnie fran&#x00E7;aise de l'Afrique
		  occidentale</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Messrs. Donnison and Edwards</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Africa, West</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
