<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-662" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-662</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of Reverend James Hamilton D.D.
			 (1814-1867)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jul 20 11:42:43 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-662</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1981/140-143; Gen. 1995/36-38; Gen.
		  2040/90</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Reverend James Hamilton D.D.
		  (1814-1867)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1861-1865">1861-1865</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>5 letters, 1 hymn, 1 small portrait. </extent>
		  <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Hamilton, James</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Presbyterian minister James Hamilton was born in Paisley on 27
		  November 1814. He was educated by a tutor at home, and then he studied at
		  Glasgow University where he graduated in 1835. In 1836 he began studies at
		  Edinburgh University with the intention of entering the Church. Hamilton was
		  licensed as a Minister in the Church of Scotland in 1838, becoming an Assistant
		  at St. George's, Edinburgh, and then at the Parish of Abernyte. In early 1841
		  he was again in Edinburgh this time at the Roxburgh Church, but in July 1841 he
		  moved to London to the National Scottish Church, Regent Square (Church of
		  Scotland). Hamilton was a hymn writer and compiler and his publications include
		  
		<title>The Mount of Olives</title> (1845), 
		<title>Emblems from Eden</title> (1856), 
		<title>A morning beside the Lake of Galilee</title> (1863), 
		<title>The psalter and hymn-book</title> (1865), and 
		<title>Book of psalms and hymns</title>. The Reverend James Hamilton D.D.
		remained in London until his death on 24 November 1867.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: letters from Hamilton about church
		  meetings; a hymn 
		<title>O waste not the smallest thing</title>, May 1861, and portrait
		with biographical note; and letter from Hamilton at Euston Square, 1863, about
		which illustrations would be appropriate for an article entitled 
		<title>Garden</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material among miscellaneous documents, purchased 1974, E. Hall,
		  Accession no. E74.25.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.8. Glover-Harriott.
		London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show another reference to material related to a Rev.
		  James Hamilton (check the Indexes for more details): letter to Rev. J. Kennedy
		  regretting that he cannot occupy his pulpit on a certain date, 1848, at Gen.
		  1801/3/8.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hamilton</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1814-1867</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scottish
		  divine</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
