<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-262" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-262</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of The Scottish Anthropological and Folklore
			 Society</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Aug 08 09:25:02 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-262</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 34-40; Gen. 40&#x002A;</physloc><unittitle>Records of The
		  Scottish Anthropological and Folklore Society</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1922-1960">1922-1960</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>7 volumes, 1 envelope. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Abercromby, John; Sayce, Archibald Henry; Rose, H.
		  J.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Scottish Anthropological and Folklore Society appeared to have its
		  origins in the Edinburgh and Lothians Branch of the Royal Anthropological
		  Institute which had been set up in 1922. At a meeting of the Council of the
		  Royal Anthropological Institute in London on 24 October 1922, an application by
		  twelve Fellows of the Institute to found a local branch in Edinburgh had been
		  accepted. A meeting to set up the branch was called at Northumberland Street,
		  Edinburgh, on 2 November 1922. Among those present were Lord Abercromby and Sir
		  P. Hamilton-Grierson. Abercromby was asked to Chair the meeting and he was
		  subsequently elected Local President with Sir Everard im Thurn, formerly
		  Governor of Fiji and High Commissioner for the Western Pacific, as
		  Vice-President, and Captain A. G. Pape as Secretary, and David MacRitchie as
		  Treasurer. The inaugural meeting of the Edinburgh and Lothians branch was held
		  in the Royal Scottish Geographical Society Meeting Rooms, Synod Hall, Castle
		  Terrace, Edinburgh, on Tuesday 6 February 1923. A lecture was given by Sir
		  Everard on 
		<title>The practical application of anthropology</title>. Meetings
		continued throughout the 1920s and into the 1930s. Then, with a fresh impetus,
		on 15 June 1932, a meeting took place at the Royal Scottish Museum of a group
		of individuals interested in setting up a Scottish Anthropological Society. A
		committee met on 18 June deciding on the aim of furthering the study of
		anthropology generally but with special emphasis on the anthropology of
		Scotland. In October 1932 came the death of Sir Everard, still a prominent
		member of the local Branch of the Institute, and that same month at a
		subsequent meeting of enthusiasts a new society was constituted. Its
		provisional council met on 8 November chaired by Lt. Col. L. M. Davies. The
		Scottish Anthropological Society agreed to set up committees to deal with: an
		anthropometric survey of Scotland; folklore; dialect; comparative religion;
		general ethnology; and, propaganda. The President of the Society was Professor
		H. J. Rose, and the Vice-Presidents were Dr. William Grant and Archibald Henry
		Sayce, Professor of Assyriology, Oxford, and whose participation provided a
		link with the Edinburgh and Lothians Branch of the Institute. In February 1933,
		Professor Sayce died, and in March 1933, 
		<title>The Scotsman</title> reported the final meeting of the local
		Branch of the Royal Anthropological Institute. Meetings of The Scottish
		Anthropological Society were held at the old Branch venue of the Synod Hall and
		talks were given on a variety of topics including: Finland; Scottish dialects
		and some methods of analysing and recording their pronunciation; the Leningrad
		Exhibition of Iranian Art, 1935, and its ethnographical aspect; Scottish
		placenames; Maya civilisation of Yucatan; a moslem community in Britain; and,
		nursery rhymes. By 1936, the Society came to be known as The Scottish
		Anthropological and Folklore Society. Into the late-1950s, the membership of
		the Society had begun to dwindle and it was wound up in early-1960. The bulk of
		the library that had been acquired by The Scottish Anthropological and Folklore
		Society was transferred, at the time, to the School of Scottish Studies,
		Edinburgh University.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The records of The Scottish Anthropological Society and of the
		  Edinburgh and Lothians Branch of the Royal Anthropological Institute include,
		  at Gen. 34-35, the General Minutes of the Branch, 1922-1933, and the Committee
		  Minutes of the Branch, 1923-1933. At Gen. 36-39 are Minute Books for 1932-1935,
		  1935-1937, 1937-1949, and 1949-1960. At Gen. 40 is a volume of Minutes of the
		  Standing Committee of Anthropological Teaching, 1934-1938, and at Gen.
		  40&#x002A; are some papers said to relate to the winding up of the Society.
		  </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Records of The Scottish Anthropological and Folklore Society were
		  received in October 1960, Accession no. E60.29.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative history was compiled using the records of the
		  Society.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Abercromby</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1841-1924</emph>
		  <emph altrender="title">5th Baron Abercromby</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Sayce</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Archibald Henry</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1845-1933</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Orientalist
		  Comparative Philologist and Egyptologist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Rose</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">H. J.</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Royal Anthropological Institute. Edinburgh
		  and Lothians Branch</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Anthropological Society</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Anthropological and Folklore
		  Society</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
