<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-611" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-611</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of George William Clarke (1849-1919)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Dec 16 09:22:08 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-611</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 15</physloc><unittitle>Papers of George William Clarke
		  (1849-1919)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1875-1969">1875-1969</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>8 items</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Clarke, George William </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="chi">Chinese.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>George William Clarke, China Inland Mission missionary to China, was
		  born on May 30 1849 in Shoreditch, East London. One of five children he began
		  working full-time in a factory when he was nine years old. In his teens he
		  attended a night school run by Annie Macpherson, the promoter of child
		  migration to Canada. It was at one of her Sunday schools that he became a
		  committed Christian and, at the age of fourteen, he became her full-time
		  assistant. When he was twenty-three he took charge of the first party of
		  Macpherson boys being sent to Canada. He had jobs there as a lumberjack and an
		  engine driver as well as studying at college. In August 1875, however, he
		  responded to Hudson Taylor's call for a group of eighteen men to join the China
		  Inland Mission with the aim of entering the nine unevangelised provinces of
		  inland China. During his first term in China he travelled over 20,000 miles
		  through twelve provinces, concentrating in the first years on Hunan, Kweichow
		  and Szechwan. In 1879, in Shanghai, he married Fanny Rossier (also referred to
		  as Marta), a Swiss missionary. Their base was to be Kweiyang, capital of
		  Kweichow, which they reached in 1880, Fanny being the first female missionary
		  to have penetrated that far west. They lost a son at the end of that year and
		  in May 1881 moved farther west into Yunnan, the first Protestant missionaries
		  to work in that province. The work was isolated and difficult with very little
		  progress. A son, Samuel, was born in 1883 but Fanny Clarke never recovered from
		  the birth and died before the end of the year. Having no-one to assist with
		  raising his son, Clarke left Yunnan in April 1884 and spent the rest of his
		  life working in north-east China. In 1886 he married Agnes Lancaster, who had
		  gone to China in 1880 and had worked in T'ai-yuen in the province of Shansi.
		  After their marriage the Clarkes were based at Kwei-hwa-ch'eng in north Shansi.
		  In 1888 they returned home on furlough then in 1889 went to Tientsin (Tianjin)
		  where Clarke was mission secretary. They had a son (John) but Agnes Clarke died
		  in 1892 after giving birth to a daughter (also Agnes). Clarke died in Shantung
		  province in 1919 and was buried in the British cemetery at Tientsin. Despite
		  his lack of formal education he had become a fluent Chinese speaker, kept
		  accurate diaries, wrote a book on some of the provinces he worked in and
		  translated an ancient Chinese classic which was later donated to the British
		  Museum. His daughter, Agnes, was a CIM missionary for forty-six years and
		  worked in east Szechwan before retiring to the CIM home for retired members in
		  Kent.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of a pamphlet by Agnes Clarke about her father
		  (1962); three volumes of diaries written by George Clarke (1879-1883); a book
		  on Kweichow and Yunnan provinces by George Clarke (1894); cuttings from 
		<title>China's Millions</title> about the Clarke family (1875-1941); and
		four photographs of the family and one of a Chinese river (circa
		1880-1890).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The items were numbered and listed in 'chronological' order by Agnes
		  Clarke.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>George Clarke gave his diaries to his daughter Agnes who added notes
		  and annotations to them at various times. She also collected articles from 
		<title>China's Millions</title> on her family. </p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western world by Agnes Clarke in 1969.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself; (2) Guinness, Geraldine. 
		<title>Story of the China Inland Mission</title>. London, 1893.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the China Inland Mission are held at the School of
		  Oriental and African Studies in London. Several of the histories of the Mission
		  or biographies of Hudson Taylor mention the Clarke family, particularly the
		  pioneering work of George and his wife Fanny: see, for example 
		<title>Story of the China Inland Mission</title> by Geraldine Guinness
		(London, 1893). Agnes Clarke mentions 'an ancient Chinese classic' translated
		by Clarke which she donated to the British Museum. She also donated a copy of
		her book 
		<title>China's man of the book : the story of William Chalmers
		  Burns</title> (London, 1968) to the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the
		Non-Western World.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p>Agnes Clarke used her father's diaries to write 
		<title>The Boy From Shoreditch</title>. London: CIM, 1962.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Clarke</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George William </emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1849-1899</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Clarke</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Agnes</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1892</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">China Inland Mission</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">China</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
