<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-581" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-581</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Ralph Morton (1900-1977) and Jenny Morton (b.
			 1901)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Nov 27 17:20:47 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-581</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 11</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Ralph Morton (1900-1977)
		  and Jenny Morton (b. 1901)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1924-1972">1924-1972</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Morton, T. Ralph </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="chi">Chinese.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Thomas Ralph Morton (known as Ralph), Presbyterian Church in Ireland
		  missionary to Manchuria, China, was born in Scotland in 1900. He studied at
		  Glasgow (United Free College subsequently Trinity College, 1922-25) and was an
		  active member of various student Christian groups such as the Student Christian
		  Movement. He became a great friend of Robert Mackie (1899-1984) who was later a
		  prominent figure on the Scottish ecumenical movement. T. Z. Koo, the leader of
		  the Chinese Student Christian Movement, visited Britain in 1924 and invited
		  Morton, with R. O. Hall, later Bishop of Hong Kong, to go to China. Morton
		  arrived in China in 1925 and was at first based in Peking for language
		  training. He moved to Moukden in Manchuria in 1926 where he worked with the
		  YMCA and then on to Kirin in 1927. His work was mainly concerned with teaching
		  and working with Chinese students, he spent much time travelling around the
		  area, trying to build networks of student movements and attending conferences,
		  but he was also involved in more general mission work such as bible teaching,
		  taking services and attending mission councils. He became engaged to Jenny
		  Baird (born 1901) in early 1926 who was at that time working for the United
		  Free Church in Bombay. They were married when Morton was home for a brief leave
		  in 1927 and she returned with him to China where she helped with his work and
		  did some teaching herself. The Mortons moved from Kirin to Hsin Min in 1929
		  where Morton took on the more general duties of a district missionary. They
		  remained at Hsin Min, with a period of leave in 1931 and six months in Peking
		  in 1934 while Morton taught at the university. The Japanese occupation and
		  increasing persecution of Chinese Christians and the authorities' mistrust of
		  foreigners persuaded the Mortons that they should leave China and they returned
		  to the UK in 1937. Morton served as minister of St Columba's in Cambridge until
		  1943 when he moved to Glasgow to become Warden of the Iona Community House. In
		  1950 he became deputy leader of the Iona Community, a position he held until he
		  retired in 1967. During the 1950s and 1960s he also lectured in sociology at
		  New College, Edinburgh and he was awarded a DD by Glasgow University in 1963.
		  Morton was the author of many articles and books and he continued writing and
		  preaching after his retirement until his death in 1977.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is in two main parts: letters from Ralph Morton (and
		  from 1927 his wife Jenny) to his parents and brothers describing his life and
		  work as a missionary in China with some reference to the political situation
		  and attitudes to religion (1925-1937); and letters from the Mortons to Robert
		  and Dorothy Mackie referring to Morton's life as a student in Glasgow (1924)
		  and to life in China (1925-1930); the collection also includes a few
		  'miscellaneous' items such as a Manchurian Student Movement Fellowship
		  newsletter (1926) and an unpublished manuscript by Morton 
		<title>China the Teacher</title> describing his life in and views on
		China (c 1971-72).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The letters are arranged in chronological order by recipient: the
		  first series of letters are those to Morton's family; the second are those to
		  the Mackies; the letters are followed by other material.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>The collection was briefly listed by Ralph Covell in 1992.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western world by Morton's family. The manuscript 
		<title>China the Teacher</title> was presented to the Centre by the
		author.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself, (2) Fulton, Austin. 
		<title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title>. Edinburgh: The Saint
		Andrew Press, 1967. (3) obituaries in 
		<title>Coracle</title> (the journal of the Iona Community, October 1977),
		(4) entries in 
		<title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scotticanae</title> (editions from 1961 and
		1981).</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Ralph Morton wrote a number of published and unpublished articles on
		  China and two published books: 
		<title>Life in the Chinese Church</title> (London: Student Christian
		Movement Press, 1931) and 
		<title>Today in Manchuria</title> (London: SCM Press 1939); Austin Fulton
		in 
		<title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title> (Edinburgh: The Saint
		Andrew Press, 1967) describes the missionary work in Manchuria and includes a
		list of sources; CSCNWW holds papers relating other missionaries in Manchuria;
		the David Lewis Beebe collection at the Lupton Library, University of Tennessee
		has correspondence between Beebe and Morton of a later period (1972-77).</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Morton</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">T. Ralph </emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1900-1977</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Irish Presbyterian Mission</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Manchuria (China)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
