<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-587" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-587</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of John M. Leggate (fl. 1940)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Nov 28 09:49:40 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-587</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 12</physloc><unittitle>Letters of John M. Leggate (fl.
		  1940)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1946-1949">1946-1949</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 item (51 pp)</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Leggate, John M.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John M. Leggate, MB ChB, FRCS, was a Church of Scotland medical
		  missionary in Manchuria and the nephew of another medical missionary in
		  Manchuria, Dr Archibald Leggate. He was appointed by the mission in 1933 and
		  retired in 1950. In 1935 he married Grace Cumming Small Clark who had been a
		  Church of Scotland missionary to Manchuria since 1930. With the Japanese
		  occupation of Manchuria the Leggates left China and spent some time in
		  Scotland. Leggate was invited to return in 1946 with an advance party to
		  re-establish the medical work at Moukden. His intention had been that his wife
		  and two children, Grace and John, should join him later but the continuing
		  fighting between communist and nationalist forces meant that the situation was
		  never stable enough for this to happen. After his return to the United Kingdom
		  Leggate was appointed dean of medicine at Liverpool University.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is a transcription of letters written by Leggate from
		  Manchuria between 1946 and 1949. The letters are mainly to his wife in Scotland
		  but some are to his children and possibly to others. The transcriptions do not
		  include the names of the recipients of the letters and are extracts from the
		  letters only, all personal references having been removed. Leggate describes
		  re-establishing the missionary work in Manchuria, in particular his medical
		  work and the medical college at Moukden, and often refers to the activities of
		  other missionaries. He also comments on the actions of the communists in
		  Manchuria and the effect on the church and mission. One of the extracts is a
		  section of a letter from Jean McMinn at Port Said on her way home (1949).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The transcription is as it was presented to the Centre.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>Leggate's original letters home were transcribed by Leggate and his
		  wife in the early 1950s to remove the more personal references. </p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The item was presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World by Mrs Jean Doyle, Edinburgh, in 1996 with Mrs Leggate's
		  permission.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <odd> 
		<head>Existence/Location of Originals</head> 
		<p>The originals were in the possession of the Leggates.</p> 
	 </odd> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself, (2) Fulton, Austin. 
		<title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title>. Edinburgh: The Saint
		Andrew Press, 1967.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the Church of Scotland foreign missions are held by
		  the National Library of Scotland and include correspondence with the Leggates.
		  Papers of other missionaries working in Manchuria are held by the Centre for
		  the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World as are several books on the
		  development of missionary work in Manchuria. Austin Fulton in 
		<title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title> (Edinburgh: The Saint
		Andrew Press, 1967) describes the missionary work in Manchuria and includes a
		list of sources.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Leggate</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John M.</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Manchuria (China)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
