<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-784" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-784</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Samuel Sebastian Wesley
			 (1810-1876)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Mar 30 11:45:07 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-784</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.7.38/3; Dk.7.38/4/1-13</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Samuel
		  Sebastian Wesley (1810-1876)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1811-1867">1811-1867</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circ 15 letters, and miscellaneous fragments.
		  </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Wesley, Samuel Sebastian</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Samuel Sebastian Wesley was born on 14 August 1810. At the age of nine
		  he became a choirboy at the Chapel Royal, St. James's Palace, London, singing
		  to George IV in Brighton at the Royal Pavilion. At the age of fifteen in 1826
		  he was appointed organist of St. James's Chapel, Hampstead Road, and in 1829
		  organist of St. Giles's Church, Camberwell. In 1832 he became the organist at
		  Hereford Cathedral where he stayed until 1835 when he became organist and
		  sub-chanter of Exeter Cathedral. At Exeter his fame as a composer of church
		  music and as an organist became established. Then, after receiving the degrees
		  of Bachelor of Music and Doctor in Music from Oxford University, an academic
		  career seemed possible, but instead in 1842 he was appointed organist at Leeds
		  Parish Church though he did do some illustrated lecturing at the then Liverpool
		  Collegiate Institution. In 1849 he accepted the post of organist at Winchester
		  Cathedral and he stayed there until 1865 when he was appointed to Gloucester
		  Cathedral. His music production included the anthem 
		<title>The wilderness</title> (1831) and the hymn tune 
		<title>Aurelia</title> as well as many other anthems and collects,
		pianoforte music, glees and songs. Samuel Sebastian Wesley died at his home on
		Palace Yard, Gloucester, on 19 April 1876.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: a letter of Wesley 'To Catholic choirs
		  and organists' about ecclesiastical modes, addressed to Vincent Novello, 1811,
		  with a musical illustration; a brief verse epistle relating to Cooper, undated,
		  and some fragments of letters and music with annotations by Dr. G. Spink the
		  donor; and, letters to R. A. Atkins, organist of St. Asaph Cathedral, Wales,
		  1843-1867.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Novello and Cooper material, Accession no. E66.42. Letters to Atkins,
		  Accession no. E67.1</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.20.
		Ubaldini-Whewell. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Wesley related material:
		  compositions, British Library, Music Collections, Ref. Add MS 40636; musical
		  MSS, Hereford Cathedral Library; letters to Benjamin Jacob relating to J. S.
		  Bach, 1808-1816, British Library, Music Collections, Ref. Add MS 62928; and
		  letters to Vincent Novello, 1811-1825, Ref. Add MS 11729.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Wesley</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Samuel Sebastian</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1810-1876</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Organist and
		  Composer</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
