<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-582" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-582</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Fergus Macpherson (b. 1921)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Nov 27 17:41:44 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-582</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 49</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Fergus Macpherson (b.
		  1921)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1950-1979">[ca. 1951-1975]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>19 boxes</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Macpherson, Fergus </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="bem">Bemba.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Fergus Macpherson, Church of Scotland missionary in Zambia and Malawi
		  and historian, was born on 9 August 1921 at Newmilns, Scotland. He was educated
		  at Edinburgh University and New College and graduated MA in 1943. Between 1943
		  and 1944 he was student assistant at Edinburgh Nicoloson Street and from
		  1944-46 at Guthie Memorial. Macpherson was ordained in 1946 and left in the
		  same year for missionary service in Mufulira, Northern Rhodesia (Zambia) where
		  he stayed until 1950. He worked as a minister and as a manager of schools, and
		  developed an increasing interest in Zambian history and education and Zambian
		  interaction with missionaries and with European culture in general. From
		  1951-1954 he was stationed at Lubwa and later was for three years Principal of
		  the Overtoun Institute, Livingstonia, Malawi. In 1959 he resigned from service
		  in Northern Rhodesia and was inducted to Greenock St Ninian's near Glasgow
		  where he stayed until 1964. Macpherson returned to Zambia and took a post as
		  research historian at the University of Zambia, Lusaka and was director of the
		  Kenneth Kaunda Foundation. Returning to Scotland in 1978 he worked at Auld Kirk
		  Kilbirnie until 1984 when he was appointed World Mission Secretary to the
		  British Council of Churches. He finally retired in October 1988. Macpherson was
		  well known in Zambia and was a personal friend of Kenneth Kaunda. Widely
		  respected as a scholar and historian Macpherson has published several works on
		  Zambia and its history as well as some fiction. He was awarded a DD from
		  Edinburgh University.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: transcripts and translations of oral
		  interviews with Kenneth Kaunda and colleagues, and with many Zambians from
		  different areas of the country; the interviews touched on social, political and
		  religious changes in Zambia (mainly conducted 1960s-1973, but referring back to
		  the 19th century and David Livingstone); papers on Zambian history and religion
		  presented at oral history seminars (1971-1974); material on the African
		  National Congress (Zambia), the United National Independence Party, nationalism
		  and Federation including correspondence, circulars, bulletins, minutes and
		  papers (1951-1970s); other papers and circulars on Zambia; and copies from
		  archives and research notes made by Macpherson.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged as described above. When the material was
		  deposited the boxes had been labelled by Macpherson and the labels have been
		  kept as the file titles above. The order of the boxes and files has been
		  somewhat changed to allow, for example, the interviews to be grouped together
		  but the order of papers within the files has not been touched.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was presented to the Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World by Fergus Macpherson in the 1990s.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <odd> 
		<head>Existence/Location of Originals</head> 
		<p>Some of the material consists of notes and copies from archives in
		  various locations including Rhodes House, Oxford and Lusaka, Zambia. </p> 
	 </odd> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using 
		<title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scotticanae</title> (editions 9, 10, and 11).</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The Centre Library holds many books and pamphlets on Zambia.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Macpherson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Fergus</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1921</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Zambia</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
