<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-399" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-399</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of the works of William Lambarde
			 (1536-1601)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Jun 28 09:25:37 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-399</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.3.64</physloc><unittitle>Collection of the works of William
		  Lambarde (1536-1601)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1501-1599">16th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 manuscript discourses. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The historian William Lambarde was born in London on 18 October 1536.
		  He inherited the manor of Watcombe in Greenwich on the death of his father in
		  1554. He was admitted to Lincoln's Inn in 1556 and studied Anglo-Saxon and
		  history. His first work was a translation of the Anglo-Saxon laws entitled 
		<title>'Archeion', sive de priscis Anglorum legibus libri, sermone
		  Anglico vetustate antiqissimo, aliquot abhinc seculis conscripti, atq; nunc
		  demum ... e tenebris in lucem vocati</title> (1568). Then came his 
		<title>Perambulation of Kent: containing the description, hystorie, and
		  customes of that shyre</title> (1576) which is probably Britain's earliest
		known county history. In 1578-1579, Lambarde was chosen as a Bencher of
		Lincoln's Inn and then became a Justice of the Peace for Kent. His duties were
		described in the 
		<title>Eirenarcha: or of the Office of the Justices of Peace, into two
		  books</title> (1581). In 1592 he was appointed a Master in Chancery and was
		made Keeper of the Records at the Rolls Chapel in 1597. Lambarde was made
		Keeper of the Records of the Tower in January 1601 and produced an account of
		the Tower records, 
		<title>Pandecta Rotulorum</title> (1601). William Lambarde died at
		Watcombe on 19 August 1601.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The works in the collection are 
		<title>Of the highe courtes of Justice in England and especiallie of the
		  Chancery Courts and of the lord Chancellor that judgethe there</title>, 
		<title>Modus sive forma Regum ... Reginarum coronacionis in regno Anglie
		  sequitur in hune modum</title>, 
		<title>Hic describitur modus quomodo Parliamentum Regis Anglie Anglicorum
		  suorum tenebatur temporibus Regis Edwardi filii Etheldridi regis</title>, and 
		<title>The charge of a Courte Leete and Courte Baron</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 11.
		Kennett-Lluelyn. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: MS of his Perambulation of Kent, 1570, Centre
		  for Kentish Studies, Ref. U47/48, ZI NRA 3509 Kent misc., and correspondence
		  (copies) with Sir John Leveson, 1585-1601, Ref. TR 1497 NRA 11021; draft of
		  Eirenarcha, 1579-1600, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS
		  41137, also miscellaneous historical collections, Ref. Cotton MS Vesp A V 1,
		  also annotations to papers and transcripts by Lawrence Nowell, Ref. Add MSS
		  43703-10, also Perambulation of Kent, commonplace book and papers, circa
		  1570-1571, Ref. Add MSS 4521, 5123, 11750, 20033, 20709, also second draft of
		  his history of Kent, 1572, Ref. Sloane MS 3168, and revision of part of
		  Eirenarcha, Ref. Eg MS 3676; diary and papers as Kent J.P., 1580-1601, Folger
		  Shakespeare Library, Ref. MS V a 207; X d 119, 120, 122 (2-4), 249, see J. H.
		  Baker, English legal MSS in USA (1985-90); miscellaneous papers, circa
		  1574-1600, University of Virginia Library, Ref. Atcheson L. Hench collection,
		  see W. H. Bond, Census of medieval and renaissance MSS in United States and
		  Canada, suppl, 1962; miscellaneous papers, Oxford University, Bodleian Library,
		  Special Collections and Western Manuscripts, Ref. MS Lat hist d 2, also printed
		  copy of Perambulation of Kent with his corrections and additions, circa 1596,
		  Ref. 4o Rawl 263; legal papers and copy of his Archeion, Harvard University Law
		  School, see Baker, English Legal MSS in the USA; miscellaneous papers including
		  accounts and pedigree, 1575-1601, Drapers' Company, Ref. H/Add.18-22 NRA 39865
		  Drapers' Co; and, correspondence with Sir John Leveson, 1585-1601,
		  Staffordshire and Stoke-on-Trent Archive Service, Staffordshire Record Office,
		  Ref. D593/S/4/14/16-18 NRA 10699 Leveson-Gower.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Lambarde</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1536-1601</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Historian</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">16th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
