<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-197" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-197</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Robert Douglas (1594-1674)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jan 23 11:40:07 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-197</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.5.30-31</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Robert Douglas
		  (1594-1674)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1601-1699">17th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="sco">Scots.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Robert Douglas was born in 1594. He was the grandson of George Douglas
		  of Lochleven who had helped Mary Queen of Scots to escape imprisonment in
		  Lochleven Castle in 1567. He was educated at St. Andrews University and took
		  the degree of M.A. in 1614. Douglas then entered the church, first as Minister
		  of Kirkcaldy in 1628 before becoming chaplain to one of the brigades of
		  Scottish auxiliaries sent to aid Gustavus Adolphus of Sweden in the Thirty
		  Years War. It was said that Gustavus highly appreciated Douglas's wisdom and
		  military skill. After his return to Scotland, he was elected as a member of the
		  General Assembly in 1638. In 1639 he was chosen as a Minister in the High Kirk
		  of St. Giles, and 1641 the Tolbooth Church. Also in 1641 he preached before the
		  Scottish Parliament. In 1642, then in 1645, 1647, 1649, and 1651, he was
		  Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland. In 1643, Douglas
		  was named as one of the Commissioners to the Westminster Assembly which
		  produced the Westminster Confession of Faith of English-speaking Presbyterians,
		  and in 1644 he was a chaplain to one of the Scottish regiments in England. In
		  1649, he and other Commissioners presented the Solemn League and Covenant to
		  Parliament, and in 1650 he was one of the churchmen who, at Dunfermline, sought
		  the signature of Charles II to a declaration of religion. This was refused by
		  the King. However, as the leader of Scotland's moderate Presbyterians, Douglas
		  officiated at the coronation of Charles II at Scone in 1651. During the
		  ceremony he preached a sermon which said that it was the monarch's duty to
		  maintain the established religion of Scotland and to bring the other religions
		  in Britain into conformity with it. Douglas assisted in the Restoration of the
		  monarchy in 1660, and afterwards was offered the bishopric of Edinburgh if he
		  would accept the introduction of episcopacy into Scotland. He refused, and was
		  latterly simply Pastor of Greyfriars' in Edinburgh and then Minister of the
		  Parish of Pencaitland, East Lothian. His publications include 
		<title>The diary of Mr. Robert Douglas when with the Scottish army in
		  England</title> (1644), 
		<title>A sermon preached at Scone, January the first, 1651, at the
		  Coronation of Charles II</title> (1651), and 
		<title>Master Douglas, his sermon preached at the down-sitting of the
		  last Parliament of Scotland</title> (1661). Robert Douglas died in 1674.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of sermons by Robert Douglas and other
		  Covenanters, 17th century.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.5. Craik-Drake.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Covenanters</emph> </subject>
		
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Douglas</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1594-1674</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Presbyterian
		  Divine, Covenanter</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
