<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-203" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-203</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Sir Charles Lyell (1797-1875)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Andrew Thomson, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jul 10 10:00:29 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-203</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 108-onwards (Lyell)</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Sir
		  Charles Lyell (1797-1875)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1823-1875">1823-1875</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>Temporarily ca. 35 boxes (9 linear metres). </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> <language langcode="fre">French, </language> and
		  <language langcode="ger">German.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Charles Lyell was born at Kinnordy, near Kirriemuir in Angus, on 14
		  November 1797. During his lifetime he wrote many geological papers, mainly
		  published by the Geological Society of London, however his reputation rests
		  almost entirely on his work 
		<title>Principles of Geology</title>, inspired in part by a European tour
		with Sir Roderick Impey Murchison and also his knowledge of James Hutton's
		Theory of the Earth. In this work, first published in three volumes
		(1830-1833), Lyell propounded his theory of uniformitarianism, which holds that
		the Earth's history is explained by gradual change over time, and that
		geological processes going on today (like erosion) have occurred in the past
		and have shaped the Earth's surface, and this had a strong influence on Charles
		Darwin. Lyell's other works include: 
		<title>The Elements of Geology</title> (1837), 
		<title>Geological Evidences of the Antiquity of Man</title> (three
		editions, 1863-1873). Charles Lyell's father was an active naturalist, and
		Lyell had access to an elaborate library which included works on geology.
		Whilst at Oxford University he attended lectures by William Buckland, Professor
		of Geology, that triggered his enthusiasm for the subject. He became more and
		more interested in the subject and made many geological tours with his family
		in England and Scotland in 1817, and on the Continent the following year, the
		first of many trips abroad. In 1828 he explored the volcanic region of the
		Auvergne, then went to Mount Etna to gather supporting evidence for the theory
		of geology he would expound in his 
		<title>Principles of Geology</title>. He also made numerous tours of the
		United States, described in 
		<title>Travels in North America</title>. His writings deal with the rock
		cycle, which explains how one type of rock is transformed into another. Lyell
		also expounds notions on volcanic forces, deposition, erosion and paleontology
		in his writings. His work helped to establish the modern study of geology and
		geologic time. In addition to rock formation, he also wrote about paleontology.
		It was Lyell who proposed the idea of reference fossils - fossils which are
		indicative of certain periods of geologic time. He divided geologic time into
		four periods: Pleistocene, Older Pliocene, Miocene and Eocene. His final work, 
		<title>The Antiquity of Man</title>, 1863, was a wide-ranging study of
		the human fossil record. In 1823 Lyell was appointed secretary of the
		Geological Society of London, and 3 years later they made him their foreign
		secretary. He was twice President in 1836 and 1850. Lyell was elected Fellow of
		the Royal Society in 1826. He was awarded a Royal Medal in 1834 and the Copley
		Medal in 1858 and in 1866 he was awarded the Wollaston Medal. In 1832 he was
		the first professor of geology at King's College, London, and became President
		of the British Association in 1864. Sir Charles Lyell died at his Harley Street
		home, in London, on 22 February 1875. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers of Sir Charles Lyell consist of: circa 10 boxes of
		  correspondence; 2 boxes of miscellaneous papers and lecture notes including
		  lectures on geology, notes on sea-serpents, notes on the New Zealand
		  earthquake, 1856, and an address on Darwin; and, circa 24 boxes of offprints of
		  papers.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) 
		<title>Sir Charles Lyell</title>. [Online]. People of Angus. 
		<extref
		 href="http://www.angus.gov.uk/history/features/people/lyell.htm">Angus Council,
		  Local History</extref> [Accessed: 8 March 2001] (2) Bailey, Edward. 
		<title>Charles Lyell</title>. London: Thomas Nelson &amp;amp; Sons Ltd,
		1962. (3) 
		<title>Sir Charles Lyell</title>. [Online].Emuseum. 
		<extref
		 href="http://www.anthro.mankato.msus.edu/information/biography/klmno/lyell_charles.html">Minnesota
		  State University</extref> [Accessed: 8 March 2001]. (4) Howard, A.V. 
		<title>Chamber's Dictionary of Scientists</title>. London &amp;amp;
		Edinburgh: W. &amp;amp; R. Chambers Ltd, 1951. (5) 
		<title>SJSU Virtual Museum</title>. [Online]. 
		<extref href="http://www.sjsu.edu/depts/museum/lye.html"> San Jose State
		  University</extref> [Accessed 8 March 2001]. (6) Williams, T.I. 
		<title>A Biographical Dictionary of Scientists</title>. London: A.
		&amp;amp; C. Black Ltd, 1969.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held
		  at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting
		  of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987;
		  and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Lyell related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): Dc.4.101-103; Gen. 108-120; Gen. 525;
		  Gen. 527; Gen. 1425-1426; Gen. 1429; Gen. 1731; Gen. 1733; Gen. 1971; Gen.
		  1996; JA 3787; Mic.M.957-958; and, more recently acquired correspondence. There
		  is also correspondence to and from Lyell in the Laing Collection, La.II and
		  La.IV. Related material is held by National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts
		  Division GB 0233 MSS 2213-2217 (1844-1872). A further 9 institutions (and 1
		  private individual) which hold archive material relating to Sir Charles Lyell
		  are noted in the National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Geology</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Geologists</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Erosion</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Naturalists</emph> </subject>
		
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Paleontology</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Lyell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Charles</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1797-1875</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Geologist </emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Murchison</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Roderick Impey</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1792-1871</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Geologist </emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Hutton</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1726-1797</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Geologist,
		  Chemist, Naturalist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Geikie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Archibald</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1835-1924</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Geologist </emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Darwin</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Charles Robert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1809-1882</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Naturalist </emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Geological Society of London</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
