<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-67"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-67</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Scotland Africa
			 '97 Archive </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
  level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-67</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1056-1059; E2006.38</physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Scotland Africa '97 Archive
		  </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1996-1997">1996-1997 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>4 boxes.
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Scotland Africa '97 (SA '97) was an umbrella organisation which aimed
		  at the strengthening of existing links between Scotland and Africa and the
		  creation of new routes to understanding and co-operation. Between May and
		  October 1997, a series of cultural events took place with these aims in mind,
		  under the banner 
		<title>Scotland Africa '97 </title>. Because of the positive feedback and
		the success of the events generally, it was decided to set up an archive
		serving as a record of the events held. It was hoped that the archive could be
		used as a source for researchers examining the impact of SA '97 and as a
		resource for anyone looking for information about the organisations involved.
		The idea for the series of cultural events came from the Centre of African
		Studies at Edinburgh University. It was intended that the events should raise
		the profile of Africa and explore the historical and contemporary links between
		Scotland and the huge continent. The events held were both large and small, and
		although many were held in Edinburgh, SA '97 offices had been established in
		Edinburgh, Glasgow and Aberdeen to support the events of organisations all over
		the country, from Dundee and Musselburgh, to Argyll and Inverness, and from
		Kelso and Dumfries, to Banchory and Stromness. The events ranged from an
		African ceramics exhibition, fashion show, and African storytime for children,
		to a rhino awareness week, a play about Mungo Park, and an exhibition on Mary
		Slessor. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>The material for the Scotland Africa '97 Archive (in Gen. 1056-1059)
		  was chosen to show the range of events which took place and the variety of
		  organisations and people involved. The main body of the material consists of
		  information of the events which took place and this is arranged alphabetically
		  by the name of the organisation involved. The events are also more fully
		  described in 
		<title>The Scotland Africa '97 Brochure </title> in Folder 2 of the
		archive. The material also includes newsletters and leaflets; management
		committee minutes and general forum minutes; accounts; funding proposals and
		grant applications; letters and cards; invitations; programmes, posters, and
		flyers; audio tapes; conference and seminar reports; press releases;
		catalogues, information sheets, and information packs; and, photographs and
		press cuttings.</p> 
		<p>E2006.38 is a folder containing 10 black and white exhibition
		  photographs taken by Matt Laver, photographer, Edinburgh. They feature: costume
		  and dance; Wole Soyinka; Julius Nyerere; Jackson Hulungwani; an Adzido dance
		  workshop; a spirit talk; Kinsi Abdulleh; a Lamu snake dance; Lorna and Jenny;
		  and, Mara.</p>
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Park</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Mungo</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1771-1806</emph> </persname> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Slessor</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Mary
		  Mitchell</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1848-1915</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Centre of
		  African Studies (University of Edinburgh)</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">University of
		  Edinburgh (Centre of African Studies)</emph> </corpname> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Exhibitions</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>Handlist, H67 </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
