<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-457" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-457</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Archibald Pitcairne (1652-1713)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Oct 4 11:56:24 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-457</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.61/191; Dc.1.62; Dc.4.101-103 Pitcairne; De.7.69;
		  Df.1.33/2</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Archibald Pitcairne
		  (1652-1713)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1692-1712">1692-1712</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box, 10 miscellaneous manuscript documents</extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Archibald Pitcairne was born in Edinburgh on 25 December 1652. He was
		  educated in Dalkeith and then from 1668 studied at Edinburgh University from
		  which he graduated with the degree of M.A. in 1671. Although it was intended
		  that he enter the Church, Pitcairne went on to study law in Edinburgh and
		  Paris, and in the latter city he became interested in medicine. On his return
		  to Edinburgh, and as a friend of Dr. David Gregory (1661-1708), he studied
		  mathematics, though medicine wasn't forgotten. Indeed, in 1675 he resumed his
		  medical studies in Paris and Rheims, the latter University awarding him the
		  degree of M.D. On his return to Edinburgh he began practice as a physician and
		  was one of the founder members of the Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh.
		  Sympathetic to the Jacobite cause, Pitcairne had to leave Scotland in order to
		  succeed in his profession and in 1692 he was appointed to the Chair of Physic
		  at Leiden University. He returned to Edinburgh in 1693 but became embroiled in
		  a catalogue of controversies and disagreements which were probably politically
		  motivated, although because he was also known to mock the Church, there may
		  have been another reason for the negative stand towards him. In 1699 though he
		  was awarded the degree of M.D. from Aberdeen University, and in 1701 he was
		  admitted to the Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh. His publications
		  include 
		<title>Solutio problematic de historicis; seu de inventoribus
		  dissertatio</title> (1688), 
		<title>De sanguinis circulatione in animalibus genitis et non
		  genitis</title> (1693), 
		<title>Dissertatio de curatione febrium</title> (1695), 
		<title>Dissertatio de legibus historiae naturalis</title> (1696), 
		<title>Epistola Archimedis ad regem Gelonem Albae Graecae, reperta anno
		  aerae Christianae 1688</title> and numerous satirical verses on the Church, and
		latin verses. Archibald Pitcairne died in Edinburgh on 20 October 1713.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: a volume of papers containing medical
		  prescriptions, notes on medical matters, correspondence, 1701-1708, and
		  entitled 
		<title>Praxeos Pitcairnianae specimina</title> and which also includes
		letters to Gregory, 1700-1708; Commentarius in partem solutionis problematic de
		inventoribus A. Pitcairnii 1688 edite a D. Gregorio Oxoniae 27 June 1692 et
		D.J.Wallisio G.P.S. tradita 30 Junii 1692; poems in Latin, 1708, 1712, and
		undated; Latin verses, 
		<title>Georgius Buchananus Gualtero Dannistono</title>; and, manuscript
		fragments.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 15. Owens-Pockrich.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Pitcairne related
		  material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letter
		  to Viscountess Stormont, 1664, at La.II.554; letter from Thomas Bower,
		  Aberdeen, 1710, at La.III.535; 
		<title>The Assemblie, or Scottish Reformation</title>, a comedy, at
		La.III.799; 
		<title>General Assembly</title>, a comedy, at La.III.456; 
		<title>The Wigg comedy</title> at La.III.798; poems in Latin, at
		La.III.629; Epistola Archimedis ad regem Gelonem Albae Graecae reperta anno
		aerae Christianiae, 1688. at La.II.36; Latin verses, 
		<title>In Jacobum 2dum Britanniae regem</title>, and 
		<title>Upon the anniversary of the Pretender's birthday</title>, and 
		<title>In Maii 29 and Juni 10, 1712</title>, and 
		<title>Ad G. Burnet epsicop. salisburensem</title>, at La.II.89, f.251;
		burlesque by Dr. Brown of Pitcairne's elegy on Gregory, at La.II.89, f.281;
		four satirical poems, 1711, at La.II.358/5; Mention in a letter from Tytler to
		Chalmers, at La.II.453/2; notes by Chalmers, at La.II.451/1; notes on his poems
		at La.III.353; an elegy on his death, at La.IV.17; and, notices at La.IV.17.
		There is also: material at S.32.65; collection of mathematical and other papers
		by James Gregory (1638-1675) and David Gregory (1661-1708) with items by or
		referring to Pitcairne, at Dc.1.61; mention of Pitcairne in letters from
		Sibbald to Sloan, at Dc.8.35.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: textbook of medicine, Society of
		  Antiquaries of London, Ref. MS 25, see P. J. Willetts, Manuscripts in the
		  Society of Antiquaries of London (2000); lecture notes, Wellcome Library for
		  the History and Understanding of Medicine, Ref. MS 100, and MS of The
		  Assemblie, Ref. MS 3916; notes, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref.
		  Sloane MSS 2582, 3198; lecture notes, 1712, University of British Columbia,
		  Woodward Biomedical Library; poems, Glasgow University Library, Special
		  Collections Department, Ref. MS Ferguson 108; letters, 1696-1711, National
		  Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 1393, 1423; letters,
		  1704-1709, National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD205/Portfolio 4, and letters
		  to Earl of Mar, 1707, Ref. GD124 NRA 32022 Erskine.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Medicine</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Pitcairne</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Archibald</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1652-1713</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physician and
		  Poet</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
