<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-246" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-246</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures of Professor James Hamilton (1767-1839)
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Jun 22 11:01:09 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-246</unitid> 
		<physloc>MS 2684; Dc.3.74</physloc><unittitle>Lectures of Professor James
		  Hamilton (1767-1839) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1802-1812">1802-1812</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>ca. 12 bound lectures. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Hamilton, James; Black, Adam; Barnes, Thomas</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Hamilton was born in Edinburgh in 1767. He was one of two sons
		  of Alexander Hamilton (1739-1802), Professor of Midwifery at Edinburgh
		  University. James Hamilton was given medical training by his father and became
		  his assistant at the age of twenty-one. He and his father founded Edinburgh's
		  Lying-in Hospital in Park Place in 1793, and later on this enterprise would
		  become supported partly from his own funds. In 1800, Hamilton succeeded his
		  father as Professor of Midwifery at the University. Their subject however had
		  been slow to be accepted by the Senate as part of the medical curriculum and in
		  1815 Hamilton raised the matter of recognition for midwifery. He faced
		  hostility however, particularly from Dr. James Gregory (1753-1821), and
		  recognition would not be achieved until 1830.</p> 
		<p>Although his classes were, for a long time, non-essential for
		  graduation, they were well attended, and Hamilton's contribution to midwifery
		  included advocacy of uterine suture after Caesarian operations and the
		  introduction of the term 'eclampsia' for convulsions in labour or
		  peurperium.</p> 
		<p>Hamilton's publications included 
		<title>A collection of engravings designed to facilitate the study of
		  midwifery</title> (1796), 
		<title>Hints for the treatment of the principal diseases of infancy and
		  childhood</title> (1809), and 
		<title>Practical observations on various subjects relating to
		  midwifery</title> (1836-1837).</p> 
		<p>Professor James Hamilton died in November 1839. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Professor Hamilton's manuscript lectures dated over the period 5
		  January to 29 January 1802 are contained within a bound notebook at MS 2684.
		  The lectures cover diseases of pregnancy, nurses, abortions, and extra-uterine
		  conception. There are also notes of Hamilton's lectures on midwifery taken down
		  in shorthand, Dc.3.74. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Notes written by Thomas Barnes were presented by Dr. Henry Barnes,
		  1910. Lectures written by Adam Black were purchased from P.M. Pollock in June
		  1987 with Accession no. E.87.69.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.8. Glover-Harriott.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) Burnett, John H. (et al.). 
		<title>The university portraits</title>. 2nd series. pp.108-109. (3)
		Material in 
		<title>Catalogue 42. P. M. Pollack. History of Medicine and
		  Science</title>. 1987.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to material relating to
		  Professor James Hamilton, including: midwifery certificates, diploma in
		  obstetrics granted to another, letter, and mention in a letter (check the
		  Indexes for more details). In addition, the UK National Register of Archives
		  (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence
		  and papers, 1803-39, at the Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh, Ref.
		  Hamilton NRA 16015 Coll. of Physicians; notes taken from lectures on midwifery
		  given by Hamilton and his father, circa 1792-93, British Library, Manuscript
		  Collections, Ref. Add MSS 45919-20.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Midwifery</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Hamilton</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1767-1839</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of
		  Midwifery</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Gregory</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1753-1821</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physician</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Black</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Adam</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Barnes</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
