<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-274" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-274</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor William Pulteney Alison
			 (1790-1859)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Aug 17 09:20:05 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-274</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.3.110; Gen. 129/2-4; Gen. 1999/1/33; Gen. 1730/1 Alison;
		  E89.80</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor William Pulteney Alison
		  (1790-1859)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 part volume, 4 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Alison, William Pulteney; Ritchie, D.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The physician William Pulteney Alison was born in 1790 at
		  Boroughmuirhead, Edinburgh. He was the elder son of the Rev. Archibald Alison
		  (1757-1839) and the older brother of Sir Archibald Alison (1792-1867). He spent
		  his early years in Kenley, Shropshire, where his father was a curate, but in
		  1800 the family moved to Edinburgh on the appointment of his father as minister
		  of the episcopal chapel in Cowgate, Edinburgh. After private tutoring at home,
		  he entered Edinburgh University, studying the arts and then medicine. He
		  graduated with the degree of M.D. in 1811 with the dissertation 
		<title>De viribus naturae medicatricibus</title>. After a tour of Europe
		in 1814, Alison returned to Edinburgh and in 1815 became a physician in the
		recently opened New Town Dispensary. There he acquired knowledge of the
		conditions of the city's poor, their sicknesses, the spread of diseases, and
		living conditions. He was particularly interested in fevers and his reports
		were published in the 
		<title>Edinburgh medical journal</title> (1817-1819). For this work he
		was elected a Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh in 1817. In his reports,
		Alison had written on his treatment of smallpox by vaccination, a pioneer
		treatment at this time. In 1820 he was appointed Professor of Medical
		Jurisprudence at Edinburgh University in succession to Andrew Duncan junior
		(1773-1832), and on the death of his uncle, James Gregory (1753-1821), he was
		elected to succeed him as Professor of the Institutes of Medicine (Physiology
		and Pathology). Alison would hold the Chair for the next twenty years until his
		appointment as Professor of the Practice of Medicine in 1842. In the late 1820s
		and early 1830s, he was very active in the fight against typhus and cholera and
		he traced the increase in the prevalence of these diseases in the cities
		directly to poverty, attacking the Scottish Poor Law through his pamphlet 
		<title>Observations on the management of the poor in Scotland, and its
		  effects of the health of the great towns</title> (1840). His other publications
		include 
		<title>Outlines of physiology: with an appendix containing heads of
		  lectures on pathology and therapeutics</title> (1831), 
		<title>Outlines of pathology and practice of medicine</title> (1844), and
		
		<title>Observations on the reclamation of waste lands and their
		  cultivation by croft husbandry: considered with a view to the productive
		  employment of destitute labourers, paupers, and criminals</title> (1850).
		Professor William Pulteney Alison resigned his Chair in 1856 and he died in
		Edinburgh on 22 January 1859. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers consist of correspondence including: at Gen. 129/2-4,
		  letters to Professor Robert Jameson about a collection of birds sent probably
		  from India, and in opposition to the proposal that natural history should be a
		  compulsory subject in the medical curriculum at Edinburgh University; other
		  correspondence to Jameson at Gen. 1999/1/33. In addition, at Dc.3.110 there are
		  extracts from Alison's lectures on clinical medicine, 1837. There is also
		  correspondence, 1843, at E89.80.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter purchased November 1989, Accession no. E89.80.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Burnett, John H. (et al.). 
		<title>The university portraits</title>. Second series. pp.7-9.
		Edinburgh: Eyre and Spottiswoode, 1986. (2) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney. 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 1. Abbadie-Beadon.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show references to other material related to
		  Professor William Pulteney Alison (check the Indexes for more details): a
		  certificate awarded to A. T. Watson, 1830, at Gen. 784/9/32; recommendation of
		  his lectures; and, in the Laing Collection, at La.II.511, a letter about
		  lodgings for students, circa 1833.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Alison</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William Pulteney</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1790-1859</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physician </emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Jameson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1774-1854</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Mineralogist
		  </emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
