<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-376" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-376</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Thomas Henry Huxley (1825-1895)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu May 09 11:07:20 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-376</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.2.96/6/3; Dc.4.101-103; Dk.8.4/2; Gen. 1731 Huxley; Gen.
		  2169/75; E94.44; E95.72</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Thomas Henry Huxley
		  (1825-1895)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1867-1884">1867-1884</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>17 letters, 1 bundle notes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Thomas Henry Huxley was born in Ealing, Middlesex, on 4 May 1825. He
		  received only two years of formal education, 1833-1835, but from around 1838
		  until 1841 he was apprenticed to his brother-in-law, medical materialist John
		  Charles Cooke. In 1841 he transferred to a practice in London's docklands, and
		  while there he studied at Sydenham College, off Gower Street. Between 1842 and
		  1845, he studied on a free scholarship at Charing Cross Hospital, and in 1845
		  announced the discovery of the layer of cells in the root sheath of hair which
		  came to bear his name. Huxley was appointed Assistant-Surgeon on HMS
		  'Rattlesnake' and served between 1846 and 1850 surveying Australia's Great
		  Barrier Reef and New Guinea. He studied the structure and growth of sea
		  anemones, hydras, jellyfish, and sea nettles such as the Portuguese man-of-war.
		  Grouping them together as (sting-celled) Nematophora (later to be classified as
		  the phylum Cnidaria or Coelenterata), he demonstrated that they were all
		  composed of two 'foundation membranes' (endoderm and ectoderm ). In 1848, he
		  sent to the Royal Society of London 
		<title>On the affinities of the family of the medusa</title>. Huxley
		returned to Britain in 1850 and that year too he was made a Fellow of the Royal
		Society. In 1854 he began lecturing in Natural History and Paleontology at the
		Government School of Mines in Piccadilly, and in 1859 some research of his
		appeared as 
		<title>The Oceanic Hydrozoa</title>. Meanwhile, from 1856, there began a
		long association between Huxley and Charles Darwin, the former seeing Darwin's
		approach as an important support to his own ambition of building a new
		scientific elite unbound by old constraints. Support of Darwin and his
		evolutionary naturalism provided him with the nickname 'Darwin's bulldog'.
		Huxley challenged the notion of supernatural creation and, as an advocate of
		agnosticism, a term which he coined, he sought no reconciliation between
		science and theology. In 1861 he observed that human and ape did not
		significantly differ and in 1863 he published 
		<title>Zoological evidence as to man's place in nature</title> and 
		<title>On the causes of the phenomena of organic nature</title>. In the
		academic session 1875-1876, he delivered a course of lectures in Zoology at
		Edinburgh University. Huxley served as President of the Geological Society
		(1869-71), the Ethnological Society (1868-71), the British Association for the
		Advancement of Science (1870), the Marine Biological Association (1884-90), and
		the Royal Society (1883-85). He also sat on several Royal Commissions,
		including that on the Sea-fisheries of the UK. His other publications include 
		<title>Lectures on the Elements of Comparative Anatomy</title> (1864), 
		<title>A Manual of the Anatomy of Vertebrated Animals</title> (1871), and
		
		<title>A Manual of the Anatomy of Invertebrated Animals</title> (1877).
		Thomas Henry Huxley died in Eastbourne, Sussex, on 29 June 1895. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The Huxley collection consists mainly of correspondence including:
		  letter to Sir W. Turner on his appointment as Professor of Anatomy, 1867;
		  letter to J. Morley, 1873; letter to Prof. J. H. Balfour, 1875; letter
		  concerning meetings of the Circumnavigation Committee; paper entitled 
		<title>Huxley as the professor; a student's reminiscences</title>;
		letters to George Lillie Craik, 1874-1884; letter to P.G. Tait, 1875; letter
		accompanying a contribution to the Carlyle Memorial Fund, 1881; letters, 1875
		and 1878; and, letter to Macmillan, 1880. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Correspondence with Geikie purchased December 1960, Accession no.
		  E60.33. Letter to Lyell, purchased 1974, Accession no. E74.9. Letter to Morley,
		  purchased December 1974, Accession no. E74.37. Letter to Mitchell, purchased
		  February 1975, Accession no. E75.7. Letter with contribution to Carlyle
		  Memorial Fund, acquired October 1975, Accession no. E75.51. Letters to Craik,
		  purchased October 1981, Accession no. E81.93. Letter to Tait, acquired May
		  1983, Accession no. E83.32. Letter purchased June 1994, Accession no. E94.44.
		  Letters purchased October 1995, Accession no. E95.72.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise
		  dictionary</title>. Part 1. From the beginnings to 1900. London: Oxford
		University Press, 1953. (2) 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Volume 10. 1939-1940.
		Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1940. (3) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Vol.6. Micropaedia.
		Ready Reference. 15th ed. Chicago and London: Encyclopaedia Britannica,
		1991.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show references to Huxley related material in the
		  Geikie collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters to Sir. A.
		  Geikie and to Macmillan, 1860-1888, at Gen. 525. The Indexes also refer to a
		  requisition for specimens required by the Professor of Natural History from the
		  Museum of Science and Art, 1876, at Da. (Gen.), and a letter of Sir Charles
		  Lyell recommending Huxley for a post in the University of London, 1856, at Gen.
		  1730 (AAF). There is also a mention of Huxley in letters of R. Dick, geologist,
		  1859, at Gen. 863/1, a memorial to Huxley is mentioned in a letter of Sir W.T.
		  Thiselton-Dyer to Sir A. Geikie, 1895, at Gen. 1426/134.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence, notebooks,
		  diaries and papers, London University, Imperial College Archives, Ref. B/HUXLEY
		  NRA 8194 Huxley, and letters (11) to Lord Playfair, 1854-1891, Ref. B/PLAYFAIR
		  NRA 11556 Playfair; 1 manuscript, sketches of flower, insects and birds, 1884,
		  Natural History Museum, Ref. L MSS HUX, and (copies) of letters from Huxley to
		  Andrew Murray, 1859-1878, Ref. L MSS MUR, and correspondence and papers
		  relating to Huxley Memorial Committee, 1895-1900; lecture notes, 1861-1862,
		  National Library of Wales, Ref. Sir John Williams MSS 358; lecture notes, 1867,
		  Wellcome Library for the History and Understanding of Medicine, and letters to
		  JT Knowles (84 items), 1871-1895, Ref. MS 5271; lecture notes, 1869-1871,
		  Oxford University: Department of Zoology; letters (11) to Sir Henry Cole,
		  1857-1887, American Philosophical Society Library, and letters to Sir Charles
		  Lyell, 1859-1868, NRA 9728 American Philosophic; correspondence with Charles
		  Darwin (12 items), 1859-1880, Cambridge University Library, Department of
		  Manuscripts and University Archives, Ref. Darwin NRA 11458 Darwin, and
		  correspondence with Sir George Stokes (81 items), 1864-1893, Ref. Add 7342,
		  7656 NRA 20700 Stokes; letters (184) to Sir Michael Foster, 1875-1895, Royal
		  College of Physicians of London; letters to George Gordon, 1857-1892, Elgin
		  Museum, Ref. NRA(S)1989 NRA 22745 Gordon; letters to George Holyoake,
		  1871-1891, Co-Operative Union Archive, Ref. MM/96636/1-12 NRA 16403 Holyoake;
		  letters to Sir Norman Lockyer, Exeter University Library, NRA 11128 Lockyer
		  Observatory; correspondence with Macmillans, 1866-1894, British Library,
		  Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 55210; letters (15) to Trenham Reeks,
		  1856-1879, British Geological Survey Library, Ref. IGS1 NRA 18675 Inst of Geol;
		  correspondence with Herbert Spencer, 1860-1875, London University Library, Ref.
		  MS 791 NRA 16253 Spencer; letters (c300) to Sir John Tyndall, Royal Institution
		  of Great Britain; and, letters (16), 1856-1893, Huntington Library.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Natural history</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Huxley</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas Henry</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1825-1895</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scientist</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
