<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-227" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-227</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Phrenological Society of
			 Edinburgh</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Apr 16 12:19:53 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-227</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 608</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Phrenological
		  Society of Edinburgh</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1820-1870">1820-1870</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes, 1 letter-book, 2 minute-books, 3 scrapbooks.
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Combe, George</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Phrenological Society of Edinburgh was formed on 22 February 1820.
		  The first meeting of the Society was held at Hermitage Place, in Edinburgh, and
		  was attended by: George Combe (1788-1858), Writer to the Signet; James
		  Brownlee, Advocate; Andrew Combe, Surgeon; William Waddell, WS; Lindsay
		  Mackersy (sic), Accountant; and, Rev. David Walsh. The Chairman of the first
		  meeting was noted as George Combe and a moving spirit of the Society was Sir
		  George Steuart Mackenzie of Coul, Baronet (1780-1848). The object of the
		  Phrenological Society was 'to hear papers' and 'to discuss questions' connected
		  with Phrenology. It would 'hold correspondence' with societies and individuals
		  taking an interest in Phrenology, and collect and pursue facts and views that
		  'may improve and enlarge the boundaries of the Science'. Although Phrenology
		  was a popular field of study well into the 20th century, it became discredited
		  by scientific research. Phrenologists looked at the skull for indications of
		  mental faculties and traits of character, and its principles were established
		  by Franz-Joseph Gall (1758-1828), an Austrian, and by Johann Gaspar Spurzheim
		  (1776-1832) and George Combe. Gall had studied the heads of prisoners and
		  inmates of lunatic asylums, and from his observations he deduced certain traits
		  in the individuals, mapping out where 'murder' or 'theft' and so on were seated
		  in the brain. Spurzheim and Combe went on to divide the scalp into regions
		  where, for example, acquisitiveness, benevolence, combativeness,
		  constructiveness, destructiveness, individuality, linguistic perception,
		  self-esteem, wit and wonder etc were seated.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The records of the Phrenological Society include, within boxes: cash
		  book; catalogues of skull casts and other; papers of the Society; six notebooks
		  including lecture titles, names of members and visitors who inspected the
		  casts, and a 'memoir on the phrenology of Hindostan' read to the Society in
		  1823. The records also include a letter-book covering the period 1820-1840,
		  minute-books for 1841-1870, and scrap-books of newspaper cuttings and printed
		  items. Some material is stamped: Henderson Trust Museum. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>Some papers, books and specimens of the Phrenological Society of
		  Edinburgh were given to the William Ramsay Henderson Trust (originally founded
		  for the study of Phrenology) for its Museum. Books were then given to Edinburgh
		  University Library, and specimens to the Anatomical Museum. In 1952, the papers
		  were transferred to Professor J. C. Brash of the Department of Anatomy,
		  Edinburgh University, before being given to the Library.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. 15th ed. Vol.9.
		Micropaedia. p.407. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., 1991. (2) Material
		in the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Lists of members of the Phrenological Society can be found in yearly
		  volumes of The Phrenological Journal and Miscellany, and later series, at
		  shelfmark Att.35.5., Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division. Also, at Gen. 1733/83 there is a letter relating to skulls from South
		  Australia delivered to the Society's collection in 1854. There are also
		  references to letters and a small group of papers of George Combe.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Phrenology</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Combe</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1788-1858</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">Phrenologist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Mackenzie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George Steuart</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1780-1848</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Mineralogist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Gall</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Franz Joseph</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1758-1828</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Anatomist,
		  Physiologist and Phrenologist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Spurzheim</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Johann Gaspar</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1776-1832</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">Phrenologist</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Phrenological Society of Edinburgh</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">William Ramsay Henderson Trust</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
