<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-742" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-742</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Rev. Robert Murray McCheyne
			 (1813-1843)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Dec 9 09:57:56 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> GB 0237 MSS MACCH
			 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-742</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS MACCH</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rev. Robert Murray
		  McCheyne (1813-1843)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1811-1848">1811-1848</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>21 notebooks, miscellaneous cards and certificates,
		  circa 350 letters, circa 165 sermons. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in
		  a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>McCheyne, Robert Murray </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Robert McCheyne was born in Edinburgh on 21 May 1813. He was educated
		  at the city's Royal High School and then he studied at Edinburgh University,
		  matriculating in 1827. In 1831, he began studies at Divinity Hall and was
		  licensed to preach in 1835. In November 1835 he was appointed as Assistant to
		  the Rev. John Bonar of Larbert and Dunipace, Stirling. He became a well-known
		  preacher and was ordained to St. Peter's Church, Dundee, in November 1836. In
		  1839 he was part of a committee sent to Palestine by the General Assembly of
		  the Church of Scotland to collect information about Jews. McCheyne and Andrew
		  Bonar (d. 1892) recorded their journey in 
		<title>Narrative of a mission of inquiry to the Jews</title> (1842). The
		Rev. Robert McCheyne died on 25 March 1843, and he was buried by St. Peter's
		Church, Dundee.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: notebooks containing a variety of
		  material including sermon outlines, poems, letters while on a trip to
		  Palestine, class notes, diary and sketches of Palestine trip, outlines of
		  talks, convocation notes, and poetry scrapbooks of others; a packet of
		  miscellaneous cards such as Edinburgh University class tickets for history,
		  philosophy, and theology, library ticket, and General Assembly ticket;
		  references to McCheyne's probity, and certificates of attendance and
		  proficiency; letters from the period November 1836 to January 1835, and
		  including correspondence from McCheyne to his family and letters to McCheyne; a
		  passport issued to McCheyne in 1839 by the British consul in Smyrna; sermons
		  and discourses from March 1837 to November 1841; some unidentified fragments; a
		  copy of 
		<title>Sketches of Palestine by the late Revd. R. M. McCheyne</title>,
		perhaps 1839; and, a copy of 
		<title>The Bible atlas, or, sacred geography delineated</title> by
		Richard Palmer (1823). </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 12. Llwyd-Mason.
		London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">McCheyne</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert Murray</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1813-1843</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister of St.
		  Peter's Church, Dundee</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Palestine</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
