<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-416" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-416</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Papers relating to Joseph Lister, 1st Baron
			 Lister (1827-1912)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Jul 29 15:52:15 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-416</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.2.76/25; Dc.2.85/10/1-3; Dc.2.96, ff.1-73; Dc.2.96, ff.87-88;
		  Dc.2.96, ff.108-111; Dc.2.96/3; Dc.2.96/6/2; Dc.2.96/7; Dc.2.96/112;
		  Dc.3.99/8-9; Dc.4.98/6 (13); Dc.4.101-103; Dk.7.60/2; Dk.7.60/10; Gen. 178/4;
		  Gen. 716F/1, 34, 36, 40, 101; Gen. 1425/345-346; Gen. 1731; Gen. 1733/44, 91;
		  Phot.Ill.15; E88.110; E2006.30</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Papers
		  relating to Joseph Lister, 1st Baron Lister (1827-1912)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1854-1908">1854-1908</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 73 letters, miscellaneous manuscript and printed
		  material, and 1 box containing honorary degrees and diplomas. </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Joseph Lister was born in Upton, Essex, on 5 April 1827. He qualified
		  as a doctor at London's University College Hospital, graduating with B.A. and
		  M.B. in 1852. He became a Fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons, London, the
		  same year. In 1853 Lister came to Edinburgh to build on his surgical
		  experience, and was then elected to vacancies that arose at the Royal Infirmary
		  and at the Royal College of Surgeons in the city. He became a Fellow of the
		  Royal College of Surgeons, Edinburgh, in 1855. In 1860 he became Professor of
		  Surgery at Glasgow University and a surgeon at the city's Royal Infirmary.
		  Lister returned to Edinburgh University in 1869 as Regius Professor of Surgery,
		  and then in 1877 he became Professor of Surgery at King's College, London.
		  Joseph Lister was famous for his work on antiseptics in surgery. He had taken
		  the research of Louis Pasteur (working on air-borne organisms) a stage further.
		  He realised that some of the organisms could cause post-operative wound
		  infections such as tetanus, blood-poisoning, and gangrene. He countered this by
		  using carbolic acid soaked in lint or calico around the wound and replaced
		  slow-to-absorb silk stitching with cat-gut stitching which absorbed the
		  carbolic acid better. He also experimented with gauze swabs and a disinfectant
		  spray for operating theatres. Lister was appointed Serjeant-Surgeon to Queen
		  Victoria in 1878, and was created a Baron in 1897. Lord Lister died on 10
		  February 1912.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material includes: holograph testimonial, 1854; letters to Dr.
		  Hooper May and testimonial, 1854-1899; testimonial in favour of Edward Hooper
		  May, 1860; letters to Baillie Johnston about the Chair of Surgery, Edinburgh
		  University, 1864; letters to Sir W. Turner, 1867-1907; commission of
		  appointment as Professor of Clinical Surgery at Edinburgh University, from
		  Queen Victoria, 1869; letter to Dr. Sharpey, circa 1870; letter discussing work
		  on antiseptics; letters to A. Wilson, 1878-1907; letters to Sir A. Geikie,
		  1893-1897; letters to Dr. D. Aitken, 1896-1897; letters to David Christison
		  about the Queen's death, John Beddoe, malaria, and Lister's work, 1900-1902;
		  letters of recommendation and support and thanks, 1879-1908; miscellaneous
		  letters, 1873-1908; prescription, 1892; certificate of attendance at classes,
		  1879; menu and table plan for a banquet in honour of Lister, 1897;
		  congratulatory address to Rudolf Virchow, 1901; photographs; diploma, Honorary
		  Fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh, 1905; photographs of some
		  of the letters in the collection, and prescription; facsimiles of some of the
		  letters in the collection; and, and inventory of donation, 1928.</p> 
		<p>There is also a collection of honorary degrees and diplomas, awarded
		  by UK and foreign institutions.</p>
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter, 6 May 1879, acquired October 1960, Accession no. E60.24.
		  Certificate and letters to Aitken, acquired 1961, Accession no. E61.41. Letter
		  to C. Brinsley Marlay, 1901, purchased 1963, Accession no. E63.4. Diplomas and
		  letters, including to Sir W. Turner, and commission from Queen Victoria,
		  acquired 1963, Accession no. E63.23. Letters including address to Virchow,
		  purchased November 1966, Accession no. E66.43. Geikie letters, acquired August
		  1968, Accession no. E68.24. Letter to Williams, 1898, purchased May 1972,
		  Accession no. E72.12. Undated letter to Crawford, purchased 1973, Accession no.
		  E73.24. Letter to Cornish, 1890, purchased October 1973, Accession no. E73.34.
		  Letter to Cheatle, 1905, purchased November 1973, Accession no. E73.50. Letter
		  to Fortescue, 1908, purchased December 1974, Accession no. E74.37. Letters to
		  Baillie Johnston, acquired April 1976, Accession no. E76.15. Diploma, Hon.
		  FRCSE, 1905, transferred from Old College, May 1976, Accession no. E76.22.
		  Letter to an unnamed, 1873, purchased February 1979, Accession no. E79.9.
		  Letters to Dr. Hooper May, purchased March 1979, Accession no. E79.33. Letter
		  to Hart, 1873, purchased July 1980, Accession no. E80.56. Letter to Sharpey,
		  purchased October 1980, Accession no. E80.218. Letter to nephew, 1898,
		  purchased January 1981, Accession no. E81.3. Testimonial, Edward Hooper May,
		  1860, purchased November 1982, Accession no. E82.79. Inventory, 1928, acquired
		  September 1988, Accession no. E88.110. Box honorary degrees and diplomas
		  accessioned August 2006, Accession no. E2006.30.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>Who was who ... 1897-1916</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1920.
		(2) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes also show: mention of Lister in a letter of John
		  Brown M.D., author of 
		<title>Rab and his friends</title>, circa 1880; appreciation of his
		character in a letter from Sir William Turner to the Rev. Dr. Wallace
		Williamson, 1912; and, the unveiling of a plaque to Syme and Lister in High
		School Yards, Edinburgh University, 1957. The local Indexes also show various
		references to material related to the Lister Memorial Scheme (check the Indexes
		for more details): printed papers relating to the Scheme, with MS notes, 1937,
		including minute of meeting 15 June 1937 and a brief historical sketch of the
		Scheme, at Gen. 784/9/19-21; and, general purposes committee, 1950-1953,
		duplicate TS, at Gen. 2248/4.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence and papers, Royal
		  College of Surgeons of England, Ref. NRA 9521 RCS scientific, see HMC MS papers
		  of British scientists 1600-1940, 1982; letters (14), 1897-1909, Royal College
		  of Physicians of London, Ref. NRA 9520 RCP, and correspondence with Sir Thomas
		  Barlow, 1897-1909, Ref. NRA 9520 RCP; correspondence and papers, 1869-1912,
		  Royal College of Physicians and Surgeons of Glasgow, Ref. RCPSG11 NRA 22540
		  Physicians Glasgow; correspondence and papers, Royal College of Surgeons of
		  Edinburgh, Ref. NRAS 1412 NRA 20261 Royal Coll Surgeons, and, correspondence
		  with John Chiene, 1870-1908, see Scottish Records Association datasheet no 6
		  part 37; correspondence, diary, sketch book and papers, Wellcome Library for
		  the History and Understanding of Medicine, Ref. MSS 3298-3303, 5018 NRA 25910
		  Wellcome Inst, and correspondence and papers with notebooks, 1833-1910, Ref.
		  MSS 6961-6989 NRA 36159 Lister, and notes of W. Sharpey's lectures, 1849-1850,
		  Ref. MSL MS 80, see HMC MS papers of British scientists 1600-1940, 1982, and
		  notes on his lectures on clinical surgery by Albert Wilson (3 vols), 1874-1877,
		  Ref. MSS 5356-58, and letters to Lister Institute, 1893-1907, Ref. SA/LIS NRA
		  29786 Lister Inst., and correspondence with Sir Edward Sharpey-Schafer,
		  1888-1899, Ref. PP/ESS NRA 25584 Sharpey-Schafer, and letters to Sir Thomas
		  Barlow, 1886-1907, Ref. PP/BAR NRA 41070 Barlow; notebooks, Coomonwealth
		  Mycological Institute, see HMC MS papers of British scientists 1600-1940, 1982;
		  case notes, for the location of these papers see HMC MS papers of British
		  scientists 1600-1940, 1982; dissertation, Royal Medical Society, see HMC MS
		  papers of British scientists 1600-1940, 1982; correspondence and papers,
		  Suffolk Record Office, Ipswich Branch, see HMC MS papers of British scientists
		  1600-1940, 1982; 1878-99: letters to Sir Henry Acland, 1878-1899, Oxford
		  University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western Manuscripts, Ref.
		  MSS Acland NRA 22893 Acland, and correspondence with Sir Henry Burdett,
		  1882-1901, Ref. MSS Eng b 2068-69, c 5894-6032, d 2867-89 NRA 39820 Burdett;
		  letters (10) to Sir Alfred Kempe, 1894-1907, West Sussex Record Office, Ref.
		  Kempe papers NRA 17595 Kempe; and, letters, Birmingham University Information
		  Services, Special Collections Department, Ref. L Add NRA 13481 Birmingham, see
		  Accessions to repositories 1969.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgeons</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgery</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Lister</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Joseph</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1827-1912</emph> <emph altrender="title">Baron Lister</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">surgeon</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Sharpey</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1802-1880</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">Physiologist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Turner</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1832-1916</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Anatomist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="othersource"> <emph altrender="surname">Geikie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Archibald</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1835-1924</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Geologist</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
