<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-508" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-508</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures and Papers of Professor Sir Thomas Grainger
			 Stewart (1837-1900)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Feb 17 10:24:16 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-508</unitid> 
		<physloc>Da.45.5, f.51; Dc.10.36; Dk.3.20-21; Dk.4.14-15; Dk.4.21-22;
		  Gen. 829-830; Gen. 1730-1732; MSS 2639-2640; MS 2667; MSS
		  2692-2693</physloc><unittitle>Lectures and Papers of Professor Sir Thomas
		  Grainger Stewart (1837-1900)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>13 volumes, 1 letter</extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Stewart, Thomas Grainger; Mickle, A. W. T. F; Taylor,
		  William; Menzies, J. D; Donald, W. Gordon; Hughes, D. J.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Thomas Grainger Stewart was born in Edinburgh on 23 September 1837. He
		  was educated at the city's Royal High School and then studied at Edinburgh
		  University from which he graduated in 1858 with the degree of MD. He then
		  studied at universities in Berlin, Prague and Vienna. On his return to
		  Edinburgh he became a house physician under Professor John Hughes Bennett
		  (1812-1875) and Professor Thomas Laycock (1812-1876) at the city's Royal
		  Infirmary. In 1861 he was lecturing on materia medica and dietetics. Stewart
		  was appointed as Pathologist to the Infirmary in 1862, as well as Physician to
		  the Sick Children's Hospital, and in 1866 he was elected as a Fellow of the
		  Royal Society of Edinburgh. At this stage in his career he had worked a great
		  deal on the kidney and kidney conditions, on dilation of the bronchi, and on
		  acute atrophy of the liver. In the 1870s he conducted lectures on Clinical
		  Medicine at the Infirmary and on the Practice of Physic at the extra-mural
		  school, and in 1876, on the death of Professor Laycock, he was appointed
		  Professor of the Practice of Physic at Edinburgh University. Stewart was
		  President of the Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh from 1889 to 1891.
		  His publications include 
		<title>A practical treatise on Bright's Disease of the Kidneys</title>
		(1869), and 
		<title>An introduction to the study of the diseases of the nervous
		  system</title> (1884). Stewart was also interested in Scottish history and
		archaeology and he wrote a drama around the Regent Moray entitled 
		<title>The good Regent: a chronicle play</title> (1898). In 1882 he was
		appointed Physician-in-Ordinary to Queen Victoria in Scotland on the death of
		Sir Robert Christison (1797-1882) and was knighted in 1894. Professor Sir
		Thomas Grainger Stewart died on 3 February 1900. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material includes: lectures on the practice of physic, 1879-1880,
		  1883-1885,1885-1886, 1889-1890, and 1897-1898 and some undated; notes of
		  lectures taken 1876-1877; letter to Miss Ferguson, 1882; and, a letter to
		  Professor Geikie about an examination in the practice of physic, 21 March
		  1898.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Brown lectures transferred from the former Central Medical Library,
		  January 1966, Accession no. E66.2. Letter to Ferguson, Index dated at 27
		  February 1969, Accession 27.2.69. Donald lectures purchased September 1984,
		  Accession no. E84.33. Hughes lectures acquired April 1986, Accession
		  no.E86.18.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>At the time of writing this description, the letter was not viewed.
		  The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following
		  material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 22. Supplement.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909. (2) 
		<title>The dictionary of national biography. The concise dictionary. Part
		  1. From the beginnings to 1900</title>. Reprinted. London: OUP. Geoffrey
		Cumberlege, 1953. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Sir Thomas Grainger Stewart
		  related material (check the Indexes for more details): signature at Dc.4.14/3,
		  f.50; testimonial in favour of A. Wilson, 1879, at Dc.4.98/2, f.56; report of
		  cases in winter session 1884-1885 in Ward 23 under the care of Stewart, at
		  Dc.6.94; notice in Sir J. S. Flett's account of student days, 1886-1894, at
		  Dc.6.116, f.64; and portraits at Phot.Ill.157/23, and in JY 1202.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: lecture notes, 1876-1898,
		  Wellcome Library for the History and Understanding of Medicine, Ref. MSS
		  4707-12; lecture notes, 1883-1887, Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh,
		  Ref. Stewart NRA 16015 Coll of Physicians; correspondence, National Library of
		  Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 7178-79; and, letters to H. W. Acland,
		  1888-1898, Oxford University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western
		  Manuscripts, Ref. MSS Acland NRA 22893 Acland.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Medicine</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Stewart</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas Grainger</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1837-1900</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Physician</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Mickle</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">A. W. T. F.</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Taylor</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Menzies</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">J. D.</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Donald</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">W. Gordon</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hughes</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">D. J.</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
