<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-483" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-483</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of material relating to the Scottish National
			 Party</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Oct 21 12:11:51 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-483</unitid> 
		<physloc> Gen. 890-892; Gen. 909-910</physloc><unittitle>Collection of
		  material relating to the Scottish National Party</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes, 2 folders</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Scottish National Party came into being in 1932 on the merging of
		  the National Party of Scotland (NPS, 1928-1932) and the moderate-rightist
		  Scottish Party (1930-1932).</p> 
		<p>The NPS had been founded in Stirling by members of the Scottish
		  National League, including the Gaelic nationalist and writer R. S. Erskine Mar
		  and poet C. M. Grieve (Hugh MacDiarmid). The NPS had soon attracted
		  left-wingers from the Scottish Home Rule Association (SHRA, 1886-1929) which
		  had emerged during the period of Gladstone's adoption of the Irish cause and
		  when Liberals had taken up the idea of home rule for Scotland, Ireland, and
		  Wales. In 1918 the SHRA had seen something of a revival and had shown a
		  socialist trend under William Gallacher, Thomas Johnston, and Roland Muirhead
		  but after long rounds of activity and support from some Labour Party leaders,
		  negotiations were eventually opened with other nationalist groups and this had
		  led to the establishment of the NPS in 1928. The new party did badly in the
		  1929 elections, but in 1931 the writer and nationalist Compton Mackenzie was
		  elected Rector of Glasgow University. During the economic crisis of the 1930s,
		  conservatives from the Scottish Party merged with the NPS - purged of its
		  extremists including C. M. Grieve - and the SNP was born. The root cause for
		  its foundation had been the failure of attempts to bring about the reform of
		  government in Scotland, in spite of commitments towards this by the interested
		  established parties of the day - Liberals, the Labour party, and the
		  Independent Labour Party.</p> 
		<p>In 1942, during the Second World War, a split emerged in the SNP over
		  party policy towards the war, but in 1945 Robert McIntyre won Motherwell for
		  the party - a constituency now in the modern Labour heartlands. This seat was
		  soon lost however, and until the 1960s few seats were fought as the party
		  established itself under the leaders McIntyre, James Halliday, and then Arthur
		  Donaldson. By the 1960s, a new generation of leaders and membership - among
		  them William Wolfe - began to achieve improved ballots particularly in
		  by-elections, and by 1967 a huge advance was shown in the constituency of
		  Pollock (Glasgow), almost won by George Leslie. Then, also in 1967, Winifred
		  Ewing captured Hamilton for the SNP from the Labour Party and on the back of
		  that success, the party made many advances in the 1968 local elections.</p> 
		<p>In an effort to halt the nationalist advance, Harold Wilson
		  established a Royal Commission on the Constitution and in his 'Declaration of
		  Perth' Edward Heath proposed a Scottish Assembly to undertake scrutiny of
		  Scottish legislation. Meanwhile the nationalist advance was slowed somewhat by
		  internal party problems and inexperience. However, when the Royal Commission
		  reported in 1973 with its recommendations for devolved Scottish and Welsh
		  assemblies, and when these received muted response from Westminster, new
		  advances were made. In 1973, Margo MacDonald won the Govan (Glasgow)
		  constituency for the SNP from Labour, and in 1974 the party won first seven and
		  then eleven seats. For the remainder of the 1970s, British domestic politics
		  became pre-occupied with the devolution debate which culminated in the 1978
		  Scotland Act and Wales Act. A referendum held in 1979 showed a small majority
		  in favour of a devolved assembly in Scotland but the 'yes' result failed to
		  reach the target of 40 per cent of the whole electorate.</p> 
		<p>In spite of this disaster, the SNP under the leadership of Gordon
		  Wilson pressed for implementation anyway but with failure to obtain a clear
		  commitment towards an assembly, the SNP Parliamentary Group took part in the
		  vote on the motion of no confidence which finally brought down the government
		  of Prime Minister James Callaghan in 1979. In the election which followed,
		  Margaret Thatcher's Conservative Party took power in the UK, and the
		  nationalist vote in Scotland collapsed.</p> 
		<p>In the early-1980s both the SNP and the Labour Party went through a
		  period of turmoil. For the SNP, battle was drawn between the leftist 1979-group
		  and the traditionalist-independence-nothing-less group, and while this was
		  underway the newly formed all-UK Social Democratic Party was beginning to make
		  headlines. When the new party created by disaffected Labour leaders then formed
		  an alliance with the Liberals, the SNP vote began to suffer again. Redefinition
		  of SNP aims was required, and in 1988 there came the commitment to Independence
		  in Europe and to a role for the country in the EC, later EU. Electoral
		  successes for Jim Sillars, Margaret Ewing, Andrew Welsh, and Alex Salmond in
		  the late 1980s marked a new revival for the party. Indeed, when Alex Salmond
		  took over the party leadership from Gordon Wilson in 1989, the SNP had become a
		  leftist social democratic party, and by 1991 it was running second place in
		  opinion polls behind the Labour Party in Scotland.</p> 
		<p>The general election in 1997 brought a Labour Party victory and with
		  it the acceptance at last that the 'settled will' of the Scottish people was to
		  see the establishment of a Scottish Parliament, and a willingness to see
		  devolved government brought to many parts of the UK. A Scotland Bill was indeed
		  enacted, a referendum called for 11 September 1997, and subsequently won by the
		  'yes' campaign. An election was held on Thursday 6 May 1999 and the Scottish
		  Parliament was formally opened on 1 July 1999, although it first sat on
		  Wednesday 12 May 1999 when Winifred Ewing was the first MSP (Member of the
		  Scottish Parliament) to take her oath. This was the first time that a Scottish
		  Parliament had sat since 1707. The SNP became the first ever party of
		  opposition in the modern Scottish Parliament. The current party leader is John
		  Swinney. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: original manuscripts of articles about
		  Scotland and the Scottish National Party (SNP) by C. M. Grieve under the
		  pseudonyms of 'Special Correspondent' and 'Mountboy', 1927 to 1929, including
		  indexes of manuscripts; and, articles about the SNP by Grieve. The latter
		  written under pseudonym are entitled 
		<title>The Scottish Nationalist Manifesto</title>, 
		<title>The case for Scottish independence</title>, 
		<title>National Party's inauguration</title>, and 
		<title>The National Party of Scotland</title>.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material purchased February 1967, Accession no. E67.9.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>Of interest too may be the Archives Hub descriptions relating to C. M.
		  Grieve, and Compton Mackenzie and entitled 
		<title>Letters to Christopher Murray Grieve (1892-1978)</title> and 
		<title>Collection of Papers relating to Sir Compton Mackenzie
		  (1883-1972)</title>. There is also the 
		<title>Records of the Scottish Constitutional Committee</title>.</p> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Scottish National Party
		  related material (check the Indexes for more details): letters about C. M.
		  Grieve's and Compton Mackenzie's stand as SNP candidates, from Grieve to R. E.
		  Muirhead, 1928, at Gen. 889, ff.53-61; mention of the SNP in a letter of Grieve
		  to H. B. Cruickshank, 1930, Gen. 886, f.8; mention in a letter from Grieve to
		  H. McCreath, 1927, at Gen. 1730-1732 Grieve; and, note on the formation of the
		  SNP by Grieve, at Gen. 2001*/52.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: papers, Glasgow City Archives,
		  The Mitchell Library, Ref. NRA 16655 Baillie's L; records, 1929-1989, National
		  Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. 6038 6649 7295 10754 NRA 29195
		  SNP, and committee, council and conference minutes and head office
		  correspondence, 1964-1995, Ref. Acc 11987, and Congress files, 1938-1962, Ref.
		  3721 NRA 29272 Muirhead, and minutes, 1926-1931, Ref. 5542 5927 8371 NRA 29260
		  Dott, and also papers of R. D. McIntyre as chairman and president, circa
		  1930-1989, Ref. 10090 NRA 39938 McIntyre.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Macdiarmid</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Hugh</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1892-1978</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">see Grieve Christopher Murray</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Grieve</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Christopher Murray</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1892-1978</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Poet 'Hugh
		  Macdiarmid'</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Scottish National Party</emph> </corpname>
		
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">National Party of Scotland</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
