<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-360" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-360</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor George Hill (1750-1819), Principal of
			 St Mary's College St Andrews </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Apr 08 11:23:20 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-360</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.4.41/72-89</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor George
		  Hill (1750-1819), Principal of St Mary's College St Andrews </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1788-1802">1788-1802</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>17 letters. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>George Hill was born in St. Andrews in June 1750. He was educated in
		  St. Andrews and studied at St. Andrews University. He was a good student and
		  attracted the attention of Lord Kinnoull, Chancellor of the University. Just as
		  he began Divinity studies his father died and instead he became tutor to the
		  eldest son of Pryse Campbell MP, one of the Lords of the Treasury. He resided
		  with the family in London and Wales and spent two years with his pupil in
		  Edinburgh where he himself finished his Divinity course.</p> 
		<p>In the early 1770s Hill was appointed joint Professor of Greek at the
		  University of St. Andrews and in 1775 he was licensed as a probationer Minister
		  by the Presbytery of Haddington, East Lothian. Thereafter he preached regularly
		  at the University. He was ordained by the Presbytery of Haddington in 1778 and
		  in 1780 became a Minister at St. Andrews University, holding his Greek Chair at
		  the same time. In 1787 he received the degree of D.D. and the same year he
		  became Dean of the Order of the Thistle.</p> 
		<p>Hill became Professor of Divinity at St. Mary's College in 1788 and
		  was promoted Principal of the College in 1791. Soon afterwards he was appointed
		  as one of the King's Chaplains in Scotland and in 1799 he became Dean of the
		  Chapel Royal. These appointments were supported by Lord Melville who consulted
		  Hill on Scottish ecclesiastical matters. Hill was Moderator of the General
		  Assembly of the Church of Scotland in 1789. His publications include 
		<title>Lectures upon portions of the Old Testament</title> (1812), 
		<title>Theological institutes</title> (1817), and the three volumes of 
		<title>Lectures on Divinity</title> (1821). Professor George Hill died on
		19 December 1819. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of correspondence with Alexander
		  Carlyle.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 9. Harris-Hovenden.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Hill related material in
		  the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): comments on the
		  arrangements for salary for the appointee to Chair of Church History, St.
		  Mary's College, circa 1793, at La.II.253; letters to T. Brydson about a work of
		  heraldry, 1789, 1792, at La.II.110(i); letter to the Lord Advocate against a
		  mission to India, 1797, at La.II.500; letters to Lord Advocate on College
		  matters, 1799, at La.II.501; letter to George Chalmers, 1804, at La.II.453/2;
		  and, letter to W. Robb, 1805, at La.II.92, f.10.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: 1793-1818: correspondence with
		  John Lee, 1793-1818, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref.
		  MSS 3431-64 passim; letters to the 1st and 2nd Lords Melville, St. Andrews
		  University Library, NRA 14799 Dundas, and letters (68), 1767-1770, Ref. MS
		  38204. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Carlyle</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1722-1805</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister of
		  Inveresk Pamphleteer</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hill</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1750-1819</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Principal of St
		  Mary&apos;s College St Andrews</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
