<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-266" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-266</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures of Sir James Ormiston Affleck
			 (1840-1922)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Aug 15 10:56:08 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-266</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.4.1; Dk.4.12-13</physloc><unittitle>Lectures of Sir James
		  Ormiston Affleck (1840-1922)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1890-1891">1890-1891</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Affleck, James Ormiston; Muirhead, C.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Ormiston Affleck was born in Edinburgh in 1840. He decided to
		  become a doctor and studied at Edinburgh University, qualifying in 1867 with
		  the degrees of M.B. and C.M. and taking the Licence at the Royal College of
		  Surgeons. After qualifying he settled down to practice in the Stockbridge
		  district of the city, but in the evening he continued to study and to work on
		  his thesis 
		<title>Functional disorders of the heart</title>. He took his M.D. degree
		in 1869 and then in 1875 he became a Fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons.
		Affleck's talents were noticed by Professor Sir Douglas Maclagan (1812-1900)
		who selected him as his Assistant in the Department of Public Health and
		Medical Jurisprudence at Edinburgh University. Because Maclagan was also one of
		the clinical teachers at the Royal Infirmary, Affleck as his Assistant soon
		became just as well known and respected in both the University and the
		Infirmary, and in 1877 he was appointed Assistant Physician to the Royal
		Infirmary. Around this time he started as Lecturer on the Practice of Medicine
		at Surgeons' Hall, Edinburgh. When his term of office at the Infirmary expired
		in 1900, he was appointed Consulting Physician at the City Fever Hospital where
		he continued to teach until 1908. He also acted as Physician to the Longmore
		Hospital for Incurables. Affleck was knighted at the Palace of Holyroodhouse,
		in Edinburgh, in 1911. Sir James Ormiston Affleck died on 24 September
		1922.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Lectures on the practice of physic, 1890-1891, at Dk.4.12-13. Lectures
		  on clinical medicine, 1890-1891, at Dk.4.1.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Edinburgh</title>. Vol.42.
		1921-1922. pp.376-379. Edinburgh: Neill and Co., 1923.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: lecture notes, 1897-1898, Wellcome Library for
		  the History and Understanding of Medicine, Reference : MSS 856-57</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physicians</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Affleck</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James Ormiston</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1840-1922</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Physician</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Muirhead</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">C.</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
