<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid publicid="GB 237 Coll-1048" countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237">GB
		237 Coll-1048</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="">Fine Art Postcard
			 Collection</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by JavaScript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2 on 
		  <date>Thu Dec 16 11:46:41 UTC 2004</date>.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1048"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-1048</unitid> 
		<physloc>E2004.31</physloc><unittitle>Fine Art Postcard
		  Collection</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1895/1960">1895-1960</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes and 17 file-drawer-set.</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English</language>
		  <language langcode="fre">French</language> <language
		  langcode="ger">German</language> <language
		  langcode="ita">Italian</language></langmaterial> 
		<origination>Department of Fine Art, Edinburgh University; History of
		  Art, Edinburgh University</origination> 
	 </did> 
	 <phystech> 
		<p>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted</p></phystech> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>History of Art (formerly the Department of Fine Art) is a popular and
		  long-established department of Edinburgh University. It has the oldest
		  full-time Chair of Art History in Britain which was founded in 1880. History of
		  Art is located at Minto House, 20 Chambers Street, Edinburgh, opposite the
		  Royal Museum of Scotland, and within easy walking distance of most of the
		  galleries and museums of central Edinburgh. History of Art has book, slide and
		  photographic collections, as well as a photographic unit. There is also a
		  laboratory for the demonstration of metalworking techniques and methods of
		  conservation.</p> 
		<p>A collection of postcards in photo albums and small file drawers was
		  gathered together by members of Fine Art staff (in the Department's early
		  years) for use as teaching aids before the advent of the popular colour slide
		  format. The early postcard collection is important in that the cards are
		  primarily of European buildings, many of which were lost or damaged during the
		  revolutions and conflicts of the 20th century.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of photo albums (filed arbitrarly) and
		  small drawer sets of postcards (filed geographically). They show European
		  buildings, many ecclesiastical. The subjects are: Italian sculpture; paintings
		  and drawings (possibly of French examples); church exteriors (England, Italy);
		  church interiors (Italy, France, England); domestic exteriors (France); secular
		  exteriors (Italy); secular interiors; doors and doorways (England); wells and
		  fountains; bridges; gateways; steps and staircases; locations in Paris, London,
		  Naples, Florence, Germany, Spain, Scotland, the Netherlands; locations in
		  Venice, Lucerne, Einsiedeln, Baden-Baden, and Heidelberg; and, British secular
		  architecture including landscapes and bridges. There are also many loose
		  postcards.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection came from the Department of Fine Art, Autumn 2004,
		  through Elizabeth Ferro, Librarian, Accession no. E2004.31.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material
		  contained in the correspondence file and University website.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <processinfo> 
		<p>Compiled by Graeme D. Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
		  Collections Division.</p> 
	 </processinfo>
    <!-- Controlled Access Terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Postcards</emph> </subject> 
		<corpname rules="ncarules"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh
		  University</emph> <emph altrender="x">Department of Fine Art</emph> </corpname>
		
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
