<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-517" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-517</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Correspondence of Thomas Perronet Thompson
			 (1783-1869)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Mar 3 10:40:44 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-517</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.4.101-103 Thompson</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence of
		  Thomas Perronet Thompson (1783-1869)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1824-1864">1824-1864</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>13 letters, 1 portrait. </extent> <physfacet>Access to
		  records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Thompson, Thomas Perronet</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The general and politician Thomas Perronet Thompson was born in Hull
		  on 15 March 1783. He was educated at Hull Grammar School and then studied at
		  Queen's College, Cambridge. On his graduation with a B.A. he became a
		  midshipman on the flagship 'Isis' and sailed to Newfoundland. After spending
		  four years in the Navy, he joined the Army in 1806 and saw action in South
		  America against the Spanish. In 1808 he became Governor of Sierra Leone, then
		  an infant colony, but he was recalled in his second year. Thompson again saw
		  action, this time in Spain, in the Peninsular War. In 1815, he was in India,
		  and he also saw action in the Arabian Peninsula, in Ras al Khaimah. In 1822 he
		  returned to Britain and obtained promotion after promotion until in 1868 he
		  became a general. Once in Britain, he took to politics and literature and
		  entered the intellectual circle around Jeremy Bentham (1748-1832). Sympathising
		  with the moves for Greek independence he wrote one or two pamphlets in 1825,
		  and he also wrote on economic matters supporting Adam Smith (1723-1790). In
		  1829 he became the proprietor of the 
		<title>Westminster review</title> and in 1835 he entered Parliament.
		Though he was defeated again in 1837, he re-entered the House in 1847 but was
		out again in 1852. Thompson was an MP again for the last time between 1857 and
		1859. He wrote on many topics including free trade, Catholic emancipation, the
		House of Lords, the theory of rent, currency, and the Corn Laws. His
		publications, many in pamphlet form, include 
		<title>True theory of rent</title> (1826), 
		<title>Catechism on the Corn Laws</title> (1827), 
		<title>Geometry without axioms</title> (1830), 
		<title>Catechism on the currency</title> (1848), and 
		<title>Fallacies on the ballot</title> (1855). Thomas Perronet Thompson
		died at Blackheath, London, on 6 September 1869. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of Thompson's letters to a variety of
		  correspondents, some undated. Includes: letter to Rev. W. J. Fox about the Corn
		  Laws and universal suffrage, 1838; letter to G. Binns about a letter to the
		  editor of the 
		<title>Sun</title>, 1852; and, an engraved portrait of Thompson, 1838.
		</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 19. Stow-Tytler.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Thompson related material
		  in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters from T.
		  P. Thompson and Sir John Bowring to F. Freshfield, 1830, in La.III.366; and,
		  letter to Mr. Carpenter, the Sun Office, enclosing some sheets from the 
		<title>Westminster review</title>, 1834, at La.II.647/371.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence and papers,
		  1804-1869, Hull University, Brynmor Jones Library, Ref. DTH NRA 10609 Thompson;
		  family correspondence and papers, 1808-1868, Leeds University Library, Special
		  Collections, Ref. MSS 277, 283 passim NRA 15923 Thompson; letters to Richard
		  Cobden, 1841-1861, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 43663
		  NRA 5927 Cobden, and correspondence with Francis Place, 1829-1845, Ref. Add MSS
		  35145-51, 37949; letters (208) to H. B. Peacock, 1844-1869, Manchester
		  University, John Rylands Library, Ref. Eng MS 1180; and, letters (17) to George
		  Wilson, 1843-1847, Manchester Archives and Local Studies.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Thompson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas Perronet</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1783-1869</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">General Colonial
		  Governor Politician Economist</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
