<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-748" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-748</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of the Rev. James Campbell Gordon
			 (1906-1980)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jan 7 10:02:39 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-748</unitid> 
		<physloc> MSS GOR 1.1-10</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rev. James
		  Campbell Gordon (1906-1980)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1898-1973">1898-1973</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 boxes, 3 folders, 4 postcard albums, 1 notebook of
		  cuttings, 1 scrapbook, 1 sketchbook, 1 leather case, miscellaneous lecture
		  notes, 1 photograph album and folder photographs. </extent> <physfacet>Access
		  to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Gordon, James Campbell</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Campbell Gordon was born in 1906. The Rev. James Campbell Gordon
		  was, for a time, Minister at the English Reformed Church, Amsterdam, 1965-1971.
		  He died in 1980.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: a typescript play sequence intended for
		  radio presentation, entitled 
		<title>And He was murdered!</title>; talks for confirmation classes;
		newspaper cuttings dealing with the English Reformed Church in Amsterdam, in a
		notebook; album of photographs commemorating the BBC TV 
		<title>Songs of praise</title> service conducted by Gordon, and
		transmitted from the English Reformed Church, Amsterdam, 21 January 1968;
		miscellaneous papers and correspondence in connection with 
		<title>Songs of praise</title>; miscellaneous papers and correspondence
		from period when Gordon was Minister in Amsterdam, 1965-1971; photograph of
		chalice that formerly belonged to English Reformed Church, Amsterdam and now at
		Heriot-Watt University; short histories, photographs, annual reports 1966-1973,
		relating to English Reformed Church, Amsterdam; material published in England,
		USA, and the Netherlands relating to Pilgrim Fathers 350th Anniversary; album
		of photographs and newspaper cuttings relating to churches; lecture synopses on
		dogmatics and apologetics; call from congregation in Karori, New Zealand, 1952,
		in a leather case; miscellaneous leaflets, photographs and guide books relating
		to Iona; and, albums of postcards of churches, and larger photographs of
		churches, in Scotland, Britain as a whole, and in Europe and America.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material
		  contained in the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Church buildings</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gordon</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James Campbell</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1906-1980</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister of
		  English Reformed Church, Amsterdam</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">English Reformed Church (Amsterdam, The
		  Netherlands)</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
