<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-285" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-285</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor James Hartley Ashworth (1874-1936)
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Oct 09 11:41:27 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-285</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.1.20-25; Dk.4.42-55; Gen. 855-859</physloc><unittitle>Papers
		  of Professor James Hartley Ashworth (1874-1936) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1892-1914">1892-1914</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>6 box files, 14 notebooks, 3 diaries, 1 envelope.
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Hartley Ashworth was born on 2 May 1874 in Accrington,
		  Lancashire, and was brought up in Burnley. In 1892 he entered Owens College,
		  Manchester, with the intention of studying chemistry. Instead, he turned
		  towards zoology. In 1895 he graduated from London University with the degree of
		  B.Sc. with Honours in Zoology and Botany, and obtained a D.Sc. from the same
		  institution in 1899. After a temporary post as Demonstrator and Assistant
		  Lecturer back at Owens, Ashworth spent several months at the Biological Station
		  in Naples where he became interested in marine biology and marine zoology. In
		  1900 he was appointed as an Assistant at Edinburgh University and in 1901 he
		  became Lecturer in Invertebrate Zoology. In 1905 a Diploma in Tropical Medicine
		  and Hygiene was instituted and Ashworth worked vigorously to organise the
		  classes in entomology and parasitology (medical entomology and protozoology).
		  The course was extended to cover Helminthology and to the institution of the
		  Diploma in Public Health and then the Diploma in Tropical Veterinary Medicine.
		  In 1919 he was appointed to a new Chair of Zoology taking over the
		  Invertebrates while Professor James Cossar Ewart (1851-1933) remained in charge
		  of Vertebrata. When James Cossar Ewart retired in 1927, Ashworth succeeded to
		  the Chair of Natural History. He worked hard to improve conditions for his
		  Department and established a building fund to which the Rockefeller Foundation
		  made a substantial grant. A new departmental building was opened at the
		  University's King's Buildings site on 15 May 1929 and became known as the
		  Ashworth Laboratory. Ashworth's publications include 
		<title>The giant nerve cells and fibres of Halla parthenopeia</title>
		(1909), a piece on Arenicolidae for the 
		<title>Catalogue of the Chaetopoda in the British Museum</title> (1912),
		and 
		<title>On larvae of Lingula and Pelagodiscus (Discinisca)</title> (1915).
		In addition to his departmental responsibilities, he was an active member of
		the Royal Physical Society, the Scottish Zoological Society, and the British
		Association, and he also served on the Council of the Royal Society of
		Edinburgh. Professor James Hartley Ashworth died on 4 February 1936.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of papers, notebooks of courses taken at Owens
		  College, Manchester, 1892-1895, and diaries of visits to, for example Australia
		  for meetings of the British Association, June-October 1914, and to Canada, USA,
		  Cuba and Panama.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Papers and notebooks presented by Mrs. J. H. Ashworth, 1953. Diaries
		  bequeathed by Mrs. Ashworth, January 1966, Accession no. E66.34.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Obituary. James Hartley Ashworth, D.Sc., F.R.S. 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol.8. 1936-1937.
		pp.74-76. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd. (2) Burnett, John H. (et al.). 
		<title>The university portraits</title>. Second series. pp.12-14.
		Edinburgh: Eyre and Spottiswoode Ltd., 1986. (3) 
		<title>Who was who 1929-1940. A companion to Who's who...</title>.
		London: Adam and Charles Black, 1941. (4) ) Obituary notices. James Hartley
		Ashworth, D.Sc., F.R.S. 
		<title>Proceedings of the Royal Society of Edinburgh</title>. Vol.56.
		1935-1936. Edinburgh: Royal Society of Edinburgh.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence, notes and collections of slides,
		  National Museums of Scotland, Chambers Street, Ref. NRA(S)3330 NRA 35316
		  National Mus of Scot; and, letters (12) to ET Browne, 1901-1915, Marine
		  Biological Association of the United Kingdom, Ref. PBR30 NRA 38150 Marine.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Zoologists</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Ashworth</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James Hartley</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1874-1936</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Zoologist</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Owens College (Manchester, England)</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
