<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-192" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-192</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Sir John William Dawson
			 (1820-1899)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Jan 10 11:36:42 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-192</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.7.57; Gen. 524/1; Gen. 526/4; Gen. 109
		  (Dawson)</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Sir John William Dawson
		  (1820-1899)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1842-1957">1842-1957</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 85 letters, 1 separate item printed
		  matter.</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The geologist and naturalist John William Dawson was born in Pictou,
		  Nova Scotia, on 13 October 1820. His parents had come to Nova Scotia from
		  Scotland, his father from Aberdeenshire and his mother from Stirlingshire. He
		  was educated at the Academy in Pictou and then studied at Edinburgh University
		  during the winters 1841-1842 and 1846-1847. He had been interested in
		  collecting fossils even as a boy, and when he settled into educational work as
		  an adult he undertook a geological survey of Nova Scotia and the study of the
		  natural history of his home province and New Brunswick. In 1842 he accompanied
		  the geologist Sir Charles Lyell (1797-1875) to the South Joggins district of
		  Nova Scotia, returning there again with Lyell ten years later. The result of
		  this work was 
		<title>Acadian geology: the geological structure, organic remains,
		  mineral resources of Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, and Prince Edward
		  Island</title> (1855). Meanwhile, in 1850, Dawson had been appointed
		Superintendent of Education in Nova Scotia, and then in 1855 he became both
		Professor of Geology and Principal of McGill University. He was made a
		Companion of St. Michael and St. George in 1881 and was knighted in 1884. He
		was the first President of the Royal Society of Canada, 1886, and President of
		the British Association for the Advancement of Science in 1886. Dawson retired
		from McGill in 1893. In addition to the work on the geology of the Canadian
		Maritimes, other publications include 
		<title>Handbook of Canadian zoology</title> (1871), 
		<title>Fossil men and their American analogues</title> (1880), 
		<title>Handbook of Canadian geology</title> (1889), 
		<title>The ice age in Canada</title> (1894), and 
		<title>Salient points in the science of the earth</title> (1894). Sir
		John William Dawson died on 19 November 1899. His son, Dr. George Mercer
		Dawson, C.M.G. (1849-1901) was for a time Director of the Geological Survey of
		Canada.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consist largely of correspondence and includes: letters
		  to Sir Archibald Geikie, 1880-1896 at Gen. 526/4; letter to Sir Joseph
		  Prestwich, 1880; a substantial number of letters to Sir Charles Lyell,
		  1842-1875, and newspaper reports of lectures delivered in Montreal, 1855, in
		  the Lyell Collection, Gen. 108 onwards; letter to Sir A. C. Ramsay, 1875, at
		  Gen. 524/1; and a programme for the unveiling of a monument to Dawson in
		  Pictou, 1957.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letters to Geikie, Prestwich, and Ramsay, transferred with others from
		  Geology Dept., December 1960, Accession no. E60.33.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 22. Supplement.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909. (2) Cooper, Thompson. 
		<title>Men of the time: a dictionary of contemporaries</title>. Revised.
		9th edition. London: George Routledge and Sons, 1875. (3) 
		<title>Who was who. A companion to Who's who...</title>. London: A. and
		C. Black, 1920.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show a reference to Dawson (check the Indexes for
		  more details) in the form of: a mention in a letter of Sir Charles Lyell to the
		  Lord Advocate, at Gen. 1733/68. The Indexes also show references to his son,
		  George Mercer Dawson. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA),
		  updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: drawings and maps,
		  Geological Society of London, see Bridson, Natural history MS resources 1980;
		  official papers, McGill University, McLennan Library, NRA 20434 Murray; and,
		  letters to Sir George Stokes, 1867-1891, Cambridge University Library,
		  Department of Manuscripts and University Archives, Ref. Add 7342, 7656 NRA
		  20700 Stokes.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Geologists</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Dawson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1820-1899</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Geologist </emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Lyell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Charles</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1797-1875</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Geologist </emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dawson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">George Mercer</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1849-1901</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Geologist</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Geikie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Archibald</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1835-1924</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Geologist </emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Canada</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">Description and travel</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
