<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-689" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-689</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Correspondence of James Anthony Froude
			 (1818-1894)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Sep 5 10:47:25 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-689</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.4.102-103 Froude; Dk.2.13, pp.45-46; Gen. 1731 Froude; Gen.
		  1733/30; E87.105; E88.51-54; E88.117; E92.17; E92.75; E94.43; E98.05-07;
		  E99.15</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence of James Anthony Froude
		  (1818-1894)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1862-1893">1862-1893</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 70 letters, 2 portrait photographs. </extent>
		  <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Froude, James Anthony</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Distinguished historian James Anthony Froude was born at Dartington
		  rectory, Devon, in 1818. He was the brother of William Froude (1810-1879),
		  engineer and naval architect, and of Richard Hurrell Froude (1803-1836),
		  divine. The younger Froude was educated at Westminster School from 1830, and
		  then privately in the village of Merton. He studied at Oriel College, Oxford,
		  from 1835, and graduated B.A. in 1842, and took his M.A. in 1843. After briefly
		  writing on the life of St. Neot for the 
		<title>Lives of the English saints</title> by John Henry Newman
		(1801-1890), Froude devoted himself to the study of modern history and
		literature. His work 
		<title>Nemesis of faith</title> (1849) was denounced at Exeter College
		and burnt. He became acquainted with Thomas Carlyle (1795-1881) and he
		submitted much of his work to Carlyle for review. When Carlyle died, Froude was
		his sole literary executor. Froude's 
		<title>History of England</title>, published 1856-1870, rivalled that of
		Thomas Babington Macaulay (1800-1859). He was elected rector of St. Andrews
		University in 1868. In 1874 he went to South Africa on behalf of the Earl of
		Carnarvon, Secretary of State for the Colonies, to ascertain what the obstacles
		to confederation might be among the different states there. His conclusion was
		that Britain should leave the states to work out their own future and retain
		control only of the Table Bay peninsula as a military and naval station. He
		returned to South Africa in 1875 this time as a member of the conference
		assembled to deliberate on a scheme for South African federation. This came to
		nothing as did another conference held in London in 1876. In 1876, Froude was a
		member of the Scottish universities commission. In 1892 he was offered the
		Regius Professorship of Modern History at Oxford University. He retired in
		1894. Froude's other works include 
		<title>The influence of the Reformation on the Scottish
		  character</title>! (1869), 
		<title>The English in Ireland in the eighteenth century (1872-1874),
		  </title> 
		<title>History of the first forty years of Carlyle's life</title> (1882),
		
		<title>History of Carlyle's life in London</title> (1884), 
		<title>Luther: a short biography</title> (1883), the poem 
		<title>Romsdal fiord</title> (1883) written after a visit to Norway, 
		<title>The science of history</title> (1884), 
		<title>Oceana, or England and her colonies</title> (1886) written after a
		visit to Australia, 
		<title>The English in the West Indies, or, the bow of Ulysses</title>
		(1888), and 
		<title>The divorce of Catherine of Aragon</title> (1891). Froude had also
		been editor of 
		<title>Fraser's magazine</title>. James Anthony Froude died on 20 October
		1894. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The correspondence consists of: letter to unnamed woman about a letter
		  of Thomas Carlyle referring to a proposal that he should enter Parliament,
		  1886; letters to William Allingham about articles for 
		<title>Fraser's magazine</title>; letters to J. W. Parker, publisher,
		about 
		<title>Fraser's magazine</title>; letter to Parker, possibly, about a
		work, maybe 
		<title>History of England</title> which he hopes Carlyle will review in 
		<title>Fraser's magazine</title>; letter to a contributor to 
		<title>Fraser's magazine</title>; letter to Pattison about the National
		Emigration Association; letter to Edward Fitzgerald about Carlyle; letter to
		Professor Peter Hume Brown; letter to a friend in Manchester about the Colonies
		and the possibility of a union between Canada and America; letters to John
		Ruskin, one about a lecture on positivism; letters to Mrs ward, 1879; letters
		to C. Butler, 1873-1892; letters to Sir W. Muir, 1892-1893 and undate! d; and,
		letters to Mrs. Forster, Mrs. Trevelyan, Reeve, and Mr. Walpole. Also a
		portrait photograph. A batch of transcripts with some of the letters.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Allingham letters, Accession no. E67.35. Parker letters, and others,
		  Accession no. E67.36. Parker letter, about review, Accession no. E67.37. Ruskin
		  letter, Accession no. E70.3. Letter to contributor, Accession no. E74.37.
		  Pattison letter, Accession no. E67.30. Fitzgerald letter, Accession no. E82.59.
		  Brown letter, Accession no. E72.16. Accession no. E87.105. Accession no.
		  E88.51-54. Accession no. E88.117. Accession no. E92.17. Accession no. E92.75.
		  Accession no. E94.43. Accession no. E98.05-07. Accession no. E99.15.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.22. Supplement.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various other references to Froude related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): letters to D. Laing, 1862, at
		  La.IV.6; letter of Froude's the subject of a letter from Sir J. Skelton to D.
		  Laing, 1864, at La.IV.17; letter from Thomas Carlyle about jane Welsh's health,
		  and about Frederick the Great, 1864, at Gen. 1730 onwards. In addition, the UK
		  National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts
		  Commission, notes several locations of Froude related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Froude</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James Anthony</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1818-1894</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Historian</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
