<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-616" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-616</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Anthony James Broomhall
			 (1911-1994)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 16:42:18 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-616</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 26</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Anthony James
		  Broomhall (1911-1994)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1890-1979">[ca. 1890-1979]</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes (574 slides plus indexes)</extent>
		  <physfacet>The images on the slides and lantern slides can be seen without the
		  need for special equipment but projectors are needed to see them at full
		  size.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Broomhall, Anthony James </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Anthony James Broomhall (Jim), China Inland Mission missionary among
		  the Nosu (Yi) people in Szechwan, Kweichow, Yunnan and Nosuland, China, and the
		  Mangyan people of Mindoro in the Philippines, was from a family with strong
		  missionary connections in China. The grandson of Benjamin Broomhall and
		  great-nephew of Hudson Taylor he was born in Chefoo, China in 1911. He was
		  educated in China and in Bath, England, then trained at London Hospital
		  graduating as a doctor in 1937. Broomhall had been interested in the Nosu of
		  south-west China since reading a book about them as a teenager and, in 1938, he
		  sailed for China with the CIM. At first his movements were restricted partly by
		  the need to learn the language but also by the Japanese occupation and he spent
		  some time at the CIM hospital at Langzhong. In 1942 he married Theodora Janet
		  Churchill and they began pioneer work amongst the Nosu but the war with the
		  Japanese soon forced them to flee to India. They were able to return in 1946
		  and continued their evangelical and medical work among the Nosu, especially in
		  Liangshan, until, with the arrival of the communists, they and their four
		  daughters were placed under house arrest. In 1951 they were expelled but
		  Broomhall continued to work for the mission. He explored the possibility of
		  medical work in Thailand which led to three CIM hospitals being established
		  there. In 1953 he and his wife began pioneering among the Mangyan people of
		  Mindoro in the Philippines where they stayed for 11 years. A gifted writer,
		  Broomhall published several works most notably 
		<title>China's Open Century</title>, a seven volume history of
		Christianity in China since the mid 19th century written during his retirement.
		Despite ill health he returned to China twice in 1988 and in 1991 when he met
		the descendants of the Nosu people with whom he had worked. He also raised
		money for hospitals in China and donated medical equipment and textbooks. He
		died on 11 May 1994 in England.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of black and white and coloured slides and
		  lantern slides relating to China, Taiwan, Malaya, the Philippines and Japan and
		  to the China Inland Mission. The slides show a wide variety of town and country
		  scenes, and images of people and places, festivals and occupations, religion,
		  and church and mission work. There is a complete index listing each slide.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material has been arranged by country with the China material in
		  the first box and the other Asian slides in the second box. Within the boxes
		  the slides are grouped according to country or theme as detailed on the
		  indexes.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>Broomhall donated slides of L. C. Wood at the same time but these were
		  subsequently treated as a separate collection. </p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The material was deposited at the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World by A. J. Broomhall circa 1986. Ralph Covell listed the
		  collection in 1992.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Anderson, Gerald (ed.). 
		<title>Biographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New York:
		Simon and Schuster Macmillan, 1998. (2) 
		<title>East Asia Millions</title> (OMF, October-December 1994), (3) 
		<title>Pray For China Fellowship</title> (OMF, September 1994)</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist and complete index is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the China Inland Mission (Overseas Missionary
		  Fellowship) are held at the School of Oriental and African Studies, London
		  University; Broomhall wrote extensively on China including books about the
		  Nosu. The slides of L. C. Wood, also a missionary with the China Inland Mission
		  were deposited by Broomhall at the same time.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Broomhall</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Anthony James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1911-1994</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">China Inland Mission</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">China</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Singapore</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malaya</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Philippines</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Taiwan</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
