<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-831" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-831</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of Horatius Bonar (1808-1889)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jul 20 11:26:51 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-831</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.4.101-103 Bonar; Gen. 1981/24; Gen.
		  2039/57</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Horatius Bonar (1808-1889)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1853-1875">1853-1875</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Bonar, Horatius</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Scottish divine and hymn writer Horatius Bonar was born in
		  Edinburgh on 19 December 1808. He was the younger brother of John James Bonar
		  (1803-1891) who preached in Greenock, and the older brother of Andrew Alexander
		  Bonar (1810-1892). Horatius Bonar was educated at the Royal High School in the
		  city and studied at Edinburgh University. On becoming a preacher he worked in
		  Leith for a while before going to Kelso as minister of the North Church. He was
		  an extremely popular preacher there and he became well-known throughout
		  Scotland. While in Leith he had begun composing hymns and he also produced
		  evangelical books. In 1883 he was Moderator of the General Assembly of the Free
		  Church. Horatius Bonar died in Edinburgh on 31 July 1889.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: a letter, 1867; letter about a full
		  answer to Mr. Christopher's letter mentioning the addressee's 
		<title>The saintly calling</title>, 1875; and, letter to 'My dear Madam'
		reluctantly responding to a request for his autograph and expressing cheer with
		what was said about his Kelso tracts, 1853.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 22 (Supplement).
		London: Smith, Elder and Co. 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show another reference to Bonar related material
		  within Special Collections Division, Edinburgh University Library (check the
		  Indexes for more details): letters (2) to D. Laing about the Bonar family,
		  Greenock, 1866. At the New College Library, Mound, Edinburgh, there is: a copy
		  of 
		<title>The Holy bible</title> belonging to Horatius Bonar, signed and
		dated 1837 on the title page, and with the text heavily underlined, at MSS
		BON.2; and, an address to theological students, material on Chalmers'
		centenary, and sermons, at MSS BOX 14.2.1-5; and hymns with corrections, at MSS
		BOX 14.3.</p> 
		<p>The collection entitled 
		<title>Papers of Rev. Andrew A. Bonar (1810-1892)</title> is held at
		Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU </p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: sermons, poems and hymns, Ref.
		  MS.1758 ff.58-74, and letters to J. J. Bonar, 1830-1873, Ref. MS 15997,
		  National Library of Scotland, Manuscript Collections</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Hymn writers</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Bonar</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Horatius</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1808-1889</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Free Church
		  Minister, Author</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
