<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-205" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-205</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Dr. John Walker (1731-1803)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Andrew Thomson, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue May 01 10:59:56 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-205</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.18; Dc.1.57-59; Dc.2.17-40; Dc.7.113/1-4; Dc.8.20; Dc.8.31;
		  Dc.10.15/1-5; Dc.10.33; Gen. 50-53; Gen. 703-12D; MS
		  2701</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Dr. John Walker (1731-1803)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1760-1803">[176-]-1803</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>55 volumes (2.5 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John Walker was born in the Canongate, Edinburgh, in 1731. After
		  grammar school studies he went to Edinburgh University where he prepared for
		  the ministry. As a student he was trained in Latin and Greek and also quickly
		  developed an interest in minerals. Influenced by William Cullen (1710-1790), he
		  became particularly drawn to chemistry and mineralogy. Walker realised that the
		  classification of minerals had been neglected so he travelled throughout the
		  British Isles, sometimes with Cullen, collecting minerals from mines and
		  outcrops. Using his own personal collection as well as that at the University
		  Museum, he had established an 
		<title>Elementa Mineralogiae</title> by the 1750s, and this
		classification was later modified to include 323 genera. Among the most
		interesting minerals that he collected in the 1760s was strontianite, from the
		mines of Leadhills. Walker became licensed to preach in 1754 and, after his
		ordination as minister of Glencorse in the Pentland Hills in 1758, soon met
		Henry Home, Lord Kames (1696-1782). Walker was commissioned by Lord Kames to
		make an extensive study of the Hebrides in 1764, a trip that he would repeat on
		several occasions. From the time of this first ministry until his appointment
		in 1779 to the chair of Natural History at Edinburgh, he spent all of his spare
		time studying botany and geology. He was greatly influenced by the works of
		Alex Frederick Cronstedt (1722-1765), and especially by the contributions of
		Carl Linnaeus (1707-1778). Walker's university lectures included discussions on
		agriculture's place in national improvement, and he held public lectures on
		agriculture and the Scottish Highlands. Walker had a major impact on the
		establishment of geology as an organised classroom subject in higher education,
		and he therefore has a legitimate claim to the title of 'Father of Geological
		Education'. One of his most significant works was his essay on peat, in which
		he made a complete analysis of the organic content and origin of the substance.
		In other papers he affirmed that petroleum occurred in rocks as a natural
		substance. His discussion of rock structures included accurate definitions of
		strike and dip as well as recognition of horizontal strata overlying tilted
		beds, a condition to which he referred as 'offlap'. Walker played an
		instrumental role in the establishment of the Natural History Society of
		Edinburgh and was appointed first secretary of the Physical Section in 1783. He
		was a long-time member of the Highland Society of Scotland, and as a result of
		his great interest in agriculture, formed the Agriculture Society of Edinburgh
		in 1792. These groups gave him the opportunity to participate in scientific
		discussions and provided an outlet for the publication of some of his articles.
		The Rev. Dr. John Walker held the Professorship at Edinburgh until his death in
		1803. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers of Rev. Dr. John Walker consist of: 16 volumes of his own
		  lecture notes on natural history at the University of Edinburgh (1766-1790),
		  covering a broad range of subjects: meteorology, geology, mineralogy, botany,
		  zoology, fossils, hydrography, rivers, glaciers, etc; 7 volumes of notes and
		  memoranda from natural history field trips (1766-1774); 5 volumes of papers and
		  correspondence on various agricultural themes; 1 volume of essays and
		  observations on philosophy, human behaviour, Scottish history and antiquities;
		  10 volumes of lecture notes on natural history taken down by David Pollock in
		  1797, 5 volumes by Thomas Charles Hope (1784), 4 volumes by T Johnson, 1 volume
		  by SW Carruthers and 1 written by John Douglas (1791); 5 volumes and other
		  papers relating to geological interests; and, correspondence with many
		  scientists of the period and a collection of Walker's sermons. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Gillispie, Charles C. (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of Scientific Biography</title>. Vol.14. New York:
		Scribner's, 1972. (2) Birse, Ronald M. 
		<title>Science at the University of Edinburgh 1583-1993</title>.
		University of Edinburgh, 1994. (3) Williams, T.I ., Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of National Biography</title>. Vol.20. London: Smith,
		Elder &amp;amp; Co, 1908. (4) Devlin-Thorp, Sheila. 
		<title>Scotland's Cultural Heritage</title>. University of Edinburgh,
		1981. (5) Taylor, George. 
		<title>John Walker: a Notable Scottish Naturalist</title>. Reprinted from
		Vol. 38. Trans. Bot. Soc. Edinb., 1959.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held
		  at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting
		  of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987;
		  and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Walker related material
		  (check the Indexes for closer details): Gen. 1999/1/154; Gen. 873/1/111-112;
		  Gen. 874/IV/51-2. There is also correspondence to and from Walker in the Laing
		  Collection at: La.III.352, La.III.353, La.III.575, as well as his sermons at:
		  La.III.132. Related material also held in: Glasgow University Archives and
		  Business Records Centre, Glasgow University Library, Department of Special
		  Collections, GB 0247 see Bridson Natural history MS resources 1980, papers;
		  National Archives of Scotland, GB 0234 GD24/502, 571, 581 NRA 29367 Stirling
		  Home, (1764-1780), letters to Lord and Lady Kames; Royal College of Physicians
		  of Edinburgh, GB 0585 see Bridson, Natural History MS resources 1980 NRA 16015
		  Coll of Physicians, (1782), lecture notes (12 vols). </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Geology</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Agriculture</emph> </subject>
		
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Natural history</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Meteorology</emph> </subject>
		
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Mineralogy</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Botany</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Zoology</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Hydrography</emph> </subject>
		
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Glaciers</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Walker</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1731-1803</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Naturalist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Hope</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas Charles</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1766-1844</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Chemist</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Pollock</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">David</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1780-1847</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight, Judge</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
