<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-138" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-138</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor Adam Ferguson
			 (1723-1816)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Dec 21 09:38:45 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-138</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.6; Mic.Dup.421 (Dc.1.42); Dc.1.77; Dc.1.84-86;
		  Dc.4.41/46-62, 97&#x002A;; Gen. 1733/93; Gen.
		  1729-1732</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor Adam Ferguson
		  (1723-1816)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1773-1808">1773-1808</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 box-files (one with circa 420 papers), 5 volumes,
		  circa 23 letters or notes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The philosopher and historian Adam Ferguson was born at Logierait,
		  Perthshire, on 20 June 1723. He was educated at home, locally in Logierait, and
		  in Perth. When he was sixteen he began studies at St. Andrews University,
		  taking his M.A. in July 1742. Studies in divinity followed, first at St.
		  Andrews, then at Edinburgh University. In 1745, Ferguson was appointed as
		  Deputy-Chaplain then Chaplain to the (42nd) Black Watch and he was present at
		  the Battle of Fontenoy (11 May 1745) a major confrontation of the War of the
		  Austrian Succession. He left the army the same year to embark on a literary
		  career. For a brief period in 1757, Ferguson held the post of Librarian at the
		  Advocates' Library in succession to David Hume (1711-1776). In 1759 he was
		  appointed as Professor of Natural Philosophy at Edinburgh University, and in
		  1764 to the Chair of the now obsolete Pneumatics and Moral Philosophy. A
		  syllabus of his lectures appeared as the 
		<title>Analysis of pneumatics and moral philosophy for the use of
		  students in the College of Edinburgh</title> (1761). In 1773 became tutor to
		Charles, the 3rd Earl of Chesterfield, accompanying him on a tour of Europe. In
		1778, Ferguson was appointed as Secretary to the Commissioners to the American
		Colonies, accompanying them to Philadelphia for the negotiation of a
		settlement. In addition to the publications mentioned above, others include a
		history or 
		<title>Essay on civil society</title> (1766) which influenced Schiller
		and Hegel, and was also known later to Karl Marx, 
		<title>Institutes of moral philosophy</title> (1772), 
		<title>History of the Roman republic</title> (1783), 
		<title>Principles of moral and political science</title> (1792), and the
		posthumous 
		<title>Biographical sketch or memoir of Lieutenant-Colonel Patrick
		  Ferguson</title> (1817). Ferguson retired from the Chair of Moral Philosophy in
		1785, but so that he could still draw a salary he was appointed to the Chair of
		Mathematics. Professor Adam Ferguson died at St. Andrews on 22 February 1816
		and he was buried in the grounds of the ruined Cathedral of St. Andrews. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The Ferguson papers consist of: correspondence with Sir John
		  Macpherson, 1773-1808; correspondence with Alexander Carlyle, 1775-1802; letter
		  to a London bookseller, a publisher, and about a publication of memoirs;
		  letters about religious intolerance among the Greeks and Romans; family
		  correspondence; a collection of essays; lectures on pneumatics and moral
		  philosophy, 1776-1785; and, proceedings of the British commissioners at
		  Philadelphia, 1778-1779.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter of Ferguson purchased July 1985, Accession no. E85.43. Letters
		  of Ferguson purchased 1975, Accession nos. E75.14 and E75.22.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance. Note in addition that material in
		  Dc.1.42 will not be issued to readers. Instead microfilm will be issued:
		  Mic.Dup.421., or Mic.Dup.89 positive.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Stephen (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 6. Drant-Finan.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Ferguson related material
		  in the Laing Collection and elsewhere (check the Indexes for more details): a
		  letter from G(eorge) Washington, 1778, at La.II.163; letters from Sir Walter
		  Scott, La.III.585; correspondence at La.II.583, La.II.483, La.II.453,
		  La.II.419, La.II.242-243, La.II.193, La.II.73/170; mentioned in letters of
		  Professor J. Black, Gen. 874; and, mentioned in a letter of Hume, 1776, and in
		  various other letters. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA),
		  updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence with
		  John Lee, 1774-1800, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref.
		  MSS 3431-64 passim; and, letters (13) to Sir James Murray-Pulteney, Pierpont
		  Morgan Library, Ref. MA487,297,1260-90 NRA 30863 Murray-Pulteney.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Philosophy</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Philosophers</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Ferguson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Adam</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1723-1816</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Philosopher</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">United States</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">Revolution, 1775-1783</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
