<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-579" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-579</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Cecil Polhill (1860-1938) and Arthur Polhill
			 (1863-1935)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Nov 25 09:59:13 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-579</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 10</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Cecil Polhill
		  (1860-1938) and Arthur Polhill (1863-1935)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1903-1926">1903-1926</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 file (c 204 pp)</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Polhill, Cecil Henry; Polhill, Arthur
		  Twisleton</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Cecil Henry Polhill, China Inland Mission missionary in China and
		  promoter of Pentecostal missions, was born into the wealthy Polhill-Turner
		  family in 1860. His father was a former Member of Parliament and the family
		  lived at Howbury Hall, near Bedford. Like Arthur, his younger brother, Polhill
		  attended Eton and then Cambridge University, Arthur studying at Trinity and
		  Cecil at Jesus. It was while he was at Cambridge in 1882 that Arthur Polhill
		  heard D. L. Moody speak and decided to devote his life to God. Cecil Polhill,
		  who had become an army officer, was influenced by his brother and was converted
		  in 1884. In 1885, after several discussion with Hudson Taylor, they decided to
		  become missionaries and in September of that year arrived in China with five
		  other Cambridge graduates as part of the 'Cambridge Seven'. The Polhills went
		  to Hanchung in Shensi where they studied the language then in 1887 moved into
		  Szechwan.</p> 
		<p>Arthur Polhill was at first based at Paoning then moved in 1888, the
		  same year that he was ordained, to Pachei where he remained until 1898. From
		  1899 he and his wife (Miss Drake, a CIM missionary in China since 1884) were
		  based at Suiting. Polhill's wife died in 1906 and he married A. A. Hart in 1908
		  and continued his evangelical work at Suiting until he retired in 1928.</p> 
		<p>Cecil Polhill was first based at Chengtu and Chungking in Szechwan but
		  his main interest was work amongst the Tibetan people. He paid an early visit
		  to Kansu, returning in 1888 to Paoning to marry E. A. Marston (a CIM missionary
		  in China since 1884). The couple spent three years in Sining in Kansu then
		  spent some time travelling along the Tibetan border before in 1892 settling,
		  with their two sons, in Sungpan in north-west Szechwan. Their arrival coincided
		  with a period of severe drought for which they were blamed by the townspeople
		  who attacked the Polhills and forced them to leave. In 1895, after a period of
		  rest in England, Polhill went to Kalimpong in India to help with work on the
		  Tibetan border and a year later his wife and family joined him in Darjeeling.
		  They soon returned to China and settled in Tatsienlu, Szechwan where they
		  stayed until they were evacuated during the Boxer rebellion. Poor health meant
		  that Polhill was sent home in 1900. He remained in England for the rest of his
		  life having inherited the family estate in 1903, but his interest in China
		  continued and he returned on short missionary tours seven times. On the way
		  back from one of these trips in 1908 he became involved with the Pentecostal
		  movement in Los Angeles. His experience led him, with Alexander Boddy, to
		  promote Pentecostalism in Britain. Polhill was particularly interested in
		  evangelism in the missionary context and, with Boddy, founded the Pentecostal
		  Missionary Union in 1909, structured along the lines of the CIM. The PMU sent
		  its first missionaries to China in 1910 and later others went to India and to
		  Tibet. Its activities were promoted through the journal 
		<title>Confidence</title> and Polhill's own 
		<title>Fragments of Flame</title> (later 
		<title>Flames of Fire</title>). Polhill was president and director of the
		PMU until 1925 when it was integrated into the Assemblies of God after which he
		retired. He died in 1938 three years after his brother Arthur.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of a copy of a draft manuscript 
		<title>Two Etonians in China 1885-1925</title> by Cecil and Arthur
		Polhill. The manuscript includes sections written by both brothers and a short,
		abridged section of 
		<title>Evangelisation of the World</title> by Benjamin Broomhall. The
		manuscript covers the brothers' early life, conversion, and work in China and
		refers to the Cambridge Seven and others working in China at the time such as
		Bishop Cassels; the development of various mission stations until 1926; and
		national events such as the Boxer rebellion. The manuscript was assembled in
		1926 but includes some sections written at an earlier date. Spaces have been
		left for photographs which are not included.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged in rough chronological order but deals with
		  Arthur Polhill's activities before his brother's.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The manuscript was donated by the Overseas Missionary Fellowship (was
		  China Inland Mission)in 1985.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <altformavail> 
		<p>A similar copy of the manuscript, also missing photographs, is held in
		  the archives of the Assemblies of God in America (Flower Pentecostal Heritage
		  Centre). </p> 
	 </altformavail> 
	 <odd> 
		<head>Existence/Location of Originals</head> 
		<p>The original manuscript is held by the Overseas Missionary Fellowship
		  (was China Inland Mission).</p> 
	 </odd> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself, (2) Anderson, Gerald (ed.). 
		<title>Biographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New York:
		Simon and Schuster Macmillan, 1998. (3) the Wholesome Words missions web
		site</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Other material relating to Cecil Polhill is held in the archives of
		  the Assemblies of God in America. The archives of the China Inland Mission (now
		  Overseas Missionary Fellowship) are held at the School of Oriental and African
		  Studies, University of London. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p>The manuscript was used by J. C. Pollock for 
		<title>The Cambridge Seven</title>, London: 1955.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Polhill</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Cecil Henry </emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1860-1938</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Polhill</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Arthur Twisleton </emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1863-1935</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">China Inland Mission</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">China</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
