<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-407" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-407</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Correspondence relating to James Maitland, 8th Earl of
			 Lauderdale (1759-1839)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Aug 31 10:22:05 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-407</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.6.19/3; Gen. 1429/16/9; Gen. 1429/18/18; Gen. 1875, no.17-19;
		  Gen. 1982/18-19, 44; Gen. 2040/120-121</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence
		  relating to James Maitland, 8th Earl of Lauderdale (1759-1839)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1798-1836">1798-1836</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>9 letters, 1 signature. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Maitland, James</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Maitland was born at Hatton House, near Ratho, Midlothian, on 26
		  January 1759. He was the second son of James Maitland, 7th Earl of Lauderdale.
		  He was educated at the Royal High School in Edinburgh, and he studied at
		  Edinburgh University. In 1774 he visited Paris and in 1775 matriculated at
		  Trinity College, Oxford, before studying at Glasgow University. In 1777 he
		  became a student at Lincoln's Inn, London, and became a member of the Faculty
		  of Advocates in 1780. A political career began in September 1780 when, after
		  the General Election, he was returned as the MP for Newport, Cornwall. From
		  1784 he was the MP for Malmesbury. In 1789, Maitland succeeded to the Earldom
		  on the death of his father, and in 1790 he was elected as a Scottish
		  representative peer at the House of Lords. Between 1796 and 1806 he was not
		  present at the Lords and during this period he attempted to become a Sheriff in
		  London. During these years too he published the successful 
		<title>Inquiry into the nature and origin of public wealth, and, into the
		  means and causes of its increase</title> (1804) which was translated in French
		and Italian. In 1806, Maitland was back in the House of Lords and he was
		appointed Lord High Keeper of the Great Seal of Scotland and he was sworn to
		the Privy Council. From 1807 he became an active member of the opposition in
		the Lords and chief among the Whig party in Scotland. In 1821 he was awarded
		the Order of the Thistle. He spoke for the last time in the Lords in July 1830.
		James Maitland, 8th Earl of Lauderdale, died at Thirlestane Castle, Lauder,
		Berwickshire, on 13 September 1839. He was buried at Haddington on 20 September
		1839. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The correspondence includes: letter about James Perry, editor of the 
		<title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 1798; letter to 'My dear Sir', 1805,
		and signed by Lauderdale, indicating use of his influence in high places;
		letter to H. Hendry, 1806; letter about the Roxburgh cause, 1810; letter to 'My
		dear Sir John', 1813, and signed by Lauderdale, about his inability to come to
		London, detained as he was by the serious illness of his daughter; letter about
		a 'curious proceeding of the Princess Charlotte', 1814; letter to G. J. Bell;
		and, a letter to (possibly) the Earl of Buchan; There is also a franked postal
		cover addressed to Messrs. Hopkins and Co., 1836, and a newspaper cutting of
		Lauderdale House, 1820.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Miscellaneous Scottish letters, purchased March 1971, Accession no.
		  E71.5. Letter, purchased June 1971, Accession no. E71.21.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 12. Llwyd-Mason.
		London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1909. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to material related to James
		  Maitland, 8th Earl of Lauderdale, in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes
		  for more details): letter to R. Hotchkis, W.S., about the Roxburgh cause, 1819,
		  and letter to Sir G. Warrender, 1839, La.II.509. There is also a mention of the
		  Earl in a letter of Sir Frederick Lewis Maitland, 1821, at Gen. 1982/44.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Lauderdale
		  related material.</p> 
		<p>In addition, to the separately described 'Correspondence relating to
		  John Maitland, 2nd Earl of Lauderdale, 1st Duke of Lauderdale (1616-1682)',
		  Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division, holds papers
		  relating to James Maitland, 9th Earl of Lauderdale, at La.II.509; and, material
		  mentioning James Maitland, 7th Earl of Lauderdale, at Dc.6.111, ff.17-18; 
		<title>A sound to the retreat of the Countess of Dysert, Lucinia</title>,
		verses, at La.II.69, f.35; information against Charles Maitland the 3rd Earl of
		Lauderdale, 1682-1683, at La.II.11; and, a letter and note relating to the Earl
		of Lauderdale, at Gen. 863/8/52-53 (check the Indexes for more details). </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Maitland</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1759-1839</emph> <emph altrender="title">8th Earl of
		  Lauderdale</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">statesman</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">18th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">19th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
