<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-425" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-425</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures and Correspondence of Professor Colin Maclaurin
			 (1698-1746)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Aug 28 16:37:23 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-425</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.17; Dc.2.57, ff.3-5; Dc.3.66; Dc.6.111, f.39; Dc.7.73; Gen.
		  75D; Gen. 1732 Maclaurin; MS 2651; Mic.M.665;
		  Phot.Ill.48</physloc><unittitle>Lectures and Correspondence of Professor Colin
		  Maclaurin (1698-1746)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1701-1799">18th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>9 letters, 4 manuscript volumes, 1 engraving.
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Maclaurin, Colin; Russell, John</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Mathematician and natural philosopher Colin Maclaurin was born in
		  Kilmodan, Glendaruel, in Argyllshire, on February 1698. He was educated in
		  Dumbarton and studied at Glasgow University where he showed an early mastery of
		  mathematics. On being awarded his MA he briefly studied Divinity. In 1717 he
		  became Professor of Mathematics at Marischal College, Aberdeen. In 1719 he
		  visited London, meeting Sir Isaac Newton (1642-1727) and becoming a member of
		  the Royal Society. On a second visit in 1721 he met Martin Folkes (1690-1754),
		  President of the Royal Society. In 1722 Maclaurin was engaged by Lord Polwarth
		  as a tutor to his eldest son, and they travelled to Lorraine. In 1725 he became
		  deputy Professor to the ageing James Gregory at Erdinburgh University. His
		  skill lay in experimental physics, astronomical observation, and practical
		  mechanics. He proposed an astronomical observatory for Scotland and he improved
		  the maps of Orkney and Shetland. His publications include his thesis 
		<title>on the power of gravity</title>, 
		<title>Geometria organica, sive descriptio linearum curvarum
		  universalis</title> (1720), 
		<title>A treatise of fluxions</title> (1742), and 
		<title>Account of the philosophical discoveries of Sir Isaac
		  Newton</title>. In 1745 he was involved in the construction of defences in
		Edinburgh against the advancing Jacobites and when the city was occupied he
		escaped to England where he fell ill. Colin Maclaurin died on 14 June 1746.</p>
		
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: 
		<title>Ane introduction to the Mathematicks</title>, being notes of
		lectures, circa 1725; a letter to an unnamed, 1717, with an engraved portrait;
		letters and microform of letters to Archibald Campbell of Knockbuy, 1725-1745;
		memorial to the Commissioners of excise, 1735; 
		<title>A collection from Mr. McLaurin's course of experiments</title>; 
		<title>A treatise of algebra</title> and 
		<title>An introduction to the method of fluxions</title>; a copy of the
		inscription on the tomb of Colin Maclaurin in Greyfriars Churchyard; and, a
		photograph of a portrait of Maclaurin.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p> 
		<title>A treatise of algebra</title>, purchased March 1961, Accession no.
		E61.9. Letters to Campbell of Knockbuy, acquired October 1970, Accession no.
		E.70.40. Notes of lectures, purchased February 1987, Accession no. E87.21.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>Note that when this record was created any associated
		  photographic/illustrative was unseen.</p> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.12. Llwyd-Mason.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Maclaurin related
		  material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters
		  to Professor C. Mackie and to Rev. R. Wallace, 1735, and 1743, at La.II.236;
		  letter from Sir D. Brewster to D. Laing, 1864, at La.IV.17. In addition, the UK
		  National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts
		  Commission, notes: papers relating to spheroids and Nugae Poeticae, British
		  Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MSS 4437, 52247; memorial to
		  Commissioners of Excise, 1735, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts
		  Division, Ref. Adv MS 23 1 13; papers, Royal Society, see HMC MS papers of
		  British scientists 1600-1940, 1982; letters to Sir John Clerk, 1737-1742,
		  National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD18/5097 NRA 29182 Clerk; letters to James
		  Spreull etc (copies), Glasgow University Library, Special Collections
		  Department, and papers relating to projected biography by J. C. Eaton; letters
		  (11) to James Stirling, 1728-1740, Private, Ref. NRA(S)2362 NRA 14810
		  Stirling.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Mathematics</emph> </subject>
		
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Mathematicians</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Maclaurin</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Colin</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1698-1746</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">Mathematician</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Russell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
