<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-383" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-383</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Commemorating the Hebrew University of Jerusalem
			 (Ha-universita Ha-'ivrit Bi-yerushalayim)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed May 22 11:39:11 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-383</unitid> 
		<physloc>Medals No. 190; Medals No. 206; Gen.
		  2212/3</physloc><unittitle>Commemorating the Hebrew University of Jerusalem
		  (Ha-universita Ha-'ivrit Bi-yerushalayim)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1925-1985">1925-1985</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 medals, 1 graduation programme, 1 typescript
		  translation, 1 philatelic first-day cover. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="heb">Hebrew.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>An important part of the Zionist vision for Israel was the founding of
		  a Jewish university. Land was acquired for this purpose on Mount Scopus and the
		  corner-stone was laid in 1918. The Hebrew University of Jerusalem was opened on
		  1 April 1925 in front of its founder Chaim (Azriel) Weizmann (1874-1952), who
		  would later become the first President of Israel. Others present included Lord
		  Balfour, Viscount Allenby and Sir Herbert Samuel. The first degrees of the
		  University were awarded in 1931. Its earliest research institutes were in
		  microbiology, chemistry and Jewish studies. By 1947, student enrolment was more
		  than 1000, and the University offered teaching in the humanities, science,
		  medicine, and education (and agriculture at Rehovot). Other units included the
		  Jewish National and University Library, a press, and an adult education
		  centre.</p> 
		<p>After the War of Independence in 1948, Mount Scopus and the University
		  campus became a demilitarised Israeli area inside Jordanian territory, cut off
		  from the main Israeli-held sector of Jerusalem. Initially the solution was a
		  scattered campus in various parts of the city, but in 1953 new building began
		  at Giv'at Ram. Work started too on a medical science campus at Ein Kerem - the
		  Hadassah Medical Organisation. By early 1967, enrolment had reached 12,500
		  between the campuses in Jerusalem and Rehovot.</p> 
		<p>By the conclusion of the Six-Day War of June 1967, Jerusalem had
		  become re-unified and Mount Scopus re-occupied, and the task of restoring and
		  enlarging the original campus began right away. After 1967, the campuses at
		  both Giv'at Ram and Mount Scopus were used by the University and Arab students
		  began to attend. Teaching was now offered in the humanities, science, social
		  sciences, law, agriculture, dental medicine, and medicine, and there were
		  schools of education, social work, pharmacy, home economics, and applied
		  science and technology and a graduate library school. Rothberg International
		  School was opened on Mount Scopus in 1971.</p> 
		<p>In 1981, construction work at Mount Scopus was completed and it again
		  became the main campus of the University. Today, with four functioning campuses
		  of Mount Scopus, Ein Kerem, Giv'at Ram, and Rehovot, and with almost 23,000
		  students the Hebrew University of Jerusalem is confident of further enhancement
		  and of becoming one of the leading universities of the world.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material consists of: a medal commemorating the opening of the
		  Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 1925; a medallion commemorating the 50th
		  anniversary, 1975; and, an account of the 60th anniversary celebrations, June
		  1985, being the programme of convocation (graduation ceremonial) and a
		  translation to English of the introduction to the convocation. There is also a
		  first-day cover (Israeli postal service) commemorating the anniversary. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Account of 60th anniversary celebrations, transferred from Principal's
		  Office, August 1985, Accession no. E85.48.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Micropaedia. Ready
		Reference. 15th edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., 1991. (2)
		Shalom - Welcome to the Hebrew University of Jersualem 
		<title>History</title>. Full-text [online]. Shalom - Welcome to the
		Hebrew University of Jersualem 
		<extref
		 href="http://www.huji.ac.il/unew/main.html">http://www.huji.ac.il/unew/main.html</extref>
		[Accessed 3 May 2002].</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Universi tah ha-'Ivrit
		  bi-Yerushalayim</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
