<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-210" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-210</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Joseph Booth (1851-1932)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised Graeme D Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Apr 26 09:48:11 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-210</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS 2501-2504</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Joseph Booth
		  (1851-1932)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1871-1990">[ca. 1871]-1990</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 boxes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Joseph Booth, English missionary to Africa, was born in 1851 in Derby,
		  England to a strongly religious family. In 1880 he emigrated to New Zealand
		  where he became a farmer then in 1887 moved to Australia where he established
		  himself as a successful small businessman. While in Australia Booth became a
		  member of the Baptist church and became convinced that it was his vocation to
		  be a missionary in Africa. In 1891, despite the death of his first wife whom he
		  had married in 1872, he left Australia with his two young children. Arriving in
		  Nyasaland (Malawi) in 1892 he established the Zambezi Industrial Mission (ZIM),
		  which he hoped would develop into a network of self-supporting communities in
		  which there was to be no colour bar. Booth's involvement with the ZIM was
		  followed by association with other industrial missions such as the Nyasa
		  Industrial Mission and the Baptist Industrial Mission. Booth organised or
		  supported several other schemes with similar aims including the African
		  Christian Union, the British Christian Union, and the British African Congress.
		  From the 1890s he was also a keen supporter of institutes to train leaders for
		  the church. He was variously affiliated to the Baptists, Seventh Day Baptists,
		  the Watch Tower movement and Seventh-day Adventists and became a vociferous
		  campaigner for the observation of the Sabbath. He aroused the hostility of
		  other missionaries and colonial authorities by advocating higher wages and more
		  political power for Africans. He spent time in Nyasaland, South Africa,
		  Basutholand (Lesotho), Britain and the United States trying to raise support
		  for his many pro-African schemes. The authorities increasingly frowned upon his
		  activities, suspecting him of fermenting African political descent. Booth
		  influenced several important African Christian figures including Elliot
		  Kamwana, Charles Domingo, John L. Dubbe and John Chilembwe. He took the latter
		  to American in 1897, a trip which coincided with the publication of Booth's 
		<title>Africa for the Africans</title> which emphasised the need for
		increased African self reliance and the role of Afro-Americans in attaining it.
		His activities led to him being accused of contributing to Chilembwe's uprising
		in Malawi and he and his second wife Annie were deported from Basutholand to
		England in 1915. Poor and unable to find work, partly due to his pacifist
		convictions, the Booths struggled to make a life for themselves. After World
		War 1 they went to South Africa where their daughter provided accommodation for
		them and where Booth's wife died in 1921. Booth and his third wife Lillian were
		forced to return to England because of ill health and possibly because Booth's
		renewed contacts with Africans were beginning to attract the attention of the
		authorities. He remained in England suffering bouts of illness until his death
		in 1932. Booth's fundamentalism and his apparently radical political and social
		views have led to varying assessments of his life and effect on African
		Christianity. He has been called by some unbalanced and dishonest and by others
		visionary and ahead of his time. Booth's own opinion of himself was a
		'pro-African politico-religious freelance type of self-assertive, and somewhat
		self dependent missionary advocate' (letter to daughter Mary 22 April
		1916).</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers include: correspondence of members of the Booth family
		  (1879-1933) mainly letters from Joseph Booth to his daughters Emily and Mary;
		  bible verses, and other personal items belonging to the Booths (c 1871-1924);
		  agreements, circulars and other material relating to Booth's life as a
		  missionary, supporter of the Sabbath and campaigner for African rights (c
		  1891-1923); correspondence between Shepperson and the Booth family and other
		  potential sources of information about Booth (1950-1982); copies of papers
		  relating to Booth held in various locations; publications by and about Booth
		  (1897-1983) including copies of Booth's 
		<title>Africa for the African</title> (1897) and Emily Booth Langworthy's
		
		<title>This Africa was Mine</title> (1952); and photographs of Booth and
		family (c 1873-1926).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The collection is in four boxes, the first three (MSS 2501-3) contain
		  the papers presented by George Shepperson and the fourth (MSS 2504) those from
		  Harry Langworthy. </p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>Professor George Shepperson first became interested in Joseph Booth
		  while researching the role of John Chilembwe in the uprising in Nyasaland in
		  1915. His research led him to contact the remaining members of Booth's family.
		  Booth himself did not leave any papers when he died: the Booths' itinerant life
		  did not allow them to keep many personal possessions. The few items kept by his
		  last wife, Lillian Booth, were destroyed on her instruction when she died. The
		  bulk of original material in the collection came from Emily Booth Langworthy,
		  Booth's daughter, both before and after her death. Other material was collected
		  or copied by Shepperson from other sources. Some of the material in the
		  collection was assembled by Professor Harry Langworthy including letters from
		  Mary Sales (Booth) inherited by her daughter Phoebe Whitehouse of Woking,
		  Surrey. </p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to the Library in 1990 by Professor Emeritus
		  George Shepperson, University of Edinburgh and by Professor Harry W.
		  Langworthy, Professor of History at Cleveland State University, Ohio and
		  great-grandson of Joseph Booth.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) information from the collection. (2) Anderson, G. H. (ed.). 
		<title>Bibliographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New
		York: Macmillan Reference USA, 1998. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University
		  Library, Special Collections and Archives. The collection is mentioned in the
		  Edinburgh University Library subject checklist (C3) 
		<title>Manuscripts on Africa</title>. There is also a handlist of the
		collection.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The papers of George Shepperson at the University of Edinburgh contain
		  further Booth papers. These include: copies of letters (1911-1912) to Booth
		  from Africans in Nyasaland about religion, in particular the Seventh Day
		  Baptist Church and the Sabbath; copies and extracts of letters (1906-1911) from
		  Booth about African churches and Indian Home Rule; notes made by Shepperson on
		  documents held by the Seventh Day Baptists including pamphlets, appeals,
		  letters and extracts from the 
		<title>African Sabbath Recorder</title>(1899-1900, 1910-1912); copy of a
		prospectus for the African Christian Union (1896); and Booth's 
		<title>Native Petition to the King</title> (1914). The Shepperson
		collection contains sections on Edwin Shaw and John Chilembwe which include
		material referring or relating to Booth and a range of photographs including
		some of mission activities. Details of related records in other repositories
		such as Rhodes House Library, the Public Record Office and the Seventh Day
		Baptist Historical Society can be found in the Booth collection.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p> 
		<title>'Africa for the African': The Life of Joseph Booth</title> Harry
		W. Langworthy (Blantyre, Malawi: CLAIM, 1996) was written using the material in
		the collection.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Africa</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Sabbatarians</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Booth</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Joseph</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1851-1932</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Missionary</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Baptist Industrial Mission</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Nyasa Industrial Mission</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Seventh Day Baptists</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Seventh Day Adventists</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Zambezi Industrial Mission</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Africa</emph> <emph altrender="x">Politics
		  and government</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Africa</emph> <emph altrender="x">Social
		  conditions</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
