<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-224" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-224</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Helen M. Taylor</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Apr 23 10:23:53 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-224</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2180/3</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Helen M.
		  Taylor</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1958-1963">1958-1963</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 file. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Taylor, Helen M.</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="nic">Other Niger-Kordofanian.</language>
		  </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Helen M. Taylor, Church of Scotland missionary and teacher, arrived in
		  Nyasaland in 1933, her first post being at a school at Loudon near Mzimba. She
		  later moved to Livingstonia and became the principal of Overtoun Institute, the
		  teacher training college there. When the Church of Scotland mission was
		  dissolved in 1960 and responsibility passed to the synod of the Church of
		  Livingstone Taylor became an elder in the Presbyterian Church of Central
		  Africa. During the troubles in Nyasaland prompted by the actions of the
		  nationalists under Hastings Banda opposed to Federation, she played and
		  important role in speaking up to safeguard the place of the church and mission
		  and the rights of normal Africans. Taylor was particularly concerned to bring
		  to the attention of the government the intimidation practised by the security
		  forces on Africans. While recognising the need for careful handling of the
		  relationship between the government and the church she opposed Federation and
		  called for the release of detained African leaders. Taylor published a pamphlet
		  on African (Malawi) religious songs and lived in Edinburgh when she
		  retired.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection covers the period of the controversy over the Central
		  African Federation and the protests of the nationalist movement under Hastings
		  Banda. The material includes papers, memoranda, telegrams and reports by Taylor
		  and others relating to the position of the church, mission and teacher training
		  college at Livingstonia and giving their opinions on the events in Nyasaland.
		  Statements and correspondence are directed to the government, the Devlin
		  Commission of Enquiry and to Hastings Banda.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is stored, in no specific order, in one file. </p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to Edinburgh University in 1983 by Miss
		  Taylor, through Professor Shepperson of the University of Edinburgh. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical note was compiled using information from the
		  collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University
		  Library, Special Collections Division. The collections is mentioned in the
		  Edinburgh University Library subject checklist (C3) 
		<title>Manuscripts on Africa</title>.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Edinburgh University Library holds some other collections relating to
		  the earlier history of the Livingstonia mission such as the papers of Robert
		  Laws. The National Library of Scotland has an extensive missionary collection
		  including material on Livingstonia. </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Africa</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Taylor</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Helen M</emph> <emph
		  altrender="epithet">Missionary</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Livingstonia Mission</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Malawi</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Overtoun Institute</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Malawi</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph> <emph altrender="x">Politics
		  and government</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
