<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-612" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-612</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Margaret Clark (b. 1920)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 15:43:13 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-612</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 32</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Margaret Clark (b.
		  1920)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1947-1964">1947-1964</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 box</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Clark, Margaret </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> <language langcode="efi">Efik, </language> and
		  <language langcode="ibo">Igbo.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Margaret Clark, Methodist Missionary Society missionary in Gambia and
		  Nigeria, was born in Hartlepool on 12 September 1920. She was brought up in a
		  Methodist family, her father being Circuit Secretary for Overseas Missions. She
		  trained as a teacher at St Hild's College, Durham where she was a member of the
		  Student Christian Movement. From an early age she had been interested in the
		  world church and this increased with her membership of the Girls' League
		  through which she met many missionaries and members of overseas churches. In
		  1945 she offered for missionary service and attended Kingsmead Missionary
		  Training College, Selly Oak for 6 months' training. In December of 1946 Clark
		  sailed to Gambia where she worked as a teacher in the Methodist Girl's High
		  School in Bathurst until early 1950. She was then transferred to Eastern
		  Nigeria arriving in the autumn of 1950. She first taught at the Methodist
		  Elementary Training Centre in Oron then from October 1953 at the Women's
		  Training College in Umuahia. She was, for a time, Literature Secretary of the
		  Girls' League and became increasingly involved in Christian literature
		  campaigns. From August 1959 she devoted herself full time to evangelical and
		  literature work, in particular to establishing and running the Mobile Bookshop
		  based at Umuahia and to organising audio-visual and literature conferences and
		  workshops. She was present at the inaugural conference of the Methodist Church
		  Nigeria in 1962. She resigned from the mission in the same year and arrived
		  back in England in 1963 to work as Juvenile Missionary Association Secretary a
		  post she held for three years. During this period she also did some writing for
		  the Edinburgh House Press and the National Christian Education Council. Clark
		  returned to Hartlepool in 1966 and moved to Northallerton in 1990.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: circular letters from Clark describing her
		  work in Gambia and Nigeria (1947-1963); material on the mobile bookshop
		  including lists of books sold and examples of Christian literature (1958-1964);
		  a Christian book list for Nigeria compiled by the Christian Council of Nigeria;
		  material on the Methodist Girls' League in Eastern Nigeria (1938-1963);
		  programmes and other items, including tape recordings, relating to the
		  formation of the Methodist Church Nigeria (1962); and papers and other material
		  on the Methodist mission and church in Nigeria in general (circa
		  1949-1962).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged as above, which is how it arrived at the
		  Centre. Several of the pamphlets and other printed articles donated by Clark
		  were put in the Centre library. These include examples of Christian literature,
		  and publications by the Methodist Missionary Society and church and by the
		  Nigerian Christian Council.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World by Miss Margaret Clark (on the suggestion of the
		  Reverend T. Kingsley Johnson) in 1993.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>May be a further deposit of tapes, photographs and slides.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself.</p>
		
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>A number of printed items that were part of the collection have been
		  placed in the CSCNWW library, see system of arrangement above; the archives of
		  the Methodist Missionary Society are held at the School of Oriental and African
		  Studies in London; there are several other collections relating to missions and
		  church in Nigeria in the Centre archives.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Christian literature</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Clark</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Margaret</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b.
		  1920</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Methodist Missionary Society</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Gambia</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nigeria</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
