<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-102"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-102</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Oriental
			 Manuscript Collection </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-102</unitid>
		
		<physloc>Oriental MSS 1-676 </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Oriental Manuscript Collection
		  </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1301-1899">14th century-19th century </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>circa 100
		  bundles palm leaves, 2 large long rolls, 1 box Oxyrynchus papyri, 4 boxes or
		  box files of copper plates, 7 boxes or box files, miscellaneous folders, circa
		  720 volumes and some in protective cases, (32 linear metres). </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Edinburgh University Library has over 650 manuscripts in oriental
		  languages originating from the countries of the Middle East, South Asia, and
		  South East Asia. Most of the collection consists of Arabic and Persian
		  manuscripts including two of the significant treasures of the Library, namely
		  the 
		<title>World history </title> of the Mongol vizier Rashid Al-Din, which
		illustrates parts of the life of the Prophet Muhammad, and the 
		<title>Chronology of ancient nations </title> of Al-Biruni, both of which
		were written in Arabic in Tabriz in Persian circa 1307 A.D. A number of Asian
		languages are included in the collection of course, and one African
		(Ethiopic/Amharic). The Asian languages are Armenian, Bengali, Burmese,
		Cambodian, Hindustani, Javanese, Malay, Mon, Pali, Panjabi, Prakrit, Sanskrit,
		Siamese, Sinhalese, Syriac, Tamil, Tibetan, Turkish and Urdu. South Asian and
		South East Asian religious texts are represented in the collection. The
		oriental collection includes material gathered by Lieutenant-Colonel John
		Baillie of Leys and presented to the Library in 1876 by his grandson, Mr. John
		B. Baillie, with the stipulation that a descriptive catalogue was prepared.
		This task was given to Mr. Mohammed Ashraful Hukk of Hyderabad who was then a
		student at the University. A greater part of the collection had been catalogued
		by 1906. Then, by 1914, Professor Hermann Ethe of Aberystwyth had added to the
		catalogue, and in the 1920s Dr. Edward Robertson carried out some more work.
		Other donors to the collection were R. M. B. Binning of the Indian Civil
		Service, George Bell M.D., and the Rev. John Dickson who had been a missionary
		in Astrakhan. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>A large part of the Oriental Manuscript Collection consists of Arabic
		  and Persian manuscripts. Arabic manuscripts include commentaries on the Koran;
		  traditions of the Prophet and Imam; prayers; law, general history and
		  biography; medicine, mathematics, philosophy and ethics; and, grammar,
		  rhetoric, poetry, prose, tales, dictionary, and controversy. Persian
		  manuscripts include theology, history, biography, and travel; mathematics and
		  astronomy; ethics, poetry, music, composition and proverbs, tales and romances;
		  grammar and dictionary; and, agriculture and war. The Arabic and Persian
		  manuscripts include the 
		<title>World history </title> of Rashid Al-Din, and the 
		<title>Chronology of ancient nations </title> of Al-Biruni, from the 14th
		century A.D. Hindustani manuscripts include history; poetry and tales; and,
		astrology. Turkish manuscripts consist of material acquired in Astrakhan and
		includes several early Ottoman texts, divans of Neva'i and items of dialectical
		interest. Included in the Oriental Collection are around 100 bundles or parcels
		of Buddhist works on palm leaves in Burmese, Pali, Sanskrit, Siamese, Tamil,
		and Tibetan. There are also Sanskrit charters on copper plates, and Oxyrynchus
		Papyri. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.5./marc 541"> 
		<p>Material gathered by Lieutenant-Colonel John Baillie of Leys was
		  presented to the Library in 1876 by his grandson, Mr. John B. Baillie. The
		  Dickson material - acquired in Astrakhan, 1819-25 - had first come into the
		  possession of the Rev. Thomas B. Dodds, of Lochee, Dundee, who had married one
		  Isabella G. Dickson in 1845. In 1889, the manuscripts were presented to the New
		  College Library by their son, J. Dickson Dodds, of Dundee. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Muhammad</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Prophet</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">d 632</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Hukk</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Mohammed
		  Ashraful</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b 1880</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Ethe</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Hermann</emph>
		  <emph altrender="dates">1844-1917</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Manuscripts, African</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Manuscripts, Arabic</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Manuscripts, Hindi</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Manuscripts, Oriental</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Manuscripts, Persian</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Manuscripts, Turkish</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<geogname source="aacr2" encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Tabriz (Iran)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>Handlist H8 which is 
		<title>A descriptive catalogue of the Arabic and Persian manuscripts in
		  Edinburgh University Library </title>, Mohammed Ashraful Hukk, et al.
		(Hertford: Printed for the University of Edinburgh by Stephen Austin &amp;amp;
		Sons, Ltd., 1925); and, Handlist H8.1 which is 
		<title>The illustrations to the world history of Rashid al-Din </title>,
		David Talbot Rice and edited by Basil Gray (Edinburgh University Press, 1976);
		Handlist H8.2 which includes 
		<title>A handlist of the Arabic, Persian and Hindustani MSS of New
		  College, Edinburgh </title> R.B. Serjeant (London: Luzac and Co., 1942);
		Handlist H9.1-12 </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
