<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-303" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-303</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Material relating to Professor James Syme
			 (1799-1870)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Nov 08 09:57:04 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-303</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.7.57-61; Df.3.41; E2006.11</physloc><unittitle>Material
		  relating to Professor James Syme (1799-1870)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1828-1869">1828-1860</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>7 volumes.</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Syme, James; Beveridge, J. Storer</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The surgeon James Syme was born in Edinburgh on 7 November 1799. He
		  was educated at the Royal High School in the city, and then studied at
		  Edinburgh University from 1815 first as a pupil of the anatomist Dr. John
		  Barclay (1758-1826). Although Syme never actually attended a course of surgery
		  lectures, Robert Liston (1794-1847) gave him charge of his dissecting rooms as
		  a demonstrator in 1818, and in 1820 he became superintendent of the Edinburgh
		  Fever Hospital. In 1822 he went to Paris, and on the retirement of Liston in
		  1823 Syme began delivering a regular course of anatomy lectures. In 1824 he
		  visited medical schools in Germany, and in the following year he added a course
		  on surgery to those already being given on surgery. In 1829, he started a
		  private surgical hospital at Minto House and then in 1833 he was appointed to
		  the Chair of Clinical Surgery at Edinburgh University. In 1838, Syme became
		  Surgeon in Ordinary to the Queen in Scotland. In 1848, he accepted the Chair of
		  Clinical Surgery at University College, London, but after some contractual
		  misunderstandings he returned to Edinburgh the same year and resumed the
		  Professorship there again. He was then elected President of the
		  Medico-Chirurgical Society of Edinburgh. Syme's publications include: 
		<title>On the excision of diseased joints</title> (1831), 
		<title>The principles of surgery</title> (1832), 
		<title>On diseases of the rectum</title> (1838), and, 
		<title>Observations in clinical surgery</title> (1861). University
		Professor James Syme died at Millbank, near Edinburgh, on 26 June 1870, and was
		buried at St. John's Episcopal Church in the city's West End.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material includes: Syme's lectures on clinical surgery, taken by
		  J. S. Beveridge, circa 1856-1860, at Dc.57-61; a volume of manuscript notes of
		  lectures on surgery delivered by Syme, 1828-1830, at E2006.11; and, a volume
		  containing Syme's diplomas, and press-cuttings relating to him, at Df.3.41.</p>
		
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>J. Storer Beveridge lectures, received 1910. Lectures on surgery
		  acquired April 2006, Accession no: E2006.11.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.19. Stow-Tytler.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various other references to Syme related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): recommendation of his lectures
		  by Joseph Lister, September 1854, at Gen. 1730 Lister; testimonial dated August
		  1852, at Dc.4.98/6, (2); mention in a letter, November 1837, at Gen./ 1429/8;
		  his opinion on the use of ether, 1847, at Dk.7.46/55; and, his views on
		  operating in a case of ovarian tumour, 1863, at Dc.4.101-103. In addition, the
		  UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts
		  Commission, notes: dissertation, Royal Medical Society, 1821, see HMC file
		  1970; and lecture notes, 1853, Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh, Ref.
		  Syme NRA 16015 Coll of Physicians.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ether</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgery</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgeons</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Syme</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1799-1870</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Surgeon </emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Lister</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Joseph</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1827-1912</emph> <emph altrender="title">Baron Lister</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">surgeon</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Beveridge</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">J. Storer</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
