<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-703" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-703</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Photographs taken in Portuguese Nyasaland
			 (Northern Mozambique) 1920-1921</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Oct 21 10:29:32 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-703</unitid> 
		<physloc>E90.61</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Photographs taken in
		  Portuguese Nyasaland (Northern Mozambique) 1920-1921</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1920-1922">1920-1922</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 folder with circa 24 photographs, 2 printed matter.
		  </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Walls, Robert Reid</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The distinguished research scientist Robert Reid Walls was born and
		  educated in Edinburgh, though his family came from Orkney. His father was a
		  scientific-instrument maker in Edinburgh, responsible for the first x-ray
		  apparatus in the city. After graduating from Edinburgh University from which he
		  was awarded the degree of MA in 1914 - and also a B.Sc. - the younger Walls
		  entered the field of electrical and mechanical instruments design. He became
		  involved in industry and management and was co-opted as a member of the British
		  Institute of Management set up by Sir Stafford Cripps. Walls travelled abroad
		  on scientific research, especially in Brazil (looking for rare minerals) and in
		  East Africa (searching for oil) spending some time in Portuguese Nyasaland
		  which today constitutes part of northern Mozambique. He became a Fellow of the
		  Royal Scottish Geographical Society for his work. Robert Reid Walls died in
		  Bournemouth on 12 September 1975. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of circa 24 mounted photographs, on paper,
		  with descriptions, of parts of Portuguese Nyasaland, now northern Mozambique.
		  They show: a caravan leaving Port Amelia (Pemba) on the Indian Ocean ; the
		  residence of the Portuguese magistrate; geology of the area; a well; Queen
		  Cona, chief of the Medo Makuas; the interior bush country; coconut plantation;
		  the Union Castle liner 'Gaika' off Port Amelia; damage after a cyclone; a
		  Banian dhow in Pemba Bay; and, views of Pemba Bay and Port Amelia. There is
		  also a copy of 
		<title>The geology of Portuguese Nyasaland</title> and 
		<title>Portuguese Nyasaland</title> by Robert R. Walls, the former
		extracted from the 
		<title>Geological magazine</title> Vol. 59., No. 695, May 1922, and the
		latter from 
		<title>The Scottish geographical magazine</title> Vol. 38., July
		1922.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Material transferred from the Centre of African Studies, Edinburgh
		  University, 27 June 1960, Accession no. E90.61.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 'Obituary'. 
		<title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 27. 1975-1976.
		pp.326-327. Edinburgh: University of Edinburgh Graduates' Association,
		1976.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Walls</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert Reid</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d.
		  1975</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Research Scientist</emph> </persname>    
		 <!--
<geogname>
<emph altrender = "a">Mozambique</emph>
</geogname>
-->
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Pemba (Mozambique)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
