<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-607" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-607</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Church of Scotland Slide and Visual Collection
			 </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 10:57:43 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-607</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 47</physloc><unittitle>Church of Scotland Slide and
		  Visual Collection </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1999">19th century-20th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 38 boxes and 16 lantern slide boxes</extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<origination>Foreign Mission Committee the Church of Scotland
		  </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Foreign Mission Committee (later Overseas Council then Board of
		  World Mission and Unity) of the Church of Scotland was responsible for the
		  Church's mission work around the world. In 1824 the Church's General Assembly
		  resolved to send its first missionary to India and appointed Alexander Duff who
		  arrived in Bombay in 1830. Other missionaries were sent to Calcutta (1830),
		  Poona (1834), and Madras (1837). The Disruption of 1843 which saw the
		  separation of the Free Church of Scotland from the main Church caused the loss
		  of most missionaries and the missionary spirit, as the work continued but under
		  the umbrella of the Free Church. The United Presbyterian Church, formed in
		  1847, inherited some existing missionaries in the West Indies and in Calabar,
		  Nigeria and by the 1870s was active in Jamaica, India, South Africa, Japan and
		  Manchuria, China. The Church of Scotland resumed its missionary work in 1857 in
		  the Punjab and in the 1870s established its first stations in Nyasaland
		  (Malawi, 1876) and China (1878). In 1900 the Free Church joined with the United
		  Presbyterians to form the United Free Church but remained separate from the
		  Church of Scotland. Co-operation between the two Churches was secured in some
		  areas, in India, for example, joint colleges were formed in Madras and
		  Calcutta. However it was not until 1929 that the Free Church and the Church of
		  Scotland joined as the Church of Scotland.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: (1) Lantern slides and glass plate
		  negatives of: China (Charles Somerville collection, Dugald Christie); Africa
		  (Malawi, Zambia, Kenya, Nigeria); India; and Jamaica. Most sets come with
		  indexes and commentaries and date from late 19th century to early-mid twentieth
		  century. (2) Slides (35 mm) of: Africa (Malawi, Zambia, Kenya, Ghana, Nigeria,
		  South Africa, Sudan and Egypt); Far East (including Taiwan and Hong Kong); Holy
		  Land; Middle East; India (including Western India, Assam, Rajasthan, South
		  India, Nagpur and Seoni, North India and Bengal, and Sentalia); Pakistan;
		  Bangladesh; Eastern Himalayas and Nepal; Wets Indies and Jamaica; and home
		  organisation and general material. Some slides have commentaries or detailed
		  indexes and all slides date from circa 1950s-1980s. (3) Display photographs of
		  India; Pakistan; Bangladesh; Africa; and Church and mission in general. Many
		  are captioned, they date from circa 1960s-1980s.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material was deposited on several occasions. Some of the later
		  deposits were in better order than the earlier ones. All material relating to a
		  particular country has now been boxed together.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was presented to the Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World by the Church of Scotland in the 1990s.
		  Many of the slides duplicate ones sent to the National Library of Scotland.</p>
		
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative history was compiled using the National Library of
		  Scotland 
		<title>Catalogue of Manuscripts</title>. Vol.6. Edinburgh: Her Majesty's
		Stationery Office, 1984.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the foreign missions of the Church of Scotland are
		  held by the National Library of Scotland, some of the material in that
		  collection duplicates this material. The Centre has several other collections
		  relating to the Church of Scotland's mission work.</p> 
		<p>Also within the ArchivesHub the Edinburgh University Library
		  collection of 
		<title>Records of the Church of Scotland General Assembly</title> may be
		of interest.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">China</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Manchuria (China)</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Malawi</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Zambia</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Kenya</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nigeria</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">India</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Jamaica</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Ghana</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">South Africa</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Taiwan</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Hong Kong (China)</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Israel</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Yemen</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Saudi Arabia</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Pakistan</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Bangladesh</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nepal</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
