<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-164" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-164</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Photographs of War-Devasted Caen, June-July
			 1944</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Nov 29 12:12:32 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-164</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dk.2.1</physloc><unittitle>Photographs of War-Devasted Caen,
		  June-July 1944</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1944">June - July 1944</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 70 photographs and postcards. </extent>
		  </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="fre">French.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Caen is a university city and commercial centre situated on the River
		  Orne in the Calvados departement of northern France, in Normandy. It is a busy
		  inland port, the river having been canalised (by Napoleon I) to the sea. The
		  importance of Caen dates to the 11th century when it was a favourite residence
		  of William I of England (William the Conqueror). An architectural gem, the city
		  was largely demolished by Allied bombing and shelling during the Normandy
		  Campaign of World War II.</p> 
		<p>As an important port and road and rail centre, Caen had been vital to
		  Allied success after D-Day. The plan had been for the British forces to seize
		  the city in the first day or two after the landings and then to take the battle
		  out into open countryside and towards the Seine. When this did not happen, it
		  was necessary to keep the German forces committed to the city and to prevent
		  them from switching attention to the all out defence of the port of Cherbourg
		  which was essential to the Allies and which the American forces were to
		  take.</p> 
		<p>During the battle for Caen, the 14th century Church of St. Peter lost
		  its famous spire, while the castle of William the Conqueror and the 17th
		  century town hall were almost destroyed. However, three outstanding examples of
		  11th century Norman architecture were preserved, namely the Abbaye aux Hommes
		  founded by William the Conqueror, who was buried there, and the Abbaye aux
		  Dames founded by Queen Matilda, and the Church of St. Nicholas. The university
		  which was founded in 1432 was destroyed, but has been rebuilt.</p> 
		<p>An imposing memorial to the Battle of Normandy (1944) has been erected
		  in the old rebuilt castle as a peace monument and museum.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection of photographs and postcards shows the war devastation
		  of Caen, June-July, 1944. The devastation is shown from different elevations,
		  and feature not only the most prominent buildings but also the extent of the
		  damage beyond the central area of the city.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Presented by Professor John Orr, 1946.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Seltzer, Leon E. (ed.). 
		<title>The Columbia Lippincott gazetteer of the world</title>.
		Morningside Heights, N.Y: Columbia University Press, 1962. (2) Various
		published sources on the Allied campaign in Normandy, 1944.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show many references to Professor John Orr related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): papers of Professor John Orr
		  (1885-1966) at Gen. 868-872 and Gen. 1842-1844. Orr held the Chair of French
		  Language and Romance Linguistics. He was Chairman of the Edinburgh-Caen
		  Fellowship.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">World War, 1939-1945</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Caen, Battle of, 1944</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Orr</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1885-1966</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of French</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Caen (France)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
