<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-256" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-256</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Committee on Voluntary
			 Organisations</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Jul 23 10:47:57 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-256</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2034-2035</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Committee on
		  Voluntary Organisations</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1974-1978">1974-1978</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Wolfenden, John Frederick; Croly, Henry Gray; and
		  others</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Committee on Voluntary Organisations was set up and jointly
		  financed by the Joseph Rowntree Memorial Trust and the Carnegie United Kingdom
		  Trust to review the role and functions of voluntary organisations in the UK
		  over the remainder of the 20th century. The Committee was appointed on 1
		  October 1974 and was composed of members from all over the UK but with none
		  'carrying a banner, political, geographical or professional' (according to the
		  published report, p.9). Members of the Committee, serving as individuals rather
		  than as representatives of any bodies or organisations, set about gathering
		  their evidence from both questionnaire and discussion. In response, over three
		  hundred submissions of written evidence were received, and over ninety
		  interviews were held. The records of the Committee were made available to
		  researchers by the Trustees of both Trusts, and copies were deposited at both
		  the British Library of Political and Economic Science (BLPES) in London and at
		  Edinburgh University Library. The Committee on Voluntary Organisations ceased
		  to exist after the report - 
		<title>The future of voluntary organisations</title> - was published in
		1978. Sir John Wolfenden (1906-1985), the Chair of the Committee, had also
		participated in the Departmental Committee on Homosexual Offences and
		Prostitution, 1954-1957. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection includes notes for researchers and indexes. Included in
		  the notes are the guidelines for giving evidence and answering the
		  questionnaire which were sent out to organisations. There is an alphabetical
		  list and numerical list (WE 1 - WE 267) of those organisations providing
		  written evidence, a subject list in addition to the alphabetical and numerical
		  lists, note covering the oral evidence, and alphabetical list and numerical
		  list (OE 1 - OE 93) of those organisations providing oral evidence.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Received from Secretary to the Committee on Voluntary Organisations,
		  April 1978. Accession no. E78.11.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>In a note to researchers on conditions of access, signed by H. G.
		  Croly (Secretary to the Wolfenden Committee on Voluntary Organisations) in
		  January 1978, it was a condition of access that anyone wishing to publish an
		  article based on evidence, or quoting from the evidence, should first obtain
		  the Trustees' approval. Their addresses were given in 1978 as: Joseph Rowntree
		  Memorial Trust, Beverley House, Shipton Road, York YO3 6RB (This organisation
		  was renamed the Joseph Rowntree Foundation in 1990, at - Joseph Rowntree
		  Foundation, The Homestead, 40 Water End, York, North Yorkshire YO30 6WP; and,
		  Carnegie United Kingdom Trust, Comely Park House, 80 New Row, Dunfermline, Fife
		  KY12 7EJ (address confirmed in 2001). At Edinburgh University Library the
		  material is generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but
		  please contact repository for details in advance and bear in mind the Trustees'
		  conditions.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative/biographical history was compiled using material
		  contained within the records, and 
		<title>The future of voluntary organisations. Report of the Wolfenden
		  Committee</title>. London: Croom Helm, 1978.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p>The report of the Wolfenden Committee was published in the form of: 
		<title>The future of voluntary organisations. Report of the Wolfenden
		  Committee</title>. London: Croom Helm, 1978.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Social service</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Volunteer workers in social
		  service</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Wolfenden</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John Frederick</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1906-1985</emph> <emph altrender="title">Baron
		  Wolfenden</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Life Peer, Committee Chairman, and
		  Educational Expert</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Croly</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Henry Gray</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b.
		  1910</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Brigadier</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Joseph Rowntree Memorial Trust</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Joseph Rowntree Foundation</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Carnegie United Kingdom Trust</emph>
		  </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
