<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>

  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-449" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-449</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Material relating to Julius Kambarage Nyerere
			 (1922-1999)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Sep 24 11:27:57 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-449</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen.784/3; Gen.173 Nyerere; MS218</physloc><unittitle>Material
		  relating to Julius Kambarage Nyerere (1922-1999)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1962-1988">1962-1988</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 7 envelopes and folder and envelopes containing
		  proofs, letters, printed matter; 1 film</extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Julius Kambarage Nyerere was born in Butiama in the former Tanganyika
		  (now Tanzania) in March 1922. He was the son of the chief of the Zanaki tribe.
		  He was educated at Tabora Secondary School and then studied at Makarere
		  University College in Kampala, Uganda. Before studying at Edinburgh University
		  - becoming the first Tanganyikan to study in a UK university - he taught in
		  several Roman Catholic schools in Tanganyika. He graduated in 1952 with the
		  degree of M.A. in history and economics, and then returned home to teach.
		  Nyerere's political career began immediately in a country held by Britain as a
		  UN Trusteeship (former League of Nations mandate). He joined the Tanganyika
		  African Association, Dar es Salaam, and became its President in 1953 before
		  transforming the organisation into the Tanganyika African National Union (TANU)
		  in 1954. In 1955 and 1956 he went to the UN in New York to petition the
		  Trusteeship Council and then the Fourth Committee of the UN General Assembly,
		  or at least its Committee on trusts and non-self-governing territories, asking
		  for a target date for the independence of Tanganyika. Although this was
		  rejected by Britain, Nyerere had shown himself to be the most prominent
		  nationalist spokesman and he was nominated as a member of the Tanganyika
		  Legislative Council. He resigned in 1957 because of the slowness of
		  negotiations towards independence, but in the elections held in 1958-1959 TANU
		  won a large number of seats in the Legislative Council. In subsequent elections
		  in 1960, TANU won practically all of the seats in a new Legislative Assembly,
		  and self-government was achieved in September 1960. He became Chief Minister,
		  and then in 1961 Prime Minister, and Tanganyika became independent in December
		  1961. The country became a republic the following year with Nyerere as its
		  President, and from 1964 he was the President of the United Republic of
		  Tanzania (Tanganyika and Zanzibar). He was re-elected in 1965 and served for
		  three additional five-year terms before resigning as President in 1985. He had
		  also been one of the founders of the Organisation for African Unity (OAU) in
		  1963 and was its Chair in 1984. In addition to his political career, he
		  translated Shakespeare's 
		<title>The Merchant of Venice</title> and 
		<title>Julius Caesar</title> into Swahili. Other publications include 
		<title>Freedom and unity</title> (1966), 
		<title>Freedom and socialism</title> (1969), and 
		<title>Freedom and development</title> (1973). The former President of
		Tanzania, Julius Kambarage Nyerere died in London on 14 October 1999.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: galley proofs of Nyerere's Swahili
		  translation of Shakespeare's 
		<title>Julius Caesar</title>; an annotated copy of the translation in
		preparation for the second edition, typescript of galley proofs, and related
		correspondence; annotated copy of the published Swahili translation, 
		<title>Julius Caezar</title> printed in Nairobi; letters to Edinburgh
		University relating to a coming conference on constitutions, and the speech
		given by Nyerere on the theme; proof of 
		<title>The Merchant of Venice</title>; a film of an interview with a
		student, 1961; and, an application form for life membership of the Friends of
		Edinburgh University Library filled up by Nyerere.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>Accession nos: E87.87; E88.103; E88.109; E93.100; E98.43. Consolidated
		  to MS 3218 November 2005. E93.100 not found at November 2005.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Proofs of Shakespeare translation, acquired October 1964, Accession
		  no. E64.67. Letter of 1986, acquired September 1987, Accession no. E87.87.
		  Letter of 1988, acquired July 1988, Accession no. E88.103. Conference address,
		  acquired September 1988, Accession no. E88.109. Film, 1961, acquired October
		  1993, Accession no. E93.100. Copy of translation, acquired 1998, Accession no.
		  E98.43.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>At the time of writing this description the filmed interviewed had not
		  been found.</p> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>Who's who 1995</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1995. (2) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Micropaedia. Ready
		Reference. 15th edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., 1991.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <bibliography> 
		<p>Within Special Collections, Edinburgh University Library, at shelfmark
		  SD 5129, there is a copy of the revised edition of 
		<title>Juliasi Kaizari</title> published in Dar es Salaam by OUP, 1969,
		and at shelfmark SD 5128, 
		<title>Mabepari wa Venisi</title> published in Dar es Salaam by OUP,
		1969.</p> 
	 </bibliography>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Nyerere</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Julius Kambarage</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1922-1999</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Former President
		  of Tanzania</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Shakespeare</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1564-1616</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Dramatist</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
