<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-432" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-432</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Correspondence relating to General Robert Melville
			 (1723-1809)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Sep 5 11:59:37 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date>Converted from EAD 1.0
			 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-432</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.4.98/1, ff.226-227; Gen. 863/2; Gen. 1875,
		  no.76</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence relating to General Robert Melville
		  (1723-1809)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1753-1772">1753-1772</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 manuscript letters or documents</extent> </physdesc>
		
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="fre">French.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Robert Melville was born at Monimail, Fife, on 12 October 1723. He was
		  educated locally at Leven and then he studied at Glasgow University and at
		  Edinburgh University. In 1744 he became an Ensign with the 25th Foot Regiment
		  (King's Own Scottish Borderers) and saw service in Flanders. French colours
		  captured by his regiment in 1747 were carried to the Duke of Cumberland by
		  Melville. He was then given his own company and after recruiting in Scotland he
		  became aide-de-camp to Lord Panmure, who commanded British forces in Scotland.
		  He was promoted to Major and served in Antigua, and saw action at Guadeloupe in
		  1759. He was appointed Lieutenant-Governor then, in 1760, Governor of
		  Guadeloupe. His brief was extended in 1763 to Governor of Grenada, the
		  Grenadines, Dominca, St. Vincent, and Tobago. When a part of these territories
		  was ceded to France after capture during the American War of Independence,
		  Melville travelled to France to negotiate on behalf of British settlers. He
		  also visited Switzerland and Italy and other parts of the continent. Earlier,
		  in 1759, he invented the carronade - a piece of light ordinance very
		  destructive against timber. The carronade was first produced for the Navy in
		  1779 - made in Carron, Falkirk - and continued to be in use until the
		  mid-nineteenth century. Apart from an interest in military matters, and in
		  particular an interest in sites of military significance, he became involved in
		  botany and botanical research. Indeed, Melville founded the Botanic Garden on
		  St. Vincent. General Robert Melville was blind in the latter years of his life.
		  At his death he was the oldest general in the British army. He died on 29
		  August 1809.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material consists of a letter to Professor R. Whytt, 1753 or 1754,
		  copies of letters to Monsieur de Valmont, Guadeloupe, 1760, and a letter to C.
		  Griffith, 1772. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 13.
		Masquerier-Myles. London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Robert Melville related
		  material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letter
		  to the Rt. Hon. Earl of Buchan, 7 December 1786, at La.II.588; and, letters to
		  G. J. Thorkelin, Dr. Cuming, and Dr. Brounlie, 1789-1799, at
		  La.III.379/564-586. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA),
		  updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: journals,
		  correspondence and papers, 1760-1823, National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD126
		  NRA 32024 Balfour-Melville; correspondence, 1786-1800, National Library of
		  Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MS 9846; letters from Captain Robert
		  Bruce, 1770-1771, London University Library, Ref. MS 882; correspondence with
		  1st Earl of Liverpool, 1763-1782, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref.
		  Add MSS 38201-210, 38304-309; and, letters to the Society of Arts relating to
		  botanical gardens in St Vincent, 1797-1802, Royal Society of Arts, Ref. RSA NRA
		  35934 RSA.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Melville</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1723-1809</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">General and
		  Antiquary</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">18th century</emph>
		  </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
