<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-349" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-349</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Professor John Gregory (1724-1773)</titleproper>
		  
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Apr 11 11:59:56 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-349</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.6.125-126; Dc.7.116; Gen. 1730 Gregory; Gen. 2106D;
		  E97.44</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor John Gregory
		  (1724-1773)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1769-1773">1769-1773</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 manuscript volumes, 1 letter, 2 batches letters
		  (fire-damaged and boxed). </extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Gregory, John; Dick, Alexander</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John Gregory was born in Aberdeen on 3 June 1724. He was the youngest
		  son of James Gregory (d. 1731), Professor of Medicine at King's College,
		  Aberdeen, and the grandson of the mathematician James Gregory (1638-1675). His
		  early education was under care of his brother, James Gregory, who had succeeded
		  his father at King's, and his cousin Thomas Reid, the metaphysician. In 1741 he
		  began medical studies at Edinburgh University and on completion of these he
		  studied at the University of Leiden, 1745-46. In 1746 he was appointed
		  Professor of Philosophy at Aberdeen University where he lectured on
		  mathematics, moral philosophy and natural philosophy. In 1749 Gregory resigned
		  the Chair and devoted himself to medical practice, moving to London in 1754.
		  While there he was elected a Fellow of the Royal Society and his success in
		  London seemed assured. However, on the death of his brother, he returned to
		  Aberdeen, succeeding to the Chair there, and lectured on and practiced medicine
		  until 1764 when he moved to Edinburgh. In 1766 Gregory was appointed Professor
		  of Medicine at Edinburgh University on the resignation of Professor John
		  Rutherford (1695-1779). Also in 1766 he was appointed as Physician to the King
		  in Scotland. His publications include 
		<title>A comparative view of the state and faculties of man with those of
		  the animal world</title> (1766) and 
		<title>Observations on the duties and offices of a physician, and on the
		  method of prosecuting enquiries on philosophy</title> (1770). Professor John
		Gregory died on 9 February 1773. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The John Gregory material consists of: a volume on the practice of
		  medicine delivered at Edinburgh, 1769-1770; lectures on the practice of
		  medicine, 1772-1773; lectures on the institutions of medicine, 1773; lectures
		  on physic, 1773; and, a letter to Nancy Ord, 1771.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Letter, purchased 1974, Accession no. E74.22.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance. Some material fire-damaged and very
		  fragile (access would probably be denied until conservation carried out).</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 8. Glover-Harriott.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show references to John Gregory related material in
		  the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): accounts of fees
		  received, personal and family expenses 1769-1773, with additional accounts to
		  1789, at La.III.793; and, a letter mentioning Gregory's appointment as H.M.
		  Physician in Scotland, 1766, at La.II.647/98. There is also an account of John
		  Gregory in Benjamin Rush's journal, 1766-1768, at Mic.M.28, ff.71-73.</p> 
		<p>There are other references to material relating to the talented but
		  complicated Gregory family (check the Indexes for more details). The Gregorys
		  were descended from the Rev. John Gregory, Minister of Drumoak. The inventor
		  David Gregory (1627-1720) and mathematician James Gregory (1638-1675), the
		  Elder, were his sons. In turn, David's son was the astronomer and Professor of
		  Mathematics David Gregory (1661-1708), and James' son was James Gregory (d.
		  1731), Professor of Medicine at King's College, Aberdeen. The son of the King's
		  College Gregory was John Gregory (1724-1773), Professor of Medicine at
		  Edinburgh University, and in turn his son was James Gregory (1753-1821)
		  Professor of Medicine, Edinburgh University.</p> 
		<p>See the HE Archives Hub for descriptions of the Edinburgh University
		  Library collections 'Papers of David Gregory (1661-1708)' and 'Lectures and
		  Cases of Professor James Gregory (1753-1821)' and 'Papers of Professor James
		  Gregory (1638-1675), the Elder'.</p> 
		<p>In addition, for John Gregory (1724-1773), the UK National Register of
		  Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes these
		  other collections: lecture notes, 1766-1771, Royal College of Physicians, Ref.
		  Gregory NRA 16015 Coll of Physicians; lecture notes, 1767-1768, University of
		  Kansas, Clendening History of Medicine Library; lecture notes, 1770, University
		  of British Columbia, Woodward Biomedical Library; lecture notes, McGill
		  University, Osler Library; lecture notes, National Library of Scotland,
		  Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 3537-41, and letters to Sir William Forbes, Ref
		  Acc 4796 NRA 29136 Stuart-Forbes; lectures on the Institutes of Medicine, in
		  the hand of Charles Cameron, circa 1770, Wellcome Library for the History and
		  Understanding of Medicine, Ref. MSS 6915-6916; letters to Sir Archibald Grant,
		  1759, National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD345 NRA 10160 Grant, see
		  NRA(S)0099; and, letters (30) to Elizabeth Montagu, Huntington Library.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Medicine</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Gregory</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1724-1773</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Medicine</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dick</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
