<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-586" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-586</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Frank Longley (fl. 1950)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Nov 28 09:40:33 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-586</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 34</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Frank Longley (fl.
		  1950)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1896-1989">1896-1989</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>10 boxes and circa 32 films</extent> <physfacet>The
		  negative photographs are of very poor quality. A reel tape player is required
		  to play the sound recordings. The films require a projector but there may be
		  copies available on video.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Longley, Frank; Longley, Jessie </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="yor">Yoruba.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Frank Hollis Longley, Methodist Missionary Society missionary in
		  western and northern Nigeria, was born in Arlesey, Bedfordshire. The family
		  moved to Royston where his father was a butcher and, after leaving school in
		  1919, Longley worked in the family shop. From an early age he had wanted to be
		  a missionary and he secured a place to train for the ministry at Richmond
		  College and later went to Headingly, Leeds. He first went to Nigeria in 1931
		  for two short spells then, in 1935, married Jessie Nellie Bannister, a trained
		  teacher from Royston. A few weeks after their wedding the Longleys left for
		  Nigeria where they were based in Oyo, western Nigeria. Apart from 2 years in
		  Ibadan they spent the next 22 years at Oyo. Conditions were difficult and they
		  were very much pioneers, but the Longleys worked hard to gain the respect of,
		  and work with, the people. Frank Longley became proficient in Yoruba and, as
		  well as evangelising, did his best to help the local communities. Jessie
		  Longley also took an active part in the work, helping out in the hostels,
		  schools and dispensaries that they opened in the area. The Longleys had no
		  children of their own but cared for and supported several local children with
		  whom they kept in touch and whose careers they followed even after they had
		  left Nigeria. In 1957 Frank Longley was appointed superintendent of the Igboora
		  and Badagry circuits and moved, with Jessie, to Igboora. In 1960 he was awarded
		  an MBE, but by this time Jessie's health was causing some concern and the
		  couple returned to England in 1963. Longley worked on the circuit in
		  Wells-next-the-Sea, Norfolk but in 1965 they were asked to return to Nigeria.
		  They were based at Oturkpo, Northern Nigeria then from 1967 at Bussa, the site
		  of the Niger River Dam and had to contend with many difficulties caused by the
		  Civil War. In 1969 they finally returned to England and Longley was appointed
		  minister at Ollerton, Mansfield. He retired from active work in 1972 and they
		  returned to Royston, to the house where Jessie had been born. The Longleys
		  returned to Nigeria for a visit in 1975. Jessie died on 7 September 1985
		  shortly after their golden wedding anniversary.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of: personal items relating to the Longleys
		  and their work including press cuttings (1915-1987); circular letters from the
		  Longleys in Nigeria (1931-1945); family and personal correspondence including
		  detailed letters from Jessie Longley to her parents (1928-1987); notebooks and
		  pocket diaries (1928-1989); addresses and talks on Nigeria (1937-1971);
		  administrative material and correspondence relating to the mission work
		  (1928-1974); letters from the children in Nigeria who the Longleys cared for
		  (1945-1988); letters from Nigerian and missionary colleagues received after
		  Jessie Longley's death (1985-1989); notes, extracts from letters and
		  biographical material collected by Longley intended for use in his memoirs
		  (various dates, compiled 1980s); press cuttings, pamphlets and articles on
		  Nigeria, the church and mission (1921-1979); photographs, slides and pictures
		  (c 1896-1980s); sound recordings including a deputation address (1960s); and c
		  32 short films made by the Longleys of Nigeria and their furloughs (c
		  1930s-1981).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material has been arranged in files as above. Most of the material
		  was not ordered when deposited but some files existed which had been created by
		  Longley including Memoirs, Children, Colleagues and Funny Letters. The
		  photograph albums had been created by Longley during the 1980s, the photographs
		  have now been removed from the albums to prevent deterioration.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>Some of the material was collected by the Longleys, other items were
		  collected by their families and then passed to Frank Longley probably around
		  the time of his wife's death.</p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The collection was deposited in the Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World by Frank Longley's nephew and niece in
		  the 1980s.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself.</p>
		
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the Methodist Missionary Society are held at the
		  School of Oriental and African Studies in London. The Centre for the Study of
		  Christianity in the Non-Western World holds other collections relating to
		  Nigeria.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Longley</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Frank</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b.1907</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Longley</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Jessie </emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1902-1985</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Methodist Missionary Society</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nigeria</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
