<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-86"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-86</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of
			 Professor Fraser Mitchell (1900-1988) </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-86</unitid>
		
		<physloc>Gen. 1948; Gen. 2271-2290 </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Professor Fraser Mitchell
		  (1900-1988) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1919-1984">circa 1919-1984 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>18 boxes, 3
		  album (2 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>William Fraser Mitchell was born in Dundee in 1900. He was educated at
		  Dundee High School, leaving in 1918. In January 1919 he matriculated at
		  Edinburgh University, studying English. He graduated with First Class Honours
		  in 1922 and then went on to Exeter College, Oxford, researching English
		  rhetorical preaching in the seventeenth century. He was awarded the degree of
		  B.Litt., and was later successful in publishing his work 
		<title>English pulpit oratory from Andrewes to Tillotson: a study of its
		  literary aspects </title> (1932). After Oxford, Mitchell studied Education at
		Moray House and Edinburgh University, and became personal assistant to
		Professor Sir Godfrey Thomson (1925-1951). After a temporary post as Lecturer
		in English at Armstrong College, Newcastle, he was appointed Lecturer in
		Education at the University of Reading in 1928 where he remained until 1944. A
		secondment to Farnborough Grammar School as an English master was followed by
		his appointment as Professor of Education in the Selly Oak Colleges,
		Birmingham, where he instructed teachers of religious knowledge, missionary
		teachers, overseas student teachers, Froebel students, and youth leaders. With
		the closure of the Department of Education at Selly Oak in 1951, Mitchell took
		a post as Assistant Lecturer in English at Huddersfield Technical College, but
		in 1955 he returned to the Midlands to take part in the establishment of the
		Malayan Teachers' College in Wolverhampton. There, three hundred students flown
		over from Malaya were trained for secondary school teaching. He then returned
		to Huddersfield Technical College for a time, was a Lecturer at the University
		of Sheffield, 1957-1958, and until his retirement in 1965 was an Assistant
		English Master at Colne Valley High School. In addition to his study of
		comparative education, religious education and comparative religion, Mitchell
		was interested in the life of James Burnett, Lord Monboddo (1714-1799). When he
		retired to Dundee, he took up his research again and involved himself in church
		work. He published collections of poetry including 
		<title>Off parade and other verses </title> (1919), 
		<title>Cobweb and mustard seed </title> (1928), and 
		<title>A slim volume </title> (1960). William Fraser Mitchell died in
		July 1988. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>The papers of Professor Mitchell at Gen. 2271-2290 include poems,
		  plays and an unfinished novel 
		<title>Moth and peaseblossom </title> which was to follow 
		<title>Cobweb and mustard seed </title> published in 1928; copies of 
		<title>A slim volume </title>; notes and manuscripts; general letters
		from between the 1920s and the 1980s; papers on educational research; letters
		to him on education; papers on contemporary poets and artists; and, material on
		religion and tolerance, and pulpit teaching. There are card indexes for
		Mitchell's research on Monboddo; letters and papers on his Monboddo research;
		newspaper and other cuttings on Monboddo; and, genealogical material relating
		to Monboddo. There is an album of Christmas cards, Victorian and Edwardian
		ephemera, postcard albums, and material on the history of Dundee. There are
		personal papers too, and Mitchell's academic hoods. At Gen. 1948 there are
		poems and an essay offered for prizes at Oxford, a typescript on paganism, a
		fragment of a novel, a typescript for a play, a verse drama, and printed
		material. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <odd encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.1"> 
		<note encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.6.1./marc 500"> 
		  <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
			 (1) 
		  <title>University of Edinburgh Journal </title>, Vol.34. No.2.
		  Dec.1989, pp.116-119, Edinburgh: University of Edinburgh Graduates'
		  Association. </p> 
		</note> 
	 </odd> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Mitchell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William
		  Fraser</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1900-1988</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">Monboddo</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James
		  Burnett</emph> <emph altrender="title">Lord</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1714-1799</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Christmas cards</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Education</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Preaching</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Religious education</emph> </subject> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Teachers</emph> <emph altrender="x">Training of</emph> </subject>
		
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<geogname source="aacr2" encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph
		  altrender="a">Dundee (Scotland)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>An important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held
		  at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to
		  the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> 
		<p>The Index to Manuscripts shows a reference to letters to W. F.
		  Mitchell covering 1947-1970 at Gen. 1971/3 </p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
