<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-745" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-745</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of James Kirkwood (c. 1650-1708)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jan 7 09:35:03 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-745</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS KIR</physloc><unittitle>Papers of James Kirkwood (c.
		  1650-1708)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1670-1709">1670-1709</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>5 items in form of registers, discourses, volumes; 1
		  book letters; miscellaneous material including lists, letters, and notes; circa
		  12 printed and manuscript tracts, talks, and pamphlets. </extent>
		  <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Kirkwood, James</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Kirkwood was born in Dunbar, East Lothian, in around 1650. He
		  graduated from Edinburgh University in 1670, and became chaplain to John
		  Campbell, Earl of Caithness, 1st Earl of Breadalbane. In 1679 he became
		  Minister of Minto. Due to the religious turbulence of the period he left Minto
		  in 1681 and went to England, to Astwick, Bedfordshire. In 1690 he was
		  responsible for the circulation of two hundred copies of the Bible in Irish
		  throughout the Highlands, and in 1699 published 
		<title>An overture for founding and maintaining bibliothecks in every
		  paroch throughout the kingdom</title> Kirkwood was an advocate of libraries in
		every parish throughout the country. James Kirkwood died in 1708.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: material including a register,
		  discourse, and sermons; 
		<title>A new family book; or, The true interest of families</title>; a
		book of letters and receipts relating to the printing and distribution of Irish
		Old Testaments and Bibles, catechisms and psalm-books, 1687-1699, including
		letters to Colin Campbell of Carquhin, Astwick, and accounts of disbursements,
		and a list of Highland parishes; material about Highland schools and libraries;
		letters about charity schools and about dissemination of Bibles in the
		Highlands; letter of Rev. Thomas Salmon containing proposals for instituting a
		Society for the Reformation of Manners in England; material relating to
		Highland libraries; letters about Irish Bibles, Highland libraries, and charity
		schools, including letters to Gilbert Burnet, Bishop Salisbury, and to George
		Meldrum; letters on charity schools and SPCK matters; a list of Catholics in
		the Highlands; a copy of 
		<title>An account of a design to erect libraries in the Highlands of
		  Scotland: as also in Orkney and Schetland</title>; copies of material on
		parochial libraries in 
		<title>Library chronicle</title>, Vol.5. 1888, and in 
		<title>The library</title> No. 1. January 1889, and other material on the
		same subject; talks, newspaper cuttings; photocopy of the negative photostat
		made from a copy of an original of 
		<title>An overture for founding and maintaining of bibliothecks</title>
		at Wigan Public Library; and, photocopy of the negative photostat of 
		<title>A copy of a letter anent a project for erecting a library in every
		  presbytry ... in the Highlands</title> made from the copy at Wigan Public
		Library.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 11.
		Kennett-Lluelyn. London: Smith, Elder, and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show reference to Kirkwood related material (check
		  the Indexes for more details): notes on Kirkwood, c. 1950-1956, by L. W. Sharp,
		  Librarian, Edinburgh University, with Photostat copies of manuscripts and
		  printed books by Kirkwood in the National Library of Scotland and other
		  libraries, at Dc.1.29. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA),
		  updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: 1687-1708:
		  correspondence, 1687-1708, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division,
		  Ref. MS 821</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Libraries</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Religious education</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Kirkwood</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph altrender="dates">?
		  1650-1708</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Advocate of Parish Libraries</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge
		  (Great Britain)</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
