<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-604" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-604</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Alan Cox (b. 1926)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity
				in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D
				Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Dec 11 10:34:37 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-604</unitid> 
		<physloc>CSCNWW 29</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Alan Cox (b.
		  1926)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1955-1993">1955-1993</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in
		  the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank
		  Street)</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 file</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Cox, Alan </origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Alan Cox, Methodist minister, was born in 1926. He worked as a
		  draughtsman until 1944 when he was called up to serve in Germany and Palestine.
		  In 1949 he spent a year at Cliff College and then trained at Hartley Victoria
		  College in Manchester. He had ministries in various locations becoming
		  Superintendent Minister of the Hemel Hempstead circuit before his retirement in
		  1992. Cox had a lifelong interest in missions and in work with children. While
		  at Cliff College he had met Alan Roberts who, with his wife Doris, became a
		  missionary in Nigeria. Cox was one of their most effective supporters and was
		  particularly successful in interesting others in the Ovim (later Uzuakoli)
		  Motherless Babies Home which they started in Eastern Nigeria in 1958. Cox
		  continued to take an interest in the Home even after the Roberts were moved to
		  Port Harcourt in 1959. The work continued, closely connected to the Leprosy
		  Settlement at Uzuakoli, supervised by Bella Teite and then Nona Bell. Shortly
		  before his retirement Cox was granted a sabbatical to travel to Nigeria and to
		  research and write about the history of the home. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Material includes correspondence about the collection (1993); prayer
		  letters of Alan and Doris Roberts founders of the Home (1955-1960) and of Nona
		  Bell, a sister at the Home (1961-1964); letters and accounts relating to money
		  raised by Cox (1958-1960); notes on the history of the home by Alfred (Fred)
		  Hasted (Welfare Officer), Bella Teite and Enid Johnson (various dates); letters
		  to Hasted from Nigeria referring to the Home (1970-1982); and articles and
		  reports relating to Uzuakoli, the Home and Leprosy Settlement, with some maps
		  (1960-90).</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material has been arranged as described above.</p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>The material was collected by Alan Cox while writing 
		<title>Uzuakoli Miracle</title> the story of the Motherless Babies Home
		in Eastern Nigeria. </p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The material was presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity
		  in the Non-Western World by the Reverend Alan Cox in 1993.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>None expected.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) the collection itself (2) Cox, Alan. 
		<title>Uzuakoli Miracle</title>. Alan Cox, 1991. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>A handlist is available.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The archives of the Methodist Missionary Society are held at the
		  School of Oriental and African Studies, London University; Cox's 
		<title>Uzuakoli Miracle</title> is in the Centre for the Study of
		Christianity in the Non-Western World library. The Centre library has other
		collections of archives and material relating to Nigeria.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Cox</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alan</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1926</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Motherless Babies Home</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Nigeria</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nigeria</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
