<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-357" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-357</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of William Henderson (fl. 1675) and his son Robert
			 Henderson (fl. 1715)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Mar 26 11:25:33 UTC 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-357</unitid> 
		<physloc>Da.1.31; Dc.1.4/1; Dc.6.51, pp. 300, 340, 393, 407, 413;
		  Dc.7.83</physloc><unittitle>Papers of William Henderson (fl. 1675) and his son
		  Robert Henderson (fl. 1715)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1601-1730">17th century - 1730</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 volumes, 1 part-volume, 1 separate manuscript
		  document. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="lat">Latin,
		  </language> and <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>William Henderson was the eleventh Librarian to Edinburgh University
		  and held the office between September 1667 and November 1684. He succeeded
		  William Somerville who had been Keeper of the Library between 1666 and 1667.
		  The same year that Henderson was chosen as Librarian, or Bibliothecar, it was
		  also decided that 'no books should be lent out of the Library without a
		  receipt'. Henderson also acted as Secretary to the University. In 1674, his
		  salary was six hundred merks (in 1707, one merk was thirteen shillings and four
		  pence Scots or one hundred and sixty pennies Scots). In 1684 Henderson's son,
		  Robert Henderson, was admitted as Librarian, but at first 'probably conjunctly'
		  with his father.</p> 
		<p>Robert Henderson had graduated with the A.M. degree (Master of Arts)
		  on 28 November 1683 and doubtless continued to study and carry out research.
		  Indeed, in 1690, after the Professor of Humanity, John Drummond, stepped down,
		  the younger Henderson was one of the candidates to succeed him. He would hold
		  the post of Librarian until 25 March 1747, having remained in office for
		  sixty-two years, longer than any of his predecessors and longer than any
		  Professor had held a teaching post at that time. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The papers of the Hendersons, father and son, consist of: the
		  commonplace book of William Henderson with additional entries by Robert
		  Henderson, content such as 
		<title>Praxis linguae latinae</title> 1688, and notes of plays read;
		William's donation book, being a record of books donated to Edinburgh
		University Library from 1667 and a list of earlier benefactors (it also
		includes later entries); Latin verses; and, commission of Robert Henderson to
		Gawin Hamilton, bookseller, to receive from the Company of Stationers in London
		books due to Edinburgh University under the Copyright Act. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Dalzel, Andrew 
		<title>History of the University of Edinburgh</title>. Vol. 2. History.
		Edinburgh: Edmonston and Douglas, 1862.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Henderson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl.
		  1675</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Librarian</emph> </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Henderson</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Robert </emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl.
		  1715</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Librarian</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
