<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-299" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-299</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Lectures of Professor John Hughes Bennett
			 (1812-1875)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Oct 24 09:32:02 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2001</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-299</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2007/1-4</physloc><unittitle>Lectures of Professor John
		  Hughes Bennett (1812-1875)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1848-1874">1848-1874</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 boxes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>John Hughes Bennett was born in London on 31 August 1812. He was
		  educated in Exeter but also spent some time in France. In 1829, he commenced an
		  apprenticeship with a surgeon in Maidstone then, in 1833, entered Edinburgh
		  University where he was an enthusiastic student of anatomy and physiology.
		  Bennett graduated with an M.D. in 1837, then went to study in Paris. There he
		  founded the Parisian Medical Society and became its first President. Study in
		  Germany followed, before a return to Edinburgh in 1841. In November 1841, he
		  began lecturing on histology at Edinburgh University, and in 1842 he competed
		  for the Chair of General Pathology, but failed. He was however elected a Fellow
		  of the Royal Society of Edinburgh and of the Royal College of Physicians, and
		  he also became a physician to the Royal Dispensary and pathologist to the Royal
		  Infirmary. In 1848, Bennett was elected to the Chair of the Institutes of
		  Medicine at Edinburgh University, a post which he held until he retired in
		  1874. Bennett's publications include: 
		<title>On the anatomy and physiology of the otic ganglion</title> (1836)
		which was written while he was a student, 
		<title>Treatise on cod-liver oil as a therapeutic agent in certain forms
		  of gout, rheumatism, and scrofula</title> (1841), and 
		<title>Hypertrophy of the spleen and liver </title> (1845) which was the
		first recorded case of leucocythaemia. He was also editor of the 
		<title>London and Edinburgh Monthly Journal of Medical Science</title>.
		Professor John Hughes Bennett died in Norwich on 25 September 1875 and was
		buried in the Dean Cemetery, Edinburgh, on 30 September.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of Bennett's lectures on physiology and
		  pathology etc between 1848 and 1874.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. London: Smith, Elder and
		Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Bennett related material
		  (check the Indexes for more details): a letter of his to Sir Archibald Geikie
		  (1835-1924), 1860, at Gen. 524/3; and, a testimonial, 1854, holograph, at
		  Dc.4.98/6 (14).</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physicians</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physiologists</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Bennett</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John Hughes</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1812-1875</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physician and
		  Physiologist</emph> </persname> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Geikie</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Archibald</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1835-1924</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Geologist </emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
