<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-335" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-335</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Manuscripts relating to Nova
			 Scotia</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Feb 19 11:01:55 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Ti me) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Oct 4 11:24:53 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-335</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.15; Gen.2027</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Manuscripts
		  relating to Nova Scotia</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1783-1813">1783-1813</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 manuscript volume, 49 letters bound in one volume.
		  </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Nova Scotia is one of Canada's Maritime Provinces - the others being
		  New Brunswick and Prince Edward Island. It comprises the Nova Scotia peninsula,
		  Cape Breton Island, and some adjacent islands. It has a population of around
		  899,900 (in 1991) and Halifax is the provincial capital. The name of the
		  province was applied by Scottish settlers.</p> 
		<p>Nova Scotia was the site of the first permanent North American
		  settlement north of Spanish Florida. It was established at Port Royal (now
		  Annapolis Royal) in 1605 by the French, although the territory was also
		  inhabited by the semi-nomadic Algonquian Indian tribes of the Abnaki and the
		  Micmac. Colonial rivalries between France and Britain throughout the 17th and
		  18th centuries led to instabilities in Nova Scotia and it passed backwards and
		  forwards between the two until the Peace of Utrecht 1713 when it was retained
		  by Britain. Cape Breton Island was kept by France. The opportunity of acquiring
		  free land attracted many new settlers from Britain, especially from Scotland,
		  and from New England to the south of the territory. During the American
		  Revolution and afterwards, many United Empire Loyalists from New England came
		  to the province.</p> 
		<p>In 1769, Prince Edward Island split away from Nova Scotia, and New
		  Brunswick followed in 1784. In 1820, Cape Breton Island was reunited with Nova
		  Scotia. It was one of the four British colonies federated into the Dominion of
		  Canada in 1867 - Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, Quebec, and Ontario.</p> 
		<p>In today's Nova Scotia, only around one eighth of the population can
		  claim descent from the French settlers. The bulk of the population is descended
		  from British or New England settlers, though there is a very small percentage
		  descended from Irish and German settlers. Other minorities include small
		  numbers of Dutch, Italians, and Hungarians, who arrived after 1945. English is
		  spoken by some 90 per cent of the population. Around 8 per cent are bilingual
		  with French and English.</p> 
		<p>Nova Scotia has been something of a pioneer in Canadian history with
		  the country's first printing press in 1751, the first newspaper in 1752 (the 
		<title>Halifax Gazette</title>), the first university in 1788-1789
		(King's College, Windsor), and the first British colony to achieve cabinet
		government responsible to the people through elected representatives.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: a descriptive sketch of Nova Scotia,
		  dated 1783 on the spine of the item; and, letters relating to Nova Scotia
		  including some from the politician Henry Dundas (1742-1811), 1st Viscount
		  Melville, on the defence of the province in the event of war with America.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Micropaedia. Ready
		Reference. 15th edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1991. (2) Nova
		Scotia. In 
		<title>The Columbia Gazetteer of the World</title>. Full-text [online,
		text-only version]. 
		<extref href="http://www.columbiagazetteer.org/">The Columbia Gazetteer
		  of the World</extref> [Accessed 21 January 2002]. </p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show other references to Nova Scotia (check the
		  Indexes for more details) in the Laing Collection: statement of the relative
		  members in the province belonging to the Church of England and to the
		  Dissenters, late 18th century, La.II.678; and, letter on behalf of the baronets
		  of Nova Scotia to Lord George Germaine claiming acknowledgement of the right to
		  their estates in the province, 1777, La.II.498.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dundas</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Henry</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1742-1811</emph> <emph altrender="title">1st Viscount
		  Melville</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Statesman</emph> </persname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nova Scotia</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
