<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-765" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-765</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of Lady Glenorchy's Chapel </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Feb 6 11:15:09 UTC 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-765</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS BOX 30.4.1-8</physloc><unittitle>Records of Lady Glenorchy's
		  Chapel </unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1787-1913">1787-1913</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place,
		  Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>circa 70 sheets or pages, 1 volume. </extent>
		  <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Lady Glenorchy's Chapel</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Willielma Campbell, Viscountess Glenorchy, was born in 1741. In 1761
		  she married John, Lord Viscount Glenorchy, the eldest son of the 3rd Earl of
		  Breadalbane. That year too her elder sister married William, 17th Earl of
		  Sutherland. Around 1764, Lady Glenorchy became deeply influenced by religion
		  and she built a church in Edinburgh which was named after her - Lady
		  Glenorchy's Chapel. Other chapels were built by her in Carlisle, Matlock, and
		  in Strathfillan on the Breadalbane Estate. On her death she left large sums to
		  the Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge (SPCK), mainly for the
		  maintenance of schools. Willielma Campbell, Viscountess Glenorchy, died in
		  1786.</p> 
		<p>Lady Glenorchy's Chapel, or Church, had been built next to Trinity
		  College in 1772. Both the Church and the College were cleared away in 1848 to
		  make way for the then North British Railway marshalling yard (now part of the
		  area taken up by the city's Waverley Station). For the Free Kirk congregation
		  descended from Lady Glenorchy's, a Free Church had been built in Greenside
		  Place in 1844. In 1875, Glenorchy Place, Greenside, was named marking that
		  connection. Trinity College kirk was re-erected in Chalmer's Close, High
		  Street, in 1872.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection is composed of: a state of debts, legacies and claim on
		  Lady Glenorchy's effects, 1787; letter of Horatius Bonar to Thomas Burns, 1913;
		  two copies of the order of service, Lady Glenorchy's New Church and Halls,
		  laying of foundation stone by the Lord High Commissioner, 1909; sermon on the
		  prevailing love of pleasure, from Isaiah 47.08, 18th century; minutes of a
		  meeting of the session of Lady Glenorchy's Chapel held in the schoolhouse,
		  1810; draft of extracts from Chapters 6-11 of 
		<title>The life of Willielma, Viscountess Glenorchy</title> by Thomas
		Snell Jones; and, notes on Alexander and James Bonar, Elders, and memo as to
		Lady Glenorchy's remains.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Harris, Stuart. 
		<title>The place names of Edinburgh their origins and history</title>.
		Edinburgh: Gordon Wright Publishing, 1996. (2) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney
		(eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.3. Brown-Chaloner.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Local lists. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes Lady Glenorchy related material: letters to Anna
		  Bruce of Arnot 1762-76, National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD242 NRA 34969
		  Shepherd.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Campbell</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Willielma</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d
		  1786</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Lady Glenorchy</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Lady Glenorchy's Chapel (Edinburgh,
		  Scotland)</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
