<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-270" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-270</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Edinburgh International Club</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Fri Aug 17 09:47:52 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-270</unitid> 
		<physloc>MSS 2269-2270</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Edinburgh
		  International Club</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1914-1986">1914-1986</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Edinburgh International Club arose out of a chance meeting in 1912
		  between Dr. Armistead, a senior student of medicine at Edinburgh University,
		  his wife, and Miss A. H. Begbie an Edinburgh citizen. An invitation to Miss
		  Begbie's home followed, and Dr. Armistead had explained to her the value of
		  their chance meeting and new friendship and how other visitors from overseas
		  would also value the experience of meeting local people in their own
		  environments. Fortnightly 'at homes' for the Armisteads and overseas
		  acquaintances resulted from this, hosted by Miss Begbie and her cousin Miss
		  Kemp. Out of these sprang the idea for a club and on Saturday 1 November 1913
		  the Edinburgh International Club was formally launched. The object of the Club
		  was to promote friendly relations and social intercourse between members of
		  various nationalities resident in Edinburgh, and the earliest meetings of the
		  body included representatives from fourteen different countries. Activities and
		  events over the years included walks, folk dancing, Polish dancing, Kenyan
		  entertainment, Ukrainian concerts, Sri Lankan evenings, and Norwegian evenings.
		  On the 50th anniversary of the Club in November 1963, the Principal of
		  Edinburgh University hosted an event for its membership at Edinburgh University
		  Library, and in 1979, the 65th anniversary year, a party was held at the
		  Triangle Coffee House, Randolph Place. By 1986 however, the Club had ceased to
		  function because of lack of support from the overseas student body towards whom
		  it had originally directed itself to assist. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The Records of the Edinburgh International Club include 8 minute books
		  for the period 1914-1986 at MS 2269, and at MS 2270 a file containing
		  historical information about the Club, cuttings, membership cards, programmes
		  of events, typescript and manuscript documents, copies of 
		<title>Concordia</title> the official newsletter of the Club, and a file
		of correspondence.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The Records of the Edinburgh International Club were received in
		  February 1988, Accession no. E88.31.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The administrative history was compiled using material contained
		  within the collection.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh International Club</emph>
		  <emph altrender="y">1914 - 1986</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
