<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-502" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-502</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Material relating to Sir James Dalrymple, Viscount Stair
			 (1619-1695)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Feb 10 15:11:27 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-502</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.10; Dc.4.24; Dc.6.20; Gen.
		  1427</physloc><unittitle>Material relating to Sir James Dalrymple, Viscount
		  Stair (1619-1695)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1601-1699">17th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>4 volumes</extent> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Dalrymple, James</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>James Dalrymple was born in May 1619 at Drummurchie, in Carrick. He
		  was the son of the Laird of Stair. Dalrymple was educated at Mauchline in
		  Ayrshire, and then he studied at Glasgow University, graduating in 1637. He
		  then intended to study law at Edinburgh University but the civil war
		  interrupted this. He served as a troop commander and remained in the army until
		  1641. He became a Regent at Glasgow University, teaching logic, morals,
		  politics and mathematics. He remained there until 1647 when he went to
		  Edinburgh, admitted to the Scottish Bar (becoming an Advocate). For a period he
		  acted as a Commissioner for the Administration of Justice under Cromwell and
		  negotiated with King Charles II in the Netherlands. In 1670, he sat on the
		  negotiations to work out a treaty of union between Scotland and England but
		  these broke down through the insistence of the Scottish side on maintaining the
		  same numbers of representatives in a union parliament as they had in their own.
		  In 1671, Dalrymple became Lord President of the Court of Session but in 1681 he
		  left for the Netherlands in order to avoid signing the Test Oath, another
		  chapter in the on-going persecution of the Covenanters. It was at this time he
		  wrote his 
		<title>Institutions of the law of Scotland</title> which illustrated
		legal links between Scotland and Europe and preserved Scots law during a time
		of great upheaval. He returned in 1688 as a supporter of the Glorious
		Revolution and was re-appointed to his post. He became Viscount Stair in 1690.
		James Dalrymple, Viscount Stair, died in Edinburgh on 25 November 1695. He was
		buried in St. Giles, Edinburgh's High Kirk. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material includes: the 'forme of process used before the Lords of
		  Councell', 1666; 
		<title>Institutio juris</title>; and, copies of 
		<title>Institutions of the law of Scotland</title> and also 
		<title>Forme off process before the lords</title> with a bookplate of
		John, Earl of Loudoun.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994. (2) Stephen,Leslie. and Lee, Sidney. (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 5. Craik-Drake.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to material related to 1st
		  Viscount Stair in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details):
		  letters to the Earl of Lauderdale, 1663-1678, at La.III.354/1; transcript of 
		<title>Institutions of the law of Scotland</title>, circa 1687, at
		La.III.416, a copy entitled 
		<title>Systema juris</title>, 1677, at La.III.417, and another copy
		entitled 
		<title>The laws and customs of Scotland in civil matters</title>, 1680,
		at La.III.418; a warrant of King Charles II appointing Sir James Dalrymple
		President of the Session, 1671, at La.II.521; and, in verse, a 
		<title>Remonstrant to president Dalrymple Stairs 1673</title> beginning
		'Remonstrant guid mess James', at La.III.383/2.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspendence, Lord Melville,
		  1691-1692, National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD26; correspondence with Duke
		  of Lauderdale, circa 1671-1690, Buckminster Park, NRA 23003 Tollemache; letters
		  to Duke of Lauderdale and Charles II, 1667-1680, British Library, Manuscript
		  Collections, Ref. Add MSS 23126-38, 23242-47 passim.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Law</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Scotland</emph> </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Dalrymple</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1619-1695</emph> <emph altrender="title">1st Viscount
		  Stair</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Statesman</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
