<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-857" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-857</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of John Tulloch (1823-1886)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Sep 13 11:08:13 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-857</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2041/181-183</physloc><unittitle>Letters of John Tulloch
		  (1823-1886)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1862-1882">1862-1882</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Tulloch, John</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Scottish theologian John Tulloch was born on 1 June 1823 at Dron,
		  near Bridge of Earn, Perthshire. He was educated in Perth and at Madras
		  College, St. Andrews, and he studied at St. Andrews University and at Edinburgh
		  University. He was licensed as a preacher by Perth presbytery in 1844 and in
		  1845 was ordained as a Minister at St. Paul's, Dundee. In 1847 Tulloch went to
		  Germany, visiting Hamburg, Berlin, and Wittenberg, and the year following he
		  began literary work writing for periodicals. In 1849 he became Minister at
		  Kettins, Angus, where he stayed until 1854. During this time he continued
		  writing too, and in 1854 he was appointed to the post of Principal and
		  Primarius Professor of Theology at St. Mary's College, St. Andrews University.
		  In 1858 Tulloch went to Paris and established a church there for Scottish
		  residents of the city, and later in the year he visited Germany again. In 1859
		  he delivered a series of lectures on Luther and other leaders of the
		  Reformation at the Edinburgh Philosophical Institution, and the same year he
		  was appointed as one of Her Majesty's chaplains in Scotland. By the time of his
		  appointment in 1875 as Chief Clerk of the General Assembly, Tulloch had become
		  the most prominent churchman in Scotland, and in 1878 he was Moderator of the
		  General Assembly. In 1882 he became Dean of the Chapel Royal and Dean of the
		  Thistle. John Tulloch died in Torquay on 13 February 1886.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material consists of: letter from Tulloch to Dempster noting 'a
		  meeting of the Education Board' and how he 'must be in Edinburgh if possible';
		  letter talking of his engagements and how busy he is; and, letter from Tulloch
		  to Hedman.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 19. Stow-Tytler.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show references to Tulloch related material (check
		  the Indexes for more details): letters to D. Laing inviting him to receive an
		  honorary degree from St. Andrews University, 1862, at La.IV.17; and, letter of
		  Tulloch (?John) D.D. to Sir C. J. Pearson, 1884, at Gen. 756, no.282.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Tulloch
		  related material.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Tulloch</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1823-1886</emph>
		  <emph altrender="epithet">Principal of St Andrew's University</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
