<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-814" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-814</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of Alexander George Fraser, 16th Baron Saltoun
			 (1785-1853), and material of other Barons Saltoun</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Tue Jun 8 09:38:55 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-814</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1968/35-40; Gen. 2041/17-19</physloc><unittitle>Letters of
		  Alexander George Fraser, 16th Baron Saltoun (1785-1853), and material of other
		  Barons Saltoun</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1821-1853">1821-1853</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>9 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Fraser, Alexander George</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The soldier and accomplished musician Alexander George Fraser was born
		  in London on 12 (or 22) April 1785 and became the 16th Baron Saltoun of
		  Abernethy in 1793 when still a child. He entered the army, the 35th Regiment,
		  in 1802, as an ensign, and was promoted to Lieutenant in 1803 and Captain in
		  1804. In 1806, with the 3rd Battalion of the 1st Grenadier Guards, Fraser
		  served in Sicily, and then in 1808 at Corunna. In 1809 he took part in the
		  Walcheren expedition, and in 1811 he was in Cadiz. With the 1st Battalion from
		  1812 through to 1814 he participated in the Peninsular Campaigns and was
		  present at the Battle of Vittoria, the Battle of the Pyrenees, the Battle of
		  Nivelle, and the Battle of Nive, and he was on the operations before Bayonne.
		  He returned to England in 1814, but was again at the Battle of Quatre Bras, and
		  at Waterloo. He was honoured with the C.B., and became a Knight of the Order of
		  Maria Theresa of Austria, and of St. George of Russia, and then in 1818 he
		  received the K.C.B. (Knight Commander of the Order of the Bath) and in 1821
		  G.C.H. (Knight Grand Cross of the Hanoverian Order). In 1825 he was promoted to
		  Colonel, in 1827 Lieutenant-Colonel, and in 1837 Major-General. In 1841 he
		  served in China during the Opium War, and in 1849 became Lieutenant-General.
		  Fraser was made a Knight of the Thistle in 1852. Lieutenant-General Alexander
		  George Fraser, 16th Baron Saltoun, died near Rothes in Scotland on 18 August
		  1853.</p> 
		<p>The 1st Lord Saltoun was the 15th century Laurence Abernethy who was
		  created Lord Saltoun of Abernethy on 28 June 1445.</p> 
		<p>After the death in 1668 of Alexander, 9th Lord Saltoun, and after the
		  death of his sister in 1669, the title was claimed by Alexander Fraser, 10th
		  Lord of Philorth, who became 10th Lord Saltoun. He died on 11 August 1693.</p> 
		<p>William Fraser (1654-1715), 11th Lord Saltoun, married a daughter of
		  Dr. James Sharp, Archbishop of St. Andrews, Primate of Scotland. He was
		  succeeded by his eldest son, Alexander</p> 
		<p>Alexander Fraser (1684-1748), 12th Lord Saltoun, married a daughter of
		  George, 1st Earl of Aberdeen, High Chancellor of Scotland.</p> 
		<p>Alexander Fraser, 15th Lord Saltoun, was born on 27 June 1758. He died
		  on 13 September 1793.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of short manuscript letters: some to John
		  Hughes, on subjects as varied as the Theatrical Fund and the Drury Lane Fund to
		  dining with the Prince of Wales; letter to Messrs. Spottiswoode and Robertson,
		  1821, informing 'that he will be present at the Election of Peers in
		  Edinburgh'; letter from Saltoun at Duns, to Messrs. Spottiswoode and Robertson,
		  1839, concerning the Harbour Bill; and, letter to 'My dear Oliphant', 1853,
		  apologising for being out when he called etc.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 7.
		Finch-Gloucester. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908. (2) Burke, Sir Bernard.
		and Burke Ashworth P. 
		<title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage,
		  the Privy Council, and knightage</title>. 87th edition. London: Burke's Peerage
		Ltd., 1929.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Barony of Saltoun related
		  material (check the Indexes for more details): letter of Alexander Fraser, 12th
		  Lord Saltoun, to 'Jeames Coak, Clark of Bamf' about the liberation from jail of
		  Peter Matthews according to the late Act of Parliament. Philorth, January 1708,
		  at Dk.7.47/39; note of Alexander Fraser, 15th Lord Saltoun, to James Cumming,
		  1782, at La.II.82; letters (6) from 15th Lord Saltoun to G. J. Thorkelin,
		  1788-1789 and undated, at La.III.379/717-722; letter of 15th Lord Saltoun to
		  the Earl of Buchan about a contested election, 1788, at La.II.588; letter of
		  15th Lord Saltoun to W. Lumsdaine. Philorth, May 1792, at La.II.509; and,
		  letter of Lady M. Saltoun (probably Margery, wife of Alexander Fraser, 15th
		  Lord Saltoun) to her sister the Hon. Mrs. Campbell. Blackheath, June 1807, at
		  La.II.511.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Saltoun
		  related material: of Fraser, Alexander Arthur (1886-1979), 19th Baron Saltoun,
		  letters to the Manchester Guardian, 1946-1951, at Manchester University, John
		  Rylands Library, Ref. Guardian archives, NRA 18162 Guardian; and various
		  locations for Fraser, Alexander George (1785-1853) 16th Baron Saltoun.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Fraser</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Alexander George</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1785-1853</emph> <emph altrender="title">16th Baron
		  Saltoun</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">General</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
