<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-834" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-834</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Letters of Thomas Edward (1814-1886)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Wed Jul 21 10:51:31 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-834</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 2040/7-8</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Thomas Edward
		  (1814-1886)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1879-1880">1879-1880</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a
		  fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Edward, Thomas</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>The Banff naturalist, Thomas Edward, was born in Gosport, Hants., on
		  25 December 1814. His father was a hand-loom linen weaver but was also a
		  Private in the Fife Militia and temporarily stationed in England (emergency of
		  the Napoleonic Wars). The early years of the younger Edward were spent in Fife
		  and Aberdeen and his interest in the natural world began as a child. For a time
		  he worked in a tobacco factory in Aberdeen before becoming an apprentice
		  shoemaker, and then going into the army. At the age of twenty he settled in
		  Banff, north-east Scotland, where he pursued his interest in natural history,
		  alongside his shoemaking. He began a collection of animals and by 1845 had
		  nearly two thousand specimens of plants and animals. Debts led to the sale of
		  his collection but he started another one only to lose it too in order to
		  support his family. A third collection had been accumulated by 1858 and he had
		  also taken to marine biology. Indeed he discovered many (at that time) new
		  species from the Moray Firth. In 1866 Edward was elected an Associate of the
		  Linnean Society of London. A biography was written of him in 1876 and he became
		  more widely known, and he received a pension from the Crown civil list. In this
		  latter part of his life, better financial circumstances allowed him to pursue
		  his interests with more zeal and he concentrated on the botany of Aberdeenshire
		  and Banffshire. Thomas Edward died on 27 April 1886.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Addressed from Banff the letters offer thanks for a note and papers,
		  and acknowledge correspondence and a request. There is also a copy of an
		  engraving of Edward as shoemaker.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>Among miscellaneous Scottish letters, purchased E. Hall, Harrogate,
		  October 1976, Accession no. E76.43.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Stephen Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). 
		<title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.6. Drant-Finan.
		London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes several locations of Edward related material:
		  correspondence and essays, 1883-1884, National Library of Scotland, Manuscript
		  Collections, Ref. MS 2227, and 1878-80 : correspondence with David Douglas,
		  1878-1880, Ref. MSS 1661-1662; and letters to Samuel Smiles, 1875-1878, West
		  Yorkshire Archive Service, Leeds, NRA 25959 Smiles.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Naturalists</emph> </subject>
		
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Edward</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1814-1886</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Naturalist</emph>
		  </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
