<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-208" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-208</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Papers of Arthur Ruffell Barlow (1888-1965)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division. Revised by Graeme D Eddie.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Apr 26 10:34:32 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-208</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 1785-1786</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Arthur Ruffell
		  Barlow (1888-1965)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1903-1965">1903-1965</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>2 boxes, 1 file, 6 volumes. </extent>
		  <emph altrender="jisc-hub16">English and Kikuyu</emph> --&gt; </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English,
		  </language> and <language langcode="kik">Kikuyu or Gikuyu.</language>
		  </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Arthur Ruffell Barlow, Church of Scotland missionary and linguist, was
		  born in Edinburgh in 1888. He was the nephew of David Clement Ruffell Scott, a
		  Church of Scotland missionary in Malawi and Kenya. In 1903 at the age of
		  seventeen Barlow joined his uncle at Scott's mission at Kikuyu, British East
		  Africa (Kenya). He assisted with the mission's work in an unofficial capacity
		  until 1908 when he was formally employed by the Church of Scotland. His
		  interest in and grasp of the Kikuyu language and dialects meant he was often
		  employed as a translator and his intimate knowledge of the Kikuyu people made
		  him a trusted counsellor. He was a good friend of Jomo Kenyatta when both were
		  young. In 1909 he became the first resident missionary at Tumutumu and acted,
		  at various times, as superintendent at both Kikuyu and Tumutumu. He was one of
		  the founders of the Kenya Missionary Council and acted as its secretary for a
		  number of years as well as playing a prominent role in the debate on church and
		  mission union in Kenya. Barlow's work with the Kikuyu language continued, he
		  prepared a grammar which became a standard and initiated a bible translation.
		  His knowledge of the language and culture and interest in questions such as
		  land reform and the rights of Africans meant that he was also often consulted
		  on African matters by government. After he retired on 30 June 1941 he continued
		  his linguistic and translation studies, at first working for two years under an
		  arrangement with the Church of Scotland. He published 
		<title>Studies in Kikuyu Grammar and Idiom</title> in 1951 which followed
		an earlier 'tentative' work in 1946. He returned to Kenya from Scotland during
		the Mau Mau troubles and in 1953 took the role of Officer in Charge of the
		Translation Bureau of the African Information Services. He left Kenya for the
		final time in 1959. Barlow devoted a large amount of time in his later years to
		the production of a Kikuyu-English dictionary on which he worked with Canon
		Henry Leakey and Leonard Beecher, both of the Church Missionary Society. The
		dictionary was finally published in 1964 and Barlow died in 1965.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The collection consists of material about the Church of Scotland
		  mission in Kenya, about Kikuyu language and culture, and about the interests
		  and concerns of Africans and their relation to the government. In particular it
		  includes: Barlow's comments on and additions to the 
		<title>Kikuyu-English Dictionary</title> by L.J. Beecher and G.S.B.
		Beecher (including volumes of the 1935 dictionary with Barlow's handwritten
		amendments) with correspondence (1956-1962) about the publication of a revised
		version; Barlow's notes and personal volumes on the Kikuyu language, songs,
		music, customs and idioms; minutes and constitution of the United Kikuyu
		Language Committee (1908-1917); letters from Barlow to his father (1904-1905)
		and personal items such as testimonials and correspondence about his retirement
		and later return to Kenya; correspondence and other items relating to David C.
		Scott's estate at Kiambu; correspondence, reports, pamphlets and papers
		produced by and about the missions at Kikuyu and Tumutumu and from the Church
		of Scotland's Foreign Missionary Council; notes on the history of the mission
		in East Africa; papers on the Kenyan Mission Council and the proposed
		federation of mission societies; material on African affairs such as the Indian
		question, Harry Thuka, the Labour Bureau Commission, land tenure, the Kikuyu
		Association, female circumcision, and education; papers concerning the Mau Mau
		rebellion including Barlow's translation of Kikuyu documents; a manifesto of
		the Kenyan African National Union (1960); press cuttings; and photographs
		(1904-1915) relating to Kenya and in particular to the missions at Kikuyu and
		Tumutumu. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement> 
		<p>The material is arranged in two boxes, with an additional loose file
		  and six volumes. The first box (Gen. 1785/1-7) contains notebooks and papers on
		  the Kikuyu language and the Beechers' dictionary; the second (Gen. 1786/1-8)
		  contains eight files of papers and correspondence on the mission and African
		  questions arranged broadly by subject but with much overlap; the loose file
		  (Gen. 1786/12) contains mainly printed pamphlets and reports; three of the
		  volumes (Gen. 1785/8-10) are the annotated 
		<title>Beechers Kikuyu-English Dictionary</title>; and the remaining
		three volumes (Gen. 1786/9-11) are photograph albums. Some photographs are also
		filed in Gen. 1786/1. </p> 
	 </arrangement> 
	 <custodhist> 
		<p>Before he died Barlow had collected some papers together with a view
		  to writing a history of the Scottish missions in British East Africa. In early
		  1965 the papers were loaned to Brian G. McIntosh (one time lecturer in history
		  at University College, Nairobi) who compiled a list of the papers which was
		  then sent to Professor George A. Shepperson, Professor of Commonwealth and
		  American History, at the University of Edinburgh. </p> 
	 </custodhist> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p>The papers were presented to Edinburgh University in 1967 by Mrs
		  Barlow. </p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <userestrict> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <altformavail> 
		<p>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections also has a microfilm
		  of the collection (Mic. Dup. 357). A copy was sent to the Kenyan High
		  Commission in 1982.</p> 
	 </altformavail> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
		  (1) Anderson, G. H. (ed.). 
		<title>Bibliographical Dictionary of Christian Missions</title>. New
		York: Macmillan Reference USA, 1998. (2) Church of Scotland Foreign Missionary
		Committee resolution, 16 February 1942 (Gen. 1786/4).</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University
		  Library, Special Collections and Archives, the index only refers to some of the
		  items in the collection. Two lists of the papers, compiled by Brian G. McIntosh
		  in 1965 are filed in the front of the first box (Gen. 1785). A note at the top
		  of the list states 'not in EUL' but the items listed are in the collection,
		  although not in any particular order. Some of the items in the collection, such
		  as the Kikuyu language material and the Mau Mau papers are not on McIntosh's
		  list. The collection is mentioned in the Edinburgh University Library subject
		  checklist (C3) 
		<title>Manuscripts on Africa</title>.</p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>Edinburgh University Library also holds the papers of John William
		  Arthur (Gen. 762-765) and George A. Grieve (Gen. 766/3-5), both missionaries at
		  Kikuyu. The papers of Scott's uncle, David Clement Scott (Edinburgh University
		  Library Gen. 717/10), relate to an earlier period before Barlow went out to
		  Africa. The Library's African Studies (CAS) collection has a collection of
		  pamphlets and printed materials relating to the church at Kikuyu. The National
		  Library of Scotland has a large collection of missionary records, including
		  some letters from Barlow. Dr Brian McIntosh in his doctoral thesis 
		<title>The Scottish Mission in Kenya 1891-1923</title> (Edinburgh
		University, 1969) has a comprehensive list of sources for the history of the
		Kikuyu mission. He mentions Barlow records at the University of London and in
		private hands.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Female circumcision</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Kenya</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Kikuyu language</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Linguistic work</emph> </subject> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph>
		  <emph altrender="z">Africa</emph> </subject> 
		<persname> <emph altrender="surname">Barlow</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Arthur Ruffell</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1888-1965</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scottish
		  Missionary</emph> </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Kikuyu Association</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Kikuyu Mission</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">United Kikuyu Language Committee</emph>
		  </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Kenya</emph> <emph altrender="x">Politics
		  and government</emph> </geogname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Kenya</emph> <emph
		  altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">Mau Mau Emergency,
		  1952-1960</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
