<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-322" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-322</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Records of the Imperial University of France</titleproper>
		  
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Thu Jan 24 12:13:20 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date>
			 </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-322</unitid> 
		<physloc>Dc.1.44; Dc.6.81-82</physloc><unittitle>Records of the Imperial
		  University of France</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>3 volumes. </extent> </physdesc> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="fre">French.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Founded around 1170, the medieval University of Paris grew out of the
		  cathedral schools of Notre-Dame. To accommodate the students many colleges were
		  built, and one of the most celebrated of these was the Sorbonne founded by the
		  theologian Robert de Sorbon (1201-1274) in around 1257. In time, the name
		  Sorbonne became a popular term for the theological faculty of Paris. During the
		  French Revolutionary and Napoleonic periods however, colleges disappeared from
		  Paris and from universities in the rest of continental Europe. With the French
		  Revolution (1789-99) came the subsequent reorganisation of many of France's
		  institutions, not least the University of Paris.</p> 
		<p>The Imperial University was created under the Empire in 1806 and
		  became operational in 1808. It was one of the cornerstones of Napoleon's
		  institutional reconstruction. The Imperial University was devoted exclusively
		  to the training of the managerial staff the country very much needed,
		  particularly in the fields of law and medicine. Faculties of literature and of
		  science were also created and these were seen as embodying the spirit of
		  positivism and faith in progress. Rather than house the Imperial institution in
		  the outdated Sorbonne, Napoleon had selected sites with new prestige - the
		  Champs-de-Mars and the Iles des Cygnes. However, he did not have time to finish
		  this project.</p> 
		<p>During the period of the Second Restoration (1815-1830) the faculties
		  of theology, literature and science were brought back to the Sorbonne in 1821
		  by the Ultras, the 'ultraroyaliste' and extreme right wing of the French
		  royalist movement representing the interests of the large landowners, the
		  aristocracy, clericalists, and former emigres. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>Documents relating to the Imperial University of France and other
		  French universities and institutes of learning. Manuscript documents.</p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) 
		<title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Micropaedia. Ready
		Reference. 15th edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, Inc., 1991. (2)
		Historique. 
		<title>La Sorbonne</title>. Full-text [online]. 
		<extref href="http://www.sorbonne.fr/">La Sorbonne</extref> [Accessed 5
		December 2001].</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Universite de Paris</emph> </corpname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Imperial University</emph> </corpname> 
		<geogname> <emph altrender="a">Paris (France)</emph> </geogname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
