<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-91"
	  encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237
		Coll-91</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of the
			 Rev. Earle Monteith MacPhail (1861-1937) </titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<change> 
		  <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> 
		  <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl
			 (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</change> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc
	encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c"
	level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<repository> 
		  <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
			 Archives </corpname> </repository> 
		<unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-91</unitid>
		
		<physloc>Gen. 2044-2073; MSS 2592-2593 </physloc><unittitle
		encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of the Rev. Earle Monteith
		  MacPhail (1861-1937) </unittitle> 
		<unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260"
		 normal="1869-1930">circa 1869-1930 </unitdate> 
		<physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>2 boxes; 31
		  separate notebooks; 1 box of notebooks. </extent> </physdesc> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> 
		<p>Earle Monteith MacPhail was born in Aberdeen in 1861. He was educated
		  at Edinburgh Academy and then at Edinburgh University where he was awarded the
		  degree of M.A. in 1883. He then studied Divinity at Edinburgh, at New College.
		  While at Edinburgh he was one of the founders of the Edinburgh University
		  Students' Representative Council, 1883-1884, and was President of the Council
		  in 1885. MacPhail also studied abroad at Jena, Tuebingen, and Berlin
		  Universities, after which he was ordained as a missionary of the United Free
		  Church of Scotland in 1890. That year too, he became Professor of History and
		  Economics at Madras Christian College. He became Principal of the College in
		  1921. Earlier, in 1899, he became a Fellow of Madras University, and in 1909
		  and again in 1919 he was the Representative of the University on the
		  Legislative Council of the Governor of Fort St. George. In 1921 and 1922 he was
		  a Member of the Legislative Council. In 1921 too, MacPhail was a Member of the
		  Central Education Advisory Board for India. Between 1923 and 1925 he was
		  Vice-Chancellor of the University of Madras, as well as being a Member of the
		  Indian Council of State in 1924. Between 1925 and 1927, he was the
		  Representative of the European Constituency of Madras in the Legislative
		  Assembly of India. In 1919, MacPhail was awarded the CBE, and in 1924 he was
		  made Companion of the Order of the Indian Empire. MacPhail died in Edinburgh on
		  19 January 1937. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> 
		<p>The papers of Earle Monteith MacPhail at shelfmark Gen. 2044-2073
		  consist of notebooks of notes from lectures at Edinburgh University and in
		  India, 1878-1890. At MSS 2592-2593 there are personal papers including
		  correspondence, a school notebook of handwriting dated 1875, and a school fees
		  receipt dated 1869; photographs; notes of Natural Philosophy classes, 1879;
		  and, essays, 1879. There is material marking celebrations of Edinburgh
		  University Tercentenary; material of the Dialectic Society and the Diagnostic
		  Society; the Students' Representative Council; the University Union; and, the
		  New College Examination Board. There are also papers relating to Madras
		  Christian College. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> 
		<p>Contact the repository for details </p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <odd encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.1"> 
		<note encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.6.1./marc 500"> 
		  <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material:
			 (1) 
		  <title>University of Edinburgh Journal </title>, Vol.8. 1936-1937,
		  p.288 (Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd). (2) 
		  <title>Who was who </title>, Vol.3. 1929-1940 (London: Adam and Charles
		  Black, 1941). </p> 
		</note> 
	 </odd> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph
		  altrender="surname">MacPhail</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Earle
		  Monteith</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1861-1937</emph> </persname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Madras Christian
		  College</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">University of
		  Madras</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
	 <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> 
		<p>An important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held
		  at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to
		  the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
