<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> 
  <eadheader> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-532" countrycode="GB">GB
		237 Coll-532</eadid> 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper>Collection of Correspondence of the Poet, Allan Ramsay
			 (1684-1758)</titleproper> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<notestmt> 
		  <note> 
			 <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division.</p> 
		  </note> 
		</notestmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form
		  which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version
		  2.</creation> 
	 </profiledesc> 
	 <revisiondesc> 
		<list> 
		  <item> Modified at: 
			 <date> Mon Mar 17 10:22:00 UTC 2003</date> </item> 
		  <item> 
			 <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD
			 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> 
		</list> 
	 </revisiondesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc level="fonds"> 
	 <did> 
		<unitid>GB 237 Coll-532</unitid> 
		<physloc>Gen. 752; Gen. 2122/14</physloc><unittitle>Collection of
		  Correspondence of the Poet, Allan Ramsay (1684-1758)</unittitle> 
		<unitdate normal="1701-1799">18th century</unitdate> 
		<repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections
		  Division</repository> 
		<physdesc> <extent>1 notebook volume with letters fixed in; 1
		  manuscript</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be
		  restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> 
		<origination>Ramsay, Allan</origination> 
		<langmaterial label="Language"> <language
		  langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist> 
		<p>Allan Ramsay was a native of Leadhills, Lanarkshire. He came to
		  Edinburgh in 1700 to start an apprenticeship with a wigmaker. He became
		  absorbed in literature however and became a bookseller with businesses in
		  Niddry's Wynd and in the High Street of Edinburgh. In 1725 he established a
		  circulating library, probably one of the earliest in Britain. In 1736 he opened
		  a theatre in Carruber's Close but this was closed by the city's authorities.
		  Ramsay published his first poems in 1721 and a second collection was published
		  in 1728. Earlier, in 1725, came the drama 
		<title>The gentle shepherd</title>, a pastoral comedy. In 1724 he
		produced an anthology of earlier Scottish verse, 
		<title>The ever green</title> and between 1724 and 1737 he brought out a
		five volume collection of traditional Scottish songs and ballads 
		<title>Tea-table miscellany</title>. Ramsay had also been interested in
		the decorative and visual arts and encouraged his artistic son, Allan Ramsay
		(1713-1784), who would become one of Britain's finest portrait artists. The
		elder Allan Ramsay died in 1758. </p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent> 
		<p>The material is composed of: autograph MS of hymn beginning 
		<title>Father and friend of humane race</title> with signed endorsement
		of Ramsay's son; and, 
		<title>The miller and his man, or self deed self fae. A tale</title>.</p>
		
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <acqinfo> 
		<p> 
		<title>The miller ...</title>, purchased from Sotheby catalogue, June
		1964, Accession no. E64.28. Hymn, purchased from Sotheby catalogue, June 1982,
		Accession no. E82.64.</p> 
	 </acqinfo> 
	 <accruals> 
		<p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> 
	 </accruals> 
	 <accessrestrict> 
		<p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p> 
	 </accessrestrict> 
	 <note> 
		<p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		<title>Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland</title>. London: Harper Collins
		Publishers, 1994.</p> 
	 </note> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<p>The local Indexes show various references to Allan Ramsay, the poet,
		  in the Laing Collection and elsewhere (check the Indexes for more details):
		  letters and papers of the Easy Club, at La.II.212; also at La.II.212
		  (asterisk), 
		<title>The gentle shepherd</title>; 
		<title>An elegy on Lucky Wood</title> at JA 2035; dedication on blank
		leaf of 
		<title>Poems</title>, at JA 3822-3823; an anthology of seventeeth century
		verse, at La.III.436; 
		<title>A session of poets calculated for the meridian of North
		  Britain</title>, 1738, at La.II.83/6; letter about Ramsay from A. B. Grossart
		to D. Laing, 1847, at La.IV.17; mention of 
		<title>The gentle shepherd</title> by W. Shenstone to McGouan, 1761, at
		La.II.423/203; 
		<title>Macbeath the tragedy</title> mentioned in a letter of G. Paton to
		J. Cumming, 1769, at La.II.82; mention of 
		<title>Tale of three bonnets</title> by A. F. Tytler to G. Chalmers at
		La.II.453/2; edition of Ramsay's poems referred to by Tytler to W. Davies,
		1799, at La.II.602; letter of Elizabeth Bell mentioning her father's belief
		that James Thomson assisted Ramsay with 
		<title>The gentle shepherd</title>, 1829, at Dc.6.111, ff.145-146; elegy
		mentioned in a letter of R. Pitcairn to D. Laing, La.IV.17; letter from
		Grossart to Laing about the authorship of 
		<title>Defence of dramatical entertainments</title>, 1847, at La.IV.17;
		letter of Grossart about his work on Ramsay and Ferguson, 1846, at
		Dc.4.101-103; and, life of Allan Ramsay the poet by Ramsay, painter, at
		La.II.212/41 and 42.</p> 
		<p>There are also references to Ramsay, the painter, in the Laing
		  Collection and elsewhere: an enquiry into the situation and circumstances of
		  Horace's Sabine Villa, at La.III.492; letter to Sir A. Lindsay, 1752, at
		  La.IV.26; letter from Lord Balcarres, at La.IV.26; letter of A. Cochrane to J.
		  Davidson about Ramsay's painting of the Duke of Argyll, 1750, at La.II.511/1;
		  life of Allan Ramsay the poet by Ramsay, painter, at La.II.212/41 and 42; and,
		  signed endorsement by Ramsay on his father's autograph MS of hymn 
		<title>Father and friend of humane race</title>, at Gen.2122/14.</p> 
		<p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by
		  the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: Ramsay MSS are among the Cowie
		  collection Autograph MS of 
		<title>The Roundell to her Health</title> and 
		<title>Bogi-dow</title>, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts
		Division, Ref. Acc 3670, 3733, and literary papers, Ref. MSS 510, 582, 804-05,
		2233, 2618, 5200, 9748-9749; poems and letters to Sir John Clerk, 1722-1755,
		National Archives of Scotland, Ref. GD18/4313-63 NRA 29182 Clerk; songs,
		Manchester University, John Rylands Library, Ref. Eng MS 748; papers,
		Huntington Library; and, literary papers, British Library, Manuscript
		Collections, Ref. Eg MSS 2023-24.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial>    <!-- control access terms -->
	 <controlaccess> 
		<subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish poetry</emph>
		  </subject> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Ramsay</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Allan</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1713-1784</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Painter</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Ramsay</emph>
		  <emph altrender="forename">Allan</emph> <emph
		  altrender="dates">1686-1758</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Poet</emph>
		  </persname> 
		<corpname> <emph altrender="a">Easy Club, Edinburgh</emph>
		  <emph altrender="y">1700 - 1800</emph> </corpname> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc>
</ead>
