<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-1040" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-1040</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>The Percy Johnson-Marshall Collection</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Sarah Higgins (Digital Library Officer), and updated and edited by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Nov 10 09:28:45 UTC 2004</date> </item> <item> Modified at: <date>Wed Nov 17 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> GB 0237 PJM converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1040"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-1040</unitid> <physloc>PJM</physloc><unittitle>The Percy Johnson-Marshall Collection</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1931/1993">1931-1993 </unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>178 metres. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Johnson-Marshall, Percy</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The urban designer, regional planner and educator, Percy Johnson-Marshall, was born in Ajmer, India, on 20 January 1915. He studied at Liverpool University School of Architecture, and began his career as a planner in 1936, working for a number local authorities: Middlesex County and Willesden Borough (1936-1938); Coventry City (1938-1941); Greater London Region (1948-1949); and, London County Council (1949-1959). He advised the Government of Burma on planning and reconstruction (1945-1946), and worked in Britain for the Ministry of Town and Country Planning (1948).</p> <p>His career in higher education began in 1959 at the University of Edinburgh Department of Architecture, first as Senior Lecturer and then, in 1964, as Professor of Urban Design and Regional Planning with his own department within Sir Robert Matthew's School of the Built Environment (1967). He was a director of the Architecture Research Unit (1961-1964) and founder of the Planning Research Unit (PRU)(1962). The PRU was involved in the preparation of regional plans including those for the Lothians, Grangemouth-Falkirk, and the Scottish Borders.</p> <p>In 1962, Percy Johnson-Marshall and Associates was launched with the commission as planning consultants to the University of Edinburgh for its Comprehensive Development Area. The practice was also involved in master plans for Sao Paulo, Porto, and Islamabad, reports for the Scottish Development Department, and various redevelopment schemes in UK towns such as Edinburgh, Kilmarnock and Salford. In 1966, Johnson-Marshall published <title>Rebuilding cities</title>.</p> <p>Percy Johnson-Marshall died on 14 July 1993. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection comprises a wide range of material connected with architecture and planning. This includes published books and journals, personal and professional papers, papers relating to various professional organisations, survey material, planning reports, government reports, plans, drawings, photographs and slides. There is also a large quantity of comparative material with major subject listings which include: Urban Design, Regional Planning, Town and Country Planning, Post-war Planning and Reconstruction, New Towns, Architecture, Urban History.</p> <p>There is material relating to: University of Liverpool studentships, 1931-1938; Willesden Borough Council, 1930-1938; Coventry City Council, 1939-1959; London County Council, 1937-1968; World War II service in India and Burma, 1940-1956; Association of Building Technicians, 1940-1965; Service Arts and Technical Organization (SATO), 1943-1946; School of Planning and Research for National Development, 1946-1957; Ministry of Town and Country Planning, 1948; International Centre for Regional Planning and Development (ICRPD), 1955-1962; teaching duties at the University of Edinburgh, 1959-1988; Percy Johnson-Marshall and Associates, 1962-1985; United Nations; Ministry of Overseas Development; Association for Planning and Regional Reconstruction; Housing Centre Trust; International Society of City and Regional Planners (ISoCARP); Modern Architectural Research Group (MARG); Mars Group of the Congres Internationaux d'Architecture Moderne; Royal Institute of British Architects; Royal Town Planning Institute;Society for the Promotion of Urban Renewal (SPUR); and, the Commonwealth Human Ecology Council (CHEC).</p> <p>There are also: collected books; collected journals; mixed correspondence and papers; and, a collection of slides.</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>The Percy Johnson-Marshall Collection consists of approximately 20 subcollections. Material which has not yet been arranged and catalogued in detail has been listed to file level.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>Gifted. Retrospective accession. Arrived during 1999-2000. Accessioned 13 September 2004. Accession no. E2004.24</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Rebuilding the city: The Percy Johnson-Marshall Collection</title>. Full-text [online]. <extref href="http://www.johnson-marshall.lib.ed.ac.uk/">Rebuilding the city: The Percy Johnson-Marshall Collection</extref> [Accessed 2 November 2004]. (2) <title>Who's who 1987</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1987.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>There are 2 handlists available for browsing. The first covers material from Percy Johnson-Marshall's personal collection. The second covers material from the former Patrick Geddes Centre for Planning Studies at the Outlook Tower. It is possible to search and browse catalogued sub-collections, and to browse handlists of manuscripts and map holdings at <extref href="http://www.johnson-marshall.lib.ed.ac.uk/index.html" title="rebuilding the city: the percy johnson-marshall collection">www.johnson-marshall.lib.ed.ac.uk</extref> </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>Percy Johnson-Marshall owned around 8,500 books relating to architecture, and town and regional planning. He also collected nearly 800 journal titles, mostly relating to architecture, and town and regional planning, although some also relate to art and literature. The runs for these are mostly incomplete, and some are sporadic. The journal titles and editions available have been listed, as have the books, and all are available for searching.</p> <p>At E2006.1 there is a seven page typescript (copy) of memories of Sir Stirrat Johnson-Marshall (1912-1981) written by Percy Johnson-Marshall in December 1981.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Architecture</emph> <emph altrender="x">Designs and plans</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Architecture</emph> <emph altrender="x">Decision making</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">City planning</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">City planners</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Regional planning</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">World War, 1939-1945</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">War</emph> <emph altrender="x">Economic aspects</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Reconstruction (1939-1951)</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Civic centers</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Johnson-Marshall</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Percy</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1915-1993</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Urban Design and Regional Planning</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Abercrombie</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Lesley Patrick</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1879-1957</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Town Planning</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Gibson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Donald Evelyn Edward</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1908-1991</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Architect and Town Planner</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Johnson-Marshall</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Stirrat</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1912-1981</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Architect</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Reilly</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Charles Herbert</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1874-1948</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Architect and Writer</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Tatton-Brown</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1910-1986</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Architect</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Percy Johnson-Marshall and Associates</emph> <emph altrender="z">Edinburgh (Scotland)</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Coventry (England)</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Liverpool (England)</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">London (England)</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Willesden (England)</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
