<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-456" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-456</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Lectures of Professor John Gustave Pilley (1899-1968)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Oct 4 11:43:45 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-456</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 2212/12/1-2; E90.55</physloc><unittitle>Lectures of Professor John Gustave Pilley (1899-1968)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1951-1965">1951-1965</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 folder, 1 envelope with documents, circa 80 audiotapes (1.25 linear metres)</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>John Gustave Pilley was born on 6 January 1899. He studied at Dulwich College and at the age of eighteen he joined the Army, serving in France with the Royal Engineers until October 1918. He then studied at Exeter College, Oxford, graduating in Natural Science in 1922 before going on to research in Physics. Pilley became a Lecturer in Education at Lverpool University in 1926 and went on to Bristol University in 1927 in the same capacity. There he specialised in Methods of Science Teaching and in Theory of Education. In 1937, after Bristol, he went to America, becoming a Visiting Professor at Wellesley College, Massachusetts, then in 1939, Head of the Education Department. His publications include <title>Electricity</title> (1927). In 1951 he became Professor of Education at Edinburgh University. Professor John Gustave Pilley died on 11 July 1968.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of: typescript transcripts from tape recordings of lectures on the theory and history of education given at Edinburgh University, 1958-1959; a copy of a typescript of the dialogue <title>Topsy among the abstractions</title>; and, audiotapes of lectures from 1951 to 1965.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Transcripts from tape recordings and typescript of dialogue, acquired from Dept. of Philosophy, June 1986, Accession no. E86.42. Audiotapes acquired from Mr. Christopher Pilley, May 1990, Accession no. E90.55.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 16. 1951-1953. Autumn 1951. p.2. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1951. (2) <title>Who was who 1961-1970</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1972.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Pilley</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John Gustave</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1899-1968</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Education</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
