<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-538" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-538</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection of Material relating to Robert Wodrow, Historian (1679-1734)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Mar 20 14:15:58 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-538</unitid> <physloc>Dc.8.1; Dc.8.110</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Material relating to Robert Wodrow, Historian (1679-1734)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1701-1799">18th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 manuscript volumes</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Wodrow, Robert</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The ecclesiastical historian Robert Wodrow was born in Glasgow in 1679. He was the son of James Wodrow, Professor of Divinity at Glasgow University. When he was twelve he entered Glasgow University (not unusual at the time), and after taking his M.A. degree and while attending theological classes he was appointed University Librarian in 1697. In 1703 he became licensed to preach by the Presbytery of Paisley with a view to becoming Minister at Eastwood. He was a Minister in Glasgow in 1712, and in Stirling in 1717 and 1726, but for much of his life he was in Eastwood. In 1721-1722 he published <title>The history of the sufferings of the Church of Scotland from the Restoration to the Revolution</title> Robert Wodrow died on 21 March 1734. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of: manuscripts <title>Admiranda and Notanda. Ane account of strange and remarkable revelations which were revealed to a Christian friend in the Shire of Dumfriece</title> and <title>A relations of a rare providence that befell a young childe daughter to a husband-man or femorer whose name is Donald McGreiger ...</title>; and, history of the Church of Scotland, 1683-1684, and corresponding to pp.333-454 of Vol.2 of the 1722 edition.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 21. Whichcord-Zuylestein. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show various references to Wodrow related material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letter book, 1698-1709, at La.III.355; letters to the Laird of Cartsburn and to the Laird of Craufordsburn, La.II.257; letter to James Anderson, La.II.102; letters to James Cranstoun, La.II.709; essay on life of James Wodrow, at La.II.690; account of manuscript in Glasgow in a letter to Sir R. Sibbald, La.III.355; life of John Davidson, at La.III.266; miscellaneous manuscripts, Vol.33 of his various manuscripts, at La.III.263; an account of the Wodrow manuscripts at Glasgow University Library, 1824, at La.III.842; letter to James Anderson to the care of Mr. Montyre at the Post Office, Eastwood, 1723, at La.II.101; sermons, 1703-1723, at La.III.116; mention in letters, 1836-1851, at La.IV.17; description of manuscript volumes now in America, 1854, at La.IV.17; correspondence between Wodrow and James Anderson, 1717-1723, in the Laing Collection; and, remarks on a volume of Wodrow letters, and mention of his sermons in letters from Joseph Bain to David Laing, in Laing Correspondence.</p> <p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: communion sermons (1 vol), 1710-1725, Glasgow University Library, Special Collections Department, Ref. MS Gen 745, and MS collections (22 vols), Ref. MS Gen 1197-1218; correspondence, collections and papers, 1699-1731, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Wodr MSS, Anal, Fol, Lett; Adv MS 27 6 2, and commonplace book, 1692, Ref. MS 2824; and, MS drafts of books II and III of History of the Sufferings of the Church of Scotland, circa 1720, British Library, Manuscripts Collections, Ref. Harl MSS 6543-44; Add MS 37996.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Church history</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Wodrow</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1679-1734</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Ecclesiastical Historian</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
