<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-1046" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-1046</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Veterinary notebooks of Anthony Hyde Smith (fl. 1935-1960)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Nov 10 11:10:30 UTC 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1046"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-1046</unitid> <physloc>E2004.30</physloc><unittitle>Veterinary notebooks of Anthony Hyde Smith (fl. 1935-1960)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1935/1960">1935-1960</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>4 boxes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Smith, Anthony Hyde; Beaumont, G. L.</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Anthony Hyde Smith graduated from the Royal (Dick) Veterinary College in Edinburgh in 1941. This is now the Royal (Dick) School of Veterinary Studies, University of Edinburgh.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of: general class notes, foolscap, dated 1936, with an Edinburgh address; anatomy loose-leaf folders (covers have Framlingham College), one dated Easter 1936; notes on jurisprudence, 1939; surgery note book, 1939; entomology note book, 1939; helminthology note book, no.4, 1939, medicine note book, no.2, 1940; surgery note book, no.2, 1940; disease untitled, 1941; reproduction untitled, 1941; surgery note book, no.3, 1941; surgery untitled, Christmas session 1941; medicine note book, no.4, 1941 (contains at back childish scribbles, with name); anatomy demonstration notes; poultry diseases; botany loose pages; loose pages biology, chemistry, and botany; pathology loose-leaf foolscap folder (containing <title>Daily telegraph</title> war map no.5; and, casebook containing a letter of reference. There is other subject-based material: chemistry and physics, 1935; pharmacology, 1939; applied anatomy, 1938; animal breeding, 1938; clinical helminthology, 1941; protozoology; milk; physiology; general medicine; virus disease; animal breeding and transport; embryology; and, pharmacology. There is also: histology sketch book, dated 1938, with signature; and anatomy sketches. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>The material came via a family member (Sue Clark, daughter of Smith) via Dick Vet. Accessioned 5 November 2004. Accession no: E2004.30.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Veterinarians</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Veterinary medicine</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Animal breeding</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Anatomy, Comparative</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Smith</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Anthony Hyde</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1935-1960</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
