<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-182" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-182</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection of material relating to Professor Thomas Craufurd (d. 1662) </titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Dec 17 16:49:08 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-182</unitid> <physloc>Dc.2.83; Dc.4.3; Dc.5.8; Dc.5.55; Dc.5.122; Gen.2212/2; E2006.14</physloc><unittitle>Collection of material relating to Professor Thomas Craufurd (d. 1662) </unittitle> <unitdate normal="1652-1791">1652-1791</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box-file containing seal, 4 volumes, 1 folder, 1 notebook case-bound. </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Henderson, William; Burton, Alexander; Drummond, David; Boswell, Alexander. Lord Auchinleck</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> and <language langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Thomas Craufurd, a graduate of St. Andrews University, had been elected Regent or Professor of Humanity at Edinburgh University on 29 March 1626. In February 1630, he was appointed to the rectorship of the Royal High School in Edinburgh. Craufurd was again elected to a University Chair in December 1640, this time becoming Professor of Mathematics. No-one had held this professorship since 1623. In January 1641 he was also received as a Regent of Philosophy. Craufurd was responsible for a history of the University, from its foundation in 1581 till the year 1646, and he had also been invited to write a Latin grammar. He had been placed on a list of candidates eligible for the post of Principal on the resignation and subsequent death of Robert Leighton in 1662. Professor Thomas Craufurd himself died in 1662. The Chair then remained dormant until 1674 when it was taken by James Gregory (d. 1675). </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>This collection of different material relating to Professor Thomas Craufurd includes a transcript of the original manuscript of his history of the University, by William Henderson, Librarian, 1673, entitled <title>Memoires of the Institution, Donations, Fabrick, Progress ... appertaining to the Universitie ... 1580 to ... 1646</title>at Dc.4.3, and there are further transcripts, 1791, at Dc.5.8., and one largely in the hand of Alexander Boswell, lord Auchinleck, at Gen. 2212/2. In the collection there are also dictates, 1652-1654, and 1661-1662, by D. Drummond at Dc.5.122 and by A. Burton at Dc.5.55. In addition, the collection includes a charter and seal of Richard Cromwell, Lord Protector of the Commonwealth, granting a house to Craufurd, 1659, at Dc.2.83. There is also a case-bound notebook containing a Register of Arms - an 18th century (or late-17th century) transcript of a manuscript of Professor Thomas Craufurd, at E2006.14.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Transcript in hand of Boswell, purchased June 1985, Accession no. E85.33. </p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Dalzel, Andrew <title>History of the University of Edinburgh from its foundation</title>. Edinburgh : Edmonston and Douglas, 1862. (2) Grant, Sir Alexander <title>The story of the University of Edinburgh</title>. London: Longmans, Green and Co., 1884.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353"> <p>The local Indexes show another reference to Craufurd related material (check the Indexes for more details), namely, the original manuscript of his history of the University, at La.III.232.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Craufurd</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d. 1662</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Mathematics</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Boswell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1707-1782</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Lord Auchinleck Judge </emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Henderson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Librarian, Edinburgh University</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Burton</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Drummond</emph> <emph altrender="forename">David</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
