<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-26" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-26</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Professor David Bayne Horn (1901-1969) </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-26</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 1824 </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Papers of Professor David Bayne Horn (1901-1969) </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1969">before 1969 </unitdate> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>15 boxes, 7 notebooks (2 linear metres). </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>David Bayne Horn was born on 9 July 1901. He was educated at Edinburgh Institution, later called Melville College (now Stewart's Daniel &amp;amp; Melville College). He then studied at Edinburgh University, gaining a first class honours degree in history, MA, 1922. In 1923, Horn joined the staff of the History Department of the University as an Assistant in History. In 1927 he became a Lecturer in History, and in 1929 was awarded the degree of D.Litt. at the University for his thesis on <title>Sir Charles Hanbury Williams and European diplomacy </title>. Horn then went on to become Professor of Modern History in 1954. A writer as well as a lecturer, his main interest lay in the field of 18th century diplomatic history and 18th century British foreign policy in particular. His publication record includes <title>A history of Europe, 1871-1920 </title> (1927), <title>British diplomatic representatives, 1689-1789 </title> (1932), <title>Scottish diplomatists, 1689-1789 </title> (1944), <title>British public opinion and the first partition of Poland </title> (1945), <title>British diplomatic service, 1689-1789 (1961), Frederick the Great and the rise of Prussia </title> (1964), <title>Great Britain and Europe in the eighteenth century </title> (1967). At the time of his death on 7 August 1969, Horn was engaged in writing a full-length history of the University, having been given two years' leave of absence for the project. In 1967 he had written a shorter history of the University. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The Papers of Professor Horn are a boxed, unnumbered, uncatalogued collection of papers, drafts, notes, and miscellaneous items. The most significant material relates to the proposed 'long history' of the University. Also included are background materials (drafts, notes, bibliographies, offprints, etc.) relating to Horn's publications on 18th century British diplomatic history: <title>The British diplomatic service, 1689-1789 </title> (1961); <title>Great Britain and Europe in the eighteenth century </title> (1967). There are also packets containing handwritten notes, maps, technical data, clippings, photos and offprints relating to Scottish mountains and climbing; various lecture notes, correspondence, bronze award medals, and loose papers. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.5./marc 541"> <p>The collection was deposited at by Horn's daughter, Hazel Horn. An initial deposit was made in October 1969 shortly after her father's death, and then in 1977 a further large instalment of notes and papers was deposited. </p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details </p> </accessrestrict> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Horn</emph> <emph altrender="forename">David Bayne</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1901-1969</emph> </persname> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Historians</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Diplomatic and consular service</emph> <emph altrender="z">Great Britain</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H26; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows correspondence with Sir Richard Lodge at Gen. 766/1. </p> </relatedmaterial> </archdesc>
</ead>
