<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-599" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-599</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Duncan Forrester (b. 1933)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 3 10:23:37 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-599</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 48</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Duncan Forrester (b. 1933)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>21 boxes</extent> </physdesc> <origination>Forrester, Duncan Baillie </origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> and <language langcode="hin">Hindi.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Duncan Baillie Forrester, Church of Scotland missionary in Madras, India and theologian, was born in Edinburgh on 10 November 1933. He was educated at St Andrew's University (1951-1955) then spent a year at Chicago University (1955-56). After working in industry for a year he went to Edinburgh University in 1957 to study for the ministry and graduated BD in 1960. He was licensed by the Presbytery of St Andrew's in 1960 and started work at St James' Mission and Hillside Church. In 1961 he went to Madras with the Church of Scotland and was the professor of politics in Madras Christian College until his return to Scotland in 1970. Forrester had been ordained in India in 1962 but he returned to a largely academic life. He was first chaplain but also lecturer at the University of Sussex (1970-1978, receiving a D Phil in 1976), then professor of Christian ethics and practical theology at Edinburgh University where he also acted as Dean of the Faculty of Divinity and was Director of the Centre for Theology and Public Issues for a period. Forrester received a ThD from the University of Iceland in 1997 and a DD from Glasgow University in 1999. He has published widely, his particular interest being in Indian politics and religion and in ethics and political theology. He retired from Edinburgh University in 2001.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of reports, articles, press cuttings, pamphlets and other papers collected by Forrester relating to India and in particular to Indian politics and religion. Some of the material includes correspondence or drafts of papers to be published by Forrester. The material dates from 1950s-1970s, mainly from the 1960s and early-mid 1970s. Topics covered include: general elections; India emergency (1975); political parties; central government, administration and constitution; state politics and federation; Madras Legislative Assembly Study (1966); politics in Tamilnadu, Madras, Andhra, Kerala, Uttar Pradesh, and Punjab; religion, secularism, communism, Harijans, and tribal politics; politics of language; community development and Panchayati Raj; education; scheduled caste graduates; caste; Coorgs; and political biography.</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>The material is arranged as described above and as deposited in the Centre. The original box titles have been kept.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>The collection was presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World by Duncan Forrester in the mid 1980s.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>None expected.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using <title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scotticanae</title> (editions 10 and 11)</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The Centre Library holds many books and pamphlets on India.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Forrester</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Duncan Baillie</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1933</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">India</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
