<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-838" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-838</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of John Faed (1819-1902) and James Faed (1821-1911)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Jul 30 09:11:55 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-838</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 2040/28-29</physloc><unittitle>Letters of John Faed (1819-1902) and James Faed (1821-1911)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1857-1865">1857-1865</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Faed, John; Faed, James</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Scottish artists John and James Faed were brothers of the oil and water-colourist Thomas Faed (1826-1900). Their sister, Miss Susan Bell Faed (1827-1900) was also a talented artist, and younger brother George Faed (1830-1852), an engraver and portrait painter. The Faeds were all born at Barley Mill, Kirkcudbright, in south-west Scotland.</p> <p>John Faed was born on 31 August 1819, and James Faed was born on 4 April 1821. John was educated at Girthon Parish School until the age of eleven and was already painting miniatures at the age of ten. By twelve he was travelling in Galloway, painting the aristocracy and well-known people. He then studied at the Trustees Academy in Edinburgh. He painted in oil and Indian ink and did miniatures, genre, and historical subjects. He illustrated <title>The cottar's Saturday night</title> and <title>Tam O'Shanter</title>. In 1864 he moved to London but returned after five years to Gatehouse-of-Fleet. In 1899 he became President of the Kirkcudbright Fine Art Association.</p> <p>James Faed showed himself as a fairly dextrous young man, able to make toys, musical instruments, salmon-flies, guns and boats. On the death of their father in 1843, he went to Edinburgh to join John and Thomas, helping John to do miniatures. He painted in oil and water-colour, and was an engraver. He did landscape, portrait miniatures, genre, and portraits. He went on to become the finest mezzotinter of his time. In 1850 he was invited by Queen Victoria to engrave Winterhalter's picture of <title>The Queen and Prince Arthur</title>. He moved to London but was back in Scotland in 1855.</p> <p>John Faed died in Kirkcudbright on 22 October 1902, and James Faed died in Edinburgh on 23 September 1911.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: a letter from John Faed talking of 'a little relaxation - not at all for the purpose of art' and how his first work on returning will be '<title>Kilmeny</title> and the other picture'. There is also a cutting of <title>The eve of Flodden</title> and illustration by Faed; and, a letter of James Faed from Comely Bank, Edinburgh, with instructions about what must be done to a piece of work, including a sketch to illustrate the instruction.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Among miscellaneous Scottish letters, purchased Ed. Hall, October 1975, Accession no. E75.50.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) McEwan, Peter J. M. <title>Dictionary of Scottish art and architecture</title>. Woodbridge, Suffolk: Antique Collectors' Club, 1994.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show a reference to John Faed related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter to Lumb Stocks, engraver, with detailed suggestions for the revision of some plates, 10 September 1857, at Dc.4.101-103.</p> <p>The Archives Hub also contains a description of the Edinburgh University Library collection entitled <title>Letters of Thomas Faed R.A. (1826-1900)</title>, also housed within the Special Collections Division.</p> </relatedmaterial> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Artists</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Engravers</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Faed</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1819-1902</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Artist</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Faed</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1821-1911 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Artist</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
