<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-741" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-741</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of the Rev. Professor William Manson (1882-1958)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 9 09:46:55 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-741</unitid> <physloc>MSS MAN</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Rev. Professor William Manson (1882-1958)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1911-1953">1911-1953</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>circa 3,580 pages manuscript, circa 1,285 pages typescript material, miscellaneous notebooks, circa 370 pages off-prints and printed material, and miscellaneous cards, fragments, cuttings, folders and files. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Manson, William</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>William Manson was born on 14 April 1882. He studied at Glasgow University, and Oriel College, Oxford. He studied Theology at the United Free College (later Trinity College), Glasgow, and was ordained in 1911. He ministered in Oban 1911-1914, and at Pollockshields East, Glasgow. He was appointed to the Chair of New Testament Language and Literature, at Knox College, Toronto, Canada, in 1919. Manson then held the Chair of New Testament at New College, Edinburgh University from 1925 to 1946, and then the Chair of Biblical Criticism from 1946 to 1952. Between 1950 and 1952 he was Vice-President of the British Council of Churches. His publications included <title>Jesus the Messiah</title> (1943), <title>The epistle to the Hebrews</title> (1951), and <title>The way of the cross</title> (1958). The Rev. Professor William Manson died on 4 April 1958.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of: formal lectures and notes on the Apocalypse, Christianity, Eschatology, Greek Bible and Language, Jesus, the Jewish people, Mark, Moses, Peter, St. Paul, the Resurrection, and the Synoptic Gospels, and much more; informal lectures and addresses on a variety of topics ; sermons and sermon fragments based on Genesis, Exodus, Samuel, the Psalms, Isaiah, Matthew, Mark, Luke, John, Romans, Corinthians, and Revelation; prayers of intercession, for world peace, communion, funeral service, Polish protestants, and more; reviews; extracts and notes from work of others; and, miscellaneous material. In MAN0606A there is a thesis, <title>The faith and theology of William Manson</title> by Kenneth S. Barker, Knox College, Toronto, Canada. There is also a mounted photograph of Manson, by Drummond Young, at MAN06-43</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>The papers have been arranged in six sections, MAN01 Formal lectures, MAN02 Informal lectures and address, MAN03-01 to -04 Sermons, MAN03-05 Prayers, MAN04 Reviews, and MAN05 Extracts and notes from work of others.</p> </arrangement> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1951-1960</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1961.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence with publishers, 1923-1931, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Dep 247 342 NRA 20220 Clark</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theology</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theologians</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Manson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1882-1958</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Theologian</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">New College (Edinburgh University)</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
