<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-780" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-780</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Records and Papers relating to Anglican-Presbyterian Relations, 1961-1966</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Mar 30 10:13:42 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-780</unitid> <physloc>MSS ANG. 1.1-6; MSS ANG. 2.1-2; MSS ANG. 3.1-4; MSS ANG. 3.1.1-19; MSS ANG. 4.1-2; MSS ANG. 5.1-3</physloc><unittitle>Records and Papers relating to Anglican-Presbyterian Relations, 1961-1966</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1947-1967">1947-1967</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>circa 40 files or volumes or bundles. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Church of Scotland: General Assembly; Church of England; Presbyterian Church of England; Anglican-Presbyterian Conversations; Henderson, Ian; Sanderson, Roy; Torrance, T. F; Turner, H. E. W; Philip, Randall; Manson, William; Overlach, Guenther</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> and <language langcode="ger">German.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Today, within the Church of Scotland, the Ecumenical Relations Committee is responsible for (according to Church of Scotland Online) encouraging and enabling an ecumenical vision in Scotland. Working in teams, through liaison, local involvement, communication and resources, members of the Ecumenical Relations Committee seek to encourage ecumenical engagement through the boards, committees, presbyteries and congregations of the Church of Scotland. They promote understanding through ecumenical engagement at international and European levels. There has been a long history of this work, and the reports and special meetings of the Inter-Church Relations Committee of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland in the 1950s and 1960s, and participation in the Anglican-Presbyterian Conversations in the 1960s has been an early component of this engagement.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: Anglican-Presbyterian Conversations, the Church, Community and State Group, 1963-1964; documents presented to the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland, including Reports of the Inter-Church Relations Committee, 1957-1966; minutes of meetings, the General Assembly's Special Committee on Anglican-Presbyterian relations, 1960-1966; minutes of meetings, the Convener's Committee, Special Committee on Anglican-Presbyterian relations, 1960-1965; minutes of meetings, the Joint Standing Committee, Anglican-Presbyterian Conversations, 1962-1965; miscellaneous material from the Church of England, the Presbyterian Church of England, sources of the Presbyterian Church in Ireland, and papers from the Anglican-Presbyterian Conference, Durham, July 1962.</p> <p>The material also includes address lists, and lists of members of committees, 1962-1966, and general correspondence, 1960-1967.</p> <p>There are papers read at meetings, arranged alphabetically by author, and material from Regional Groups of the Anglican-Presbyterian Conversations (Glasgow, London, North of England, Scottish Group, Edinburgh Group), material from Subcommittees of the Anglican-Presbyterian Conversations (Apostolic Succession, Ministerial Order, Open Communion, Doctrine of Holy Communion, and Unity and Uniformity), and miscellaneous newspaper cuttings.</p> <p>The collection includes papers, theses, and addresses, on various topics within ecumenism including work by Ian Henderson, Roy Sanderson, T. F. Torrance, and H. E. W. Turner, given between 1960 and 1963, on the meaning of unity, apostolic succession, non-theological factors in relations between the churches, lay difficulties about union, survey of the task, the recognition of ministries, reconciliation, and Holy Communion.</p> <p>There are also reports from Church of Scotland presbyteries regarding the Special Committee on Anglican-Presbyterian relations statements, <title>Viewpoint of the Church of Scotland</title> and <title>Unity and uniformity</title> 1964-1965, and a file belonging to Sir Randall Philip Q.C., including reports, correspondence etc., 1954-1957.</p> <p>In addition there is a thesis submitted at Heidelberg, 1969, by Guenther Overlach, <title>Die Unionsgespraeche der kirche von Schottland mit der kirche von England .. seit 1930</title>, author's files of additional material in German and in English, papers on inter-church relations, 1947-1951, Professor William Manson, and an annotated typescript of the English translation of Overlach's thesis by Harold Knight.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Church of Scotland. Boards and Committees. Contacts and information</title>. Full-text [online]. <extref href="http://www.churchofscotland.org.uk/boards/ecumenical/ecumenical.htm">Ecumenical relations</extref> [Accessed 14 January 2004].</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Christian union</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Henderson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Ian</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Sanderson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Roy</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Torrance</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Thomas Forsyth</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1913</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Turner</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Henry Ernest William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1927-1969</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Theologian </emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Philip</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James Randall</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1900-1957</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Barrister and Public Servant</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Manson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1882-1958</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Theologian</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Overlach</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Guenther</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1969</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of England</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Presbyterian Church of England</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Presbyterian Church in Ireland</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Anglican-Presbyterian Conversations</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
