<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-60" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-60</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Archives of the Scottish Students' Song Book Committee Ltd. </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-60</unitid> <physloc>MSS 3172-3185 </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Archives of the Scottish Students' Song Book Committee Ltd. </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1891-1997">1891-1997 </unitdate> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>4 boxes; 26 song books; 3 ledgers; 1 engraved copper plate; 1 folder of certificates. </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>The Scottish Students' Song Book Committee was set up in December 1889 with the aim of producing a collection of songs for use by students. The lack of such a collection had long been felt in Scotland. In the mid-1880s a committee had been set up in St. Andrews to collect and publish the songs popular among the students there. This had met with difficulties however, and instead it was agreed to abandon the scheme and to prepare an Inter-University Song Book under the auspices of the then four Scottish Students' Representative Councils. With the less than enthusiastic support of the four SSRCs, the Scottish Students' Song Book Committee set about its task under the editorial convenership of Dr. Millar Patrick. <title>The Scottish Students' Song Book </title> went on sale in March 1891 and was an immediate success, selling out in three weeks. Later editions appeared in 1892 and 1897. The great success of the book made it necessary to form a limited company in 1891 - the Scottish Students' Song Book Committee Ltd. - which had throughout the 20th century produced several editions of the <title>Song Book </title> and its companion <title>The British Students' Song Book </title> (1912). Since 1891, some 400,000 copies had been sold. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The archives of the Scottish Students' Song Book Committee contain administrative records and miscellaneous items, including the memorandum and articles of the Committee, minute books, ledgers, administrative correspondence, folders of financial records, photographs; art-work for an illustrated edition; and, an engraved copper plate for printing shareholders certificates. The archive also includes printed material, mainly <title>The Scottish Students' Song Book </title> in various editions, as well as <title>The British Students' Song Book </title> in 1st, 2nd, and Revised editions, and other song books. </p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details </p> </accessrestrict> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Patrick</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Millar</emph> </persname> <corpname encodinganalog="marc 610"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Students&apos; Song Book Committee Ltd.</emph> </corpname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Students&apos; songs</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Songbooks</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H60 </p> </otherfindaid> </archdesc>
</ead>
