<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-650" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-650</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Professor Alan J. Steele (b. 1916)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu May 1 10:16:32 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-650</unitid> <physloc>E91.62; E92.24; E93.59; E95.45</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor Alan J. Steele (b. 1916)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box containing 7 folders, miscellaneous typescript documents and pamphlets, articles etc. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Steele, Alan John</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> and <language langcode="fre">French.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Alan John Steele was born in Bellshill, Lanarkshire, on 11 April 1916. He was educated at the Royal Grammar School in Newcastle-upon-Tyne, and at Blyth Secondary School. He studied at Edinburgh University and at Grenoble and in Paris. He graduated from Edinburgh with First Class Honours in French Language and Literature. During the Second World War he served at sea with the Maritime AA Regiment, Royal Artillery, and in Algeria, Italy, and Greece. In 1946 Steele was appointed as an Assistant in French at Edinburgh University, and he became a Lecturer in 1947, and Senior Lecturer in 1960. He was a Director of Studies from 1949 to 1960. In 1961 he became Professor of French at Edinburgh University. His publications include <title>Three centuries of French verse, 1511-1819</title> (1956).</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers are composed of: <title>Elegie</title>; papers relating to the teaching of language; reviews including off-prints; obituaries; addresses and talks; lectures; off-prints; translation of Tam O'Shanter entitled <title>La chevauchee de Jacques Bonhomme</title>; typescript poems; and, texts of pamphlets, articles, and addresses.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>The material was acquired from Professor Steele, July 1991, Accession no. E91.62. Translation of Tam O'Shanter, acquired from Professor Steele, January 1992, Accession no. E92.24. Typscript poems, acquired from Professor Steele, June 1993, Accession no. E93.59. Texts of pamphlets etc., acquired from Professor Steele, July 1995, Accession no. E95.45.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>Items at E92.24, E93.59, and E95.45 had not been checked at the time of creating this description. The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 20. 1961-1962. p.97. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1962. (2) <title>Who's who 1987</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1987.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show a few references to Steele related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter from Professor Gordon Donaldson, 1963, in Gen. 1730 onwards; and, letter from Professor J. Orr, 1963, at Gen. 2180/14/1.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">French language</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">French literature</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Language and languages</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Steele</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alan John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">b. 1916</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of French</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
