<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-625" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-625</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Correspondence of Samuel Solomonovich Koteliansky (1880-1955)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Apr 7 14:09:18 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-625</unitid> <physloc>E93.3</physloc><unittitle>Correspondence of Samuel Solomonovich Koteliansky (1880-1955)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1929-1933">1929-1933</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>circa 14 letters</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Koteliansky, Samuel S.</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Samuel Solomonovich Koteliansky was born in 1880. His translations of nineteenth century Russian writers first started to appear in the 1920s. He translated some of the so-called 'untranslatable' and extremely difficult Russian texts including the diaries, personal letters and notebooks of Anton Chekhov and others. He also translated I. A. Bunin and Fyodor Dostoevsky. Samuel Solomonovich Koteliansky died in 1955.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The correspondence consists of autographed letters from Koteliansky to Sir Sidney Philip Waterlow referring to much in the literature of the period including reference to D. H. Lawrence, H. G. Wells, Evelyn Waugh, and Aldous Huxley.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material purchased from M. Silverman, London, March 1993, Accession no. E93.3.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection and from patches of online information.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence and papers, 1914-1950, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MSS 48966-75 52923 58372 60489; correspondence (57 items) with the Hogarth Press, Reading University Library, Ref. MS2750; and, letters to Leonard Woolf, 1929-1931, Sussex University Library Special Collections, Ref. SxMs 13/Pt III NRA 42924 Woolf.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph> <emph altrender="z">20th century</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Koteliansky</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Samuel Solomonovich</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1880-1955</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Translator</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Waterlow</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Sydney Philip</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1878-1944</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Diplomat</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
