<?xml version="1.0"?> <!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd"> <ead> <eadheader> <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-1054">GB 237 Coll-1054</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of the Logie Family of Ministers (1768-1948)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <publicationstmt><publisher>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections</publisher> <address> <addressline>George Square</addressline> <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline> <addressline>Scotland</addressline> <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> </address> <date type="single" normal="20050701" certainty="certain">01 July 2005</date> </publicationstmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>EAD generated XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation> <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="ENG">English</language></langusage><descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions compiled in line with the following standards: <bibref> <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards</corpname>, <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard Archival Description</title>, <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint><date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date></imprint> </bibref> and <bibref> <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname><title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate Names</title>, <imprint><date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date></imprint></bibref></descrules> </profiledesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1054"> <did> <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-1054</unitid> <physloc label="Shelfmark" encodinganalog="shelfmark">E2005.08</physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312">Papers of the Logie Family of Ministers (1768-1948)</unittitle><unitdate normal="1790/1940" encodinganalog="isadg(2)313">1790-1940</unitdate><repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="NAHSTE31">Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections</repository> <physdesc label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description" encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" audience="external"> <extent type="linear" unit="metre">4 boxes, unsorted</extent></physdesc> <langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial> <origination label="Name of Creator(s)" encodinganalog="isadg(2)321">Logie, William; Logie, William, Logie, Robert Scarth Valentine</origination> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322"> <head>Administrative/Biographical History</head> <p>The Rev. Dr. William Logie was born in Kirkwall on 23 February 1786, the son of Alexander Logie, a Kirkwall merchant. He was educated at Kirkwall School and the studied at Edinburgh University. Logie was licensed by the Presbytery of Kirkwall in 1809 and he was ordained at Lady Kirk on 25 April 1811. On 22 March 1814 he married Elizabeth Scarth of Kirkwall, and the pair had nine children. He received the degree of D.D. from Edinburgh University on 25 March 1854. The Rev. Dr. William Logie (Senior) died on 5 September 1856. His wife died on 6 January 1862. </p> <p>William Logie, third and youngest son of the Rev. Dr. William Logie (Senior) was born on 19 March 1824. He was educated in Kirkwall, and then studied at Edinburgh University where he graduated with the degree of B.A. in 1843. Logie was licensed by the Presbytery of Kirkwall in 1845. On 3 August 1847 he married Helen Scott Brown of Inverbervie, Kincardineshire, and the pair had eight children. He received the degree of D.D. from Glasgow University in 1863. The Rev. Dr. William Logie (Junior) died on 5 January 1878. His wife died on 26 September 1890. </p> <p>Robert Scarth Valentine Logie, fourth and youngest son of the Rev. Dr. William Logie (Junior) was born on 15 April 1868. He was the twin brother of Helen Euphemia Logie. He studied at Edinburgh University, receiving the degree of M.A. in 1890. Logie was licensed to preach in 1894, and was an assistant at St. Paul's, Perth, St. Bernard's, Edinburgh, and at Kelvinhaugh. He was Minister at Rickarton, Fordoun (near Stonehaven), Kincardineshire, and at Aberdalgie and Dupplin, Perth. He married twice - firstly to Jean Elliot Turnbull in 1906 with whom he had two sons, and then secondly, after the death of Jean in 1915, to Ethel Margaret Theresa Masson in 1917 with whom he had another son. The Rev. Robert Scarth Valentine Logie died on 9 November 1948. His second wife died on 26 February 1920.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331"> <head>Scope and Content</head> <p>The collection, as yet unsorted, is composed of : the manuscript preaching journal of Robert Scarth Valentine Logie and circa 100 sewn sheafs of manuscript notes - sermons; a catalogue of 468 discourses, or sermons, of William Logie (Senior), and accompanying manuscript sermon notes, together with a manuscript sermon preached in Lady Kirk, Kirkwall, 18 January 1816, for the National Thanksgiving 1816, the day appointed for thanksgiving after the final defeat of Napoleon Bonaparte (transcript copy also); sermon notes of William Logie (Junior); and, miscellaneous manuscript notes</p> <p>The collection also includes printed material: <list> <item><title>Acts of the General Assembly against profanities ... 1694</title></item> <item><title>The principal acts of the General Assembly ... May 18, 1843</title></item> <item><title>Sermons, by the Rev, George Goldie </title></item> <item><title>The Church of Scotland year-book 1913</title></item> <item><title>A ... summary of the laws and regulations of the Church of Scotland</title></item> <item><title>Whole service as conducted in the High Church of Glasgow</title></item> <item><title>The precher's commentary. A homiletic commentary ...</title></item> </list> ... of which the latter there are 13 issues.</p> <p>There is also a copy of <title>Cases decided in the Court of Session [...] Court of Teinds [...] and in the Court of Justiciary</title> which includes the Kirkwall manse process on p.546, at which the Rev. W. Logie was the Charger. There is a document inserted into the volume relevant to the case too.</p> <p>The collection also contains manuscript volumes written by the Logie family. There is: a book of essays read before the Orkney Literary Society, 1803-04; a book of cash received 1824; a roll of the parishioners of Kirkwall and St. Ola attending St. Magnus' Church, 1825-26; sacramental exercises, 1829; a list of new communicants, 1825, and other notes; and, a volume of various notes of William Logie, 1809.</p> </scopecontent> <!--Delete any tags not required--><descgrp> <head>Administrative Information</head> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341"> <head>Conditions Governing Access</head> <p>Open to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345"> <head>Other Finding Aids</head> <p>None prepared.</p> </otherfindaid> <note encodinganalog="isadg(2)361" audience="external"> <!--General notes--> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Scott, Hew. <title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scoticanae</title>. Vol.7. 1928. pp.224-225. (2) Scott, Hew. <title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scoticanae. The succession of ministers in the Church of Scotland from the Reformation</title>. Vol.1. Synod of Lothian and Tweeddale. 1915. p.362. (3) Scott, Hew. <title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scoticanae. The succession of ministers in the Church of Scotland from the Reformation</title>. Vol.4. 1923. p.195. (4) Scott, Hew. <title>Fasti Ecclesiae Scoticanae. The succession of ministers in the Church of Scotland from the Reformation</title>. Vol.8. 1950. p.360.</p> </note> <processinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)371"> <head>Archivist's Notes</head> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections.</p> </processinfo></descgrp> <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38"> <head>Index</head> <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381"> <head>Subjects</head> <!-- LCSH --> <subject source="lcsh"><emph altrender="a">Sermons</emph></subject> <subject><emph>Church records and registers</emph></subject> </controlaccess> <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE382"> <head>People</head> <!-- NCA Rules --> <persname rules="ncarules"><emph altrender="surname">Logie</emph><emph altrender="title">Rev. Dr.</emph><emph altrender="forename">William</emph><emph altrender="dates">1786-1856</emph><emph altrender="epithet">Minister</emph><emph altrender="other"></emph></persname> <persname><emph altrender="surname">Logie</emph><emph altrender="title">Rev. Dr.</emph><emph altrender="forename">William</emph><emph altrender="dates">1824-1878</emph><emph altrender="epithet">Minister</emph></persname> <persname><emph altrender="surname">Logie</emph><emph altrender="title">Rev.</emph><emph altrender="forename">Robert Scarth Valentine</emph><emph altrender="dates">1868-1948</emph><emph altrender="epithet">Minister</emph></persname> </controlaccess> <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE384"> <head>Places</head> <!-- LCSH --> <geogname source="lcsh"><emph altrender="a">Kirkwall (Scotland)</emph></geogname> </controlaccess> </controlaccess> </archdesc> </ead> 