<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-862" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-862</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of Sir Thomas Watson (1792-1882)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Sep 15 11:55:59 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-862</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 2042/47-48</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Sir Thomas Watson (1792-1882)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1840-1854">1840-1854</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Watson, Thomas</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Thomas Watson was born in 1792. He studied medicine in London and Edinburgh, and obtained his M.D. at Cambridge in 1825. Watson became a leading physician in London, 1825-1870. He was physician to Middlesex Hospital, London, 1827-1843, and was a Professor at University College, London, 1828-1831, and at King's College, London, 1831-1840. He was created a Baronet in 1866. Sir Thomas Watson died in 1882.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of letters written by Watson from Henrietta Street (presumably in London) and from Arbroath. One of the letters points out that he was 'taken by a telegraphic summons to Liverpool' and that his 'yesterday's patients here were neglected or postponed'. The letter was subsequently enclosed and sent to another with the lines signed by James Bright. The other letter refers to 'verses written by Alex Smart - author of Rambling Rhymes in the lunatic asylum Morningside, Edinburgh'.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: case book, 1853-1856, Wellcome Library for the History and Understanding of Medicine, Ref. MS 4978.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physicians</emph> </subject> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Watson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Thomas</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1792-1882</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">1st Baronet Physician</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
