<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-268" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-268</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Mark Aleksandrovich Aldanov (1889-1957)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Aug 15 11:40:42 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-268</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 565</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Mark Aleksandrovich Aldanov (1889-1957)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1921-1957">1921-1957</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>ca. 350 letters and postcards. </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Aldanov, Mark Aleksandrovich; Landau, Mark Aleksandrovich</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="rus">Russian.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Mark Aleksandrovich Aldanov was born on 7 November 1889 in Kiev in the Ukraine. He lived in St. Petersburg, but in 1919 he left the new Communist Russia for France before moving to the United States in 1941. As a writer he is best known for work bitterly critical of the Soviet system. His publications include <title>Two revolutions</title> (1921) which was a work comparing the Russian and French revolutions, a tetralogy on revolutionary France <title>Myslitel</title> (1923-25), a scientific treatise <title>Actinic chemistry</title> (1936), an anti-Soviet satire <title>Nachalo kontsa</title> (1939), and <title>Istoki</title> (1947) which was a picture of Europe in the 1870s. His works have been translated into some twenty-four languages. Mark Aleksandrovich Aldanov (M. A. Landau) died in Nice, in the south of France, on 25 February 1957.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers of Mark Aleksandrovich Landau consist of correspondence (over 200 letters and over 40 postcards) to Ivan A. Bunin (1870-1953), the Russian novelist and Nobel Prize winner, 1933, between 1921 and 1953. There are also over 100 letters and postcards from Landau and his wife to Mrs. I. A. Bunin, 1921-1957; letters to Vera Bunin, 1930-1948; letters to Vera Bunin, 1932-1955, with telegrams, cards and photo; and, letters 1948-1952.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Papers purchased April 1962 from L. Zuroff, Paris, Accession no. E62.17. Papers received from Dr. M. Greene, Department of Russian, March 1972, later 1972, and October 1977, Accession no. E72.17 and E72.40 and E.77.34.</p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1951-1960. A companion to Who's who</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1961.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: letters to Boris Elkin (130 leaves), 1939-1957, Oxford University, Bodleian Library, Special Collections and Western Manuscripts, Ref. MS Russian d 7 NRA 20351 Elkin</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Aldanov</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Mark Aleksandrovich</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1886-1957</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Writer </emph> </persname> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Landau</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Mark Aleksandrovich</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1886-1957</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Writer</emph> </persname> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Bunin</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Ivan Alekseevich</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1870-1953</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Poet and Novelist</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
