<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-352" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-352</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Abraham Guyot (fl. 1792)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Apr 11 12:06:41 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-352</unitid> <physloc>Dc.3.104/2; Dc.6.111, ff.6-9, 95</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Abraham Guyot (fl. 1792)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1792-1793">1792-1793</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>4 manuscript letters or documents. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="fre">French.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>A passport issued by the Municipality of Paris noted that Abraham Guyot in 1792 was aged forty-nine years, born perhaps around 1743. He had come from the Neuchatel district of Switzerland.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: a letter to Dugald Stewart, 1793; a passport of the Municipality of Paris in favour of Guyot, 1792; sonnets by Guyot; and a certificate of citizenship of Vallangin, Switzerland, 1793.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show another reference to Guyot related material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters to T. Beddoes, President of the Natural History Society of Edinburgh, 1786, and to John Walker, Professor of Natural History at Edinburgh University, 1794.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Poetry</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Guyot</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Abraham </emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1792</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Swiss</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
