<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-601" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-601</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Isabel Fleming (fl. 1940) and Jessie Service (fl. 1950)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 3 10:43:54 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-601</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 7</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Isabel Fleming (fl. 1940) and Jessie Service (fl. 1950)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1923-1955">1923-1955</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 file (4 items)</extent> </physdesc> <origination>Fleming, Isabel N; Service, Jessie W. </origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Isabel N. Fleming, M.A., was a Church of Scotland missionary in Manchuria, China and, for a time, in Livingstonia, Malawi. She first went to China in 1923 and worked as a science teacher at Moukden Medical College where she later became warden of the Women's Student Hostel. Along with the other Manchurian missionaries she was forced to leave China in 1942 and, instead of returning to the UK, she went straight to Livingstonia, Malawi where she was based from 1942-1945. She returned to Manchuria in 1947 and later, after she left China for the last time, lived in Edinburgh. Her good friend Jessie Wilson Service went to Manchuria with the Church of Scotland as an evangelist in 1931. She spent some time working in the north of Manchuria and, at the end of 1939, returned to Moukden as YWCA General Secretary. Like Fleming she was in Livingstonia between 1942 and 1945, returning to Manchuria in 1947. She also worked in Livingstonia from 1953 to 1956 then returned to Edinburgh where she died. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of: diary entries by Fleming describing her arrival and early travel in China (c 1923-1925); memoirs by Fleming and Service describing the months around Pearl Harbour and missionary internment and evacuation (cover 1937-1942); and notes by Fleming on how God reveals Himself (1955).</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>The material is arranged as above. The diary pages are loose and were not in order, as far as possible they have now been arranged in date order.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>The Church of Scotland deposited with the Centre several collections relating to missionaries in China and these papers probably formed part of this deposit.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>None expected.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material: (1) the collection itself, (2) Fulton, Austin. <title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title>. Edinburgh: The Saint Andrew Press, 1967.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The archives of the foreign missions of the Church of Scotland are held by the National Library of Scotland. They contain correspondence with both women. Several other collections relating to Manchuria have been deposited in the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World. Austin Fulton in <title>Through Earthquake Wind and Fire</title> (Edinburgh: The Saint Andrew Press, 1967) describes the missionary work in Manchuria and includes a list of sources.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Fleming</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Isabel N.</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Service</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Jessie W.</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Manchuria (China)</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
