<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-859" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-859</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Material relating to Sir Patrick Walker (fl. 1790-1835), Baronet</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Sep 13 11:53:40 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-859</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 2042/27-31</physloc><unittitle>Material relating to Sir Patrick Walker (fl. 1790-1835), Baronet</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1822-1833">1822-1833</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>5 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Walker, Patrick</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Sir Patrick Walker was an Advocate living in the Drumsheugh area of Edinburgh in 1828-1830.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of: letter from Cte. O'Hegerty at Hollyrood House, Edinburgh, to Walker, indicating that 'Cte. O'Hegerty and few others of the king's attendants will accept the offers of Sir Patrick, and will be tomorrow at eleven o'clock in the Gallery'; letter to Sir Patrick Walker at Drumsheugh, from Viscount Valletort, requesting his 'presence to attend the Funeral of the Right Honorable Lady Caroline Anne Macdonald of Clanranald' in the Chapel Royal, Holyrood, April 1824; letter from Sir Herbert Taylor at Windsor Castle indicating that a letter of Walker's has been submitted to the King, 1832; covering letter of introduction, 1833, from the numismatist and politician John Brodribb Bergne (1800-1873); and, letter from S. Shepherd, 1822. </p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection, and the Edinburgh and Leith Post Office Directory.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show various references to Walker related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter to A. Steele about books and papers left by Dr. J. Walker and their possible publication, 1823, at La.II.509; letters (2) to D. Laing about plays performed in Scotland before James VI and Charles I, 1827, at La.IV.17; letter to R. Stevenson, at Gen. 1429/5, no. 3; letter from Henry Erskine, 1790, at Gen. 1995/25; letter from the Duke of Atholl about a commission of arbitration in the Isle of Man, 1795, at Gen. 1995/2; letter from the Marquess of Lothian, 1813, at Gen. 1995/49; letter from Viscount Melville, 1820, at Gen. 1982/46; letter from N. Knowlys, at Gen. 1982/12; letter from the Earl of Rosebery about opening Cramond Bridge, 1824, at Gen. 1983/72, and an invitation at Gen. 1982/87; letter from W. C. Pettigrew about the Coronation Roll, at Gen. 1982/85; letters (2) from Sir Robert Liston about well boring, at Gen. 1995/46-48; letter from le Duc de Blacas, 1831, at Gen. 1995/10; letter from the Duke of Gordon, 1835, at Gen. 1995/28; letter from William Dundas of Arniston, at Gen. 1995/22; letter from Sir John Sinclair, at Gen. 1983/96; and, mention of a proposed memoir of Walker in a letter of Dr. R. Hamilton to W. H. Lizars, at Dk.6.20/134.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Walker</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Patrick</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1790-1835</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Advocate</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">19th century</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
