<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-408" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-408</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Lectures of William Leechman (1706-1785)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Jul 17 14:40:42 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-408</unitid> <physloc>Dc.7.86; Dc.8.119</physloc><unittitle>Lectures of William Leechman (1706-1785)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1761-1770">1761-1770</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 manuscript volumes. </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Leechman, William; Stirling, Robert</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>William Leechman was born in 1706 at Dolphinton, Lanarkshire. He was educated at the local school until the Baillie family - in gratitude for the cutting down of the executed body of Baillie of Jerviswood (d. 1684) by Leechman's father - helped him to attend Edinburgh University and the study of Divinity. He graduated in 1724. He then became a tutor to James Geddes (died circa 1748) and to William Mure of Caldwell, Ayrshire. Leechman was licensed to preach by the Presbytery of Paisley in 1731 and he was ordained Minister of Beith in 1736. In 1743 he was elected Professor of Divinty at Glasgow University. In 1744 the Presbytery of Glasgow accused him of making heretical statements in a sermon <title>On the nature, reasonableness, and advantages of prayer</title> (1743). In 1757, Leechman was Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland, and in 1761 he was appointed Principal of Glasgow University. William Leechman died on 3 December 1785. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The lectures are composed of <title>Observations on the truth of the Christian religion taken from the lectures of Dr L. at Glasgow</title>, 1761, and <title>Lectures on composition by the Reverend Mr. Leechman</title>, 1770.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography.</title>. London: Vol. 11. Kennett-Lluelyn, 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show another reference to Leechman related material (check the Indexes for more details): a letter to J. Sharpe, 1781, at La.II.99. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence with Edmund Burke, 1783-1785, Sheffield Archives, Ref. WWM NRA 1083 Wentworth Woodhouse; letters to Mure family, 1736-1776, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 4941-46 passim; and, letters (40) to Joshua Sharpe relating to university finance, 1762-1785, Glasgow University Library, Special Collections Department, Ref. MS Murray 659.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Leechman</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1706-1785</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Principal of Glasgow University</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Stirling</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Robert</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Glasgow University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
