<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-295" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-295</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Professor James Beattie (1735-1803)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Oct 24 09:23:20 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-295</unitid> <physloc>Dc.2.63-65; Dc.8.28; Dc.5.116-117; Dk.3.2, pp.201-209; Dk.5.28</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor James Beattie (1735-1803)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1760-1809">[ca. 1760-1803]</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>7 volumes. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The poet, essayist and moral philosopher, James Beattie, was born in Laurencekirk, Kincardineshire, on 25 October 1735. He studied at Marischal College, Aberdeen, studying Greek and taking the degree of M.A. in 1753. After graduation he took up the post of schoolmaster and parish clerk at Fordoun, near Laurencekirk, and began writing and contributing to the <title>Scots Magazine</title>. Attendance at divinity lectures followed, again at Marischal College, and in 1758 he became a schoolmaster at Aberdeen Grammar School. To his surprise, in 1760, he was elected to the Chair of Moral Philosophy and Logic at Marischal College (now part of Aberdeen University). Beattie's publications include <title>Original poems and translations</title> (1761), <title>Essay on truth</title> (1770), <title>The Minstrel</title> (1771), <title>Evidences of the Christian religion</title> (1786), and the two volumes of <title>Elements of moral science</title> (1790 and 1793). Beattie declined the vacant Chair of Moral Philosophy at Edinburgh University in 1773. After a long illness which struck him in April 1799, Professor James Beattie died on 18 August 1803.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers in the collection include: lectures on moral philosophy at Marischal College, 1777-1778, at Dc.64-65; observations on logic, at Dk.3.2, pp.201-209; principles of natural religion, 1778, at Dc.2.63; a view of the practical part of the moral philosophy of the Stoics, 1778, at Dc.8.28; a volume of poems including <title>The Minstrel</title>, at Dk.5.28; and, notes of lectures on pneumatology and ethics at Marischal College, 1760, at Dc.5.116-117. </p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.2. Beal-Browell. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Beattie related material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letter to a bookseller in Edinburgh, 1783, at La.II.589; salary receipt, 1767-1768, at La.II.152; recommendation, 1771, at La.II.588; and, Latin epitaphs at La.II.417. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence and biographical papers, 1761-1802, at the National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Acc 4796 NRA 29136, and letters to Aaron Lithgow, 1758-1767, Ref. MS.2543 ff.1-13; correspondence and papers, Aberdeen University, Special Libraries and Archives , Ref. MS 30; and, letters (12), 1774-1792, at the Huntington Library.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ethics</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Stoics</emph> </subject> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Beattie</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1735-1803</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Poet </emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Aberdeen University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
