<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-552" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-552</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Lectures of Geoffrey D. Carnall</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Apr 7 11:57:55 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> Revised <date> July 10 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-552</unitid> <physloc>E87.58; E95.48</physloc><unittitle>Lectures of Geoffrey D. Carnall</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1960-1969">1960-24 January 1969</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 folder, miscellaneous bundles of typescript, 1 envelope with lectures. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Carnall, Geoffrey D.</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Geoffrey D. Carnall has taken the degrees of M.A. and B.Litt. He was appointed as a Lecturer in English Literature at Edinburgh University in 1960 and continues to be (in 2003) an Honorary Fellow at The School of Literatures, Languages and Cultures. In 1969, Carnall initiated, with Martin Pollock, the then Professor of Molecular Biology, a teach-in at Edinburgh University on the topic of Chemical and Biological Warfare (a teach-in being 'a prolonged and public discussion on a matter of national concern' and a concept originally growing out of the nature and conduct of the Vietnam War). Key experts came to Edinburgh, including a Government Minister and senior staff from the Research Establishment at Porton Down. Mr. Tam Dalyell (elected Edinburgh University Rector in 2003) was also present as a speaker, as was Mr. V. G. Filatov, a Counsellor at the (then) Soviet Embassy. Carnall has published <title>Robert Southey and his age: the development of a conservative mind</title> (1960), <title>Robert Southey</title> (1964), and <title>To keep the peace</title> (1965). He co-edited <title>The Impeachment of Warren Hastings: papers from a bicentenary commemoration</title> (1989), and he edited and completed John Butt's <title>The mid-eighteenth century</title> (1979) and Marjorie Sykes <title>An Indian tapestry: Quaker threads in the history of India, Pakistan and Bangladesh; from the seventeenth century to independence</title> (1997). With others he was involved in <title>The representation of business in English literature</title> (2000). He has also published many essays.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of lectures on rhetoric, 1960-1964, and, transcript and correspondence on a teach-in on chemical and biological warfare, 24 January 1969, tape transcripts.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Warfare lecture, acquired from G. D. Carnall, April 1987, Accession no. E87.58. Lectures, rhetoric, acquired from G. D. Carnall, July 1995, Accession no. E95.48.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using freely available online information, and the following published material: (1) <title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol.20. 1961-1962. p.8. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1962. (2) <title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol.24. 1969-1970. pp.90-91. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1970.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Rhetoric</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English literature</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Chemical warfare</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Biological warfare</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Weapons of mass destruction</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Carnall</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Geoffrey D.</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1960-2000</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Honorary Fellow at Edinburgh University</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
