<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-258" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-258</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Lectures and Correspondence of Sir Ludovic J. Grant (1862-1936)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Jul 23 15:47:32 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-258</unitid> <physloc>Dk.6.8; Gen. 145/2/198, 202</physloc><unittitle>Lectures and Correspondence of Sir Ludovic J. Grant (1862-1936)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1890-1922">1890-1922</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box, 2 letters. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Ludovic James Grant was born on 4 September 1862 and was the eldest son of Sir Alexander Grant (1826-1884), Principal of Edinburgh University. He was educated at Fettes College, Edinburgh, and then studied at Balliol College, Oxford. Grant was called to the Scottish Bar - becoming a Member of the Faculty of Advocates - in 1887 and he became Regius Professor of Public Law at Edinburgh University in 1890. He held the Chair until 1923. During his tenure, the First World War saw an assault on the principles of his subject - public international law. However, with the prospect of a new post-war world order of peace based on the principles of the League of Nations, public international law was invested with renewed importance and the University's course was increased from forty to eighty lectures. Grant was also Secretary of Senatus, 1897-1918, then Secretary of the University, 1918-1919. He was Dean of the Faculty of Law, 1894-1910. Sir Ludovic J. Grant died on 11 February 1936. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of lectures on international law, 1890-1922, manuscript, at Dk.6.8., and letters to Arthur Berriedale Keith, July 1917, typescript, at Gen. 145/2/198, 202.</p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material: (1) Rice, D. Talbot. <title>The university portraits</title>. pp.92-94. Edinburgh: The University Press, 1957. (2) <title>Who was who 1929-1940. A companion to Who's who ...</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1941.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Index to Accessions Since 1987 gives reference to letters from Sir A. Grant to Sir Ludovic J. Grant, at E91.57.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">International law</emph> </subject> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Grant</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Ludovic James </emph> <emph altrender="dates">1862-1937</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Public Law</emph> </persname> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Keith</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Arthur Berriedale</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1879-1944</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Sanskrit Scholar Constitutional Lawyer and Historian</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
