<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-183" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-183 </eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Samuel Rutherford Crockett (1860-1914)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Dec 17 16:40:21 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-183</unitid> <physloc> Gen. 1730 Crockett; Dk.1.3.14; Dc.4.101 Crockett; E90.126; E90.127; E91.4; E93.14 </physloc><unittitle>Papers of Samuel Rutherford Crockett (1860-1914)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1894-1913">1894-1913</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>11 letters, 1 postcard portrait. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The novelist Samuel Rutherford Crockett was born in Little Duchrae, near New Galloway, Kirkcudbrightshire, Scotland, on 24 September 1860. He studied at Edinburgh University, at Heidelberg, and at Edinburgh's New College. He graduated from Edinburgh University in 1879. Crockett entered the Free Church of Scotland in 1886 and was a minister for some years in Penicuik , Midlothian, where he was ordained. With the success of early novels such as <title>The stickit minister</title> (1893) and <title>The lilac sunbonnet</title> (1894) Crockett gave up the ministry for writing and journalism. His work is seen as leading the &quot;Kailyard&quot; or &quot;Kitchen garden&quot; school of writing which sentimentally portrayed Scottish rural life, and utilised the Scots dialect in a manner set by J. M. Barrie (1860-1937). His publications also include <title>The raiders</title> (1894), <title>Red cap tales</title> (1904), <title>The men of the mountain</title> (1909), and <title>The moss troopers</title> (1912). Samuel Rutherford Crockett died in Tarascon, near Avignon, France, on 21 April 1914.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers of Samuel Rutherford Crockett consist largely of correspondence. Content is varied, as are the correspondents, and the letters include those to Ashcroft Noble, mentioning Barrie, Lang, Ian Maclaren, and Stevenson, 1894; to W. K. Dickson, 1895; to I. W. Austin, 1906; to the Rev. William Thomson, 1913; and to bookseller and librarian in Penicuik. There is also a postcard photograph of Crockett. The letters are about the sale of his novels, thanks, requests for loans of books, honour banquet, and illness. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Letter to J. W. Austin received January 1967, Accession no. E67.29. Letter purchased 1972, Accession no. E72.16. Material purchased January 1978, Accession no. E78.1. Letters received February 1979, Accession no. E79.12. Material purchased December 1990, Accession nos. E90.126 and 127. Material purchased January 1991, Accession no. E91.4. Material purchased March 1993, Accession no. E93.14. </p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who. A companion to Who's who...</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1920. (2) <title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Vol.3 Micropaedia. 15th edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica Inc., 1991.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish literature</emph> <emph altrender="z">20th century</emph> </subject> <persname source="othersource"> <emph altrender="surname">Crockett</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Samuel Rutherford</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1860-1914</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Novelist </emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
