<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-423" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-423</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Professor Charles Mackie (1688-1770)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Aug 28 16:47:15 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-423</unitid> <physloc>Dc.1.47; Dc.5.24/1-2; Dc.7.79; Dc.8.24, 50-51; Dk.7.51; MS 2648; Phot.1143</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor Charles Mackie (1688-1770)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1694-1955">1694-1955</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>8 volumes (most manuscript), miscellaneous. </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Mackie, Charles; Sharp, L. W.</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> and <language langcode="lat">Latin.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Charles Mackie was born in Limekilns, Fife, on 31 March 1688. He was educated at Edinburgh University, graduating in 1705, and then he studied abroad at Groeningen in the Netherlands, 1707-1708, and at Leiden, 1715. During the purge of Jacobites within Scotland's university system a vacancy for Mackie seemed possible, and in 1719 he was offered the new Chair of Universal History at Edinburgh University. He held this until 1753. Professor Charles Mackie died in 1770. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of: an alphabetical biographical dictionary; dictates <title>Annotationes in ontologiam Gerrardi de Vries</title> and <title> Annotationes in pneumatologiam Gerrardi de Vries</title> taken down by Mackie when a student, 1703-1704; catalogue of library entitled <title>Libri historici, antiquarii, literatores, poetae, etc</title>; chronological notes of the birth and death Mackie's children, circa 1800; commonplace books containing chiefly notes and extracts on Roman history, Scottish history, and general history; <title>Index funereus 29 annorum</title> or lists of persons deceased, circa 1800; <title>Notae in Horatii Turselini Romani Historiarum epitomas ...</title>, 1743; copy of letter to Lord Balgonie at Groeningen in the Netherlands, 1742; and paper on Mackie, circa 1945-1955. </p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>Note that when this record was created any associated photographic/illustrative was unseen.</p> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Sharp, L. W. 'Charles Mackie, the first Professor of History at Edinburgh University'. <title>The Scottish historical review</title>. Vol. 41. No. 131. 1962. pp.23-45. Edinburgh: Thomas Nelson, 1962.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show various references to Mackie related material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): accounts and a few miscellaneous papers, at La.II.90/2-9; commonplace book, including an index funereus or chronological list of persons deceased, 1737-1749, at La.III.537; <title>A general table of chronology for the assistance of the memory</title>, 1765, at La.III.253; lectures and papers, 1719-1753, at La.II.37; notebook containing conspectus of classical authors, chronology chiefly biographical BC 924-AD1603, at La.III.558; notes and extracts from the correspondence of William Carstares, 1694-1710, at La.II.685; notes in a copy of the <title>Edinburgh almanack</title>, 1750, at La.III.644; form of a discharge for salary, 1767, at La.II.90/2; lectures on universal history based on Torsellino's <title>Historiarum ... epitomae libri decem</title>, 1747-1748, at La.III.237; lectures on Roman antiquities, 1759, at La.III.785; letter to G. Drummond, 1726, at La.II.91; letter to John Mitchell, 1739, at La.II.90/1; letter to W. Wishart, 1740, at La.II.233; letters to Wallace, 1752, at La.II.96/1; letters to the Lord Provost of Edinburgh, 1753-1754, at La.II.90/2; letter to unnamed nobleman, 1757, at La.II.90/3; letter to Boswell, Lord Auchinleck, 1766, at La.II.176; letters to Mackie, 1707-1765, at La.II.91; letters from Dunlop, 1734, 1745, at La.II.581; letter from A. Gordon, 1730, at La.II.220; letter from Maclaurin, 1735, at La.II.236/1; letters from Mitchell, 1717-1746, at La.II.90/1; letter from Tullideph, 1739, at La.II.187/11; letter from Wallace, 1752, at La.II.96/1; letter from Stewart, 1718, at La.II.91; and, mention of Mackie's cousin a letter by Johnson, 1722, at La.II.91.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Mackie</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Charles </emph> <emph altrender="dates">1688-1770</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Historian</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Sharp</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Lauriston William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1897-1959</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Librarian and Archivist</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Rome</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Scotland</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
