<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-647" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-647</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Professor Alexander Augustine Parker (1908-1989)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Apr 24 12:06:00 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-647</unitid> <physloc>E93.47</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor Alexander Augustine Parker (1908-1989)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box of circa 35 notebooks. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Parker, Alexander Augustine</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> and <language langcode="spa">Spanish or Castilian.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Alexander Augustine Parker was born in Montevideo, Uruguay, in 1908. He was educated at Hawkesyard School (later Blackfriars School, Laxton) and then studied at Gonville and Caius College, Cambridge. Between 1933 and 1939 he was a Fellow of Gonville and Caius College. In 1939 he was appointed Lecturer and Head of the Department of Spanish at Aberdeen University, and then in 1949 came the appointment of Reader in Spanish at Aberdeen. Parker became Professor of Spanish at the University of London, King's College, in 1953, and then in 1963 he was awarded the Chair of Hispanic Studies at Edinburgh University. Prior to that, in 1960-1961, he had been seconded to the University College of the West Indies. Between 1970 and 1978, Parker was Professor of Spanish Literature at the University of Texas, at Austin. His publications include <title>Literature and the delinquent: the picaresque novel in Spain and Europe 1599-1753</title> (1967), and <title>The philosophy of love in Spanish literature 1480-1680</title> (1985). Professor Alexander Augustine Parker died on 23 November 1989.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of student and later notebooks on Spanish literature, language, including notes on: criticism of Galdos; Conceptismo, metaphysical wit; minor dramatists, Golden Age; mystics and religious literature; plays, Tirso; criticism, Tirso de Molina; plays, criticism of Lope; criticism, plays, mythology of Calderon; picaresque novel in Europe; Unamuno; Gongora, criticism; Cervantes, criticism; Quevedo; Rojas Zorrilla, plays; Gracian, critical; Ruiz de Alarcons, plays; Libro de Buen Amor; fate, omens, and prophecy; tragedy; courtly love; and, miscellaneous material.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material acquired from Professor Parker, May 1993, Accession no. E93.47</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 21. 1963-1964. p. 8. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1964. (2) <title>Who's who 1987</title>. London: A. and C. Black, 1987.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Spain</emph> <emph altrender="x">Study and teaching</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Spanish literature</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Spanish language</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Picaresque literature</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Courtly love in literature</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Parker</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander Augustine</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1908-1989</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Hispanic Studies</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
