<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-252" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-252</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Lectures and Correspondence of Professor Sir Richard Lodge (1855-1936)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Jul 17 12:06:41 GMT+0100 (GDT) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-252</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 2011; Gen. 796-799; Gen. 771-772D; Gen. 766/1</physloc><unittitle>Lectures and Correspondence of Professor Sir Richard Lodge (1855-1936)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1889-1935">1889-1935</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box, 6 notebooks, 1 file. </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Lodge, Richard; Craw, Barbara M; Robbie, Herbert James Liddell; Horn, David Bayne</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Richard Lodge was born at Penkhull, Staffordshire, on 20 June 1855. He was educated at Christ's Hospital and then at Balliol College, Oxford. After graduating, he was appointed Fellow and Lecturer of Brasenose College, 1878, and Tutor in 1883. Lodge was the first Professor of History at Glasgow University, and was appointed in 1894 to the newly-founded Chair. He held the post until 1899 when he became Professor of History at Edinburgh University, a Chair which he held until his retiral in 1925. On his appointment at Edinburgh, the subject was still a fairly new one as a qualification for the Ordinary MA and as an Honours group and the Chair itself, like that in Glasgow, was only created in 1894. On his retiral, history at the University was thriving and it was through the efforts of Lodge that historical study in Scotland advanced to the level it did. Edinburgh became a centre of historical study and Lodge himself was an leading authority on 17th century English history and 18th century European diplomacy. His publications include <title>The student's Modern Europe: a history of modern Europe; from the capture of Constantinople by the Turks, 1453 to the treaty of Berlin, 1878</title> (1885), <title>Richelieu</title> (1896), <title>The history of England: from the Restoration to the death of William III, 1660-1702</title> (1910), and <title>A history of modern Europe from the capture of Constantinople, 1453, to the Treaty of Berlin, 1878</title> (1914). Lodge was knighted in 1917. Professor Sir Richard Lodge died in 1936.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>Lectures on British history, 1907, 1922-1923, at Gen. 796-799 and Gen. 771-772D; Correspondence with Professor David B. Horn about historical research and publications, 1921-1935, and other manuscript material to 1958, at Gen. 766/1; Offprints of articles by Lodge on the subject of history, as well as articles given to him by others, 1889-1933, also letters, at Gen. 2011.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Correspondence with Horn received from Professor D. B. Horn, June 1964, Accession no. E64.48. Lectures taken down by H. J. L. Robbie received from Mrs. H. J. L. Robbie, October 1964, Accession no. E64.58. Lectures taken down by Barbara M. Craw received November 1942, Accession no. E65.25. </p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material: (1) Rice, D. Talbot (compiler) <title>The university portraits</title>. pp.137-139. Edinburgh: The University Press, 1957. (2) <title>Who's who 1930</title>. London: A. and C. Black.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show various references to other Lodge related material (check the Indexes for more details): letters to others at Gen. 756, no.149, and Sar.Coll.136 and 158, and at Dc.4.101-103, and in JA 615, and Gen. 1952/5. </p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Historians</emph> </subject> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Lodge</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Richard</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1855-1936</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Historian</emph> </persname> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Horn</emph> <emph altrender="forename">David Bayne</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1901-1969</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Historian</emph> </persname> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Craw</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Barbara M.</emph> </persname> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">Robbie</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Herbert James Liddell</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Glasgow University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
