<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-595" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-595</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Photographs of Emily Godfrey (fl. 1930)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Nov 29 11:33:30 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-595</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 20</physloc><unittitle>Photographs of Emily Godfrey (fl. 1930)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1901-1999">20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box</extent> <physfacet>The images on the lantern slides can be seen without the need for special equipment but a projector is needed to see them at full size.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Godfrey, Emily</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Emily Godfrey, Methodist Missionary Society missionary in Eastern Nigeria, was the first missionary nurse at Ama Achara, near Umuahia, Abia state. A dispensary was opened there in 1921 and for many years the station was manned only by a female nurse and evangelist, with occasional help from doctors. Godfrey oversaw a gradual expansion of the work and, as more buildings were added, a fully functioning hospital was established. She left Nigeria in the 1940s.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of photographs, negatives and lantern slides (3 slides only) showing the hospital at Ama Achara, patients and staff, missionaries, church workers, other areas in Eastern Nigeria including Calabar, and mission work in general; most of the photographs are from the 1920s-mid 1940s but there are some earlier ones of Mary Slessor; and there is also a printed article on the hospital (1937).</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>Most of the photographs are pasted into exercise books, many are captioned in Emily Godfrey's hand, some were annotated at a later date by the Reverend Smith. Most of the negatives are not captioned. </p> </arrangement> <custodhist> <p>Some pamphlets and printed reports of the mission were included in the collection but these were filed separately in the Centre library. Some of the photographs were identified and annotated at a later date by the Reverend S. W. Smith.</p> </custodhist> <acqinfo> <p>The material was deposited at the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World by Emily Godfrey when the Centre was part of Aberdeen University.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>None expected.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using Familusi, M. M. <title>Methodism in Nigeria</title>. Nigeria, NPS Educational Publishers Ltd., 1992. </p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The archives of the Methodist Mission are held by the School of African and Oriental Studies in London. Emily Godfrey also donated some reports and other printed material relating to the mission in Nigeria which were deposited in the Centre's library.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Godfrey</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Emily </emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1930</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Methodist Missionary Society</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nigeria</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
