<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-596" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-596</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Mark Glasswell (1938-1995)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 3 09:01:04 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-596</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 30</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Mark Glasswell (1938-1995)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1920-1992">[ca. 1920]-1992</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 file</extent> </physdesc> <origination>Glasswell, Mark Errol</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> and <language langcode="ger">German.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Mark Errol Glasswell, priest and lecturer in Sierra Leone and Nigeria, was born on 16 May 1938. He graduated BA in theology from Durham in 1960 then took his Ph.D. in New Testament studies at Durham in 1965. He also studied at Ridley Hall (1963-64) and Westcott House (1966) Cambridge. He was ordained as a priest in Durham in 1967. In 1965 he had begun working as a lecturer in theology at Fourah Bay College, Sierra Leone (later part of the University of Sierra Leone) and he continued there until 1974. Glasswell was also honorary curate at St Patrick's, Kissy between 1966 and 1969, then served at Holy Trinity in Free Town. He spent a year (1974-75) as an assistant priest and part time lecturer in Durham before moving to Nigeria where he worked as senior lecturer in the Department of Religion at the University of Nigeria, Nsukka (1975-85). In 1985 he returned to England and became a priest then Rector at Sampfords, Chelmsford where he remained until his retirement in 1988. He continued to be active in promoting the study of theology, acting as a course writer and examiner for various institutions in the UK and Africa. He was also in demand as a speaker, was involved in editing several journals, and published numerous articles. Glasswell died in January 1995.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of: personal items relating to Glasswell's career (1964-1992); correspondence with students and colleagues in Africa (1966-1985); papers, articles and sermons on theology and on religion in Africa (c 1967-1984); and material on the North German Mission to West Africa, with correspondence with Rudolph Bultmann (c 1920-1969). </p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>The material is in one file.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>The material was presented to the Centre by Father Patrick, CSWG, The Monastery of Christ the Saviour, Hove in 1996. </p> </acqinfo> <appraisal> <p>Only a selection of correspondence survives so it is possible that the material was sorted by Father Patrick first.</p> </appraisal> <accruals> <p>None expected.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the collection itself.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>Other material from Glasswell was also presented to the Centre and is in the Centre library.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Christianity and other religions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Glasswell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Mark Errol </emph> <emph altrender="dates">1938-1995</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Nigeria</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Ghana</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
