<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-591" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-591</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection of James Hector (1845-1934)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Nov 29 10:31:34 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-591</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 4</physloc><unittitle>Collection of James Hector (1845-1934)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1801-1999">19th century-20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 volumes</extent> </physdesc> <origination>Hector, James </origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> <language langcode="fre">French, </language> and <language langcode="ben">Bengali.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>John Hector, United Free Church of Scotland missionary in Calcutta, India, was born in Aberdeen on 21 December 1845. Educated at Aberdeen University he graduated MA in 1860 and later DD in 1884. He attended Aberdeen Free Church College then secured a post teaching missionaries at Kinnoir, Huntly in 1870 followed by a spell as a missionary assistant at Paisley St George's in 1871. In the same year he was ordained for foreign mission service with the Free Church and was appointed to Calcutta. In 1876 Hector married Margaret Pittendrigh and in 1887 he became principal of Duff College, Calcutta. He oversaw the recovery of the college from a period of depression and it developed into a well organised and efficient institution. His skilful management and genial personality made him popular with both teachers and pupils and his period as principal saw the largest pupil numbers the college had yet had. Hector was invalided home and formally retired from the mission on 31 December in 1902. He was the Duff Lecturer in Evangelistic Theology at the United Free Church Colleges between 1904 and 1905. Hector died on 19 December 1934.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of three volumes which seem to date from after Hector's return from India but contain extracts from lectures given and hymns, songs and verses collected while he was there: (1) volume, similar to a commonplace book, with hymns, songs and verses noted by Hector, some translated by him from Bengali or French, and some other notes and newspaper articles (various dates); (2) extracts from Hector's lectures to his students in Calcutta (extracts written by Hector at a later date?), notes on books, articles and events (from c 1914-1918) with newspaper cuttings on the war, and a cutting on the Scottish Churches College (was Duff College); (3) volume of notes by Hector for addresses to meetings includes cuttings and articles about missions and missionaries (1927-1930).</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>The material is in three volumes.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>The material was deposited at the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World by Hector's grandson Gordon Hector.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>None expected.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lamb, J. A. (ed.). <title>Fasti of the United Free Church of Scotland 1900-1929</title>. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1956. (2) Tomory, A. and MacDonald, K. S. <title>Story of our Bengal Missions</title>. Edinburgh: United Free Church, circa 1904.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The archives of the United Free Church are with the Church of Scotland material in the National Library of Scotland and contain many letters to Hector.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missions</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Missionaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hector</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John </emph> <emph altrender="dates">1845-1934</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Church of Scotland</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">India</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
