<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-454" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-454</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Lectures and Notes of Professor Sir George Walter Prothero (1848-1922)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Oct 4 12:03:46 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-454</unitid> <physloc>Dk.5.42-62</physloc><unittitle>Lectures and Notes of Professor Sir George Walter Prothero (1848-1922)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1801-1999">19th century - 20th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>20 boxes, 1 parcel (1 linear metre)</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>George Walter Prothero was born on 14 October 1848 in Wiltshire. He was educated at Eton and studied at King's College, Cambridge and at the University of Bonn. He became an Assistant Master at Eton and then Lecturer at the Universities of Nottingham and Leicester. In 1876 he became a Lecturer in History and Tutor at King's College and in 1894 he was appointed Professor of History at Edinburgh University. Between 1901 and 1905 he was President of the Royal Historical Society. Prothero lectured in Cambridge, in Boston, at Johns Hopkins, and in Oxford. In 1916 he was Governor of Holloway College, and between 1918 and 1919 he was the Director of the Historical Section at the Foreign Office. After the end of the First World War, Prothero was a member of the British Peace Delegation, 1919. His publications include <title>Life and times of Simon de Montfort</title> (1877), <title>Memoir of Henry Bradshaw</title> (1889), and <title>German policy before the war</title> (1916). Professor Sir George Walter Prothero died on 10 July 1922. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: lecture notes and notes of reading on British, European, and Roman history.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Presented by the Royal Historical Society, 1935.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1916-1928</title>. 3rd edition. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1962.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Prothero related material (check the Indexes for more details): letters to C. Sarolea, 1911-1912, and undated, at Sar.Coll.30; copies of letters from Sarloea, 1911-1913, also at Sar.Coll.30; letters to A. Berriedale Keith about the British Dominions, 1917-1919, Gen. 145/2/150, 152-157, 167, 175-179, 191, 194-197, 199. There are also letters and postcards between Mrs. Mary F. Prothero and Sarolea, at Sar.Coll.30.</p> <p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: correspondence, diaries and papers, 1886-1922, Royal Historical Society, Ref. Prothero NRA 43391 Prothero; miscellaneous correspondence, 1894-1912, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 10113-10581 Passim; journals and notebooks, 1872-1922, Cambridge University: King's College Archive Centre, Ref. Misc 77 NRA 33931 Prothero, and miscellaneous correspondence and papers mainly relating to his biography of Henry Bradshaw, c.1855-1889, Ref. Bradshaw Papers passim NRA 41733 Bradshaw, and letters to Oscar Browning, c.1876-1913, Ref. OB NRA 21235 Browning; letters to Lord Acton, 1896-1901, Cambridge University Library, Department of Manuscripts and University Archives, Ref. Add MSS 6443, 7731, 8119 NRA 37383 Acton; correspondence with H. Dawson, 1915-1919, Birmingham University Information Services, Special Collections Department, Ref. WHD NRA 14020 Dawson; correspondence with Sir Charles Dilke, 1905-1909, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 43921; letters (10) to Sir Edmund Gosse, 1899-1913, Leeds University, Brotherton Library, Ref. Library Publications no 3 NRA 9840 Gosse; letters (38) to Karl Pearson, 1879-1916, London University: University College London (UCL) Manuscripts Room, Ref. PEARSON NRA 18115 Pearson; letters to Peveril Turnbull, 1901-1902, Derbyshire Record Office, Ref. D1453 NRA 43527 Turnbull; and, letters to G. E. Morrison, 1914-1920, State Library of New South Wales, Mitchell Library, Ref. ML MSS 312 NRA 25521 Morrison.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Historians</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Prothero</emph> <emph altrender="forename">George Walter</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1848-1922</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Historian</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Europe</emph> <emph altrender="a">History</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Rome</emph> <emph altrender="a">History</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
