<?xml version="1.0"?> <!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd"> <ead> <eadheader> <eadid publicid="GB 237 Coll-890" countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237">GB 237 Coll-890</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="">Papers of Katherine Cameron MacArthur (1906-1987)</titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by JavaScript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2 on <date>Wed Dec 15 11:02:17 UTC 2004</date>.</creation> </profiledesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-890</unitid> <physloc>E2003.35</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Katherine Cameron MacArthur (1906-1987)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1923-1943">1923-1943</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 boxes containing circa 47 notebooks.</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial> <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial> <origination>MacArthur, Katherine Cameron</origination> </did> <phystech> <p>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted</p></phystech> <bioghist> <p>Katherine Cameron MacArthur was born in 1906. She was educated at Perth Academy in the early-1920s, and studied at Edinburgh University where she graduated with the degree of M.A. in 1929. She taught English, Speech Training and Drama at St. Columba's School for Girls in Kilmacolm (then in Renfrewshire), at Edinburgh Ladies' College (then in Queen Street, Edinburgh), and in Nottingham. She was Headmistress of St. Columba's, Kilmacolm from 1945 until her retirement in the early-1970s. Katherine Cameron MacArthur died in 1987.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The hand-written note material is contained in the form of soft- and hard-back notebooks, some of these being Edinburgh University notebooks, some being those of Edinburgh Ladies' college. There are also some early notes from school days at Perth Academy, 1923-1924. One of the notebooks is addressed as Balfour Hostel, East Suffolk Road, Edinburgh, another is addressed St. Columba's School, Kilmacolm, and another St. George's Training College. One notebook contains a timetable for classs in July 1943 at St. Andrews School of Drama. The notes are almost entirely related to English and the teaching of English and include varied subjects with teaching such as Psychology, Montessori, Inflection, Speech, Chaucer, and Shakespeare. There are also Scripture notes and notes on Character tests, and there are notes on French Prose taken during lectures by Professor Sarolea. There is also some printed material in the collection, being an untitled English exercise book, <title>The art of the spoken word</title> by Mrs. Tobias Matthay which was one of the Festival Booklets, No.12 (1922), a copy of <title>Merchant maiden. Magazine of Edinburgh Ladies' College</title> (December 1942), <title>Mimes and miming</title> by Isabel Chisman and Gladys Wites (1926), <title>Sample class exercises in rhetoric and composition</title> published in Edinburgh by Oliver and Boyd (1926), <title>Some suggestions for the teaching of English in secondary schools in England</title> by the Board of Education, London (1924), <title>Announcement issued 1st February 1941</title> by the Scottish Universities Entrance Board, and <title>The persepective of biography</title> by Sidney Lee, published by The English Association (September 1918), and <title>The early Wordsworth</title> by E. De Selincourt also published by The English Association (November 1936).</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material donated by Judge David A. O. Edward C.M.G., Q.C., F.R.S.E., Cameron's nephew, Edinburgh, but came to us through Iain MacIver, MSS Division, National Library of Scotland, March 2003, Accession no. E2003.35.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987.</p> </otherfindaid> <processinfo> <p>Compiled by Graeme D. Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </processinfo> <!-- Controlled Access Terms --> <controlaccess> <subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">English language</emph> <emph altrender="x">Study and teaching</emph> </subject> <subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Students</emph> </subject> <subject encodinganalog="JISC-HUB43" source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Note-taking</emph> </subject> <persname> <emph altrender="surname">MacArthur</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Katherine Cameron</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1906-1987</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Headmistress at St. Columba's School, Kilmacolm</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh Universiy </emph> <emph altrender="z">Edinburgh (Scotland)</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc> </ead> 