<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-436" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-436</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Material relating to Admiral Sir Alexander Milne (1806-1896)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Sep 19 13:59:30 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-436</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 755D; Dc.4.101-103 Milne</physloc><unittitle>Material relating to Admiral Sir Alexander Milne (1806-1896)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1859-1870">1859-1870</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 letters, 1 photograph portrait album (small)</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Alexander Milne, son of Admiral Sir David Milne (1763-1845), was born on 10 November 1806. Like his father he followed a naval career becoming the senior naval lord of the Admiralty and Commander-in-Chief of the North American, West Indian, and Mediterranean stations, and elder brother of the Trinity House. He was given a Baronetcy in 1876. Admiral Sir Alexander Milne, 1st Baronet, G.C.B. died on 29 December 1896. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material consists of: a letter to D. M. Home, 1859; and, a photograph album. </p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Album, acquired 1964, Accession no. E64.36.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Burke, Sir Bernard. and Burke, Ashworth (eds.). <title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage, the privy council, and knightage</title>. 87th edition. p.1401. London: Burke's Peerage Ltd., 1929.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: naval memorandum book, 1858-1872, Boston Public Library, see R Morriss, Guide to British Naval Papers in North America (1994); correspondence and papers, 1817-1895, National Maritime Museum, Manuscripts Section, Ref. MLN/101-99 NRA 30121 National, see Quarterly return MS79/093; letters to Sir James Graham and Duke of Newcastle, 1854-1855, Nottingham University Library, Department of Manuscripts and Special Collections, Ref. Ne NRA 7411 Pelham; letters (37) to Duke of Somerset, 1861-1865, Ref. D-RA NRA 11704 Ramsden; correspondence with Sir Charles Napier, 1847-1854, British Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MSS 40024-42; correspondence, diaries and papers, 1825-1896, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, NRA 29189 Milne; and, correspondence with Charles Wood, 1855-1857, British Library, Manuscript Division , Ref. ADD MSS 49532 Passim.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Milne</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1806-1896</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Admiral of the Fleet</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">19th century</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
