<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-740" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-740</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of the Very Rev. Alexander Martin (1857-1946)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 9 09:37:13 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-740</unitid> <physloc>MSS MART</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Very Rev. Alexander Martin (1857-1946)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1885-1944">1885-1944</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>21 boxes, 1 volume. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Martin, Alexander</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Alexander Martin was born in 1857. He was the son of the Rev. Hugh Martin, the Free Church minister of Panbride, near Carnoustie, Angus. He was educated at George Watson's College, Edinburgh, and he studied at Edinburgh University and at New College, Edinburgh (Theological Hall). From 1880 until 1883 he was an Assistant to the Professor of Moral Philosophy at Edinburgh University, and from 1886 to 1888 he was Examiner in Mental Philosophy. Martin had also been Minister of Morningside Free Church in the city. He was appointed to the Chair of Apologetics and Practical Theology at New College, Edinburgh University, in 1897. He served in this capacity until 1927. From 1918 until 1935 he was Principal of New College, and he was latterly Principal Emeritus. Martin had also been Chaplain to the King in Scotland, appointed in 1929. His publications included <title>Winning the soul</title> (1897), <title>The present position of apologetics</title> (1897), and <title>The finality of Jesus for faith</title> (1933). The Very Rev. Alexander Martin died on 14 June 1946.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: in Boxes 1 and 2, private notebooks on Church and State, national recognition of religion, conferences including conference with Church of Scotland and union conferences, some material undated, and from 1909 to 1929; Boxes 3 to 8, pamphlets and reports, and some Scottish maps, some material undated, and 1869-1944; Box 9, pamphlets and magazines related to House of Commons debates, House of Lords debates, and <title>Church union, news and views</title>, the <title>Record of the Church of Scotland</title>, the <title>Presbyterian register</title>, and various others, 1921 to 1939; Box 10 assorted folders including tracts, teinds, tithes, property, regium domum, union assembly programs and material on Faith and Order; Box 11, speeches, notes and miscellaneous material; Boxes 12 to 14, reports and memoranda; and, Box 15 and 16, clippings folders; Boxes 17 to 21, letters in folders, 1885-1944. There is also one volume of manuscript notes in shorthand, Alexander Martin's <title>Lectures on apologetics</title>, New College, Edinburgh, academic session 1897-1898.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1941-1950</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1952.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. There is an Index of Correspondence (Boxes 17-21), with box/folder/folio information, and sender/recipient information, and date.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes these locations of Martin related material: letters to E. O. Davies, National Library of Wales, Ref. PCW MSS 3539-5389 passim. NRA 28345 Presb Church Wales; and, correspondence with publishers, 1932-1936, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Dep 247 342 NRA 20220 Clark</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theology</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theologians</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Martin</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1857-1946</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Principal of New College Edinburgh</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">New College (University of Edinburgh)</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
