<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-543" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-543</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Lectures and Notes of Professor William Rutherford (1839-1899)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Mar 25 14:21:54 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-543</unitid> <physloc>Dk.3.13-16; Dk.4.11; Dk.5.34-35; Gen. 1409-1410; Gen. 1906-1908; Gen. 2007/7, 11-12; Gen. 2152D; JA 3617; JA 3621</physloc><unittitle>Lectures and Notes of Professor William Rutherford (1839-1899)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1874-1899">1874-1899</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>17 manuscript volumes</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Rutherford, William; Gray, J. A; Vignal, M; Taylor, William; Easterbrook, Charles Cromhall; Simpson, Sutherland</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>William Rutherford was born at Ancrum Craig, Roxburghshire, on 20 April 1839. He was educated locally before studying at Edinburgh University. He graduated in 1863 with the degree of M.D. He became a House Physician at the Royal Infirmary in the city and also a House Surgeon, and was also an Assistant Demonstrator at Edinburgh's Surgeon's Hall. He learned from the likes of Daniel Rutherford Haldane (1824-1887), James Spence (1812-1822), and Sir John Struthers (1823-1899). Rutherford then went abroad to expand his knowledge of experimental physiology, studying in Berlin, Dresden, Prague, Vienna, Leipzig, and Paris. He returned to Edinburgh in 1865. In 1869 he was appointed Professor of Physiology at King's College, London, and in 1871 he became Professor of Physiology at the Royal Institution of London. Rutherford then became Professor of Physiology at Edinburgh University in 1874. His publications include <title>Outlines of practical histology</title> (1875), <title>An experimental research on the physiological actions of drugs on the secretion of bile</title> (1880), and <title>A textbook of physiology</title> (1880). Professor William Rutherford died on 21 February 1899.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of: lectures on physiology, 1874-1875; lectures on physiology, 1887-1888; lectures on physiology by graduate of 1892; notes of lectures on physiology, 1899; laboratory records of research on biliary secretion, 1875-1876; notes made by Rutherford in his copy of <title>Grundriss der physiologie des menschen</title> by L. Hermann; notebook of physiological apparatus seen on visits to the Continent, 1870-1880; notes, corrections and additions made by Rutherford in his copy of <title>Practical histology</title>, published by himself in 1876; lectures on the Institutes of Medicine (physiology), 1882-1883; and, lecture book used for the preparation of lecture experiments and diagrams on physiology, compiled by Dr. Sutherland Simpson.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Lectures, 1874-1875, acquired February 1968, Accession no. E68.5. Notebook of apparatus, 1874-1875, acquired October 1982, Accession no. E82.71. Cromhall notes, purchased June 1972, Accession no. E72.26</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 22. (Supplement). London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Rutherford related material (check the Indexes for more details): letter to Professor Geikie about an examination in physiology, 1898, at Da.45.5, f.49; letter from W.G.Adams, 1876, in JA 3621; letter from John Cavafy, 1876, in JA 3621; letter from Septimus Harwood, 1880, in JA 3617; notice of Rutherford in Sir J. S. Flett's account of his student days, 1886-1894, at Dc.116, f.46, 50; and, small portrait photo (c.d.v) at Phot.Ill.90.</p> <p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: lecture notes, 1885-1886, Royal College of Physicians, Ref. Rutherford NRA 16015 Coll of Physicians; and, lecture notes, 1881-1882, Royal College of Surgeons of England.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physiology</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Physiologists</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Rutherford</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1839-1899</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Physiologist</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Gray</emph> <emph altrender="forename">J. A.</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Vignal</emph> <emph altrender="forename">M.</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Taylor</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Easterbrook</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Charles Cromhall</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Simpson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Sutherland</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
