<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-768" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-768</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Rev. David Plenderleath (d. 1779)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Feb 6 12:20:10 UTC 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-768</unitid> <physloc>MSS BOX 13.1.1-9</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Rev. David Plenderleath (d. 1779)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1731-1764">1731-1764</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>15 leaves or pages. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Plenderleath, David</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The Rev. David Plenderleath had been licensed by the Presbytery of Kincardine in 1731. He was also presented to the Parish of Ormiston in 1732, and called by the Presbytery of Dalkeith in 1746. The Rev. David Plenderleath died in 1779.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: a licence by the Presbytery of Kincardine, 1731; presentation by John Cockburn of Ormiston in favour of Plenderleath to the Parish of Ormiston, 1732; petition from the heritors and elders of the Parish of Dalkeith to the Presbytery of Dalkeith about the call to Plenderleath, 1746; presentation by the Duke of Buccleuch in favour of Plenderleath, 1746; warrant of the Duke of Buccleuch to Gilbert Grierson regarding the settlement of Plenderleath in the Parish of Dalkeith; call from the heritors and elders in the Parish of Dalkeith to Plenderleath, 1746; copies of memorials from Plenderleath to the Duke of Buccleuch anent augmentation of stipend, 1751; letter of Caroline, Countess of Dalkeith to Sir W. Douglas, with reference to Plenderleath, 1755; and, bond by Plenderleath to Mr. James Scott.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained within the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes at Special Collections Division, Edinburgh University Library, show references to possible Plenderleath material (check the Indexes for more details): a David Plenderleath admitted to the use of Edinburgh University Library, with signature, 22 February 1728, at Da. 2.1, p.55; and, a letter from a David Plenderleath to Charles Mackie, at Melvill, 13 November 1730, at La.II.91.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Plenderleath</emph> <emph altrender="forename">David</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d. 1779</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Minister</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Scott</emph> <emph altrender="forename">A. Francis</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1695-1751</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">2nd Duke of Buccleuch</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
