<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-739" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-739</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of the Very Rev. Professor William P. Paterson (1860-1939)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 9 09:19:52 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-739</unitid> <physloc>MSS PAT 01-05</physloc><unittitle>Papers of the Very Rev. Professor William P. Paterson (1860-1939)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1898-1934">1898-1934</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, New College Library, Mound Place, Edinburgh EH1 2LU</repository> <physdesc> <extent>circa 35 printed items, circa 15 manuscript items, 8 photographs. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Paterson, William P.</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>William P. Paterson was born in 1860, and he was educated at Edinburgh's Royal High School. He then studied at Edinburgh University, finishing in 1883, and at Leipzig, Erlangen, and Berlin, 1883-1885. Paterson became Parish Minister of Crieff, Perthshire, in 1887, and then in 1894 he was appointed to the Chair of Systematic Theology at Aberdeen University. In 1903 came his appointment to the Chair of Divinity at Edinburgh University where he remained until 1934. In 1919, Paterson carried out the duties of the Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland. His publications included <title>St. Paul's teaching</title> (1903), and <title>The rule of faith</title> (1912). He edited <title>German culture</title> (1915), and edited with Dr. D. Watson <title>Social evils and problems</title> (1918). His sermons and Gifford Lectures were also published, and he wrote articles for dictionaries and encyclopaedias. The Very Rev. Professor William P. Paterson died on 10 June 1939.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of: lectures, toasts, orations given by Paterson on e.g. John Knox and Sir Walter Scott; essays and sermons; notes and summaries; material in a tour of France; off-prints; orders of service; visiting cards; and, assorted photographs of Paterson.</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>The collection has been arranged into five sections: PAT01 Books, PAT02 Theological Papers, PAT03 General Address, PAT04 Extracts from periodicals, and PAT05 Miscellaneous.</p> </arrangement> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Who was who 1929-1940</title>. London: Adam and Charles Black, 1941.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Local lists. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Paterson related material in the Sarolea Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letters to C. Sarolea, 1912, in Sar.Coll.30;letter to Sarolea, 1925, in Sar.Coll.138; and, letters to Sarolea, 1926, 1929, and undated, in Sar.Coll.227.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theology</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Theologians</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Paterson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William P.</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1860-1939 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Divinity</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">New College (Edinburgh University)</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
