<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-668" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-668</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Col. Stanislas Machowicz (fl. 1935-1939)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon May 12 09:33:02 UTC+0100 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-668</unitid> <physloc>Dk.6.17</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Col. Stanislas Machowicz (fl. 1935-1939)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1935-1939">1935-1939</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 box-file containing 5 files. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Machowicz, Stanislas</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="pol">Polish.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Colonel Stanislas Machowicz was Military Commandant of the city of Warsaw, 1935-1939. This was the very short pre-war period during which the 'Colonels' had succeeded Marshall Josef Pilsudski on his death in 1935, and which was marked by increased antagonism between the right and left in Poland.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of 5 files within a box-file and comprising, in Polish, the various chapters of <title>Droga do Katastrofy. Wspomnienia Wojskowego Komendanta Miasta Warszawy z lat 1935-39</title>. There is an English translation of the contents of this work with the English title, <title>The road to disaster. Reminiscences of the military commandant of the city of Warsaw 1935-39</title>.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material deposited by A. J. A. Malkiewicz on 3 July 1957 and to become property of the Library after 40 years (1997).</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>This material was noted as 'for restricted use' until 1997. Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Machowicz</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Stanislas</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl. 1935-1939</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Colonel, Military Commandant of Warsaw</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Poland</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">20th century</emph> </geogname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Warsaw (Poland)</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
