<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-136" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-136</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Professor J. Finlayson (1758-1808)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Tue Dec 18 09:43:20 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-136</unitid> <physloc>Dc.4.41/97; Dc.8.142/1-2; Gen. 774-778; Gen. 1379-1381; MSS FLE </physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor J. Finlayson (1758-1808)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1794-1808">1794-1808</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division; Edinburgh University, New College Library</repository> <physdesc> <extent>10 volumes, 1 letter. </extent> </physdesc> <origination>Pollock, David; Finlayson, James</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>James Finlayson was born at Nether Cambushenie, near Dunblane, on 15 February 1758. He studied at Glasgow University and later became tutor to the sons of Sir William Murray of Ochtertyre. Finlayson became licensed to preach in 1785. He assumed the duties of Professor of Logic at Edinburgh University in 1786, and he was ordained as a minister in 1787 in the Parish of Borthwick near Edinburgh. With a rising reputation on matters of ecclesiastical policy, he dedicated a lot of time to the study of the laws, constitution and history of the Scottish church. In 1802, Finlayson was elected as Moderator of the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland. Among his publications were the four volumes of <title>The sermons of Hugh Blair</title> (1815-1816). Professor James Finlayson died on 28 January 1808.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers include: lectures, 1795-1796; lectures on logic, 1796-1797; lectures on logic and metaphysics, 1807-1808; and, a letter concerning publication of the memoirs of Alexander Carlyle, 1806. The papers also include lectures, 1794-1795, housed within Edinburgh University's New College Library, at MSS FLE.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Lectures acquired 1964, Accession no. E64.59. Lectures acquired 1968, Accession no. E68.33.</p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 7. Finch-Gloucester. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show other references to Finlayson related material (check the Indexes for more details): certificates awarded to individuals in 1796 and 1800.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Logic</emph> </subject> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Finlayson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1758-1808</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Logic</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Pollock</emph> <emph altrender="forename">David</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1780-1847</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight Judge </emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Edinburgh University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
