<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-371" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-371</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Professor John Lizars (c. 1787-1860)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Apr 22 09:31:12 GMT+0100 (GMT Daylight Time) 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-371</unitid> <physloc>Dk.5.9-11; Gen. 1733/49</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Professor John Lizars (c. 1787-1860)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1801-1899">19th century</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>3 manuscript volumes, 1 letter. </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>John Lizars was born in Edinburgh around 1787. He was the son of a publisher and engraver in the city, Daniel Lizars (died 1812), and brother of William Home Lizars (1788-1859). He was educated at the Royal High School and studied at Edinburgh University. After obtaining his medical diploma in 1810, he served as a naval surgeon seeing active service during the Peninsular War. He returned to Edinburgh in 1815 and was admitted as a Fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh. Lizars became successful in a surgical partnership in the city and then as a teacher of anatomy and surgery, and in 1831 he was appointed to the Chair of Surgery at the Royal College of Surgeons. His appointment was combined with that of a senior operating surgeon at the Royal Infirmary where Robert Liston (1794-1847) was a colleague. His publications include <title>A system of anatomical plates of the human body, accompanied with descriptions, and physiological, pathological, and surgical observations</title> (1822), <title>Observations on extraction of diseased ovaria</title> (1835), and a <title>System of practical surgery, with numerous explanatory plates, the drawings after nature</title> (1835). These were used very extensively by nineteenth century medical students. Lizars also contributed to the major medical journals of the day. Professor John Lizars died on 21 May 1860.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material consists of notes of lectures taken down by John Lizars at Edinburgh University, 1807-1808, and a letter about the sixth edition of his treatise on tobacco believed to 'stagger Smokers of the pernicious weed', 1856.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Letter purchased March 1983, Accession no. E83.20.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol. 11. Kennett-Lluelyn. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show a reference to Lizars related material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): mention of the publication of Lizars's <title>Anatomical plates of the human body</title> in letters of D. Lizars and W. H. Lizars to S. Highley, a bookseller in London, at La.II.426/293-295. Lizars is also mentioned in letters of George Cook to Sir W. Jardine as a favoured candidate for the Chair of Anatomy and medicine at St. Andrews University, 1840, at Dk.6.20/52-53. In addition, at Da., there is an anatomy class-list, 1852-53.</p> <p>There is a reference to Daniel Lizars, publisher father of John Lizars: mention of his new newspaper in a letter, 1830, at Dk.6.20/125.</p> <p>For Lizars's brother William Home Lizars there are references to: sketches of the College, 1823, at E89.93; an invitation to an unnamed to attend funeral of D. Lizars, 1812, at La.II.316; letters to Sir W. Jardine about plates for illustrations, Dk.6.20/207-209; letters, 1838-1840, at Dk.6.20/45, 65, 134, 149, 197; and, mentions in letters 1829-1841, at Dk.6.20/98, 122, 125-126, 161-186.</p> <p>In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: lecture notes and anatomical drawings, 1820-1835, Royal College of Physicians of Edinburgh, Ref. Lizars NRA 16015 Coll of Physicians</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Surgeons</emph> </subject> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Lizars</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">? 1787-1860</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Surgeon</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Lizars</emph> <emph altrender="forename">William Home</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1788-1859</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Painter and Engraver</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Lizars</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Daniel</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d. 1812</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Publisher, Engraver</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
