<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-725" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-725</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of Jeanie Robertson (1908-1975)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Nov 19 10:52:22 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-725</unitid> <physloc>E89.92</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Jeanie Robertson (1908-1975)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1954-1956">1954-1956</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>1 folder of circa 160 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Robertson, Jeanie</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="sco">Scots, </language> and <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>The Scottish traditional folk singer Jeanie Robertson was born in 1908. She was from a travelling family from the North East of Scotland. Robertson sang in the old style having learned most of her songs through the oral tradition of her family. Her singing was featured on the 1959 LP <title>Jeanie Robertson, The Great Traditional Ballad Singer.</title> Her mother was Marie Stewart from Ballater a small town on rural Deeside, Aberdeenshire, and with the Robertsons on her fathers side she was part of two old travelling dynasties. Widely regarded as a seminal figure in music culture of Scotland's travelling people Jeanie was a contemporary of Jimmy McBeth, Belle Stewart and Flora MacNeil. In recognition of her services to traditional music she was awarded the MBE in 1968. Jeanie Robertson died on 13 March 1975.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is largely composed of circa 160 letters from Robertson to the poet Hamish Henderson (1919-2002). It also contains her equity card and a recording contract.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material acquired from H. Henderson, School of Scottish Studies, Edinburgh University, December 1989, Accession no. E89.92</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>Jeanie Robertson</title>. Full-text [online]. <extref href="http://home.btclick.com/scotsmusic/robertson.htm">Jeanie Robertson. Traditional Scottish ballad singer</extref> [Accessed 5 November 2003].</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Folk singers</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Ballads, Scots</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Travellers (Nomadic people)</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Robertson</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Jeanie</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1908-1975</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Traditional Scottish Ballad Singer</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
