<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-530" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-530</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection of Sketches and Reports of Wounded at the Battle of Waterloo</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Mar 17 11:13:52 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-530</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 594-595D</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Sketches and Reports of Wounded at the Battle of Waterloo</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1815">[1815]</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 manuscript volumes</extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>After 23 years of warfare between France and other European powers, the Battle of Waterloo fought in the afternoon and evening of 18 June 1815 brought the final defeat of the French army of Napoleon Bonaparte. The battle was fought three miles south of the village of Waterloo (twelve miles south of Brussels) during the One Hundred Days of Bonaparte's restoration and after some secondary fighting in the area on 16 June. The French army of 72,000 faced the 113,000 allied British, Dutch, Belgian, German and Prussian forces under Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington, the 'Iron Duke', and Gebhard Leberecht von Bluecher. Other prominent commanders were Michel Ney and Emmanuel de Grouchy, who were both Marshals of France, and Georges Mouton, Comte de Lobau, and Karl von Buelow and H. E. K. von Zeiten of the Prussian forces. Napoleon lost 25,000 men either killed or wounded, and 9,000 captured, while the allies lost 23,000. Napoleon abdicated four days later.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of sketches by Dr. Thomson and Dr. Somerville of the wounded at the Battle of Waterloo, and reports, descriptions of cases many with drawings of wounds, and statistical tables of the wounded at the site, probably done in 1815.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material acquired June 1962, Accession no. E62.43-44.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) <title>The new encyclopaedia Britannica</title>. Vol.12. Micropaedia. Ready Reference. 15th edition. Chicago: Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1991.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Waterloo, Battle of, 1815</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">War</emph> <emph altrender="x">Relief of sick and wounded</emph> </subject> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Waterloo (Belgium)</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
