<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-729" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-729</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Collection of Professor Hedley Duncan Wright (1891-1942)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Dec 1 09:06:27 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-729</unitid> <physloc>E96.4; E96.16</physloc><unittitle>Collection of Professor Hedley Duncan Wright (1891-1942)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1910-1940">1910-1940</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 boxes containing 5 medals and 5 volumes including album, diaries, reprints. </extent> <physfacet> Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Wright, Hedley Duncan</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Hedley Duncan Wright was born on 3 March 1891 in Ulverstone, Tasmania, and was of Scottish descent. He studied at Queen's College, Hobart, where he obtained a B.A. (Tasm) in 1910, and then at Edinburgh University where he studied Medicine and obtained the M.B. and Ch.B., in 1916. Subsequently at Edinburgh he was awarded his M.D. in 1925, and D.Sc. in 1927. During the First World War, Wright served with the Royal Army Medical Corps for four years, in France, India, and Persia. After the war he returned to Edinburgh to take up research in Bacteriology. At Edinburgh University he held the post of Lecturer, 1920-1921, and at the Royal College of Physicians he held the post of Assistant Superintendent of the Research Laboratory, 1921-1923. In 1923 he went to London to become Lecturer and Reader at the University College Hospital. From 1930, Wright was Professor of Bacteriology at the University of Sydney, Australia, and then in 1934 he returned to Britain to become Professor of Bacteriology at the University of Liverpool. He was also the City Bacteriologist. Professor Hedley Duncan Wright died in Liverpool on 9 September 1942.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection is composed of a volume containing reprints of his articles, two diaries for the periods 1910 onwards and 1918 onwards, an illustrated transcript of the diaries with biographical details, and an album of photographs taken mainly in Persia during the First World War. There are also 5 medals.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material acquired from Dr. Peter H. Wright, February 1996, and May 1996, Accession nos. E96.4 and E96.16.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) 'Obituary'. <title>University of Edinburgh journal</title>. Vol. 12. 1942-1943. p.54. Edinburgh: Oliver and Boyd, 1943.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Diaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Wright</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Hedley Duncan </emph> <emph altrender="dates">1891-1942 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Professor of Bacteriology</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Iran</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
