<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-38" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-38</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Colin Campbell Collection </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852">GB 237 Coll-38</unitid> <physloc>MSS 3096-3102</physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Colin Campbell Collection </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1553-1836">1553-1836 </unitdate> <origination encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.1./marc 700">Colin Campbell of Achnaba </origination> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>7 boxes (1 m). </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>Colin Campbell, the son of Patrick (Dubh Beg) Campbell of Innerzeldies, ancestor of the Barcaldine family, was born in 1644. He was educated at St. Salvator's College, St. Andrews, graduating on 27 July 1661. Thereafter he may have studied at one of the English universities either as a companion or tutor to his relative, Robert of Glenorchy (Sir Robert Campbell of Glenorchy) an ancestor of the marquises of Breadalbane. In 1666 or 1667 he was admitted as minister of the Parish Church of Ardchattan and Muckairn in Lorne. On 12 January 1676 he was suspended from the ministry on a charge of pre-nuptial intercourse but was restored 25 June 1676. In addition to carrying out his professional duties, Campbell had a deep interest in mathematics and astronomy and was a correspondent of Sir Isaac Newton. Indeed, the <title>Dictionary of National Biography </title> (1908) tells us that in a letter to James Gregory, Professor of Mathematics at Edinburgh and formerly of St. Andrews, Newton had said of Campbell, 'he would make children of us all'. From his father, Campbell inherited the farm of Drimvuick in the parish, but exchanged these for the farm of Achnaba. Campbell died 13 March 1726. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The Colin Campbell Collection contains Gaelic verse, mainly songs; sermon notes and scripture expositions, the earliest being 1703; manuscript treatises; Colin Campbell correspondence, the earliest being 1664; miscellaneous manuscripts including domestic accounts, medical papers, minutes etc; notebooks, accounts, letters and scraps of Patrick Campbell of Achnaba; letters from mathematicians to Colin Campbell, and mathematical papers; a body of accounts, the earliest being 1553; a body of notebooks; and, bound volumes. </p> </scopecontent> <custodhist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.4."> <p>The Colin Campbell Collection has been preserved and added to by his descendants right down to the modern time. In 1773, his great-granddaughter Elizabeth was married to Angus Gregorson of Ardtornish and their granddaughter, also Elizabeth, was in possession of the Collection until she passed it to her nephew Angus M. Gregorson, circa 1910. Material held on deposit.</p> </custodhist> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details </p> </accessrestrict> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Campbell</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Colin</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1644-1726</emph> </persname> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Gregory</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1638-1675</emph> </persname> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Newton</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Isaac</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1642-1727</emph> </persname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish Gaelic literature</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish literature</emph> <emph altrender="y">To 1700</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Scottish literature</emph> <emph altrender="y">18th century</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Astronomy</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Mathematics</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Mathematicians</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H38; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.5.3."> <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows references to other Colin Campbell mss at La.II.695/1-5. </p> </relatedmaterial> </archdesc>
</ead>
