<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-194" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-194</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Henrietta E. M. Halliwell-Phillipps (d. 1879)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Jan 10 09:35:45 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-194</unitid> <physloc>H-P.Collection 327-330; E97.63</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Henrietta E. M. Halliwell-Phillipps (d. 1879)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1836-1875">1836-1875</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>4 volumes (large), 1 volume (small). </extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Henrietta Elizabeth Molyneux Phillipps was the eldest daughter of Sir Thomas Phillipps (1792-1872), antiquary and bibliophile, and Harriet, the daughter of Lieutenant-General Sir Thomas Molyneux of Castle Dillon, Co. Armagh. Henrietta's father had inherited the estates of Child's Wickham, Buckland, and Middle Hill, around Broadway, Worcestershire. The biographer of Shakespeare, James Orchard Halliwell (1820-1889), was a frequent visitor to the Phillipps home at Middle Hill and although Sir Thomas had refused his consent Henrietta married Halliwell on 9 August 1842. In spite of the ensuing rift between father and daughter, Henrietta inherited Middle Hill on Sir Thomas's death in 1872. That same year she was involved in a riding accident which led to a level of incapacitation, and Halliwell (now called Halliwell-Phillipps) took over the management of the Worcestershire property. Henrietta Elizabeth Molyneux Halliwell-Phillipps died on 25 March 1879. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers consist of the four volume diary of Mrs. Henrietta E. M. Halliwell-Phillipps covering the 1830s to the 1870s . There is a separate additional small diary for 1842.</p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.15. Owens-Pockrich. London: Smith,Elder and Co., 1909. (2) Stephen, Leslie. and Lee, Sidney (eds.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.8. Glover-Harriott. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1908.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>Related material being the Collection of James O. Halliwell-Phillipps (H-P Coll., designated locally as L.O.A.). This collection contains extracts from the diaries of H. E. M. Halliwell-Phillipps and letters to James Orchard Halliwell-Phillipps and others (see local Indexes for shelfmark L.O.A.).</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Halliwell-Phillipps</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Henrietta Elizabeth Molyneux</emph> <emph altrender="dates">d. 1879 </emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Wife of James Orchard Halliwell-Phillipps</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
