<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-593" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-593</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Adrian Hastings (1929-2001)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Caroline Brown, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World, Edinburgh University, and edited by Graeme D Eddie.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Fri Nov 29 12:00:42 UTC 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-593</unitid> <physloc>CSCNWW 36</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Adrian Hastings (1929-2001)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1935-1982">1935-1982</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University, Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World (Thomas Chalmers House, 16 North Bank Street)</repository> <physdesc> <extent>6 boxes</extent> </physdesc> <origination>Hastings, Adrian Christopher</origination> <langmaterial label="Languages"> <language langcode="eng">English, </language> <language langcode="fre">French, </language> and <language langcode="ger">German.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Adrian Christopher Hastings, Catholic priest and theologian, was born in Kuala Lumpur on 23 June 1929 where his father was a lawyer, but was raised, from the age of two, in Worcestershire. Hastings was brought up a Roman Catholic but his family had a long tradition of Anglicanism and throughout his life he was a strong supporter of ecumenicism. He was educated at Benedictine Douai Abbey School and read history at Worcester College, Oxford, graduating in 1949. From an early age Hastings had wanted to work with the church and in his third year at Oxford he had joined the White Fathers with a view to going to Africa as a missionary. It soon became clear to him that to be a missionary would be inadequate and that he should go to Africa as a priest. He managed to secure a post under the only African Catholic bishop at the time, Joseph Kiwanuka of Masaka, Uganda; went to Rome for his training; and was ordained 1955. Three years later he finally left for Masaka where he acted as a curate and taught in the seminary. After the culmination of the Second Vatican Council Hastings was made responsible for disseminating its finding to the region's clergy, which he did from a base in Tanzania between 1966 and 1968. Throughout the 1960s he was involved in forging links with the wider church in Africa and with Anglican communities in particular, and from 1968-1970 was on the staff of the Mindolo Ecumenical Foundation in Zambia. Ill health and his uncertainty about his ability to contribute as a white British theologian to the new independent African churches led Hastings to return to Britain in 1970. He was commissioned to make a study of marriage in Africa then, after a brief spell teaching at Selly Oak, Birmingham, he became, in 1973, Leverhulme Fellow at the School of Oriental African Studies, London where he stayed until 1976. Hastings spent the rest of his career as an academic: as fellow of St Edmund's House, Cambridge (1974-1976); lecturer in religious studies, Aberdeen University (1976-1982); professor of religious studies, University of Zimbabwe (1982-1985); and professor of theology and later head of department, Leeds University (1985-1994). His interests in religion in Africa, and in theology and church history in the 20th century, were reflected in numerous scholarly publications including <title>A History of African Christianity 1950-1975</title> (1979), <title>The Church in Africa 1445-1950</title> (1994), and <title>A History of English Christianity</title> (1986) and he was a respected editor of the <title>Journal of Religion in Africa</title> between 1985 and 1999. Hastings remained a somewhat radical and campaigning figure. He came to public prominence in 1973 during a meeting of the Catholic Institute for International Relations when he spoke out against Portuguese colonial oppression in Africa at the time of a visit of the Portuguese prime minister to Britain. He continued campaigning against injustice in Africa and elsewhere, becoming in the 1990s a founder member of the Alliance to Defend Bosnia-Herzegovina. He also continued to be outspoken against what he perceived as shortcomings in the Catholic church, such as attitudes to contraception and the authoritarianism of the Papacy. These beliefs led him to be marginalised by the Catholic church, in particular after he married Ann Spence in 1979 declaring that the theological justification for compulsory celibacy was wrong. Hastings was widely respected and, shortly before he died, it was proposed to elect him to Fellowship of the British Academy. He died in Leeds on 30 May 2001.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The collection consists of material relating to: Hastings' study of and book on Christian marriage in Africa (1951-1974); the use of catechists in Africa by the Catholic church (1967-1970); the Catholic Institute of International Relations, including publications, papers, minutes and reports (1971-1982); the diploma of religious studies at Makere University, Uganda (1968-1972); seminars in Africa including a seminar for young Catholic men at Lubushi, Zambia (1962), and seminars on the church in Tanzania (1969) and on Christianity in independent Africa (1975); the church and human rights in particular in Africa (1968-1978); the China Study Project (1973-1974); and John Membe (1935, 1969-1977).</p> </scopecontent> <arrangement> <p>Most of the material was arranged in files with titles as above, the remaining material was filed as appropriate.</p> </arrangement> <acqinfo> <p>The material was presented to the Centre for the Study of Christianity in the Non-Western World by Adrian Hastings in the 1990s.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Not certain.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </accessrestrict> <userestrict> <p>Contact the repository for details.</p> </userestrict> <note> <p>The biographical history was compiled using obituaries published in <title>The Times</title> 31 May 2001, <title>The Independent</title> 7 June 2001, and <title>The Guardian</title> 15 June 2001.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>A handlist is available.</p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>It is possible that other papers and similar material was given to the Centre by Adrian Hastings and is now in the Centre library.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Marriage</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hastings</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Adrian</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1929-2001</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Membe</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John Lester</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Catholic Institute for International Relations</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Africa</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
