<?xml version="1.0"?> <!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd"> <ead> <eadheader> <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-1061">GB 237 Coll-1061</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>George Baillie Collection of Music Manuscripts</titleproper> </titlestmt> <publicationstmt><publisher>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections</publisher> <address> <addressline>George Square</addressline> <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline> <addressline>Scotland</addressline> <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline> </address> <date type="single" normal="20070205" certainty="certain">05 February 2007</date> </publicationstmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>EAD generated XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation> <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="ENG">English</language></langusage><descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions compiled in line with the following standards: <bibref> <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards</corpname>, <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard Archival Description</title>, <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint><date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date></imprint> </bibref> and <bibref> <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname><title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate Names</title>, <imprint><date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date></imprint></bibref></descrules> </profiledesc> <!--Enter revisiondesc here if required--> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1061"> <did> <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-1061</unitid> <physloc label="Shelfmark" encodinganalog="shelfmark">E2005.15</physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312">George Baillie Collection of Music Manuscripts</unittitle><unitdate normal="1700/1823" encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" certainty="uncertain">1700-1830</unitdate><repository label="Repository" encodinganalog="NAHSTE31">Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections</repository> <physdesc label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description" encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" audience="external"> <extent type="linear" unit="metre">17 vol. music mss; 4 additional sets manuscripts </extent></physdesc> <langmaterial><language langcode="eng">English</language>; <language langcode="ita">Italian</language></langmaterial> <origination label="Name of Creator(s)" encodinganalog="isadg(2)321">Baillie, George</origination> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322"> <head>Administrative/Biographical History</head> <p>Among the composers represented in the George Baillie collection are: Giovanni Battista Bononcini; and, Alessandro Scarlatti (1660-1725).</p> <p>Giovanni Battista Bononcini was born in Modena, Italy in 1670. He was the eldest son of Giovanni Maria Bononcini (1642-1678). Bononcini trained as a cellist in Bologna where he published two collections of trios (1685) and three of sinfonie (1685-1687). He was a member of the Accademia Filarmonica, and was a musician at San Petronio, and maestro di cappella at Monte San Giovanni, Modena </p> <p>Bononcini went to Milan, commissioned to the Duke of Modena, and then to Rome. In Rome he worked with the poet Silvio Stampiglia on, among other things, an opera, <title>Il trionfo di Camilla</title>, which was the highlight of the Naples Carnival 1696-1697.</p> <p>In 1698, Bononcini was recruited to the court of Leopold I (Holy Roman Emperor) in Vienna where he became a favourite of Joseph, the son and heir, who succeeded as Joseph II (Holy Roman Emperor) in 1705. He was joined in Vienna by Stampiglia and his own younger brother Antonio Maria Bononcini, also a cellist and opera composer. On the death of Joseph II in 1711, Bononcini left the court in Vienna for Rome where he stayed until 1719.</p> <p>Bononcini's work made Italian opera popular in England, partly because it was translated for English voices. In 1719, he was invited to London by the Earl of Burlington to become a composer for the Royal Academy of Music under the direction of G. F. Haendel (Handel). In London, he was well received and his opera <title>Astarto</title> opened at the King's Theatre, Haymarket, in 1720. In the early 1720s he spent some time in Paris, and on his return to London he became director of the private concerts of the Duchess of Marlborough, a post he held until 1731.</p> <p>The early 1730s again saw him in Paris and Lisbon. His last known work was a <title>Te Deum </title> commissioned by the Empress Maria Theresa in 1741. Cellist and composer Giovanni Battista Bononcini died in Vienna in 1747.</p> <p>Alessandro Scarlatti was born in Palermo on 2 May 1660. His first opera was a resounding success and he attracted the attention of Queen Christina of Sweden who made him her 'maestro di cappella'. In 1684 he was appointed 'maestro di cappella'' at the royal court in Naples which he dominated in the production of operas. By 1700 the War of the Spanish Succession was threatening the stability of the court of Naples so Scarlatti moved to Florence in 1702. Failing to find a post at the court of Prince Ferdinando de' Medici, he took his family to Rome where he found a post at the church of San Maria Maggiore. A papal ban of opera forced him to concentrate on writing oratorio and cantatas. In 1707 he was in Venice but his operas failed there and he returned to Rome and to San Maria Maggiore. Life as a church musician gave him little satisfaction and so in 1708 he accepted an invitation from the new Austrian viceroy to return to his post at Naples where he remained there for the rest of his life.</p> <p>Scarlatti's various works included <title>Gli equivoci nel sembiante</title> 1679, <title>Il Pirro e Demetrio </title> 1694, <title>La caduta dei Decemviri</title> 1697, <title>Mitridate Eupatore </title>, <title>Il trionfo della liberta</title>, and <title>La Griselda</title> 1721.</p> <p>Alessandro Scarlatti died in Naples on 22 October 1725.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331"> <head>Scope and Content</head> <p>Much of the material currently contained within the George Baillie Collection has noted upon it the P-purchase number and shelfmark of its older location in the Reid Music Library. These aids are noted below for the benefit of those having accessed the material in the older location.</p> <p>The collection is composed of the following:</p> <p>In Box No: 1 <list> <item><title>Contemporary Yugoslav Music</title> by Dragotin Cvetke. Ph.D. printed, bound</item> <item><title>Ettrick. Rhapsody on an original theme</title> by Ramsay Kay. Mss</item> <item><title>Ettrick. Rhapsody on an original theme</title>by Ramsay Kay. Mss. Score. Parts: flutes, oboes, clarinets, bassoons, horns, trumpets, trombones, tuba, timpani, violins, cello, double bass</item> <item>Work by T.H.Parry-Williams</item> <item><title>Duetti</title> by Steffani. Mss. Bound, P 1432., M78 Stef-4</item> <item><title>Duetti del Grua</title> Mss. P1437., 784.21062(45)</item> <item><title>Cantata di Pergolese</title> 1732. Mss. P 1428., M78 Perg-26</item> <item>Diverse works. P 1435., 784.21(45)</item> </list> </p> <p>In Box No: 2 <list> <item>Diverse works. Mss. Bound</item> <item><title>Di Diversi Cantata</title> by Mr. Bain 1722. Mss. P 1436., 784.5(45)</item> <item><title>Bononcin Cantat</title> by Bononcini. Mss. P 1425., M78 Bon-26</item> <item><title>Scarlatti Arie'</title> Scarlatti Arie'. Mss. P 1430., M78 ScaA-4</item> </list> </p> <p>In Box No: 3 <list> <item><title>Concerto for violin and string orchestra</title> by Hans Gal. Copy. Notebook. M78 Gal-21(6)</item> <item><title>Cantate'</title> Vol.1. Mss. P 1433., 784.5(45)</item> <item><title>Italian duetts</title> 1824. Mss. P 1439., 784.21062(45)</item> <item><title>Italian opera music</title> 1824. Mss. P 1440., 784.21062(45)</item> <item><title>Arie e Cantate del Bononcini</title> Works of Giovanni Battista Bononcini</item> </list> </p> <p>Contained within the musical works, <title>Arie e Cantate del Bononcini</title>, are: <list> <item><title>Sembre tiranno amor</title></item> <item><title>Se amar mi vuoi</title></item> <item><title>Ascolta o Figlio</title></item> <item><title>E'ver che mi piacette</title></item> <item><title>Clori dal colle al prato</title></item> <item><title>Merce' d'amico raggio</title></item> <item><title>Quanto piace agl'occhi mici</title></item> <item><title>Veggio la bella dori</title></item> <item><title>Usignuol che col mio canto</title></item> <item><title>Combattuta alma mia</title></item> <item><title>Fissai caro mio</title></item> <item><title>Clori bell' idol mio</title></item> <item><title>Torno a voi piante amorose</title></item> <item><title>La nuvoletta</title></item> </list></p> <p>There are also two arie by Handel (G. F. Haendal): <list> <item><title>Poterti dir vorrei</title></item> <item><title>Son confusa Pastorella</title></item> </list></p> <p>In Box No: 4 <list> <item><title>Italian duetts</title> 1823. Mss. P 1438., 784.21062(45)</item> <item><title>La Calfurnia arie del Bononcini</title> P 1424., M78 Bon-26</item> <item><title>L'astarto arie del Bononcini</title> P 1423., M78 Bon-26</item> <item><title>Duetto … Alesandro Scarlatti</title> Mss. P 1431 M78 Scar-4(2)</item> </list></p> </scopecontent> <!--Delete any tags not required--><descgrp> <head>Administrative Information</head> <acqinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)324"> <head>Immediate Source of Acquisition</head> <p>Reid Music Library</p> </acqinfo> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341"> <head>Conditions Governing Access</head> <p>Open to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345"> <head>Other Finding Aids</head> <p>A list of material contained in the Baillie Collection has been prepared.</p> </otherfindaid> <note encodinganalog="isadg(2)361" audience="external"> <p>Much biographical and encyclopaedic information about Giovanni Battista Bononcini online. The biographical notes here were created using [online] <extref href="http://www.baroquemusic.org/bqxbononci.html">Baroque Composers and Musicians. Giovanni Battista Bononcini.</extref> [accessed 6 January 2007] and [online] <extref href="http://w3.rz-berlin.mpg.de/cmp/scarlatti_a.html">Extracts from Grove Concise Dictionary of Music.</extref> [accessed 6 January 2007].</p> </note> <processinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)371"> <head>Archivist's Notes</head> <p>Compiled by Graeme D. Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections.</p> </processinfo></descgrp> <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38"> <head>Index</head> <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381"> <head>Subjects</head> <!-- LCSH --> <subject source="lcsh"><emph altrender="a">Music</emph><emph altrender="y">18th century</emph><emph altrender="x"></emph></subject> <subject><emph altrender="a">Violoncellists</emph></subject> <subject><emph altrender="a">Composers</emph></subject> </controlaccess> <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE382"> <head>People</head> <!-- NCA Rules --> <persname><emph altrender="surname">Baillie</emph><emph altrender="forename">George</emph></persname> <persname rules="ncarules"><emph altrender="surname">Bononcini</emph><emph altrender="forename">Giovanni Battista</emph><emph altrender="dates">1670-1747</emph><emph altrender="epithet">Cellist, Composer</emph></persname> <persname><emph altrender="surname">Scarlatti</emph><emph altrender="forename">Alessandro</emph><emph altrender="dates">1660-1725</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Baroque composer</emph></persname> <persname><emph altrender="surname">Handel</emph><emph altrender="forename">George Frideric</emph><emph altrender="dates">1685-1759</emph></persname> </controlaccess> </controlaccess> </archdesc> </ead> 