<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-61" encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-61 </eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Firth of Forth Defences in the 20th Century </titleproper> </titlestmt> </filedesc> <revisiondesc> <change> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </change> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.4./isad(g) 3.4.1./isad(g) 3.4.4./marc 351$c" level="fonds"> <did> <repository> <corpname>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives </corpname> </repository> <unitid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.1./marc 852"> GB 237 Coll-61 </unitid> <physloc>Gen. 978-982; PC 57 </physloc><unittitle encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.2./marc 245">Firth of Forth Defences in the 20th Century </unittitle> <unitdate encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.3./marc 260" normal="1879-1987">1879-1987 </unitdate> <origination encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.1./marc 700">Captain Bruce Alexander Stenhouse </origination> <physdesc encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.1.5./marc 300$a"> <extent>5 boxes; 1 plan chest drawer. </extent> </physdesc> </did> <bioghist encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.2.2./marc 545"> <p>Bruce Alexander Stenhouse was born 15 September 1911 in Sheerness, Kent. He attended preparatory schools in Plymouth and Gibraltar, locations presumably determined by his father's service in the Royal Navy, and then between 1920 and 1930 he attended Edinburgh Academy. During the Second World War he served with the 257 Coast Battery, Royal Artillery, in East Lothian, but he also served in North Africa and Italy. In 1950 he became Registrar at Edinburgh Academy, retiring in 1976. Prior to his retiral he had been toying with the idea of compiling a history of the defence of the coast of Scotland from early times. He set about building up a mass of Public Record Office references from the Admiralty, the Committee for Imperial Defence, and the War Office, and he had sounded out various ex-Forth Coast Gunners and other likely sources for inputs towards the project. Stenhouse died in Edinburgh on 25 April 1991. Stenhouse's research was presented to by his widow in 1996. </p> </bioghist> <scopecontent encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.3.1./marc 520"> <p>The collection includes Public Record Office references, 1879-1956; correspondence of B.A. Stenhouse and Major D. Rollo (Retired), H.Q. Royal Artillery, Woolwich, 1979-1987, relating to research on coastal defence, in addition to miscellaneous correspondence 1976-1990; material relating to batteries and forts, including Forth Artillery Defences 1880-1980; papers relating to the defence of islands; newspaper cuttings; material on attacks and disasters; aerial photographs, and camp and group photographs; and, photographs of ships, armoured trains, and forts and batteries. There is also a plan chest drawer of photographs, maps and plans, including group photographs of the Forth Heavy Brigade and OTC, 1933-1935, camp photographs at Kincraig, 1949, and maps and plans of installations and batteries at Carlingnose, North Queensferry, and Cromarty. </p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.2./marc 540"> <p>Contact the repository for details </p> </accessrestrict> <controlaccess> <persname encodinganalog="marc 700"> <emph altrender="surname">Stenhouse</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Bruce Alexander</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1911-1991</emph> </persname> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Defenses</emph> </subject> <subject source="unesco" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Defence</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Fortification</emph> </subject> <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="marc 650"> <emph altrender="a">Batteries (Ordnance)</emph> </subject> <subject source="aacr2" encodinganalog="marc 651"> <emph altrender="a">Firth of Forth (Scotland)</emph> </subject> </controlaccess> <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isad(g) 3.4.6."> <p>Handlist, H61 </p> </otherfindaid> </archdesc>
</ead>
