<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-865" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-865</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Letters of Francis Wemyss-Charteris (1772-1853), 8th Earl of Wemyss and March</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Sep 15 10:53:07 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-865</unitid> <physloc>Gen. 2042/70-71</physloc><unittitle>Letters of Francis Wemyss-Charteris (1772-1853), 8th Earl of Wemyss and March</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1822-1847">1822-1847</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 letters. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Charteris, Francis Wemyss-</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Francis Wemyss-Charteris was born on 15 April 1772. He succeeded to the lands of Wemyss in August 1808 on the death of his grandfather Francis (1723-1808), 7th Earl of Wemyss. His own father, Francis, Lord Elcho, had died in January 1808. The younger Francis also succeeded to the Earldom of March and the lands and lordship of Neidpath on the death of William, 4th Duke of Queensberry, in 1810. Francis was Lord Lieutenant of Peebleshire. In May 1794 he married Margaret, daughter of Walter Campbell of Shawfield. Francis, 8th Earl of Wemyss and March, died on 28 June 1853. He was succeeded by his son Francis (1796-1883), 9th Earl of Wemyss.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material is composed of letters written by the Earl from Queen Street, and from Stanway Hall, Moreton-in-the-Marsh, Gloucestershire, and signed Charteris Wemyss and March. One letter is to 'My dear sir' and referring to an 'unopened' book that he must return because he has 'been so engaged lately preparing for our departure that I really have had no time to look at it'. Wemyss still hopes 'to have an opportunity of shaking hands' with the correspondent and indicates that he 'can execute any commission' in London for him. The other is to Lord Strathallan indicating that if he is 'well and able to qualify' he can provide help for Strathallan 'at the ensuing General Election'.</p> </scopecontent> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Burke, Sir Bernard. and Burke Ashworth P. <title>A genealogical and heraldic history of the peerage and baronetage, the Privy Council, and knightage</title>. 87th edition. London: Burke's Peerage Ltd., 1929. </p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Charteris</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Francis Wemyss-</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1772-1853</emph> <emph altrender="title">8th Earl of Wemyss and March</emph> </persname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">Great Britain</emph> <emph altrender="x">History</emph> <emph altrender="y">19th century</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
