<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-721" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-721</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Alexander Low Bruce (1839-1893)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Wed Nov 19 11:00:44 UTC 2003</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-721</unitid> <physloc>MSS 2499/11-16</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Alexander Low Bruce (1839-1893)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1873-1893">1873-1893</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>4 volumes, 2 envelopes or folders. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Bruce, Alexander Low</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Alexander Low Bruce was a native of Edinburgh and was born in 1839. He was educated at the city's Royal High School and then received business training in a Leith office. When still a teenager he entered the employment of William Younger, brewers. He went to London becoming a branch manager for the firm at St Paul's wharf, Upper Thames Street. In 1873 he went to the USA to take orders for the firm's products and while there he kept a diary of this extensive tour (which included New York, Boston, Toronto, Ottawa, Quebec, Chicago, Omaha, St Louis, Salt Lake City, San Francisco and New Orleans). In 1876, Bruce married David Livingstone's daughter Agnes. In Edinburgh again, he became a partner then deputy chairman of Younger's. Bruce was deeply interested in the commercial expansion of the British Empire and travelled to Africa in furtherance of this. He was also a keen admirer of the work of the Louis Pasteur whom he had met when French scientist visited the city in 1884. He resolved to make a gesture to the University in memory of Pasteur's visit by promoting the founding of a Chair in the new discipline of Public Health. He did not live to see this however. Alexander Low Bruce died on 27 November 1893.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The papers contain: copies of letters of William Ewing of the Scottish Exploration Company to Alexander Low Bruce and to Cecil J. Rhodes; letters, telegraphs, banquet seating plan; a letter-book; diary of Bruce's <title>American journey 1873</title>; an album of newspaper cuttings; and, a memoriam volume.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Cuttings, <title>American journey 1873</title>, letters, telegraphs, memoriam, acquired from Professor G. Shepperson, October 1988, Accession nos. E88.145-148. Ewing letters, acquired from Professor G. Shepperson, February 1989, Accession no. E89.19. Letter-book, acquired from Professor G. Shepperson, March 1990, Accession no. E90.20.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection, and: (1) <title>Alexander Low Bruce (1839-1893)</title>. Full-text [online]. <extref href="http://www.chs.med.ed.ac.uk/phs/home/bruce.html">Department of Public Health Services Edinburgh University</extref> [Accessed 24 October 2003]. </p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes Bruce related material: 1858-93: correspondence and papers relating to business and politics, 1858-1893, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. Acc 11777.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Diaries</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Bruce</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Alexander Low</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1873-1891</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">son in law of David Livingstone</emph> </persname> <persname source="nra"> <emph altrender="surname">Rhodes</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Cecil John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1853-1902</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Imperialist and Benefactor</emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">William Younger and Co Ltd, brewers</emph> </corpname> <geogname> <emph altrender="a">United States</emph> <emph altrender="x">Description and travel</emph> </geogname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
