<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-788" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-788</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Papers of Erica Hunt (fl. 1920-1984)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Apr 12 09:28:14 UTC+0100 2004</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-788</unitid> <physloc>MSS 2471-2481</physloc><unittitle>Papers of Erica Hunt (fl. 1920-1984)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1892-1969">1892-1969</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>11 boxes. </extent> <physfacet>Access to records in a fragile condition may be restricted.</physfacet> </physdesc> <origination>Hunt, Erica</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Erica Hunt latterly lived in Chirnside, Berwickshire. She had interested herself in family histories, and local lore.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material contained in the collection includes: letters from Jamaica, 1935-1944, and letters from Hunt's mother in Jamaica, pre-1929, in Box 2471; business matters; notes on Wanlockhead families; Norwegian family trees and notes on Norwegian ancestry, in Box 2472; diaries of period in Jamaica, in Box 2473; cuttings, notes, and magazines; material on Blackadder, in Box 2474; notes on Greece, Poland, Moscow and Leningrad (St. Petersburg), 1961-1969; notes on Norway and Germany, 1969; printed material entitled <title>John of the Bass. The story of John Blackadder, Covenant Minister</title>; and, the Hunt family tree, in Box 2475; material in 11 notebooks on Blackadder intermarriages, in Box 2476; newspapers; notes; material on family weddings, in Box 2477; material on Chirnside, Berwickshire, in several loose-leaf folders, in Box 2578; photographs, notes and diaries, in Box 2479; wooden box containing family letters from Giessen, 1892-1895; and, local lore, in Box 2480; and, in Box 2481, loose-leaf note books.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Material received from Mrs. E. Hunt, Edinburgh, 4 November 1984, Accession no. E88.9.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using material contained in the collection.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Hunt</emph> <emph altrender="forename">Erica</emph> <emph altrender="dates">fl 1920-1984</emph> </persname> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Blackadder</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1615-1686</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Scottish Clergyman</emph> </persname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
