<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-434" countrycode="GB">GB 237 Coll-434</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Material relating to Professor John Millar (1735-1801)</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Thu Sep 5 12:15:45 UTC+0100 2002</date> </item> <item> <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date> Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 Coll-434 </unitid> <physloc>Dc.2.45-46; Dc.4.41/108; Dk.7.47/15 </physloc><unittitle>Material relating to Professor John Millar (1735-1801)</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1779-1794">1779-1794</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections Division</repository> <physdesc> <extent>2 manuscript volumes, 2 letters</extent> </physdesc> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English.</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>John Millar was born in the parish of Shotts, Lanarkshire, on 22 June 1735. He was taught to read by his uncle and he went to school in Hamilton. His studies continued in Glasgow and he attended lectures in moral philosophy. Although it was intended that he become a Minister, he followed a course in law. Millar became an Advocate in 1760 and in 1761 became Professor of Law at Glasgow University. He gave lectures in Government, on Civil Law, Jurisprudence, Scottish Law, and English Law. He supported the American struggle for independence and favoured parliamentary reform at home. He supported the agitation against the slave trade and sympathised with French revolutionaries. His works include <title>The origin of the distinction of ranks, or An enquiry into the circumstances which gave rise to influence and authority in the different members of society</title> (1771), and <title>Historical view of the English government from the settlement of the Saxons in Britain to the accession of the House of Stewart</title> (1787). Professor John Millar died at the family estate of Millheugh, Blantyre, on 30 May 1801.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The material includes: a letter to Alexander Carlyle, 1782; student's notes of Millar's lectures on the institutions of civil law, 1794; and, a letter addressed to J. Rait 'at Professor Miller's'.</p> </scopecontent> <acqinfo> <p>Letter to J. Rait has Accession no. E59.4.</p> </acqinfo> <accruals> <p>Check the local Indexes for details of any additions.</p> </accruals> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the following material: (1) Lee, Sidney (ed.). <title>Dictionary of national biography</title>. Vol.13. Masquerier-Myles. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p> </note> <otherfindaid> <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p> </otherfindaid> <relatedmaterial> <p>The local Indexes show a reference to Millar related material in the Laing Collection (check the Indexes for more details): letter to the Earl of Buchan, 1763, at La.II.588. In addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical Manuscripts Commission, notes: lecture notes, Glasgow University Library, Special Collections Department, see Sturges, Economists papers 1750-1950, 1975, Accessions to repositories 1983; lecture notes, 1779-1781, National Library of Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 2743, 3930-31; lecture notes, 1782, Aberdeen University, Special Libraries and Archives, see Sturges, Economists papers 1750-1950, 1975; and, letters to William Adam, 1784-1799, Private, Ref. NRA(S)0063 NRA 9954 Adam.</p> </relatedmaterial> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Civil law</emph> </subject> <persname source="ncarules"> <emph altrender="surname">Millar</emph> <emph altrender="forename">John</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1735-1801</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Law Professor </emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Glasgow University</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
