<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!--prepared using the archives hub isad(g) template version 2, from the university of liverpool library-->
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead> <eadheader> <eadid mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 EUA GD17" countrycode="GB">GB 237 EUA GD17</eadid> <filedesc> <titlestmt> <titleproper>Records of the Natural History Society of Edinburgh</titleproper> </titlestmt> <notestmt> <note> <p>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections.</p> </note> </notestmt> </filedesc> <profiledesc> <creation>This document was generated by Javascript from an HTML form which structured the input according to the elements of ISAD(G) Version 2.</creation> </profiledesc> <revisiondesc> <list> <item> Modified at: <date> Mon Dec 17 16:32:00 GMT+0000 (GMT Standard Time) 2001</date> </item> <item>Converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02.xsl (sy2003-10-15), <date normal="20050223">23 February 2005</date></item> </list> </revisiondesc> </eadheader> <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-EUA-GD17"> <did> <unitid>GB 237 EUA GD17 (formerly Da 67 NAT)</unitid> <unittitle>Records of the Natural History Society of Edinburgh</unittitle> <unitdate normal="1782/1806">1782-1806</unitdate> <repository>Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections</repository> <physdesc> <extent>13 volumes</extent> </physdesc> <origination>Natural History Society of Edinburgh</origination> <langmaterial label="Language"> <language langcode="eng">English</language> </langmaterial> </did> <bioghist> <p>Societas Naturae Studiosorum Edinburgena or the Natural History Society of Edinburgh was set up in 1782 with the object of investigating Natural History and Chemistry. The Society was founded by James Edward Smith (1759-1828) and four or five of his friends. It would be 'a society for the prosecution of natural history'. It continued for some thirty years, coming to an end in 1812 when it was absorbed by the Royal Physical Society of Edinburgh which despite its name had a pronounced natural history orientation.</p> </bioghist> <scopecontent> <p>The records consist of: a photo-copy of <title>Laws of the Society instituted at Edinburgh for the investigation of Natural History</title> published in Edinburgh by C. Stewart, 1803; and, twelve volumes covering the period 1782 to 1806 containing manuscript accounts of papers read to the Society. Early examples of these include <title>A account of the Capra ibex and Capra Rupicapia</title> read on 12 April 1782, and <title>An essay on collecting and preserving specimens of plants</title> read on 19 April 1782.</p> </scopecontent> <accessrestrict> <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please contact repository for details in advance.</p> </accessrestrict> <note> <p>The administrative/biographical history was compiled using the material contained in the collection, and in: James Edward Smith and the Natural History Society of Edinburgh, by D. E. Allen. <title>The Journal of the Society for the Bibliography of Natural History</title>. 1978. Vol.8. No.4. pp.483-493. London : The Society, 1936-1980.</p> </note> <!-- control access terms --> <controlaccess> <subject source="lcsh"> <emph altrender="a">Natural history</emph> </subject> <persname source="othersource"> <emph altrender="surname">Smith</emph> <emph altrender="forename">James Edward</emph> <emph altrender="dates">1759-1828</emph> <emph altrender="title">Sir</emph> <emph altrender="epithet">Knight, Botanist </emph> </persname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Natural History Society of Edinburgh</emph> </corpname> <corpname> <emph altrender="a">Royal Physical Society of Edinburgh</emph> </corpname> </controlaccess> </archdesc>
</ead>
