<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-44">GB 237
		Coll-44</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Pollock-Morris
			 Correspondence. Letters of Professor Robert Jameson (1774-1854) </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-44">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Pollock-Morris
			 Correspondence. Letters of Professor Robert Jameson (1774-1854) </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code"> GB 237 Coll-44</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Gen. 1996/1-17 </physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Pollock-Morris Correspondence. Letters
		  of Professor Robert Jameson (1774-1854) </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1812-1854">1812-1854 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>17 box
		  files (1 linear metre). </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>The mineralogist Robert Jameson was born in Leith on 11 July 1774. His
		  early education was received in Leith and then he became the apprentice of a
		  surgeon in Leith, with the aim of going to sea. He also attended classes at
		  Edinburgh University, studying medicine, botany, chemistry, and natural
		  history. By 1793, and influenced by the Professor of Natural History, John
		  Walker (1731-1803), he abandoned medicine and the idea of being a ship's
		  surgeon, and focused instead on science, particularly geology and mineralogy.
		  Jameson was given the responsibility of looking after the University's museum.
		  In 1793, he went to London, meeting naturalists and visiting museums to take
		  notes. A visit to the Shetland Islands followed in 1794, to explore the
		  geology, mineralogy, zoology and botany there. This led to the publication of 
		The mineralogy of the Shetland Islands and of Arran, with an
		  appendix containing observations on peat, kelp, and coal  (1798).
		Earlier, in 1796, Jameson read two papers rejecting the vulcanist
		interpretation of the formation of Earth that had been put forward by Edinburgh
		geologist James Hutton (1726-1797). Hutton had propounded the theory that the
		features of the Earth's crust were caused by natural processes over geologic
		time; the principle of uniformitarianism. Instead, Jameson supported the ideas
		of Abraham Gottlob Werner (1750-1817) who had proclaimed the aqueous origin of
		rocks; that rocks were formed when immense quantities of minerals precipitated
		out of the waters of the biblical flood. Other visits to the Scottish islands
		in the north and west, and to Ireland, produced the two volume 
		Mineralogy of the Scottish isles  (1800) which was a
		fuller description of his views. In 1800, he spent a year at the mining academy
		in Freiburg, Saxony, to study under Werner. He returned to Edinburgh in 1802.
		On the death of Walker in 1803, Jameson was appointed Regius Professor of
		Natural History and Keeper of the University Museum. Over his fifty year
		tenure, he built up a huge collection of mineralogical and geological specimens
		for the Museum, including fossils, birds and insects. Although he had been one
		of the great exponents of Werner's geological tenets and founded the Wernerian
		Natural History Society in 1808, Jameson afterwards admitted conversion to the
		views of Hutton. He died in Edinburgh on 19 April 1854. Shortly after his
		death, the University Museum was transferred to the Crown and became part of
		the Royal Scottish Museum (now Royal Museum) in Edinburgh's Chambers Street.
		</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The Jameson Letters in Gen. 1996/15-17, from other correspondents,
		  hold a wide range of content, mostly in English, but some in German and French,
		  on matters ranging from accounts and bills, the health of Abraham Gottlob
		  Werner, Jameson's own health, specimens and catalogue of minerals,
		  contributions to journals, and various introductions. Some of the letters are
		  also about personal matters and plans. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)324">
        <head>Immediate source of acquisition</head>
        <p>Papers referred to as the Pollock-Morris collection of manuscripts
		  were preserved by Mrs. Jane Catherine Pollock-Morris, the great-grand-niece of
		  Robert Jameson. Pollock-Morris was the mother of Mrs. Seton Dickson of
		  Symington, Ayrshire, owner of the Pollock-Morris MSS in the late-1960s, and who
		  gifted several Jameson items to Edinburgh University Library. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H44; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows papers and correspondence of Robert
		  Jameson at Gen. 121-131, notebooks containing diaries of tours and
		  mineralogical notes of walks at Dc.7.125-136. Other journals, notes, and
		  letters of Professor Jameson are within Gen. 1999. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
