<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-40">GB
		237 Coll-40</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Papers of James Murray, 2nd Duke of Atholl
			 (1690-1764)</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-40">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Papers of James Murray, 2nd Duke of Atholl
			 (1690-1764)</unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-40</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Dc.1.37/1-2</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Papers of James Murray, 2nd Duke
		  of Atholl (1690-1764)</unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1701-1799">18th century</unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>circa 150 letters. </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label="">
        <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>James Murray was born on 28 September 1690. He was the third son of
		  John Murray, 2nd Marquis and 1st Duke of Atholl (1660-1724). By June 1714, Lord
		  James had reached the ranks of Captain and Lt.-Col. in the 1st Footguards
		  (King's Company). Then came the Jacobite Rebellion of 1715 in support of the
		  'Old Pretender', James Francis Edward Stewart (1688-1766), and led by John
		  Erskine, 11th Earl of Mar. Lord James joined the Duke of Argyll's government
		  forces at Perth in January-February 1716 and marched in pursuit of the
		  Jacobites to Aberdeen. To the north, at Peterhead, the 'Old Pretender' had
		  arrived from Lorraine just before Christmas, but with the collapse of the
		  Rebellion he sailed from Montrose, Angus, just a few weeks later.</p>
      <p>Lord James' older brother, William Murray, Marquis of Tullibardine
		  (1689-1746), had taken part in the indecisive Rebellion and his rights to the
		  family honours and estates were therefore stripped from him by Act of
		  Parliament. These would now pass to Lord James since the eldest brother, John
		  Murray, had been killed earlier at the Battle of Malplaquet in August 1709.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, in 1715, Lord James had been elected MP for Perthshire, and
		  in 1722 he was chosen again. On the death of his father in 1724, he became 2nd
		  Duke of Atholl. His rather than William's succession to the family honours and
		  estates was confirmed by a new Act of Parliament in 1733. That same year he was
		  appointed Lord Privy Seal. In 1734, he received the Order of the Thistle. In
		  1736, James Murray, now 2nd Duke of Atholl, also inherited sovereignty of the
		  Isle of Man and an English barony through a family connection to the 10th Earl
		  of Derby. Between 1737 and 1741 he was able to sit in Parliament both as an
		  English Baron and a Scottish Peer.</p>
      <p>In July 1745, the 'Young Pretender' Prince Charles Edward Stewart
		  (1720-1788) accompanied by William Murray (titular Duke of Atholl) and six
		  other supporters landed at Moidart in the west of Scotland. Within six weeks of
		  the raising of the Jacobite standard at Glenfinnan in August 1745, Charles had
		  overrun Scotland and James Murray had fled southwards. The dispossessed William
		  Murray now took possession of Blair Castle in Perthshire, the family seat.</p>
      <p>By December, the Jacobites had reached Derby, and although still
		  undefeated they won practically no support either in the Lowlands of Scotland
		  or in England, and they began a fateful withdrawal to Scotland. James Murray
		  joined the army of the Duke of Cumberland in pursuit of Prince Charles and the
		  Jacobites and arrived in Edinburgh on 30 January 1746. He continued northwards
		  to the Atholl estates and summoned his men to attend him and to join the
		  government troops in their march towards Inverness. In April 1746, at the
		  Battle of Culloden, the last battle to be fought on British soil, the Jacobites
		  were defeated. James Murray, 2nd Duke of Atholl, regained Blair Castle and the
		  Atholl estates.</p>
      <p>In 1763, Murray resigned the office of Lord Privy Seal on his
		  appointment as Keeper of the Great Seal and as Lord Justice General. James
		  Murray, 2nd Duke of Atholl, died at Dunkeld, Perthshire, on 8 January 1764.
		  </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The collection contains letters to the Duke about the Jacobite
		  Rebellion, 1745-1746, along with a few earlier papers.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Generally open for consultation to bona fide researchers, but please
		  contact repository for details in advance.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Important finding aids generally are: the alphabetical Index to
		  Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives, consisting of typed slips in sheaf binders and to which additions
		  were made until 1987; and the Index to Accessions Since 1987. </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>Check the local Indexes for references to the Atholl family. In
		  addition, the UK National Register of Archives (NRA), updated by the Historical
		  Manuscripts Commission, notes the following relating to James Murray, 2nd Duke
		  of Atholl: correspondence and papers, 1681-1714, Blair Castle, Ref. NRA(S)0234
		  NRA 11000 Stewart-Murray; legal correspondence, 1705-1723, National Library of
		  Scotland, Manuscripts Division, Ref. MS 1403, and correspondence with the 1st
		  and 2nd Marquesses of Tweeddale, 1696-1716, National Library of Scotland,
		  Manuscripts Division, Ref. MSS 6487, 6488, 7020-7030, 7104 passim;
		  correspondence with the Earl of Dunmore, circa 1703-1710, College of William
		  and Mary, NRA 22219 Murray; letters to Lord Godolphin, 1703-1708, British
		  Library, Manuscript Collections, Ref. Add MS 28055; letters to Duchess of
		  Hamilton, 1713-1716, Private, Ref. NRA(S)2177/C3 NRA 10979 Hamilton;
		  correspondence (15 items) with Lord Leven, 1708-1721, National Archives of
		  Scotland, Ref. GD26/13/152 NRA 29368 Leslie Melville, also correspondence with
		  Earl of Mar, Ref. GD124 NRA 32022 Erskine, and letters to Duke of Montrose,
		  1703-1717, Ref. GD 220/5 NRA 32572 Graham.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <note>
        <head>Note</head>
        <p>The biographical/administrative history was compiled using the
		  following material: (1) Keay, John. and Keay, Julia (eds.). 
		Collins encyclopaedia of Scotland. London: Harper Collins,
		1994. (2) Lee, Sidney (ed.). 
		Dictionary of national biography. Vol.13.
		Masquerier-Myles. London: Smith, Elder and Co., 1909.</p>
        <head>Archivist's Note</head>Compiled by Graeme D Eddie, Edinburgh University Library, Special
				Collections Division</note>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
