<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 PC Coll-13">GB 237
		Coll-13</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>William Playfair Architectural Drawings</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-13">
    <did>
      <unittitle>William Playfair Architectural Drawings</unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-13</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">PC Playfair 1-72</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">William Playfair Architectural
		  Drawings</unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1817/1849">1817-1849</unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>5062
		  drawings in 72 plan chest drawers. </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <origination encodinganalog="isadg(2)321" label="Name(s) of creators">William Henry
		  Playfair</origination>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>The architect William Henry Playfair was born in Russell Square,
		  London, July 1789. On the death of his father, Playfair was sent to reside with
		  his uncle in Edinburgh. Professor John Playfair, mathematician and geologist
		  and a leading figure in the Edinburgh Enlightenment, took control of his
		  nephew's education. Following his father's profession, the young Playfair
		  studied under William Starke of Glasgow. His first public appointment was the
		  laying out of part of the New Town in Edinburgh in 1815. Then, after a visit to
		  France in 1816, he established himself professionally by winning the commission
		  in 1817 to complete the unfinished University buildings (leaving the front as
		  designed by Robert and James Adam). He also designed the city's Royal Terrace
		  and Regent Terrace on the Calton Hill estate; the unfinished National Monument
		  on Calton Hill; and, the Royal Scottish Academy and the National Gallery on the
		  Mound. While Playfair's most important works in Edinburgh have been executed in
		  the Greek revivalist or classical style - earning for Edinburgh the title of
		  'Athens of the North' - he was competent in other styles too. New College,
		  housing the University's Faculty of Divinity and the Church of Scotland's
		  General Assembly Hall (the latter being the temporary home of the Scottish
		  Parliament from 1999) is a jagged-lined rendering of the Gothic style. He also
		  built country houses and mansions in the Italianate and Tudor styles. Playfair
		  died in Edinburgh after a long illness on 27 May 1857. After his death, his
		  drawings - regarded as valuable academic remains of a leading figure in
		  Edinburgh's Enlightenment - were preserved in the Library of the University of
		  Edinburgh. While the University expressed willingness to accept the drawings,
		  they asked that they should be catalogued. This was quite a task for Playfair's
		  Trustees when they examined the contents of the Playfair house and office at 17
		  Great Stuart Street in the city's New Town, and so they retained James A.
		  Hamilton, Playfair's clerk, to sort and catalogue the drawings. Over five
		  thousand drawings were eventually presented to the University. However, an
		  almost equal amount of material was rejected as unworthy of presentation and
		  probably included sketch books, preliminary designs and returned presentation
		  drawings, competition designs, specifications and letters. When Playfair's
		  library and picture collection were auctioned (by Nisbet of Hanover Street,
		  Edinburgh) in November 1857, no mention was made of the rejected material. One
		  of the questions for history is, what happened to the material discarded by
		  Hamilton? </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The drawings in the collection range from Playfair's student drawings,
		  sketch designs and preliminary schemes, to many presentation drawings in
		  watercolours. The earliest catalogued plans, elevations and sections relate to
		  the commission to complete the University (the College of Edinburgh), 1817
		  onwards. The Advocates' Library, Royal Terrace, Regent Terrace, the National
		  Gallery, the National Monument, and New College also feature in the collection.
		  Other material relates to the Observatory, Edinburgh, and Dollar Academy and
		  Bathgate Academy, and other commissions up to around 1849. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H13: 
		Catalogue of Architectural Drawings by W.H. Playfair </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
