<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-51">GB 237
		Coll-51</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Papers relating to Sir Roderick Impey Murchison and his
			 Family </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-51">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Papers relating to Sir Roderick Impey Murchison and his
			 Family </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code"> GB 237 Coll-51
		  </unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">MS 2216; MSS 2262-2268 </physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Papers relating to Sir Roderick Impey
		  Murchison and his Family </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1771-1935">1771-1935 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>7 boxes (1
		  m). </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>Roderick Impey Murchison was born 19 February 1792 at Tarradale, in
		  Ross-shire, Scotland. He was the eldest son of Kenneth Murchison by his wife,
		  the daughter of Roderick Mackenzie of Fairburn. Murchison went to grammar
		  school in Durham and in 1805 was sent to the military college, Great Marlow,
		  after which he joined the 36th regiment and saw action in Portugal and at
		  Corunna. Murchison's army career also took him to Sicily, Ireland, and Paris.
		  Marriage in 1814 marked a turning point in his life and a tour of Europe was
		  followed by a settled country life. In the early 1820s, acquaintanceship with
		  Sir Humphrey Davy encouraged the pursuit of a scientific career and in 1824 he
		  attended lectures at the Royal Institution. In 1825 he became a fellow of the
		  Geological Society of London and that same year his first paper was read to the
		  Society, on the geology of parts of Sussex, Hants and Surrey. In the following
		  five years Murchison explored Scotland, France, and the Alps, working with Adam
		  Sedgwick and Charles Lyell. In 1831 he was elected president of the Geological
		  Society and the same year he and Sedgwick began a study of Wales. Murchison's
		  studies of the Early Paleozic rocks in South Wales were the basis of his work 
		The Silurian System  (1839). With the establishment of the
		Silurian system, research into the geology of south western England and the
		Rhineland founded the Devonian System, and Russian explorations became the
		basis for his proposal of the Permian System. Out of the Russian expeditions,
		Murchison, with others, wrote 
		The geology of Russia in Europe and the Ural Mountains 
		(1845). Murchison was knighted in 1846, and he was appointed director general
		of the Geological Survey of Great Britain, and director of the Royal School of
		Mines and the Museum of Practical Geology, London, in 1855. Between 1863 and
		1871 he was Patron of the Edinburgh Geological Society and in 1871 he founded a
		chair of geology and mineralogy at the University of Edinburgh. Struck by
		paralysis in 1870, Murchison died after an attack of bronchitis on 22 October
		1871. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The material in the collection includes single letters to and from
		  Roderick Impey Murchison, 1816-1865; the history, chronology, and genealogy of
		  the family; documents relating to Murchison's father, Kenneth Murchison,
		  1751-1796; and, materials relating to Murchison himself, such as notebooks,
		  account books, passport, diary, medals, and illuminated scroll. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H51 </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
