<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-38">GB 237
		Coll-38</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Colin Campbell
			 Collection </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-38">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Colin Campbell
			 Collection </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-38</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">MSS 3096-3102</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Colin Campbell Collection </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1553-1836">1553-1836 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>7 boxes (1
		  m). </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <origination encodinganalog="isadg(2)321" label="Name(s) of creators">Colin Campbell of
		  Achnaba </origination>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>Colin Campbell, the son of Patrick (Dubh Beg) Campbell of
		  Innerzeldies, ancestor of the Barcaldine family, was born in 1644. He was
		  educated at St. Salvator's College, St. Andrews, graduating on 27 July 1661.
		  Thereafter he may have studied at one of the English universities either as a
		  companion or tutor to his relative, Robert of Glenorchy (Sir Robert Campbell of
		  Glenorchy) an ancestor of the marquises of Breadalbane. In 1666 or 1667 he was
		  admitted as minister of the Parish Church of Ardchattan and Muckairn in Lorne.
		  On 12 January 1676 he was suspended from the ministry on a charge of
		  pre-nuptial intercourse but was restored 25 June 1676. In addition to carrying
		  out his professional duties, Campbell had a deep interest in mathematics and
		  astronomy and was a correspondent of Sir Isaac Newton. Indeed, the 
		Dictionary of National Biography  (1908) tells us that in
		a letter to James Gregory, Professor of Mathematics at Edinburgh and formerly
		of St. Andrews, Newton had said of Campbell, 'he would make children of us
		all'. From his father, Campbell inherited the farm of Drimvuick in the parish,
		but exchanged these for the farm of Achnaba. Campbell died 13 March 1726. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The Colin Campbell Collection contains Gaelic verse, mainly songs;
		  sermon notes and scripture expositions, the earliest being 1703; manuscript
		  treatises; Colin Campbell correspondence, the earliest being 1664;
		  miscellaneous manuscripts including domestic accounts, medical papers, minutes
		  etc; notebooks, accounts, letters and scraps of Patrick Campbell of Achnaba;
		  letters from mathematicians to Colin Campbell, and mathematical papers; a body
		  of accounts, the earliest being 1553; a body of notebooks; and, bound volumes.
		  </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <custodhist encodinganalog="isadg(2)323">
        <head>Archival History</head>
        <p>The Colin Campbell Collection has been preserved and added to by his
		  descendants right down to the modern time. In 1773, his great-granddaughter
		  Elizabeth was married to Angus Gregorson of Ardtornish and their granddaughter,
		  also Elizabeth, was in possession of the Collection until she passed it to her
		  nephew Angus M. Gregorson, circa 1910. Material held on deposit.</p>
      </custodhist>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H38; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows references to other Colin Campbell mss
		  at La.II.695/1-5. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
