<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-36">GB 237
		Coll-36</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Archives of
			 Messrs. Christian Salvesen Limited </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-36">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Archives of
			 Messrs. Christian Salvesen Limited </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-36</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Gen. 1925 </physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Archives of Messrs. Christian Salvesen
		  Limited </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1852-1969">1852-1969 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>100 boxes,
		  331 volumes (55 linear metres). </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label="">
        <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
      </langmaterial>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>The firm of Christian Salvesen Ltd. was first founded as a private
		  unlimited company in 1872. The firm began in premises in Bernard Street, Leith,
		  bought by Salve Christian Fredrik Salvesen, a Norwegian from Mandal, for
		  business as a shipbroker and shipowner. Christian Salvesen had first arrived in
		  Scotland in 1851 to manage a Grangemouth shipbroking business owned by his
		  brother, Johann Theodor Salvesen, in partnership with the Edinburgh merchant
		  George Vair Turnbull. The firm imported grain for domestic use and for
		  distillation, and timber for pit-props, housebuilding, and for railway
		  sleepers. Exports were mainly coal and iron. In addition to these commodities,
		  the firm also dealt in cargoes of salt and Norwegian herring, and high profits
		  were obtained from the flood of Australia-bound migrants and gold prospectors.
		  In 1853, Salve Christian Fredrik took Johann Theodor's place as a partner and
		  carried on in the firm until 1872 when he went into business on his own. This
		  coincided with the advent of the steamship and the expansion of maritime
		  commerce with German and Baltic ports following the Franco-Prussian war. Later
		  on, in the 1880s, three of his sons would join him and carry on the business
		  after his death in 1911. By then the firm's vessels were trading with ports on
		  the Baltic, and in Norway and Sweden, and were servicing whaling stations in
		  the Arctic, Iceland and the Faroe Islands. Cargo lines were also opened up
		  between Leith, Malta, and Alexandria, and then into the Black Sea. During the
		  first decade of the 20th century, the shipping industry was in a depressed
		  state and, globally, shipping companies made heavy losses. The Salvesen fleet
		  fared no better, although the company's whaling interests which had expanded as
		  far as the Falkland Islands and South Georgia did help it at times to show
		  profit. In the early decades of that century, whaling dominated Salvesen's
		  business and indeed the firm led the whaling industry at a time when food oils
		  and other products from the Antarctic were considered a boundless resource. A
		  third generation of Salvesens had entered the business in the troubled economic
		  period of the inter-war years. The firm managed to ride these out, and in
		  whaling it expanded and modernised. As stocks began to diminish however, the
		  firm of Salvesen - whalers for nearly 70 years - was prominent in urging
		  conservation. By the 1960s and 1970s a fourth generation was still playing an
		  important role in the firm, although by then Salvesen was no longer a family
		  firm. Diversification had been an important key to the survival of the firm
		  over these decades, from importing and exporting of timber and coal, to whaling
		  and a tanker fleet, shipping steel and coke to Norway for the Norwegian
		  shipbuilding and steel industries, factory fishing trawlers, and then to
		  shore-based cold storage, canning, property development and also to
		  house-building. Into the 21st century it is as frozen food merchants and for
		  the distribution of quick frozen vegetables that the name Christian Salvesen
		  PLC is better known. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The Archives of Christian Salvesen Ltd. span well over one hundred
		  years from the 1850s to the 1960s. They contain ledgers, private journals, cash
		  books, invoice books, letter books, day books, official files, station records,
		  stock books and accounts, correspondence and documents, order books, records of
		  telegrams of Turnbull, Salvesen &amp;amp; Co., Christian Salvesen &amp;amp;
		  Co., and South Georgia Co., and various subsidiary companies. There is material
		  relating to Salvesen ships generally, in the form of ship books with shares,
		  dividends, proceeds and etc., ship ledgers, outward and inward manifest books,
		  valuations of Salvesen ships, tanker voyages, and correspondence and documents;
		  and, material relating to individual ships in the form of voyage books,
		  ledgers, day books, and order books. There are particulars of ports arranged
		  alphabetically. The collection includes material on whaling including sales and
		  purchases of whale products; catch records from 1914-1946; notes regarding
		  whaling activities; cargo and sales; position books showing position of ships;
		  scientific results of marine biological research; and, correspondence and
		  documents. There is material relating to Government Ministries such as the
		  Ministry of Food and the Ministry of War Transport in the form correspondence
		  and documents; material on the Salvesen partners and others, including
		  financial papers, investment registers, personal papers, diaries, notebooks,
		  letter books, letters, and estate matters; and, staff material such as income
		  tax returns, ledgers, salaries books, and correspondence and documents relating
		  to sea-going staff and whaling officers. Other miscellaneous material includes
		  newspaper cuttings and photographs; some volumes of Lloyd's register; history
		  records; personal and private biographical material on the Salvesen family;
		  insurance correspondence; donations, subscriptions, patronage related to
		  Salvesen charitable interests; desk diaries; and, other miscellaneous records.
		  </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)324">
        <head>Immediate source of acquisition</head>
        <p>The archives of Messrs. Christian Salvesen Limited were surveyed by
		  the National Register of Archives (Scotland) in 1968, and then in 1969 and in
		  subsequent years they were transferred from the various office premises of the
		  firm to be placed on deposit in Edinburgh University Library. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H36 </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
