<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-39">GB 237
		Coll-39</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>The Allinson Papers </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-39">
    <did>
      <unittitle>The Allinson Papers </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code"> GB 237 Coll-39</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">MSS 3186-3197 </physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">The Allinson Papers </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1881-1984">1881-1984 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>1 box; 8
		  scrapbook albums; 3 folders. </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>Thomas Richard Allinson held particular views on how best to restore
		  the sick back to health again. He advocated hydrotherapy, abstention from
		  tobacco and alcohol, fresh air, no drugs or vaccination, and a healthy
		  vegetarian and wholemeal diet. Allinson was born 29 March 1858 in Hulme,
		  Manchester. He went to school in Lancaster and Manchester. In 1874 he was a
		  medical student in Edinburgh, at the Royal College of Surgeons. While in
		  Edinburgh, he is said to have won a medal in practical chemistry, and a special
		  prize in public health, and to have taken a double qualification as a
		  Licentiate of the Royal College of Surgeons and Physicians, LRCSP. After
		  studying in Edinburgh he assisted in a general practice in Hull, followed by a
		  visit to Paris. Around this time he became interested in hydrotherapy - the use
		  of water in the treatment of illnesses. He was next to be found assisting in a
		  general practice in Shoreditch where he acted as police surgeon and parish
		  doctor. While in Shoreditch, Allinson developed an opposition to stimulants
		  such as alcohol and tobacco, advocating abstention from alcohol consumption.
		  Vegetarianism became an interest of his too, and he joined the Food Reform
		  Society. In 1887, he wrote an article strongly opposed to drugs which he said
		  were poisons, and to vaccination which he said was dangerous. Instead, he
		  advocated a healthy diet and exercise. He was of course attacked by other
		  doctors and, after lengthy public and professional debate over his arguments,
		  Edinburgh's Royal College of Surgeons struck him off the roll. Undaunted, he
		  continued to use the letters Ex-LRCP.Ed after his name. In 1890, Allinson
		  opened the Hygienic Hospital in Willesden where patients were treated according
		  to his principles of hygienic medicine. He wrote widely on the advantages of
		  wholemeal bread and wholemeal and vegetarian cookery, and in 1892 he purchased
		  a stone grinding flour mill in London's Bethnal Green. This was established as
		  the Natural Food Company Ltd., 305 Cambridge Road, London. Allinson died in
		  1918 but after his death the demand for wholemeal bread continued to rise and
		  two more mills were acquired in Newport, Monmouthshire, and Castleford,
		  Yorkshire. Today, Allinson traditional flour is part of the product range of
		  Allied Mills Ltd. The material known as the Allinson Papers was presented to in
		  June 1987 by Booker Health Foods, one of the trade names of which, at that
		  time, was Allinson. In the 1980s, the parent company of Booker Health Foods
		  Ltd. was Booker McConnell plc, later Booker plc. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The collection of Allinson Papers consists of a mixed box of small
		  printed items and pamphlets, posters, photographs, and bundles of newspaper and
		  magazine cuttings; a number of scrapbook albums containing mainly newspaper
		  cuttings relating to Allinson, and dating variously from 1881 to 1918; and,
		  folders containing scrapbooks of newspaper cuttings, handbills, and lecture
		  posters from the 1880s to 1918. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H39 </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
