<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-25">GB 237
		Coll-25</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Papers of Thomas
			 Nelson &amp;amp; Sons Ltd. </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-25">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Papers of Thomas
			 Nelson &amp;amp; Sons Ltd. </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code"> GB 237 Coll-25</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Gen. 1728/1-821 </physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Papers of Thomas Nelson &amp;amp; Sons
		  Ltd. </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1861-1960">1861-1960 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>66 boxes,
		  156 document bundles, 290 letter books, 27 ledgers (64 linear metres).
		  </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>The British publishing firm of Nelson is still a prominent one. The
		  firm has a long history and its name is derived from a small bookselling
		  business established in Edinburgh in 1789. The founder of the bookshop was
		  Thomas Neilson (1780-1861). Neilson extended his interests to include
		  publishing, particularly of religious and educational texts, and he began with
		  the publication, in monthly parts, of 
		The Pilgrim's Progress . In 1818, the name of the firm was
		changed to Thomas Nelson because of the tendency among customers to misspell
		Neilson. In 1835, Thomas was joined in the business by his son William Nelson
		(1816-1887) and a little later by his younger son Thomas Nelson (1822-1892) who
		joined the firm at the age of seventeen. The business, located in Edinburgh's
		West Bow, gradually built up and extended based on the formula of reprinting
		standard authors at low prices. In 1852, the elder Thomas retired, and in 1858
		the name of the firm changed to Thomas Nelson and Sons, as it has remained ever
		since. Earlier, in 1844, the younger Thomas was given the task of establishing
		a London branch in Paternoster Row, and in 1854 a New York office opened in the
		city's Nassau Street. In Edinburgh during 1845-46, the firm transferred from
		the West Bow to larger custom-built premises at Hope Park just to the south of
		the old part of the city. At Hope Park, with a workforce of six hundred, all
		the activities connected with the production of books were carried out under
		one roof: printing, stereotyping, bookbinding, lithographing, engraving,
		woodcutting, warehousing, and even dyeing of the plain white calico used in
		bindings. From 1856, colour-printing became a feature of their production and
		by 1860 the firm was the leading publisher of cheap colour-printed titles. In
		1878 however, the Hope Park factory caught fire and nothing was saved except
		the stereotyped plates. Even as the building burned, Thomas was ordering new
		machinery and temporary accommodation, and within a year new buildings were
		raised and all departments were in full production again. From his earliest
		years with the firm, Thomas exhibited a mechanical bent and in 1850 he invented
		a rotary press with curved stereotyped plates fixed on cylinders and with a
		continuous web of paper - the type of press used in the newspaper industry well
		into the 20th century. The production of Thomas Nelson and Sons was largely
		focused on story books and books of travel and adventure by popular authors,
		and particularly intended for young readers. A series of school books was
		initiated, and after the Education Act of 1871 which had prompted a demand for
		improved school-books Nelson's began their series of 
		Royal readers . In the early 1900s, and certainly in 1907,
		John Buchan (1875-1940), writer of fiction and history, was a member and
		literary adviser to Thomas Nelson and Sons. The firm also published his work.
		Nelson had also published works by Bagehot, Belloc, G.K.Chesterton, Erskine
		Childers, H. J. Newbolt, Mark Twain, and H.G. Wells, among many others. Today,
		Nelson's is one of Britain's leading publishers of educational titles, offering
		materials for all ages, from nursery level to further education, and in all
		subject areas. In March 2000 its head office was in Walton-on-Thames, Surrey.
		</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The Papers of Thomas Nelson &amp;amp; Sons Ltd. consist of: general
		  day books, ledgers, account books, details of sundry creditors, letter books,
		  and commission books for the years 1861-1915; general correspondence and
		  letters to and from a variety of individuals 1895-1960; material from trade
		  representatives, editorial notices, sales department material; and other
		  miscellaneous material. Within the Nelson Papers there is a very large body of
		  correspondence between John Buchan and Nelson's covering the years 1909-1929.
		  The correspondence includes letters about manuscripts submitted from authors,
		  about photographs and other illustrations for works, about translations of
		  works published, about terms of contract and royalties, and about new work
		  published by other firms. The correspondence also deals with Buchan's own
		  material. The Buchan Correspondence consists of over 4,700 letters and has been
		  given the shelfmark Gen. 1728/B/1-14. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlists, H25; H25.1 </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
