<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-16">GB 237
		Coll-16</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Papers of Joseph
			 Black (1728-1799) </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-16">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Papers of Joseph
			 Black (1728-1799) </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-16</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Gen. 873-875</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Papers of Joseph Black
		  (1728-1799)</unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1754/1799">1754-1799</unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>5 boxes.
		  </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>Joseph Black was born in Bordeaux, France, on 16 April 1728. His
		  father, of Scottish descent and a native of Belfast, was involved in the wine
		  business in France. Black was educated in Belfast and then studied medicine and
		  natural sciences at Glasgow University where his chemistry instructor was
		  William Cullen (1710-1790). In 1751 Black transferred his medical studies to
		  Edinburgh. In 1756 he succeeded Cullen as Lecturer in Chemistry at Glasgow
		  University and was also appointed Professor of Anatomy, later on exchanging to
		  the Chair of Medicine. Black also practiced as a physician. Through his
		  investigation of the heating of magnesium carbonate, he anticipated the
		  findings of Antoine Laurent Lavoisier (1743-1794), and indeed of modern
		  chemistry, by indicating the existence of the gas carbon dioxide as distinct
		  from common air. An account of his studies was published in 
		Experiments upon magnesia alba, quicklime, and some other alcaline
		  substances  (1756). Black's work at Glasgow led to the doctrine of
		latent heat. He verified the hypothesis in 1761, thereafter teaching the
		doctrine and doubtless influencing his friend James Watt (1736-1819) in the
		construction of the condensing steam engine. Black also founded the theory of
		specific heats. In 1766 until 1799, Black was Professor of Chemistry at
		Edinburgh University. Joseph Black died in Edinburgh on 10 November 1799. His
		lecture notes, supplemented by those of his pupils, were written and published
		posthumously by John Robison as 
		Lectures on the elements of chemistry, delivered in the University
		  of Edinburgh  (1803). </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The Joseph Black Manuscript collection consists of volumes of
		  correspondence between himself and a variety of persons (including James Watt,
		  Prince Paul Dashkov, Johann Albrecht Euler), and on a variety of subjects:
		  linen bleaching, use of lime water, assays of ores, civic water supply,
		  mineralogical specimens, absorption of heat etc. There are family letters too,
		  between Black and his father and his brothers Samuel, George and Thomas, again
		  on a variety of subjects: legal and money matters, health matters, trade with
		  America, French flax, naval telegraphy, French prisoners in Edinburgh Castle
		  etc. There are also manuscript copies of Black's Chemistry Lectures. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H16; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows at various shelfmarks references to
		  notes of lectures taken down by others, an autobiographical note from Black's
		  birth to his graduation, and printed tables. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
