<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-45">GB 237
		Coll-45</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>W. H. Auden
			 Collection </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-45">
    <did>
      <unittitle>W. H. Auden
			 Collection </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-45</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">MS 3080; Gen. 2239/1-2; Auden Collection
		  1-805</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">W. H. Auden
		  Collection </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1920-1972">circa 1920-1972 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>3 boxes;
		  circa 800 books. </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>Wystan Hugh Auden, poet, playwright, librettist, critic, editor,
		  translator, and hero of the Left during the Depression, was born on 21 February
		  1907 in York. The family moved to Birmingham in 1908. At the age of eight he
		  was sent to St. Edmund's preparatory school in Surrey, and then attended
		  Gresham's School, Holt, in Norfolk. The young Auden was interested in science
		  and biology, and intended to become a mining engineer, but by 1922 he had
		  discovered poetry. In 1925 he entered Christ Church, Oxford, where he
		  established himself as a poet. After graduating in 1928, he spent a year
		  abroad, in Berlin. Between 1930 and 1935, Auden was a schoolmaster at
		  Larchfield Academy, Helensburgh, Scotland, and at Downs School, Colwall, near
		  Malvern, England. He married Erika Mann, writer, and daughter of Thomas Mann,
		  in 1935, in order to provide her with a British passport. They would later
		  divorce. With others, Auden founded the Group Theatre, 1932. He worked with the
		  GPO film unit in 1935 and collaborated on films such as 
		Night Mail  and 
		Coal-face . He travelled to Iceland in 1936 and in 1937
		served as a stretcher-bearer for Loyalists during the Spanish Civil War. In
		1938 he travelled to China with Christopher Isherwood. With Isherwood, Auden
		went to the USA in 1939, teaching there and becoming an American citizen in
		April 1946. He was Associate Professor of English Literature, Ann Arbor
		University, Michigan, and held a Guggenheim Research Fellowship, 1942. Between
		1956 and 1961 he was Professor of Poetry, University of Oxford, and Honorary
		Student of Christ Church, Oxford, 1962. Auden received King George's Gold Medal
		for poetry, 1937; the Pulitzer Prize, 1948; the Bollingen Prize, 1953; the
		National Book Award, 1956; the Feltrinelli Prize, 1957; and, the National Medal
		for Literature, USA, 1954. For more than 20 years, Auden lived with Chester
		Kallman, an American poet and close friend. Auden's first book of poetry 
		Poems  (1934) was printed privately by Stephen Spender.
		His early work was a fusion of material from Icelandic sagas, Old English
		poetry, Marx, Freud, and school stories and humour. It was material produced
		between 1933 and 1938, warning of the bad side of capitalism and the rise of
		totalitarianism, that made him the hero of the Left, an example being 
		Look, stranger!  (1936). On disillusionment with the Left
		and having settled in the USA, Auden underwent deep change and edged towards
		Christian commitment in 
		New Year letter  (1941). From 1948, Auden established a
		pattern of leaving New York every year to spend the summer in Europe, mainly on
		the island of Ischia, Italy, but latterly in Kirchstetten, Austria. 
		The shield of Achilles  (1955) and other sequences of
		poems were published during this period. With Kallman, Auden collaborated on 
		The rake's progress  (1951) for Igor Stravinsky. Auden
		died in Vienna, 28 September 1973. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The W. H. Auden material is a small collection formed by gift and
		  purchase over the years, serving as a complement to the Auden collection of
		  around 750 printed items purchased from Auden's bibliographer, B.C.Bloomfield
		  in 1982, and augmented by gift by him and purchase since then. The W. H. Auden
		  material consists of an autograph essay, typescripts, and miscellaneous notes.
		  There is correspondence in the form of postcards, and typed and hand-written
		  letters. Most of the Bloomfield Auden collection of printed items has yet to be
		  catalogued. In addition, in the Papers of Professor Archibald H. Campbell, not
		  yet catalogued, there is a box containing press cuttings and letters concerning
		  Auden and Stephen Spender, Spender letters, and some items from Auden to
		  Campbell. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H45 </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
