<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-33">GB 237
		Coll-33</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Papers of David
			 Gregory (1661-1708) </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-33">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Papers of David
			 Gregory (1661-1708) </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code"> GB 237 Coll-33</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Dc.1.61; Dk.1.2 </physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Papers of David Gregory (1661-1708)
		  </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1507-1706">1507-1706 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>1 volume; 3
		  box files. </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>David Gregory, the astronomer and mathematician, was born at
		  Kinnairdie in Banffshire, north east Scotland on 24 June 1661 (though some
		  references suggest 6 March 1659). From Marischal College, Aberdeen, he entered
		  Edinburgh University, graduating M.A. on 28 November 1683. A month prior to his
		  graduation he was elected to the Chair of Mathematics, at one time occupied by
		  his uncle, the mathematician James Gregory (1638-1675). In 1684, David Gregory
		  published in Edinburgh his 
		Exercitatio geometrica de dimensione figurarum  in which,
		with the assistance of his uncle's work, he extended the method of quadratures
		by infinite series. As a professor, Gregory was the first to lecture publically
		on the Newtonian philosophy. His lecture notes show that they covered a broad
		range of subjects including geodesy, optics, dynamics, and various branches of
		mathematics. In 1691 he went to London where he was introduced to Newton and
		recommended to John Flamsteed (1646-1719), the first astronomer royal. With the
		combined influence of Newton and Flamsteed, Gregory was awarded the Savilian
		Chair of Astronomy at Oxford in 1691. In 1692 he took the degrees of M.A. and
		M.D. at Oxford, and he became a master commoner of Balliol College. Also in
		1692, he was elected a fellow of the Royal Society. In 1699 he was appointed as
		mathematical tutor to William, Duke of Gloucester. The substance of his work
		delivered in Edinburgh, and published there in 1684, was contained in his 
		Catoptricae et dioptricae sphaericae elementa  (1695) and
		was adapted to undergraduates. In this work, Gregory gave the first hint of the
		achromatic telescope when he referred to the possibility of counteracting
		colour aberration in lenses by combining in them media of different densities.
		The work was reprinted in Edinburgh in 1713 and translated into English (from
		Latin) in 1715. His principle work however was 
		Astronomiae physicae et geometricae elementa  (1702). This
		was the first text-book on gravitational principles and it remodelled astronomy
		in conformity with physical theory. His next work, in Greek and Latin, was 
		Euclides  (1703) which was an edition of all the writings
		attributed to Euclid. In 1704, Gregory was nominated to the committee charged
		by Prince George with the inspection and printing of the Greenwich
		observations, and in 1705 he was chosen as honorary fellow of the Royal College
		of Physicians of Edinburgh. Gregory died on 10 October 1708 at the Greyhound
		Inn at Maidenhead, Berkshire, while on his return to London from Bath after
		taking the cure there for consumption. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The content of the Papers of David Gregory have been indexed within
		  the handlist H33. The majority of the papers deal with mathematical questions,
		  and there are many about astronomy and optics. There is also a provisional
		  index of subjects from acid, agriculture, and archaeology, to the Darien
		  Scheme, law, tide tables, and university. There is a provisional index too of
		  personal names from Queen Anne, Bernoulli, Tycho Brahe, and Cassini, to Euclid,
		  Edmond Halley, James VI, Mercator, Sir Isaac Newton, Ptolemy, Pythagorus, and
		  Torricelli. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H33; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows, at various shelfmarks, references to
		  many additional notes by David Gregory at Dc. 1.62., inscription and
		  annotations by him in a Greek manuscript at Dc. 4.85., and treatises,
		  lectiones, notes and letters at various shelfmarks. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <separatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353(a)">
        <head>Separated Material</head>
        <p>A list of books, theses, letters and family records which would assist
		  in the study of the Papers of David Gregory has also been drawn up and is held
		  within the handlist H33. While some of the books and theses are held within
		  Edinburgh University Library, others may be found at the National Library of
		  Scotland; Aberdeen University Library; Edinburgh Public Library (Reference
		  Library); the Scottish Records Office; the Lyon Office; the British Library;
		  and, John Rylands Library, University of Manchester. </p>
      </separatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
