<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-15">GB 237
		Coll-15</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Papers and
			 Correspondence of Charles Sarolea (1870-1953)</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-15">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Papers and
			 Correspondence of Charles Sarolea (1870-1953)</unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-15</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Gen.187-267</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Papers and Correspondence of Charles
		  Sarolea (1870-1953) </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1897/1952">1897-1952</unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>81 boxes
		  (11 linear metres).</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>Charles Sarolea was born in Tongres in the Belgian province of
		  Limbourg on 25 October 1870. He was educated at the University of Liege. In
		  1894 he was appointed to the newly-founded Lectureship in French at Edinburgh
		  University and in 1918 he became the University's first Professor of French. He
		  held the Chair of French and Romance Philology until his resignation in1931.
		  University teaching had only been part of his career, for Sarolea was also a
		  linguist, claiming a knowledge of at least eighteen languages, and also a
		  bookman and author. His book collection of some 200,000 works was said to be
		  the largest private library in Europe. His own authorship covered political,
		  philosophical and literary subjects and included 
		The Anglo-German problem  (1912), 
		Europe's debt to Russia  (1916), 
		Europe and the League of Nations  (1919), and 
		Daylight on Spain  (1938). Sarolea became a naturalised
		citizen of the UK in November 1912, but for over 50 years he represented
		Belgium as its Consul, latterly Consul-General, in Edinburgh. French
		scholarship probably owes an important debt to Sarolea. He held honorary
		degrees from the Universities of Brussels, Montreal, and Cleveland, and
		received the Belgian award, Chevalier of the Belgian Order of Leopold. He died
		in Edinburgh on 11 March 1953. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The Sarolea collection has been preserved in 234 numbered files in 81
		  boxes. The collection covers the years 1897-1952 and relate to all of the
		  Professor's various activities and interests. For convenience, it can be
		  divided into four main divisions. Firstly, there are the Everyman papers
		  relating to the weekly literary journal 
		Everyman, his life, work and books  with which Sarolea had
		an interest from 1914,. Within the Everyman division there are editorial papers
		dated from 1912 and 1916, and business archives between 1912 and 1917. The
		editorial papers consist of correspondence between Sarolea and contributors to 
		Everyman  and manuscripts of articles offered for
		publication, while the business archives comprise the correspondence of
		publisher J.M. Dent, financial and legal papers, matters relating to
		advertising and printing, many letters of appreciation and criticism, and a
		number of competition essays. Secondly, there are papers relating to Edinburgh
		University. These consist of correspondence with the Principal on six public
		lectures delivered by Sarolea in 1917; correspondence and papers on general
		University administrative matters between 1919 and 1930; correspondence and
		papers relating to the work of the French Department between 1911 and 1936;
		and, correspondence relating to Sarolea's retirement and pension, 1923-52.
		Thirdly, there are writings by Sarolea. Spanning the years 1911 and 1950, these
		are papers, mostly typescript with some autograph corrections, comprising
		drafts of books or parts of books, articles for journals and newspapers,
		university lectures, addresses at meetings, contributions to public debates,
		and radio talks. Fourthly, there are miscellaneous papers and correspondence.
		This division is itself subdivided into four main groups. There is general
		correspondence from 1897 to 1952 and including family papers; correspondence
		with publishers, 1909-43; correspondence with individual persons or
		organisations, 1919-46; correspondence and papers relating to foreign countries
		and including Sarolea's relations with the Belgian royal family, and Belgian
		consular correspondence. This latter group also includes correspondence
		relating to the then Czechoslovakia, between the years 1919 and 1942 and there
		are letters from Eduard Benes and Jan Masaryk </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)324">
        <head>Immediate source of acquisition</head>
        <p>The papers and correspondence of Professor Charles Sarolea were
		  purchased for in 1954. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H15; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows Sarolea lectures on French literature
		  taken down by a W.S. Mitchell, at Gen. 784/2. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
