<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-49">GB 237
		Coll-49</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Papers of Fred Urquhart </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-49">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Papers of Fred Urquhart </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code"> GB 237 Coll-49</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">MSS 2803-2839 </physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Papers of Fred Urquhart </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1930-1994">1930-1994 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>37 boxes (5
		  m). </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <origination encodinganalog="isadg(2)321" label="Name(s) of creators">Frederick Burrows
		  Urquhart </origination>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>The writer Frederick Burrows Urquhart was born on 12 July 1912 in
		  Edinburgh. Although he wrote a number of novels, Fred Urquhart's strength was
		  the short story in which his characters did the talking. He had an ear for all
		  forms of accent and dialect and took ungrammatical yet creative liberties with
		  the language. Although he spent many years in southern England after the war,
		  his creative impulses were rooted in Lowland Scotland: on the Firth of Forth
		  and Clydeside; in coastal Wigtownshire where he was at school for a while; and
		  on Tayside, where he also spent some of his childhood . His stories generally
		  dealt with the lives of ordinary people, and the cruelty and violence of such
		  lives was a constant theme. He was particularly sensitive to the violence dealt
		  out to women, and his homosexuality probably enabled him to portray the female
		  psyche with insight and tenderness. The ugliness of war (he was a pacifist) was
		  an extension of these concerns. The son of a chauffeur, Urquhart was educated
		  at Stranraer High School and Broughton Secondary School. On leaving school at
		  the age of fifteen he worked for some years in a bookshop in Edinburgh. At the
		  same time he began to write, and from the early 1930s onwards had stories
		  published in periodicals as well as broadcast on the radio. He left the
		  bookshop in 1935 to concentrate on writing. His first published novel was 
		Time Will Knit  (1938), the story of working-class
		Edinburgh life. When war came in 1939 Urquhart, as a declared conscientious
		objector, was sent to work on the land. It was at this point that his first
		collection of short stories appeared, 
		I fell for a Sailor  (1940). In 1944 Urquhart was working
		in England at Woburn Abbey, the estate of the Duke of Bedford, which made a
		good base for contacting artistic and literary circles in London. He soon met
		the Scottish painters Robert Colquhoun and Robert MacBryde who had moved to
		London from Glasgow themselves only a year or two before, and he also got to
		know George Orwell and Rhys Davies. In these early post-war years came his
		second collection of stories, 
		The Clouds are Big with Mercy  (1946). From 1947 Urquhart
		worked as a reader for a London literary agency and from 1951-54 was a
		script-reader for Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer. Further volumes of short stories
		appeared, among them 
		The Last GI Bride Wore Tartan  (1947) and 
		The Year of the Short Corn and Other Stories  (1949). Two
		more novels appeared , 
		The Ferret was Abraham's Daughter  (1949) and 
		Jezebel's Dust (1951). With a decline in interest for the
		serious short story, Urquhart took on a number of editing tasks, and was also a
		reader for Cassell &amp;amp; Co. Ltd., 1951-74, the London scout for Walt
		Disney Productions, 1959-60, and a reader for J.M. Dent &amp;amp; Sons Ltd.,
		1967-71. He kept on writing too, and there was a final novel, 
		Palace of Green Days  (1979), which drew upon childhood
		memories of Perthshire, where his father was chauffeur to the Earl of
		Breadalbane at Taymouth Castle. There appeared further collections of short
		stories, notably 
		A Diver in China Seas  (1980), which was impressive for
		its insight into its women characters. With his companion, the dancer Peter
		Wyndham Allen, Urquhart had moved into a house in Ashdown Forest in East Sussex
		in 1958, but when Wyndham Allen died in 1990 Urquhart moved back to Scotland
		and settled in Musselburgh. He died in Edinburgh on 2 December 1995. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The Papers of Fred Urquhart contain drawings, diplomas, essays,
		  stories, poems and early manuscripts; and, various notes, and typescripts.
		  There are reports and correspondence from periods with Cassell, and J.M. Dent,
		  and relating to work with other publishers and MGM and Walt Disney. The
		  collection includes diaries and notebooks on H.E. Bates from the 1930s; and,
		  address books and diaries covering several decades. There is correspondence
		  with his parents between 1936-1965, and a great deal of letter and postcard
		  communication up to 1994. Some material (for example correspondence with Herta
		  Ryder) is restricted until 2005. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H49 </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
