<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-28">GB 237
		Coll-28</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Correspondence
			 and Papers of the Goodsir Family </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-28">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Correspondence
			 and Papers of the Goodsir Family </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code"> GB 237 Coll-28</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Dc.5.129; Gen. 289-307F; Gen. 1428; E2006.29
		  </physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Correspondence
		  and Papers of the Goodsir Family </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1750-1870">circa 1750-1870 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>2
		  notebooks; 1 bundle anatomical drawings; 12 boxes (2 linear metres). </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <origination encodinganalog="isadg(2)321" label="Name(s) of creators">John Goodsir,
		  surgeon, of Largo; John Goodsir, surgeon, of Anstruther; Professor John Goodsir
		  (1814-1867); Harry Duncan Spence Goodsir, surgeon; Rev. Joseph Taylor Goodsir;
		  Robert Anstruther Goodsir </origination>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>The family of Goodsir had been settled on the east coast of Fife for
		  several generations and the name was said to have been German. John Goodsir was
		  born in Anstruther, Fife, on 20 March 1814. Goodsir was the son of Dr. John
		  Goodsir of Anstruther and the grandson of Dr. John Goodsir of Largo in Fife. He
		  was educated in Anstruther and then at St. Andrews where he followed four years
		  of an Arts course but did not take a degree. In 1830 he was apprenticed to an
		  Edinburgh surgeon-dentist and at the same time he attended medical and anatomy
		  classes and learned practical surgery. In 1835 he took charge of the practice,
		  and that year also obtained the license of the Royal College of Surgeons,
		  though he did not take the M.D. degree. He then joined his father in practice
		  in Anstruther. While there in dental practice, Goodsir wrote his first piece of
		  scientific work, 
		On the origin and development of the pulps and sacs of the human
		  teeth  (1839). He also gave time to research in marine zoology, geology
		and archaeology, and wrote on anatomy and physiology. In 1840 Goodsir went to
		Edinburgh and in 1841 he was appointed Conservator of the Royal College of
		Surgeons Museum, and in 1842 he moved to the University becoming Curator of the
		University's Anatomical Museum. On the death of Alexander Monro, tertius
		(1773-1859), he was elected as Professor of Anatomy at Edinburgh University.
		His enthusiasm soon raised the Anatomy Department from the bad state into which
		it had fallen under Monro. He described the anatomy of the horse and electric
		fish, and in 1847 he began a course of summer lectures on the invertebrata.
		Goodsir investigated cellular physiology and pathology and insisted on the
		importance of the cell as the centre of nutrition. He claimed that the cell was
		divided into a number of departments. His work influenced that of the German
		physiologist Rudolf (Carl) Virchow (1821-1902) who offered insights into
		pathological processes. In 1853, Goodsir's health began to deteriorate -
		wasting of the spinal cord - and much of his lecturing tasks were delegated to
		assistants, although he continued with his museum work. John Goodsir died at
		Wardie, Edinburgh, on 6 March 1867. Goodsir's brother Harry Duncan Spence
		Goodsir succeeded him as Conservator of the Royal College of Surgeons Museum.
		Harry Goodsir sailed with the ill-fated Franklin Expedition in 1845, and
		perished with it. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The correspondence and papers of the Goodsir Family includes material
		  relating to John Goodsir, Professor of Anatomy at Edinburgh University, his
		  father John Goodsir, surgeon of Anstruther, his grandfather John Goodsir,
		  surgeon of Largo, and his brothers Harry Duncan Spence Goodsir, surgeon, and
		  Rev. Joseph Taylor Goodsir. Among the correspondence are letters from and
		  relating to Henry Mackenzie, the author of 
		The man of feeling . Among the papers are notes by Harry
		D. S. Goodsir on crustacea; Goodsir diplomas; the dissecting room notebook of
		Professor Goodsir, and notes of his lectures; and, diary of Joseph Taylor
		Goodsir covering the years 1850-1870. At Dc.5.129 is a medical notebook with a
		description of rickets, circa 1769, owned by John Goodsir, surgeon of
		Anstruther. At Gen. 1428 are Professor Goodsir's lectures on anatomy, 1862-63.
		At E2006.29 are four sets of Chinese anatomical diagrams from the collection of
		Professor Goodsir.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>An important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held
		  at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to
		  the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows, at various shelfmarks, references to
		  diplomas of Professor Goodsir at Da.Cyl., letters of Goodsir, class
		  certificates signed by him, notes of his lectures on anatomy taken down by
		  others, and various anatomy class lists. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
      <odd/>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
