<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-14 ">GB 237
		Coll-14</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Papers of James
			 Cossar Ewart</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-14">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Papers of James
			 Cossar Ewart</unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-14</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Gen. 132-139; Medals No. 123</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Papers of James Cossar
		  Ewart</unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1866/1935">1866-1935</unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>8 boxes (1
		  linear metre); 17 medal boxes. </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <origination encodinganalog="isadg(2)321" label="Name(s) of creators">James Cossar Ewart</origination>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>James Cossar Ewart was born in Penicuik, Midlothian, 26 November 1851.
		  He was educated in Penicuik and entered the University of Edinburgh as a
		  medical student in 1871, graduating as a Bachelor of Medicine and Master of
		  Surgery in 1874. Until 1878 he was Curator of the Zoological Museum at
		  University College, London. While in London he published a number of papers on
		  the structure of the retina and lens, the sexual organs of the lamprey, and the
		  placentation of the Shanghai River deer. His research on Bacillus anthracis was
		  presented as a thesis for the degree of Doctor of Medicine at Edinburgh. After
		  a brief return to Edinburgh as Lecturer in Anatomy in the Extra-Mural School,
		  at the end of 1878 he was appointed to the Chair of Natural History in the
		  University of Aberdeen. While in Aberdeen Ewart became interested in marine
		  biological investigation and established an experimental station on the coast
		  in the area. There he worked in his spare time on fishery problems, and, with
		  George John Romanes, on the locomotor system of echinoderms. In 1882, Ewart
		  became Regius Professor of Natural History at the University of Edinburgh and
		  held this position for forty-five years, retiring in 1927. Also in 1882, Ewart
		  joined the Fishery Board of Scotland as scientific adviser, publishing several
		  papers on the fertilisation of herring ova and the natural history of the
		  herring, cod, and other fish. He also carried out some work on the electric
		  organ in the skate. Ewart had also given some attention to the development of
		  the horse, particularly to the bones of the limbs. Around 1894, he had started
		  investigations into experimental breeding, and much of this work was done
		  before the rediscovery of Mendel's laws of heredity. Rather than the classical
		  experiment using an Arab mare and quagga, and then an Arab stallion with the
		  progeny, Ewart's experiments used Burchell's zebra. The results of his work
		  were published in 
		The Penycuik experiments  (1899). As a result of Ewart's
		knowledge and experience, the Board of Agriculture for Scotland formed a
		special committee on animal breeding in 1913. After the First World War, this
		scheme was enlarged and a new Department of Genetics was formed at the
		University of Edinburgh. Meanwhile, Ewart had turned his attention to the
		origin and history of feathers in birds and their relation to scales in
		reptiles. The rearing of penguins at the then fairly new Edinburgh Zoo provided
		him with the relevant material. James Cossar Ewart died in Penicuik on New
		Year's Eve 1933 after a short illness. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The James Cossar Ewart Collection consists of diplomas, medals and
		  badges, letters and papers. The collection of medals and badges,1866-1931,
		  includes those presented at school in Penicuik and while at Edinburgh
		  University. There are also items won for prize animals (St. Kilda ewe, Libyan
		  stallion, Celtic mare and foal, Arab Highland pony etc.) at various shows. The
		  certificates, diplomas and letters of appointment span the years 1870 to 1927.
		  There are biographical papers covering 1875-1934. Photographs include those of
		  Professor Ewart himself and staff, and of zebra hybrids. Spanning the years
		  1870 to 1935, there are miscellaneous papers in connection with lectures,
		  lecture course, press-cutting books, personal notebooks, and letters. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)324">
        <head>Immediate source of acquisition</head>
        <p>The James Cossar Ewart Collection was deposited in on 22 April 1954.
		  It was arranged and listed in the Department of Zoology after receipt from
		  Messrs. McAndrew, Wright &amp;amp; Murray, W.S., Edinburgh, 17 November 1953.
		  </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H14; Another important finding aid is the alphabetical Index
		  to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and
		  Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987.
		  </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>The Index to Manuscripts shows at various shelfmarks references to
		  notes of Ewart's lectures taken down by others, and letters of Ewart. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
