<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-18">GB 237
		Coll-18</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Letters to
			 Christopher Murray Grieve (1892-1978)</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-18">
    <did>
      <unittitle>Letters to
			 Christopher Murray Grieve (1892-1978)</unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-18</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Gen. 2094; MSS 2942-2961</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">Letters to Christopher Murray Grieve
		  (1892-1978)</unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1978">before
		  1978</unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>35 boxes, 1
		  large portfolio, 37 manuscript folders (6 linear metres). </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <origination encodinganalog="isadg(2)321" label="Name(s) of creators">Christopher Murray
		  Grieve, also known as: Hugh MacDiarmid </origination>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>Poet, essayist, literary critic, historian, and social commentator,
		  Christopher Murray Grieve, also known as Hugh MacDiarmid, was born on 11 August
		  1892 in Langholm, Dumfriesshire. He was educated at Langholm Academy then at
		  Broughton Junior Student Centre in Edinburgh prior to studying at Edinburgh
		  University. After wartime service with the Royal Army Medical Corps, 1915-20,
		  in Salonika, Italy, and France, he became a journalist in Montrose, Angus.
		  There he worked for the 
		Montrose Review  and edited three issues of the first
		post-war Scottish verse anthology 
		Northern Numbers  (1921-23). In 1922 he founded the
		journal 
		Scottish Chapbook , advocating the revival of Scottish
		literature. Grieve was a Labour member of Montrose town council from 1923, but
		in 1928 he was one of the founder members of the National Party of Scotland
		(now the Scottish National Party). Later on however he came to accept Marxist
		philosophy. He was a formal member of the Communist Party from 1934 until 1938
		when he was expelled, and rejoined in 1957. Indeed, in 1964 he was a defeated
		Communist candidate opposing Sir Alec Douglas-Home in a Perthshire constituency
		in the General Election. In 1929, he worked on 
		Vox  in London, and in 1930 was living in Liverpool,
		working as a public relations officer. Another spell in London followed. In
		1933 Grieve moved to Whalsay in the Shetland Islands, staying there until 1941.
		In these wartime years, he worked as a manual labourer on Clydeside, 1941-43,
		and then on British merchant ships engaged in estuarial duties, 1943-45. After
		the Second World War, he lived in Glasgow, Strathaven in Lanarkshire, and then
		from 1951 in Biggar on the upper Clyde. As a poet, Grieve (Hugh MacDiarmid) was
		the pre-eminent Scottish figure in the first half of the 20th century, and was
		the leader of the Scottish literary renaissance. Indeed, he has been
		acknowledged as the greatest Scottish poet since Robert Burns. Grieve rejected
		English as a medium and wrote in an amalgam of various Scots dialects. Later on
		he wrote Scotticised English, and then returned to Standard English. His poetic
		work in these mediums, and under the pseudonym Hugh MacDiarmid, included 
		A drunk man looks at the thistle  (1926), 
		To Circumjack Cencrastus  (1930), 
		Scots unbound  (1932), 
		Stony limits  (1934), 
		Second hymn to Lenin  (1935), 
		A kist of whistles  (1947), and 
		In memoriam James Joyce  (1955). Other works include 
		The kind of poetry I want  (1961), 
		The company I've kept  (1966), 
		Celtic nationalism  (1968), 
		A lap of honour  (1969), 
		Song of the Seraphion  (1973), and 
		John Knox  (1976). These titles represent only a very
		small proportion of Grieve's enormous output as poet, prose writer, editor, and
		translator. He was writing well into the 1970s but died of cancer in Edinburgh
		on 9 September 1978. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The collection of letters to Christopher Murray Grieve (Hugh
		  MacDiarmid) are organised alphabetically and into acquisitions pre-1987 (Gen.
		  2094) and material acquired more recently (MSS 2942-2961). The correspondents
		  include private individuals and publishers; names such as William Darling,
		  Richard Demarco, Eric Linklater, David Daiches, Norman MacCaig, Sir Compton
		  Mackenzie, Edwin Muir, Ezra Pound, Bertrand Russell, and William Butler Yeats.
		  </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H18.1; Handlist H18.2; Another important finding aid is the
		  alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at Edinburgh University Library, Special
		  Collections and Archives. Additions to the typed slips in sheaf binders were
		  made until 1987. </p>
      </otherfindaid>
      <relatedmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)353">
        <head>Related Units of Description</head>
        <p>also holds around 1,800 volumes from Grieve's (Hugh MacDiarmid's)
		  library. The deposit contains books and periodicals, loose pamphlets, and
		  miscellaneous material (at SC 7000-8648 and SD 5950-6108). In addition, the
		  Index to Manuscripts shows at various shelfmarks original manuscripts and
		  proofs of Grieve's work, typescripts, notes and glossaries, miscellaneous
		  essays on Scottish subjects, and letters of and to Grieve. There are a few
		  other volumes from his library at shelfmark JA. </p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
