<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-41">GB 237
		Coll-41</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>C. H. Waddington Archive </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-41">
    <did>
      <unittitle>C. H. Waddington Archive </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code"> GB 237 Coll-41</unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">MSS 3021-3079</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">C. H. Waddington Archive </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="1923-1975">1923-1975 </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>57 boxes (8
		  m); 4 volumes; 1 folder. </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>Conrad Hal Waddington was born in Evesham, 8 November 1905. The son of
		  a tea planter, he spent the first three years of his life in Coimbatore, Tamil
		  Nadu (South India). At the age of four he returned to England to live with an
		  aunt and uncle on a farm in Sedgeberrow. After sharing a governess with his
		  cousin, he went to Aymestry House Preparatory School in Malvern Link at the age
		  of nine. A scholarship to Clifton followed, and a move to Weybridge, living
		  with his grandmother. It was his grandmother who encouraged his early interests
		  in natural history, geology and archaeology. After Clifton he went to Sidney
		  Sussex College, Cambridge, on a scholarship, and took the Natural Sciences
		  Tripos in 1926. Early postgraduate years included studies in palaeontology,
		  philosophy, geology, and embryology. Between 1933 and 1945, Waddington was
		  Embryologist and Lecturer in Zoology at Strangeways Research Laboratory,
		  Cambridge. He was a Fellow of Christ's College, Cambridge, 1934-45. During the
		  Second World War, Waddington worked on photographic reconnaissance and with
		  anti-shipping strikes. In 1945 came a first offer of a chair of genetics at
		  Edinburgh University, but Waddington declined because he felt his future lay
		  with the new National Animal Breeding and Genetics Research Organisation
		  (NABGRO). When it was suggested however that NABGRO might be found a permanent
		  headquarters in Edinburgh, with Waddington combining the position of chief
		  geneticist at the Organisation with the chair of animal genetics at the
		  University, he agreed, and a research institute grew in Edinburgh from 1947
		  (the Institute of Animal Genetics). Into the 1950s, this grew into the largest
		  genetics department in the UK and one of the largest in the world. By the end
		  of the 1950s though, the research institute had become more and more
		  compartmentalised, and Waddington himself had become interested in the setting
		  up of an Epigenetics Laboratory. Into the 1960s, he played a major role in the
		  expansion of the biological faculty of Edinburgh University. In 1970, he
		  accepted an invitation from the State University of New York to spend two years
		  in Buffalo occupying the Albert Einstein Chair in Science. While in Buffalo,
		  and shortly before his return to Edinburgh in 1973, Waddington suffered a heart
		  attack. Following a further heart attack outside his home, he died on 26
		  September 1975. Waddington had been awarded the CBE in 1958, and had been
		  elected a Fellow of the Royal Society of Edinburgh in 1948. He became a foreign
		  member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 1959 and of the Finnish
		  Academy in 1957. In 1974 he had been elected a Fellow of the Deutsche Akademie
		  der Naturforscher Leopoldina, a scientific academy dating from 1677. Waddington
		  held honorary degrees from Aberdeen, Dublin, Geneva, Montreal and Prague. He
		  had a long record of publication, from 1939 to the 1970s. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>The Waddington Archive consists of scientific notebooks and bundles of
		  notes; manuscripts and typescripts of essays, articles and larger works;
		  photographic illustrations for publications; correspondence with publishers;
		  correspondence with scientific journals; scientific correspondence;
		  correspondence with societies; material relating to meetings and conferences;
		  papers and books for review; University of Edinburgh files; and other
		  miscellaneous files. The Archive also contains confidential personal files
		  which are not available for consultation until 2025. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlist, H41 </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
