<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <eadid countrycode="GB" mainagencycode="237" publicid="GB 237 Coll-1">GB
		237 Coll-1 </eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>The Laing Collection </titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher>Edinburgh University Library</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>George Square</addressline>
          <addressline>Edinburgh, EH8 9LJ</addressline>
          <addressline>Scotland</addressline>
          <addressline>United Kingdom</addressline>
        </address>
        <date normal="" certainty=""></date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>EAD generated in XMetal, adapting methodology developed by the
		  NAHSTE project in 2001.</creation>
      <langusage>This finding-aid is in<language langcode="eng">English</language>
      </langusage>
      <descrules encodinganalog="isadg(2)372" audience="external">Descriptions
		  compiled in line with the following standards: 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="International Council on Archives Committee on Descriptive Standards" source="ncarules" role="author">International Council on Archives Committee on
				Descriptive Standards</corpname>, 
			 <title render="italic">ISAD(G) General International Standard
				Archival Description</title>, 
			 <edition>2nd edition</edition>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" certainty="certain" normal="2000">2000</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref> and 
		  <bibref>
          <corpname normal="National Council on Archives" source="ncarules" role="author">National Council on Archives</corpname>
          <title> Rules for the Construction of Personal, Place and Corporate
				Names</title>, <imprint>
            <date type="publication" normal="1997" certainty="certain">1997</date>
          </imprint>
        </bibref>
      </descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="fonds" id="GB-237-Coll-1">
    <did>
      <unittitle>The Laing Collection </unittitle>
      <repository>Edinburgh University Library Special Collections</repository>
      <unitid encodinganalog="isadg(2)311" label="Reference code">GB 237 Coll-1 </unitid>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">Coll-1 </physloc>
      <physloc encodinganalog="shelfmark" label="Shelfmark">La.I - La.V</physloc>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="isadg(2)312" label="Title">The Laing Collection </unittitle>
      <unitdate encodinganalog="isadg(2)313" label="Date" normal="800-1899">9th century -
		  19th century </unitdate>
      <physdesc encodinganalog="isadg(2)315" label="Extent and Medium of the Unit of Description">
        <extent>circa 300 boxes, circa
		  740 volumes (maximum 72 linear metres). </extent>
      </physdesc>
      <origination encodinganalog="isadg(2)321" label="Name(s) of creators">David Laing (1793-1878)
		  </origination>
      <langmaterial encodinganalog="isadg(2)343" label=""/>
    </did>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="isadg(2)322">
      <p>David Laing, eminent historian, antiquary and bibliographer, was the
		  second son of the Edinburgh bookseller William Laing (1764-1832) and was born
		  on 20 April 1793. He was educated at the Canongate grammar school and later on
		  attended Greek classes at Edinburgh University. At the age of fourteen he
		  became apprenticed to his father who, at the time, was the only bookseller in
		  Edinburgh dealing in foreign literature. Laing was able, occasionally, to
		  travel abroad in search of rare or curious books. In 1821, he became a partner
		  in his father's business and throughout his life he was an avid collector of
		  manuscripts and rescued many from destruction. The first published work of his
		  own was 
		Auctarium Bibliothecae Edinburgenae sive Catalogus Librorum quos
		  Gulielmus Drummondus ab Hawthornden D.D.Q. Anno 1627  (1815). Among
		other works, Laing also reprinted Thomas Craig's 
		Epithalamium on the marriage of Darnley and Mary Stuart 
		(1821). When Sir Walter Scott founded the Bannatyne Club in 1823 for the
		printing of material and tracts relating to Scottish history and literature,
		Laing - a friend of Scott's - became Secretary of the Club and chief organiser
		until its dissolution in the 1860s. Laing was also associated with the
		Abbotsford Club, the Spalding Club, and the Wodrow Society, each of which had
		been set up for the publication of manuscripts and for the revival of old
		texts. When the keepership of the Advocates' Library fell vacant in 1818, Laing
		was a candidate but was not elected. He became Keeper of the Library to the
		Society of Writers to Her Majesty's Signet, a post which he occupied from 1837
		until his death. On his appointment to the post, he gave up his business as a
		bookseller and disposed of the stock in a public sale. Laing died at
		Portobello, in Edinburgh, on 18 October 1878. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="isadg(2)331">
      <p>After the death of David Laing, his private library was sold in an
		  auction occupying thirty-one days. His collection of charters and other papers
		  is of national importance and the most distinguished of its kind in any
		  Scottish university. It is an essential source for the 18th century, and a much
		  used one for all periods of Scottish history from the earliest times. The Laing
		  Collection falls into five sections, designated as La.I., La.II., La.III.,
		  La.IV., and La.V. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <descgrp>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="isadg(2)324">
        <head>Immediate source of acquisition</head>
        <p>The Laing collection, the largest single manuscript collection in
		  Edinburgh University Library, was bequeathed in 1878. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="isadg(2)341">
        <head>Conditions Governing Access</head>
        <p>Contact the repository for details </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid encodinganalog="isadg(2)345">
        <head>Finding Aids</head>
        <p>Handlists, H1; H2; H3; H4; H5; H.5.1; H5.2; H5.3; H5.4.2. Another
		  important finding aid is the alphabetical Index to Manuscripts held at
		  Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections and Archives. Additions to
		  the typed slips in sheaf binders were made until 1987. As a result of a project
		  supported by the Scottish Higher Education Funding Council (SHEFC), section IV
		  of the Laing Collection has been conserved and catalogued. </p>
      </otherfindaid>
    </descgrp>
    <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE38">
      <controlaccess encodinganalog="NAHSTE381">
        <head>Indexing:</head>
        <subject authfilenumber="999999999">Awating indexing</subject>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
